<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000608"><!-- LP4 -->
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Catherine McRobert</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Catherine McRobert, 18 January 1846</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2005-05-10</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000608</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0145</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>McRobert, Catherine</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1846-01-18">18 January 1846</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Chonuane</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Wellcome Institute for the History of Medicine. Library; 7329 04</bibl><!--1846-01-18--><!--Original:1846-01-18-->
				<bibl xml:id="extent">4 pages</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2005-05-10</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Initial Transcription
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2006-02-11</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>first proof
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2006-02-20</date>
				<name xml:id="JB">Janet Browne</name>second proof
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2006-03-02</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>final proof
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000608_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1'-->
<!--Hand 01 4 top left--><!--Hand 02 64765 top right--><!--added to top of letter-->
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">Written in haste so do not 
<lb/>criticize</p><!--end of added lines-->
<lb/><lb/><p rend="right"><space extent="6" unit="words"/><placeName>Chonuane</placeName> 18 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1846</p>
<lb/><p>My Dear <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>Robert</persName></p>
<lb/><p><space extent="5" unit="words"/><space extent="1" unit="chars"/>A considerable time has elapsed since we 
<lb/>had the pleasure of hearing from you. What is the matter, you 
<lb/>certainly never were compelled to listen for months to the 
<lb/>wearisome round of news, maka hela, of this country 
<lb/>enough to make me pant with feverish desire for 
<lb/>something from the world <unclear cert="medium">sick</unclear> in order to realize 
<lb/>the <del type="strikethrough"><unclear cert="low">f</unclear></del> refreshment good news imparts. It is now a 
<lb/>long time since we heard from the <placeName>Kuruman</placeName> side and all 
<lb/>we hear from the natives they well characterize as lies only 
<lb/>there is so little truth in public report here a native 
<lb/>always begins by saying "there are no news. none at all 
<lb/>We have heard a few lies only." And then beginning their 
<lb/>story it is sure to be rumours of war - contentions 
<lb/>between tribes or something so vague we can scarcely 
<lb/>make head or tail of it. Why dont you write 
<lb/>more frequently then? The Penny Post has made 
<lb/>you all so expert in the use of the pen you have 
<lb/>no excuse.</p>
<lb/><p>We heard last week from an authentic source 
<lb/>that <persName>Sekhomi</persName> the chief of the <term type="tribe">BamangWerto</term> had 
<lb/>put a large party of <term type="tribe">Matibele</term> to death. They came 
<lb/>last year to reside with him and being dissatisfied 
<lb/>with his government began to flee to a neighbouring 
<lb/>chief when to prevent the whole following that example 
<lb/>those who remained were indiscriminately massacred 
<lb/>A little more than ten months ago <persName>Mosilikatze</persName> sent 23 
<lb/>men to the <term type="tribe">Bamangwerto</term> for tribute. <persName>Sekhomi</persName>
<lb/>laid an <unclear cert="high">ambuscade</unclear> for them and the poor fellows 
<lb/>being hemmed in in a deep valley I well know 
<lb/>were everyone cut off: A gentleman lately saw 
<lb/>their bones. I do not wish to harrow up 
<lb/>your feelings by these stories But when I 
<lb/>mention the fact of the destruction of the men </p>
<ab>
<lb/><!--written up side of p. 1--><persName>Ralph Lindsay</persName> Esq<hi rend="sup underline">re</hi> has contributed £ 10..10 for another but I dont know anything 
<lb/>about him Do you know him? does he intend to continue the sum? I am at a loss 
</ab>

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000608_0002"/><!--pb/@n='2'-->
<ab>
<lb/><!--up side of p.2-->for want of proper information <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Philip</persName> only notified the simple fact and no 
<lb/>more about it. If you know him I should like to hold some communication <gap agent="damage"/>
</ab>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent"><persName>Mosilikatze</persName> and likewise that the <term type="tribe">Bamangwerto</term> have 
<lb/>subsequently "lifted" some of that gentleman's cattle 
<lb/>and no attempt has been made to punish them, I give 
<lb/>you th information as evidence that <persName>Mosilikatzes</persName>
<lb/>power is on the wane. And we probably will be allowed 
<lb/>to carry on our operations without any hindrance 
<lb/>from him. He was once the great obstacle in the 
<lb/>way of the evangelization of the interior. God in His 
<lb/>providence has removed him out of the way and there is 
<lb/>now every probability that this region will become 
<lb/>the abode of righteousness and peace. A large tribe 
<lb/>of <term type="tribe">Matibele</term> or <term type="tribe"><unclear cert="high">Joolarhs</unclear></term> lives about 10 days East of <persName>Sechele</persName>
<lb/>they have fought three times with <persName>Mosilikatse</persName> and <unclear cert="low">with</unclear>
<lb/>more or less success each time. He is now at a great 
<lb/>distance from us. And long may it remain so. He 
<lb/>has too long been the cause of lamentation cursing &amp; sorrow 
<lb/>here. But I must return to the point for which I 
<lb/>introduced the deeds of <persName>Sekhomi</persName>, viz, to <unclear cert="high">give</unclear>
<lb/>a deed of <unclear cert="high"><persName>Mosheu</persName></unclear> of whom you may have read 
<lb/>in either <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffats</persName> work or speeches. A village 
<lb/>about 12 or 14 miles from <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName> was lately 
<lb/>ransacked by a party of <term type="tribe">Korannas</term> from the 
<lb/><placeName>Vaal river</placeName>. The whole of the cattle &amp; goods of the 
<lb/>people were swept off, and a few lives were lost 
<lb/>When the marauders reached <unclear cert="high">their</unclear> residence next to 
<lb/>that of <persName>Mosheu</persName>, their horses &amp; <unclear cert="high">selves</unclear> being all tired 
<lb/>by the long journey (nearly 200 miles) <persName>Mosheu</persName>
<lb/>lost no time in ordering them to restore everything 
<lb/>and as he is a man of authority among them 
<lb/>they do not dare to refuse obedience to what <persName>Mosheu</persName>
<lb/>told them was the Divine will they made restitution 
<lb/><unclear cert="high"><del type="strikethrough">for</del></unclear> they had stolen And <persName>Mosheu</persName> calling on the 
<lb/>owners of the cattle and goods delivered the 
<lb/>whole into their hands. He would not even accept 
<lb/>a present for what he had done</p>


	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000608_0003"/><!--pb/@n='3'-->
<ab>
<lb/><!--written up side of p. 3, v. unclear, beginning of each line missing--> any unless perfectly sure of their characters as also of <gap agent="damage"/>
<lb/>supports him David is <gap agent="illegible"/>doing well
</ab>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">I have heard the above particulars from the natives, I am 
<lb/>not yet aware of the whole of the facts But what a 
<lb/>contrast to <persName>Sekhomi</persName>, I have conversed with <persName>Mosheu</persName>
<lb/>and found him a simple humble minded Christian 
<lb/>When I reproved <persName>Sekhomi</persName> for having murdered his 
<lb/>brother he replied "But he killed me first" referring 
<lb/>to the fact of his brother having broken allegiance 
<lb/>And rose up and went off to another part of the town 
<lb/>But afterwards enquiring whether it were true that I saw 
<lb/>all who were dead <unclear cert="high"><del type="strikethrough">alive</del></unclear> still in existence, I replied yes &amp; 
<lb/>you will see your brother and stand to be judged by 
<lb/>his side. He replied "maka hela" his only. <unclear cert="low">Let your</unclear>
<lb/>prayers <unclear cert="low">be made without ceasing for conversion</unclear>
<lb/>of these degraded <unclear cert="high">Heathen</unclear></p>
<lb/><p><persName>Sechele</persName> the chief to whom we have transferred 
<lb/>our labours is an intelligent man, and it is probable 
<lb/>if allowed to dwell in peace will become both rich 
<lb/>and powerful. You would be amused to see his 
<lb/>royal highness <persName>Prince Al.</persName> &amp; not he but a king stand 
<lb/>up to his knees in water and two persons scrubbing 
<lb/>his royal person all over. As a preliminary to 
<lb/>his washing his wardrobe himself. It takes a whole 
<lb/>day to wash an old red coat and a few other <unclear cert="high">duds</unclear> which 
<lb/>if sold to a Jew in London would not realise 5/ 
<lb/>His wives too are fond of European clothing. And as 
<lb/>Mrs <gap agent="damage"/><!-- bottom of page missing--></p>


	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000608_0004"/><!--pb/@n='4'-->
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">instructed to mention. Anything which will make strong 
<lb/>patchwork. If furnished by any of our friends you 
<lb/>may assure them we shall take every pains to make 
<lb/>their gifts of use in the course of Christ. For the labour 
<lb/>paid by their gifts we shall endeavour to pay the 
<lb/>carriage which is always considerable in this 
<lb/>distant region. I have mentioned tools for the 
<lb/>native teachers to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Whish</persName>, they are exceedingly 
<lb/>valuable, the natives are all <unclear cert="high">fond</unclear> of working 
<lb/>with them And as a few I have are too often 
<lb/>lent the station is rather hard put to for mending 
<lb/>sometimes I have bought all or nearly all those</p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent"><!--written sideways on bottom half of letter on address page, end of each line missing-->Proceed with the instructions of * M<gap agent="damage"/>
<lb/>he is furnished with the leading pa<gap agent="damage"/>
<lb/>in a sermon he makes a good addr<gap agent="damage"/>
<lb/>of it Love to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi></persName><gap agent="illegible"/><space extent="1" unit="words"/><space extent="3" unit="chars"/>Affectionately</p> 
<lb/><p rend="right"><space extent="3" unit="words"/>DL.</p>
<!-- note under paragraph in different hand -->
<lb/><note n="*" anchored="true">A native tracker supported by Chris <gap agent="damage"/>
<lb/>Friends in Glasgow</note>

<!--envelope not transcribed-->
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>