<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_002999"><!-- LP120 -->
	<teiHeader xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Remarks on the African Fever on the Lower Zambezi</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">David Livingstone</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2006-10-09</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_002999</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Not Catalogued</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient">Unknown Recipient</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date">12 November 1859</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Unknown</bibl>
				<bibl>Printed Material</bibl><!--1859-11-12--><!--Original:1859-11-12-->
				<bibl>2 pages</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2006-06-23</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Initial Transcription
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_002999_0001"/><!--pb/@n='473'-->
<cb xml:id="p473-colA" n="column a"/><!-- Coding of smallCaps needs to be checked-->
<lb/><p rend="center">ORIGINAL COMMUNICATIONS.</p>
<lb/><p rend="center">REMARKS ON THE AFRICAN <term type="ailment">FEVER</term></p>
<lb/><p rend="center">ON THE <placeName>RIVER ZAMBEZI</placeName>.(<note n="a" place="marginbottom" rend="left" anchored="true"><!--p-->This interesting paper has been forwarded to us with the following 
<lb/>note by Sir James Clark: - 
<lb/><!--/p--><!--p--><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>, - I receive the accompanying paper from Drs. Livingstone and 
<lb/>Kirk, through the Foreign Office, a few days ago. If you agree with me 
<lb/>that it is of sufficient importance to be communicated to the Profession, I 
<lb/>shall feel obliged by its insertion in the <hi rend="italic"> Medical Times and Gazette</hi>
<lb/><!--/p--><!--p-->22 B, Brook-st., Grosvenor sq., NOV. 5, 1859. I am, &amp;c. J. Clark.<!--/p--></note>)</p>
<lb/><p rend="center">By <persName>DAVID LIVINGSTONE</persName><hi rend="smallcaps">AND</hi><persName>JOHN KIRK,</persName> M.D.</p>
<lb/><p>While employed in trying to open up <placeName>Africa</placeName> to the influences 
<lb/>of civilisation and commerce, the first thing that naturally 
<lb/>attracted our attention as Medical men was the <term type="ailment">fever</term>, which 
<lb/>hitherto has proved one of the great barriers to the advances 
<lb/>of Christian nations into the interior of the continent. </p>
<lb/><p>We have enjoyed considerable facilities for observing the 
<lb/><term type="ailment">disease</term> during the last twelve months, not only among those 
<lb/>of the expedition, but likewise among the Portuguese and 
<lb/>natives; and our experience having been very different from 
<lb/>that of others, we deem it desirable to lay the results before 
<lb/>our Medical brethren. </p>
<lb/><p>Our observations are far from being so full as might be 
<lb/>desired, but when travelling in this country, where the grass 
<lb/>towers over head and almost hides the narrow path, it is of 
<lb/>the utmost importance to possess correct views at the 
<w>begin-<lb break="no"/>ning.</w> Our remarks may thus prove serviceable in preventing 
<lb/>others from making a wrong commencement. </p>
<lb/><p>About a month was spent by the Expedition in 
<w>endeavour-<lb break="no"/>ing</w> to find an opening through <placeName>the Delta</placeName>, from the sea to the 
<lb/>main river. </p>
<lb/><p>This part may be described as abounding in mangrove 
<lb/>swamps and damp plains covered with gigantic grasses. 
<lb/>The mangrove swamps emitted a most offensive smell, and 
<lb/>gave us the impression that they were most fitly named, "the 
<lb/>hot-beds of <term type="ailment">fever</term>." </p>
<lb/><p>Above the <placeName>the Delta</placeName> the river is remarkable for the quantity of 
<lb/>fine sand which it carries in its waters, and deposits 
<w>every-<lb break="no"/>where</w> in banks which during about half the year are exposed 
<lb/>to the sun; there is comparatively little mud, and in this 
<lb/>respect as well as in the greater height of its banks which 
<lb/>are also of sand, it differs greatly from the rivers of the west 
<lb/>coast. </p>
<lb/><p>The <placeName>mountains of Meramhalla</placeName>, 4000 feet high appears to 
<lb/>the east of <placeName>Senna</placeName>, and a range of hills on the north bank 
<lb/>of the river stretches from that village up to <placeName>Lupata</placeName>, 
<lb/>above which the country is hilly, and the banks of the river 
<lb/>rocky. </p>
<lb/><p>Warned by the fate of the "Great Niger Expedition," it 
<lb/>was resolved that no unnecessary delay should take place in 
<lb/>the <placeName>the Delta</placeName> and that the prophylactic use of <term type="curative">quinine</term> should be 
<lb/>tried. </p>
<lb/><p>The season chosen for entering the river was the winter 
<lb/>(from May to August), the most healthy time for Europeans, 
<lb/>though not the most favourable for navigation, and during 
<lb/>the stay of the Expedition among the mangroves not a 
<lb/>single case of <term type="ailment">fever</term> occured among the members, or among 
<lb/>the officers and men of the <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, and H.M.S. <hi rend="italic">Hermes</hi>, who 
<lb/>accompanied it. </p>
<lb/><p><term type="curative">Quinine</term> was taken regularly by all the Europeans, with a 
<lb/>single exception, to the amount of two grains in sherry wine 
<lb/>daily; and we were quite disposed to attribute our immunity 
<lb/>to the prophylactic so much praised for its efficacy on the 
<lb/><placeName>Niger</placeName>; although the former experience of one of us suggested 
<lb/>its total inefficiency to ward off an attack. </p>
<lb/><p>Three of our number became affected with incipient 
<w>cin-<lb break="no"/>chonism;</w> in their case the dose was lessened. We seemed 
<lb/>always to be on the verge of cinchonism, as an additional dose 
<lb/>could produce <term type="ailment">deafness</term> and <term type="ailment">ringing in the ears</term> to an intense 
<lb/>degree in the course of a few hours. </p>
<lb/><p>The following is the number of those who escaped without 
<lb/>a single case of sickness, although exposed to hard work in 
<lb/>the sun, and frequently sleeping in the boats in the lower 
<lb/>part of the <placeName>the Delta</placeName>: - 16 officers, 37 seamen, 12 <term type="tribe">Krumen</term>, and 
<lb/>2 boys from <placeName>Sierra Leone.</placeName></p><cb xml:id="p473-colB" n="column b"/>
<lb/><p>Three of our number were left in charge of goods on an 
<lb/>island about twenty miles above the mangrove swamps, but 
<lb/>probably not beyond their influence. The soil was of 
<lb/>stratified sand, with an alluvial layer on the surface, covered 
<lb/>with grasses. The neighbouring country presented the same 
<lb/>aspect as the island, and was similarly constituted. Previous 
<lb/>to this there had been hard work and constant excitement. 
<lb/>Those left on the island, although less exposed, had a 
<w>com-<lb break="no"/>paratively</w> inactive life. They had not been many days alone 
<lb/>when two of their number became sick. </p>
<lb/><p><persName>Mr. B</persName> -- was seized with slight rigors, severe <term type="ailment">headache</term>, 
<lb/><term type="ailment">delirium</term>, with <term type="ailment">contracted pupils</term>. These symptoms were 
<lb/>sudden, and followed a imprudent course of exposure to the 
<lb/>sun. Although removed in a few hours, they speedily 
<lb/>returned after renewed exposure; but this time more severe, 
<lb/>the full <term type="ailment">bounding pulse</term>, <term type="ailment">dry tongue</term>, and <term type="ailment">hot <term type="bodypart">skin</term></term> showing the 
<lb/>intensity of the <term type="ailment">fever.</term>. <term type="ailment">Vomiting</term>, which now commenced, 
<lb/>proved the most troublesome symptom, and became an obstacle 
<lb/>to all treatment, as remedies were not retained beyond a few 
<lb/>seconds. Although the other symptoms abated after twelve 
<lb/>hours, <term type="ailment">vomiting</term> continued, and soon the disease returned in a 
<lb/>more severe form, running on to <term type="ailment">muttering delirium</term>, with 
<lb/>involuntary picking of the bedclothes. </p>
<lb/><p>When on the verge of <term type="ailment">coma</term> remedies began to be retained, 
<lb/>and the action of a large <term type="curative">dose of calomel with jalap resin</term>
<lb/>relieved the <term type="ailment">cerebral disorder</term>, and, by reducing the <term type="ailment"><w>irri-<lb break="no"/>tability</w> of the <term type="bodypart">stomach</term></term>, allowed <term type="curative">quinine</term> to be given. 
<w>Con-<lb break="no"/>valescence</w> was very rapid; in a few days all trace of the 
<lb/>disease had gone. </p>
<lb/><p>A fortnight afterwards <persName>Mr.B</persName> -- was again seized with 
<lb/>the same symptoms, <term type="ailment">vomiting</term> again being the great obstacle, 
<lb/>and, from its continuance after the others had been subdued, 
<lb/>rendering the convalescence slow. <term type="ailment">Loss of memory</term> and 
<lb/><term type="ailment">muscular weakness</term> continued for some time after this attack. 
<lb/>While <persName>Mr.B</persName> -- was sick, <persName>Mr C.L</persName> -- had <term type="ailment">fever</term> also, but 
<lb/>in a very different form, and we did not then recognise the 
<lb/>two as being the same disease. In him the symptoms were 
<lb/>those of a <term type="ailment">cold</term>, such as we see in Europe, -- at first frontal 
<lb/><term type="ailment">headache</term>, <term type="ailment">pain</term> in the <term type="bodypart">back</term> and <term type="bodypart">limbs</term>, lassitude and 
<w>in-<lb break="no"/>difference</w> to what went on around; this state was followed 
<lb/>by one in which he lay without speaking, <term type="ailment">headache</term> had gone, 
<lb/>the pulse was small and thready; the <term type="bodypart">skin</term> at one time 
<lb/>burning hot, at others coated with a clammy perspiration. In 
<lb/>this case slight <term type="ailment">diarrhœa</term> had continued from the beginning. 
<lb/><term type="curative">Quinine</term> was tolerated; but although the constitutional action 
<lb/>was evident, yet the <term type="ailment">fever,</term> did not abate until a <term type="curative">mercurial 
<lb/>purgative</term> had been given. </p>
<lb/><p>These were the first cases of <term type="ailment">fever</term> among us, nor did we 
<lb/>see more for some time afterwards. </p>
<lb/><p>In the month of August all the goods had been conveyed 
<lb/>as far as <placeName>Shupanga</placeName>. Two officers were left there in charge, 
<lb/>while the steam-vessel proceeded to <placeName>Tette</placeName>, taking with her 
<lb/>those who had suffered when at the island. </p>
<lb/><p>At the time the Portuguese were engaged in war against a 
<lb/>party of rebels, and the army being destitute of Medical 
<lb/>appliances of every description, an opportunity was offered of 
<lb/>observing the <term type="ailment">fever</term> and other diseases in their worst forms 
<lb/>among those exposed without proper shelter or food, and in 
<lb/>subjects frequently worn out by consitutional disease. </p>
<lb/><p>The <persName>commanding officer</persName> was the first case we were requested 
<lb/>to see: he had obstinately refused all remedies, but being 
<lb/>then in a state of <term type="ailment">coma</term>, and unable longer to refuse, <term type="curative">an active 
<lb/>purge </term> was given, followed by thirty-grain doses of <term type="curative">quinine</term>, 
<lb/>which soon restored health. In him there had been no other 
<lb/>symptom beyond those of severe consitutional <term type="ailment">fever</term> running 
<lb/>on rapidly to <term type="ailment">coma</term>. This is the type most frequent in the 
<lb/>lower parts of the <placeName>the Delta</placeName>, especially at <placeName>Quillimane</placeName>. In the 
<lb/>vicinity of <placeName>Tette</placeName> it is seldom fatal. The limited experience 
<lb/>we here had seems to indicate that the type once established 
<lb/>has a constant tendency to recur. Should further observation 
<lb/>confirm this, it would become of importance to send all 
<lb/>Europeans on their arrival to higher lands; so that, should 
<lb/>they be subject to <term type="ailment">fever</term>, they might have it in its milder form 
<lb/>first, and carry that with them to the more unhealthy 
<lb/>localities. </p>
<lb/><p>While the party at <placeName>Shupanga</placeName> enjoyed good health, 
<w>not-<lb break="no"/>withstanding</w> the partial discontinuance of <term type="curative">quinine</term>, several 
<lb/>cases happened on board the steam-vessel. We may mention 
<lb/>that the accomodation on board was both very scanty and 
<lb/>very uncomfortable. Water running into the cabin while the 
<lb/>vessel was under steam, so as to keep the beds constantly wet 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_002999_0002"/><!--pb/@n='474'-->
<lb/><cb xml:id="p474-colA" n="column a"/>beneath; fortunately the weather was dry, or the rain would 
<lb/>have poured in from above also, as we subsequently 
<w>expe-<lb break="no"/>rienced.</w></p>
<lb/><p><persName>Mr.R</persName> --, the engineer, had taken <term type="curative">quinine</term> with unvarying 
<lb/>regularity, had an excellent appetite, and seemed to enjoy 
<lb/>the climate; in working the engine he was obliged to see the 
<lb/>fire lighted at 2 1/2 a.m., in order to have steam by 7 a.m. </p>
<lb/><p><persName>An officer</persName> had shifted his bed through the night, so as to 
<lb/>prevent <persName>Mr. R</persName> -- getting his clothes, and he proceeded to 
<lb/>light the fire in his shirt; the consequence was <term type="ailment">pains</term> all over 
<lb/>the body and <term type="bodypart">limbs</term>, the <term type="bodypart">bones</term> being especially sore, the <term type="bodypart">face</term>
<lb/>flushed, <term type="bodypart">eyes</term> suffused, <term type="ailment">headache</term>, and quick pulse. The 
<lb/><term type="bodypart">bowels</term> had been regular, and the <term type="bodypart">tongue</term> clean. A <term type="curative">pill</term><w>com-<lb break="no"/>posed</w> of resin of jalap, calomel, rhubarb, and <term type="curative">quinine</term>, which 
<lb/>had formerly been found efficient in <term type="ailment">fever</term>, was given, more as 
<lb/>a precautionary measure, than from a belief that this was a 
<lb/>case of the complaint. It seemed more a <term type="ailment">common cold</term> than 
<lb/>the African <term type="ailment">fever</term>. As soon as the remedy had operated, the 
<lb/>symptoms abated. <term type="curative">Quinine</term> was given, and one dose of 
<lb/>ten grains produced severe cinchonism, from which, when 
<lb/>he recovered, he was quite well without loss of strength. </p>
<lb/><p>Towards the end of the rainy season the members of the 
<lb/>Expedition were divided, those who had previously suffered 
<lb/>from <term type="ailment">fever</term> remained at <placeName>Tette</placeName>, while we went down the 
<lb/><placeName>Zambezi</placeName> to the sea, and explored the River <placeName><choice><sic>Shine</sic><corr>Shire</corr></choice></placeName>, both very 
<lb/>unhealthy districts. While one of us was exposed to sun 
<lb/>and rain navigating the vessel, and ashore superintending 
<lb/>the wooding, the other was engaged botanising among grass 
<lb/>jungles and mangrove swamps. Yet both of us escaped 
<lb/>entirely. The use of <term type="curative">quinine</term> had been completely abandoned, 
<lb/>and we are inclined to attribute our good health to the regular 
<lb/>and active exercise which both these occupations imply. In 
<lb/>this respect our experience corresponds with that of the 
<lb/>Portuguese residents, who assert that while actively 
<w>em-<lb break="no"/>ployed</w> they enjoy good health. </p>
<lb/><p>While we explored the high lands around Lake Shirwa the 
<lb/>steam-vessel was left in the River <placeName><choice><sic>Shine</sic><corr>Shire</corr></choice></placeName>, under the care of 
<lb/><persName>Quartermaster Walker</persName>. We were absent twenty-four days, 
<lb/><persName>Walker</persName> was seized with <term type="ailment">fever</term> the day we left: it commenced 
<lb/>suddenly, though he taken <term type="curative">quinine</term> regularly. On our 
<lb/>return we found that he had been <term type="ailment">delirious</term> most of the time. 
<lb/>and the <term type="ailment">fever</term> had shown no signs of abating; but the action 
<lb/>of purgatives, followed by <term type="curative">quinine</term>, soon restored health, and 
<lb/>in subsequent attacks, when at the sea-coast, among the 
<lb/>mangroves, no difficulty was experienced in cutting short the 
<lb/>attacks at the beginning. </p>
<lb/><p>Our own experience in the high lands between the <placeName><choice><sic>Shine</sic><corr>Shire</corr></choice></placeName>
<lb/>and <placeName>Lake Shirwa</placeName> during twenty-four days, when we were 
<lb/>exposed in the early hours to the dew from the long grass, 
<lb/>continuing the march without interruption throughout the 
<lb/>remainder of the day over rough country under the tropical 
<lb/>sun, and then sleeping in the open air, and yet enjoying 
<lb/>perfect health, as did also the natives who were with us, 
<lb/>shows clearly that there exists within a short distance of the 
<lb/>coast a healthy region well suited for the residence of Europeans. </p>
<lb/><p>This region is elevated above the sea from 3000 to 4000 
<lb/>feet, and shut off from the coast lands by the range of high 
<lb/>mountains to the east of <placeName>Lake Shirwa</placeName>. It is of easy access 
<lb/>by the <placeName><choice><sic>Shine</sic><corr>Shire</corr></choice></placeName>, which flows to the foot of the hills, and is 
<lb/>navigable the whole distance. To the north, the southern 
<lb/>extremity of a chain of lakes, which extend far into the 
<lb/>interior of the continent, reach within thirty miles of the 
<lb/>River <placeName><choice><sic>Shine</sic><corr>Shire</corr></choice></placeName>. This elavated region may be looked on as the 
<lb/>entrance, by means of these inland seas, to a great part of 
<lb/><placeName>Central Africa</placeName>, cut off hitherto from communication with 
<lb/>European nations by the unhealthy lands which bound the 
<lb/>coasts. </p>
<lb/><p>The result of our experience has been to discontinue the 
<lb/>daily use of <term type="curative">quinine</term>. It had been persevered in long after 
<lb/>the conviction of the members had been against its 
<w>prophy-<lb break="no"/>lactic</w> power. It is our conviction that we owe our escape 
<lb/>from the disease far more to the good diet provided for us by 
<lb/>H.M. Government than to the use of <term type="curative">quinine</term>. We have 
<lb/>been as fully exposed to the malarious influence as any party 
<lb/>is likely to be. The vessel in which we have to navigate 
<lb/>is one which takes in so much water that our beds are 
<w>con-<lb break="no"/>stantly</w> damp, and often rotten beneath, with a quantity of 
<lb/>water in the bilge of the ship. Yet we have found the <term type="ailment">fever</term>
<lb/>quite amenable to treatment when taken early, and attention 
<lb/>paid to any local congestions which may manifest themselves. 
<lb/><cb xml:id="p474-colB" n="column b"/>Let it not be thought that we undervalue <term type="curative">quinine</term>, to it we 
<lb/>trust for the removal of the disease when given after 
<w>purga-<lb break="no"/>tives;</w> in all forms of the <term type="ailment">fever</term> we have found it of the 
<lb/>greatest value, and three does have always proved sufficient 
<lb/>to induce the constitutional action even in those who have not 
<lb/>been taking it previously. </p>
<lb/><p>We have found the <term type="ailment">fever</term> assuming a formidable type only 
<lb/>when permitted to go on unchecked for some time in those 
<lb/>exposed to great <term type="ailment">fatigue</term>, damp, and <term type="ailment">poor diet</term>, or when the 
<lb/>irritable state of the <term type="bodypart">stomach</term> prevented the administration of 
<lb/><term type="curative">quinine</term>. </p>
<lb/><p>In regard to the complications most frequently seen, among 
<lb/>ourselves <term type="ailment">vomiting</term> has been the most troublesome, and 
<w>blister-<lb break="no"/>ing</w> over the <term type="bodypart">stomach</term> has seemed the best means of stopping 
<lb/>it. We have fortunately escaped without more serious 
<lb/><term type="ailment">inflammatory lesions of the internal organs</term>; but among the 
<lb/>Portuguese two cases have been observed with <term type="ailment">pneumonia</term>; 
<lb/>both proved fatal - the <term type="curative">tartarate of antimony</term> seemed to have 
<lb/>no effect, while <term type="curative">stimulants</term> were equally powerless when once 
<lb/>sinking had commenced. <term type="ailment">Enlargements of the <term type="bodypart">spleen</term></term>, when 
<lb/>of recent date, have yielded quickly to the use of the <term type="curative">sulphate 
<lb/>of iron and quinine</term>. </p>
<lb/><p>The ship's company, consisting of <term type="tribe">Krumen</term>, have showed no 
<lb/>greater immunity than the Europeans. The experiment of 
<lb/><term type="curative">quinine</term> was made with them, but its prophylactic action 
<lb/>proved equally feeble as in our own case. </p>
<lb/><p>In future Expeditions of a similar nature, we beg to suggest 
<lb/>that the work of the contracting ship-builders be more 
<lb/>scrupulously tested than it had been in our case, when the 
<lb/>defects once observed completely baffled all attempts at 
<lb/>remedy. </p>
<lb/><p><placeName>Zambesi</placeName>, July 1859 </p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>