<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_002515">
	<teiHeader xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Roderick Impey Murchison</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">David Livingstone</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2008-07-02</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_002515</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Royal Geographical Society, Archives, DL 4/4/6</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">1916</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient">Roderick Impey Murchison</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date">2 February 1867</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Bemba</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: unknown</handNote>
				<handNote xml:id="hand02">Scribe: unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2008-07-02</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>Initial Transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2009-01-29</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Christopher Lawrence</name>Proof by Chris Lawrence
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_002515_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Bemba</placeName> 2<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">nd</hi></hi> February </p>
<lb/><p rend="right">1867</p>
<lb/><p><hi rend="underline">Private</hi></p>
<lb/><p>My Dear <persName>Sir Roderick</persName></p>
<lb/><p>This is the first 
<w>oppor-<lb break="no"/>tunity</w> I have had of sending a letter to the Coast 
<lb/>and it is by a party of black Arab slave 
<lb/>traders from <placeName>Bagamoio</placeName> near <placeName>Zanzibar</placeName>. They 
<lb/>had penetrated here for the first time and came 
<lb/>by a shorter way than we did. In my Despatch 
<lb/>to <persName>Lord Clarendon</persName> I give but a meagre geographical 
<lb/>report because the traders would not stay 
<lb/>more than half a day but having written that 
<lb/>through the night I persuaded them to give 
<lb/>me an hour or two this morning - and if 
<lb/>yours is fuller than his Lordship's you will 
<lb/>know how to manage. I mentioned to him 
<lb/>that I could not go round the North end of 
<lb/><placeName>Lake Nyassa</placeName> because the Johanna men would 
<lb/>have fled at first sight of danger - and they 
<lb/>did actually flee on the mere report of the 
<lb/>acts of the terrible Mazitu at its Southern 
<lb/>extremity. Had I got them fairly beyond the 
<lb/>Lake they would have stuck to me but so long 
<lb/>as we had Arab slave parties passing us they 
<lb/>were not to be depended on - and they were 
<lb/>such inveterate thieves it was quite a relief 
<lb/>to get rid of them, though my following was reduced 
<lb/>to nine African boys - freed ones from a 
<lb/>school at <add place="above"><placeName>Nassick</placeName></add><placeName>Bombay</placeName>. I intended to cross at 
<lb/>the middle of the Lake, but all the Arabs fled 
<lb/>as soon as they heard that the English were coming, 
<lb/>and the owners of two dhows now on the 
<lb/>Lake kept them out of sight lest I should burn 
<lb/>them as slavers. I remained at the town of 
<lb/><placeName>Mataka</placeName>, which is on the water shed between Coast 
<lb/>and Lake &amp; about 50 miles from the latter. <choice><reg>h</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>ere are 
<lb/>at least a thousand houses and he is the most 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_002515_0002"/><!--pb/@n='2'-->
<lb/>powerful chief in the Country. I was in his 
<lb/>district which extends to the Lake from the middle 
<lb/>of July to the end of September. He was very 
<lb/>anxious that some of the liberated boys should 
<lb/>remain with him and I tried my best to induce 
<lb/>them but in vain. He wished to be shewn how 
<lb/>to make use of his cattle in agriculture. I promised 
<lb/>to try &amp; get some other boys acquainted with Indian 
<lb/>agriculture for him. That is the best point I 
<lb/>have seen for an influential station &amp; <persName>Mataka</persName>
<lb/>shewed some sense of right when his people went 
<lb/>without his knowledge to plunder at a part of 
<lb/>the Lake<reg>;</reg> he ordered the captives &amp; cattle to be sent back. 
<lb/>This was his own spontaneous act &amp; it took 
<lb/>place before our arrival but I accidentally 
<lb/>saw the strangers. They consisted of fifty four 
<lb/>women<reg>,</reg> children<reg>,</reg> about a dozen boys &amp; 30 head 
<lb/>cattle &amp; calves. I gave him a trinket in memory 
<lb/>of his good conduct at which he was delighted 
<lb/>for it had not been without opposition that he 
<lb/>carried out his orders &amp; he shewed the token 
<lb/>of my approbation in triumph.</p>
<lb/><p>Leaving the shores of the lake we endeavoured 
<lb/>to ascend <persName>Kirk's</persName> range but the people below were 
<lb/>afraid of those above and it was only after <choice><sic>and</sic><corr>an</corr></choice> old friend 
<lb/><persName>Katosa</persName> or <persName>Kiemasusa</persName> had turned out with his 
<lb/>wives to carry our extra loads that we got up. 
<lb/>It is only the edge of a plateau - peopled by various 
<lb/>tribes of <term type="tribe">Manganja</term> who had never been engaged 
<lb/>in slaving - in fact they had driven away a 
<lb/>lot of Arab slave traders a short time before. 
<lb/>We used to think them all <term type="tribe">Maravi</term> but <persName>Katosa</persName>
<lb/>is the only <term type="tribe">Maravi</term> chief we know. The <term type="tribe">Kanthunda</term>
<lb/>or "climbers" live on the mountains that rise out 
<lb/>of the plateau. <term type="tribe">Chipeta</term> live more on the plains 
<lb/>there. <term type="tribe">Echewa</term> still further North<reg>.</reg> We went West 
<lb/>among a very hospitable people till we thought 
<lb/>we were past the longitude of the <term type="tribe">Mazitu</term> - then 
<lb/>turned North &amp; all but walked into the hands 
<lb/>of a marauding party of that people. After a rather 
<lb/>zig-zag course we took up at the point we had left 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_002515_0003"/><!--pb/@n='3'-->
<lb/>in 1863 or say 20′ west of <placeName>Chimanga's</placeName> - crossed the 
<lb/><placeName>Loangwa</placeName> in 12° 45′ south, as it flows in the bed of an 
<lb/>ancient Lake - and after emerging out of this great 
<lb/>hollow ascended the plateau of <placeName>Lobisa</placeName> at the southern 
<lb/>limit of 11° South. The hills on one part of it rise 
<lb/>up to 6600 feet above the sea. While in the lowlands 
<lb/>I could easily supply our party with meat, large game 
<lb/>being abundant but up on these Highlands of the 
<lb/><placeName>Babisa</placeName> none were to be found. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he country 
<w>depopu-<lb break="no"/>lated</w> by the slaving in which the people engaged is 
<lb/>now a vast forest with here &amp; there at wide intervals 
<lb/>a miserable hamlet. The grain is sown in little 
<lb/>patches in the forest &amp; they had nothing to sell. We 
<lb/>had now a good deal of actual gnawing hunger 
<lb/>as day after day we trod the sloppy dripping 
<lb/>forests which yield some wretched wild fruits &amp; 
<lb/>lots of mushrooms. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice> woman can collect a 
<lb/>loads - 1/2 a hundred weight &amp; after cooking pounds 
<lb/>them into what they call porridge. <choice><reg>B</reg><orig>b</orig></choice>ut woe is me! 
<lb/>they are good only for producing dreams of the roast 
<lb/>beef of bygone days. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey collect six kinds &amp; 
<lb/>reject about ten - some as large as the crown 
<lb/>of one<reg>'</reg>s hat. When we got to the <placeName>Chambeze</placeName> as the 
<lb/><placeName>Zambese</placeName> is here called it was true to its character of 
<lb/>abundant animal life in its waters &amp; on its banks we soon got an antelope. We crossed it in 10 ° 34′. 
<lb/>It was flooded with clear water but the lines of 
<lb/>bushy trees which shewed its actual banks were not 
<lb/>more than forty yards apart. We came here on the 
<lb/>last day of January - a stockaded village with three 
<lb/>lines of defence - the inner one having a deep dry 
<lb/>ditch round it. I think if I am not mistaken 
<lb/>that we are on the watershed we seek between the 
<lb/><placeName>Chambeze</placeName> &amp; <placeName>Luapula</placeName>. I have not had anytime 
<lb/>to take observations as it is the rainy season 
<lb/>and almost always cloudy but we shall rest a 
<lb/>little here and get some flesh on our bones. 
<lb/>We are about 10° 10′ South &amp; 31° 50′ East. Alt. 
<lb/>about 4500 feet above the sea. The <placeName>Loapula</placeName> or 
<lb/><placeName>Luapula</placeName> is said to be very large but I hope to 
<lb/>send fuller information from <placeName>Tanganyika</placeName>. 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_002515_0004"/><!--pb/@n='4'-->
<lb/>I have done all the hunting myself - have enjoyed 
<lb/>good health, &amp; no touch of fever - but we lost 
<lb/>all our medicine - the sorest loss of goods I 
<lb/>ever sustained. So I am hoping if fever comes 
<lb/>to fend it of by native remedies &amp; trust in 
<lb/>in the watchful care of a Higher Power. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he chief 
<lb/>here seems a jolly frank person but unless 
<lb/>the country is insecure I don<reg>'</reg>t see the use of 
<lb/>his lines of circumvallation. He presented a 
<lb/>cow on our arrival &amp; a huge elephant<reg>'</reg>s tusk 
<lb/>because I had sat on it.</p>
<lb/><p>I have had no news whatever from the coast 
<lb/>since we left it but hope for letters and our 
<lb/>second stock of goods - a small one - at <placeName>Ujiji</placeName>. 
<lb/>I have been unable to send anything either - 
<lb/>some letters I had written in hopes of meeting 
<lb/>an Arab slave trader but they all "skedaddled" as 
<lb/>soon as they heard that the "English were coming<reg>".</reg>
<lb/>I could not get any information as to the 
<lb/>route followed by the Portuguese in going to <placeName>Cazembe's</placeName>
<lb/>till we were on the <placeName>Babisa</placeName> plateau. It was then 
<lb/>pointed out that they had gone to the Westward of 
<lb/>that which from the <placeName>Loangwa</placeName> valley seems a range 
<lb/>of mountains. The makers of maps have 
<lb/>placed <add place="above">it</add> much too far East. The repetition of 
<lb/>names of rivers which is common in this 
<lb/>country probably misled them. There are four 
<lb/><placeName>Loangwas</placeName> flowing into <placeName>Lake Nyassa</placeName>.</p>
<lb/><p>Would you kindly say to <persName>Captain Richards</persName>
<lb/>that I had to draw some rifles &amp; ammunition 
<lb/>from the H.M.S. Wasp and I shall feel obliged if 
<lb/>he makes that right. Also that <persName>Casella</persName> has 
<lb/>given me Aneroids without a single note or 
<lb/>hint as to their errors - not a vestige of error 
<lb/>of either boiling point or common thermometers 
<lb/>I tried them as the level of the sea - "<hi rend="underline">Maker to the 
<lb/>Admiralty</hi>" seems to counterbalance the care with which 
<lb/>he used to test them all at <placeName>Kew</placeName>. He shall hear or it yet. </p>
<lb/><p rend="center">With kindest regards to <persName>Lady Murchison</persName>.</p>
<lb/><p rend="center">I am ever affectionately yours </p>
<lb/><p rend="center"><persName>David Livingstone</persName></p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>