<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P5 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000672">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Robert Moffat 1</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Robert Moffat 1, [4 May?] 1849</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London, UK</pubPlace>
				<publisher>University College London</publisher>
				<date>2013</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000672</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">University of London. School of Oriental and African Studies; CWM/LMS/Africa/Odds - Livingstone, Box 4-02</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0203</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Moffat, Robert 1, 1795-1883</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1849-05-04">[4 May?] 1849</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">[Kolobeng]</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="und">Undetermined</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2013-03-19</date>
				<name xml:id="KS">Kathryn Simpson</name>Initial transcription and XML encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2013-10-26</date>
				<name xml:id="AM">Anne Martin</name>Proofreading.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2013-12-05</date>
				<name xml:id="HFB">Heather F. Ball</name>Additional encoding.
            
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000672_0001"><!--pb/@n='1r'--></pb>
<lb/><p><!-- The number 2 (encircled) appears here. It does not appear to be in Livingstone's hand AM -->My Dear Father</p>
<lb/><p>Yours by <persName>Ratseki</persName> came to hand about a week after <persName>Mary</persName>
<lb/>left - the accounts came the day before her departure and
<lb/>being then in the hurry of packing &amp; loading I only looked to see who
<lb/>was debtor &amp; who creditor. After returning from the <term type="tribe">Wanketse</term>
<lb/>I looked over the whole and as you <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> claim perfection
<lb/>you will not be surprised though in my queries &amp;c I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice>
<lb/>exhibit the same virtue - 12<choice><abbr>/</abbr><expan>shillings</expan></choice> are put down as sent to
<lb/><persName>Mr Helmore</persName> by a man whose name nearly <unclear cert="low">blotted</unclear> out seems
<lb/>to be <persName>Mokitlan</persName> - Have you any recollection as to what this
<lb/>money was sent for - or if any other money was sent 
<lb/>at <supplied cert="high">the</supplied> same time - I have a distinct recollection of having paid
<lb/>off the money sent by <persName>Mebaloe</persName> viz 24 dollars &amp; writing a    
<lb/>note to <persName>Mr Helmore</persName> to use his influence with <persName>Moyahe</persName> to furnish
<lb/>the hiefers <persName>Mebaloe</persName> wished. Do you know <persName>Mokitlan</persName> - If you
<lb/>see him will you be kind enough to ask him about it
<lb/>Have you any note of the 12<choice><abbr>/</abbr><expan>shillings</expan></choice> perhaps <persName>Mebaloe</persName>'s was sent at 
<lb/>same time - I have no recollection of sending any money except for
<lb/>that of <persName>Mebaloe</persName><choice><abbr>viz.</abbr><expan cert="high">videlicet</expan></choice> 24 dollars.
<lb/>A Khoodoo's skin 6<choice><abbr>/</abbr><expan>shillings</expan></choice> we only got a portion of it. I mention
<lb/>this that you may try &amp; recollect - they are of course dearer
<lb/>with you than they are here but surely not 12<choice><abbr>/</abbr><expan>shillings</expan></choice>- The chue iron 
<lb/>was not paid for. I have three pairs of tongs - One I took with
<lb/>me from <placeName><settlement type="village">Mabotsa</settlement></placeName> because I had been at all the trouble
<lb/>of carrying bellows &amp;c. in and I had not a single pair - The
<lb/>other pair are those charged in the account and the third
    
       

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000672_0002"><!--pb/@n='1v'--></pb>
<lb/>a small pair I am not sure whether I got them from you or from
<lb/><placeName><settlement type="village">Mabotsa</settlement></placeName> - I have a distinct recollection of the first pair for they were
<lb/>of this shape <!-- figure: drawing of a pair of tongs --> &amp; I cut the nose off in the belief that I should
<lb/>make a better use of them than <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> E</persName><!-- unsure if this is edwards or elliot --> would and they in my
<lb/>opinion were society's property. I have besides two very small
<lb/>pairs &amp; no more. If the idea I had formed of them being society's
<lb/>property <del type="cancelled">I shall p</del> is incorrect I shall pay them - I think
<lb/>I left 5 or 6 pairs with him &amp; only took what I thought least
<lb/>useful - Am sorry to see myself in debt again. Would
<lb/>like much better if it were you - If <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi><choice><abbr>M</abbr><expan>Moffat</expan></choice></persName> has put
<lb/>as much in her will for me. I make it over to you in
<lb/>order to get free, even if it is £100 I shall give it you
<lb/>for the £30. I wish you would take a peep into the
<lb/>document &amp; see how much I am to get - and when we
<lb/>have made the arrangement I shall no longer be wishing
<lb/>that she may cut her stick. <persName>Mary</persName> will tell you that
<lb/>we shall need tea coffee &amp; rice should you be sending to
<lb/><placeName><settlement type="town">Colesberg</settlement></placeName>. I mentioned glass and may add soap. But we
<lb/>shall not probably need anything else. except hiefers and
<lb/>I feel very unwilling to buy anything except what is
<lb/>absolutely necessary till I get out of debt- I would send
<lb/>for a pair of ploughs from <persName>Wilkie</persName> but for it - Extra
<lb/>tugs &amp; <unclear cert="low">Mirrles</unclear> which things I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> know make the
<lb/>ploughs £4.15 each. Now if I could send £12 or perhaps
<lb/>£11 for one as usually made &amp; another extra strong &amp; 
<lb/>a wheel <del type="strikethrough">they</del><add place="below">˄</add><add place="above">one if not both</add> would surely do for this country - I remember
    
       

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000672_0003"><!--pb/@n='2r'--></pb>
<lb/>the ploughs used in <placeName><country>Scotland</country></placeName> have no wheels but are all iron
<lb/><persName>Sechele</persName> wants one- Do you think it would be will to order
<lb/>wheels for both or simply to try how the <term type="nationality">Scotch</term> plough at
<lb/>£4.15 will do for this country - Or if <add place="above">of</add> extra strength where
<lb/>ought the extra strength to be put - I feel at a loss on this
<lb/>point - My father lives near to <persName>Wilkie</persName> &amp; purposes to get one
<lb/>for us ― Although in debt I feel strongly inclined to
<lb/>order one for £6 If you are sending money to <placeName><country>England</country></placeName>
<lb/>this year can you let me have so much of it, 5<choice><abbr>/</abbr><expan>shillings</expan></choice> goes
<lb/>a good way in iron in <placeName><country>Scotland</country></placeName>- perhaps that on
<lb/>the beam so as to make the whole £5 will be enough
<lb/>If you are not sending we can wait another year</p>
<lb/><p>I never made any remarks on <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Elliot</persName><supplied cert="high">'</supplied>s letter because
<lb/>I was quite ignorant of the matter. A circular sent some
<lb/>time before about the reduction of the sum expended on <placeName><bloc>Africa</bloc></placeName>
<lb/>with the request to hear our opinion on the subject induced
<lb/>me to tell them what I had seen - in <placeName><settlement type="town">Algoa Bay</settlement></placeName>, &amp;c.
<lb/>and I expressed the opinion that the colony was no longer
<lb/>a missionary field - and the sum proposed was quite
<lb/>enough if missionaries now in the colony would only
<lb/>come on to the regions which could still claim the
<lb/>help of missionary societies - I compared the supplies
<lb/>of <placeName><settlement type="town">Algoa Bay</settlement></placeName> - <placeName><settlement type="town">Uitenhage</settlement></placeName> - <placeName><settlement type="town">Graaf<supplied>f</supplied> Reinet</settlement></placeName><placeName><settlement type="town">Colesberg</settlement></placeName> with
<lb/>certain villages at home, and felt quite certain those
<lb/>at home had not <choice><orig>ₑ⁄₃</orig><reg>1/3</reg></choice> of the supply. I could not speak of
<lb/>other places. It is well you did what you have done 
    
       

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000672_0004"><!--pb/@n='2v'--></pb>
<lb/>If we are not in the black books with our own consciences
<lb/>we may whistle oer the <unclear cert="low">lave</unclear> o't whoever is pleased or grumpy
<lb/>the arrangement with the <add place="inline">˄</add><add place="above">small</add> rifle cannot be made. I had
<lb/>written you twice &amp; <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> no answer about the ivory. The
<lb/>letter in which you desired me to sell it came a little too late
<lb/>and I wished to get your property out of the way of the
<lb/><choice><sic>boers</sic><corr>Boers</corr></choice>. We thought then they might be wicked enough
<lb/>to come<supplied cert="high">.</supplied></p>
<lb/><p>The note which puzzled the <choice><sic>boers</sic><corr>Boers</corr></choice><supplied cert="high">'</supplied><term type="bodypart">brains</term> was written
<lb/>by me. on the morning they came - that being the same morning
<lb/>that we heard of the sad circumstance mentioned in my
<lb/>last - I asked <add place="below">˄</add><add place="above"><persName>Sechele</persName></add> himself if the report of his connection
<lb/>with the woman were true as the people were talking of it
<lb/>he replied by saying I shall ask her and sent his uncle
<lb/>to her. She refused at first to tell but at last said
<lb/>that he had himself been to her twice on the occasion of this
<lb/>visit of <persName><unclear cert="low">Sentuke</unclear></persName> - She sent his uncle to tell me the whole
<lb/>&amp; said he had fallen by the temptation of Satan. He could not
<lb/>deny it that he had gone on that occasion and did not
<lb/>wish as he was conscious of guilt to press her to tell
<lb/>of any one else - the law being in that case death - Do
<lb/>not give me up because of this - I shall never give up <persName>Jesus</persName>
<lb/>you &amp; I will stand before him together &amp;c. The conclusion
<lb/>to which I came immediately was he has apostatized
<lb/>and if he has become our enemy I may as well leave
    
       

	<pb n="0005" facs="liv_000672_0005"><!--pb/@n='3r'--></pb>
<lb/>2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> sheet
<lb/>and try some other tribe. <persName>Mary</persName> said - Let us both go now - I answered
<lb/>him by saying that the blame must not be put on Satan - He had
<lb/>done it of his own free will and since he had of his own
<lb/>free will forsaken the laws of <persName>Christ</persName>. Why not tell it at the time
<lb/>and not continue to appear as one of his people when in his
<lb/><term type="bodypart">heart</term> he knew he was serving another. About <del type="cancelled">two</del><add place="above">one</add> hour<del type="cancelled">s</del>
<lb/>after that the Boers came and the same man was sent down
<lb/>to request me to write a note to them to the effect that though
<lb/>he did not come to see them he thanked them for their message
<lb/>that morning. (They had sent a message in the morning before they
<lb/>came about their object in coming) The man came to me
<lb/>and said he is thankful for the message <add place="below">˄</add><add place="above">you sent</add> and wishes you
<lb/>to write it out for him — I wrote a few sentences in
<lb/>Sitchuana similar to the above answer, and to the best <!-- Should Sitchuana be tagged as a language? HB 12-5-13 -->
<lb/>of my recollection they might be thus "You have not sinned
<lb/>against me but against <persName>Jesus</persName>. You must not blame
<lb/>Satan for you have broke<supplied cert="high">n</supplied> the laws of Jesus of your
<lb/>own accord. And you ought to have told me when you
<lb/>did so or when you concluded to obey him no longer
<lb/>My <term type="bodypart">heart</term> is broken, first <persName>Isack</persName> - then you - I can
<lb/>no longer be a teacher here." without opening it he
<lb/>sent it to the Boers - <persName>Sechele</persName> never dreamed it was
<lb/>for him - For when I asked him after reading yours
<lb/>what he had done with the note I had written on the morning
<lb/>the <choice><sic>boers</sic><corr>Boers</corr></choice> came he instantly replied I sent it over to them
<lb/>they were on the other side of the <placeName><settlement type="village">Kolobeng</settlement></placeName> - I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice>

	<pb n="0006" facs="liv_000672_0006"><!--pb/@n='3v'--></pb>
<lb/>wonder <persName>Edwards</persName> was required to make it out - My <term type="bodypart">heart</term> was
<lb/>full of conflicting emotions but not of the sort he conjectured
<lb/>Our connection with him is of a very different sort from
<lb/>that which existed between <persName><unclear cert="medium">Mosielele</unclear></persName> &amp; us or that which
<lb/>prevails there now. We have no contention or wrangling
<lb/>or <unclear cert="low">petting</unclear>. He never attempted to justify himself in sin Nor
<lb/>would he care although <persName>Isaac</persName> were in Davy Jones locker
<lb/>He used to coax <persName>Isaac</persName> to read with him by giving him food
<lb/>but the gentleman interfered disagreeably between <persName>Paul</persName> &amp; him (<unclear cert="medium">I</unclear>)<!-- not sure about this, might be and 'I' or an 'S' -->
<lb/>and his conduct generally has made him anything but
<lb/>liked among the people — <persName>Sechele</persName> is suspended of course
<lb/>from fellowship and will be so even though he should
<lb/>walk with propriety till a considerable time after the woman
<lb/>brings forth - - That which made me believe his professions
<lb/>of sorrow were sincere was he never in the least swerved
<lb/>in his conduct towards us, nor yet in his general <w>deport-
<lb break="no"/>-ment</w>. When we thought that it was all over with us
<lb/>here we thought he had apostatized completely and as such
<lb/>usually do would become our enemy &amp; fight against us. And
<lb/>as we have nothing here apart from working for <persName>Jesus</persName>'
<lb/>cause it would be folly to remain with our hands bound
<lb/>Even now I think that a few months absence from 
<lb/>them occasionally will be beneficial. <term type="ailment">Hunger</term> is very
<lb/>great &amp; all the attention is taken up in caring for the 
<lb/><term type="bodypart">body</term>. School is very thin &amp; so is the church generally
<lb/>Now we have neither printing nor translating
    
       

	<pb n="0007" facs="liv_000672_0007"><!--pb/@n='4r'--></pb>
<lb/>I could work at other things but whatever they might be it
<lb/>would not be Missionary work. It would be merely passing the
<lb/>time, so I begin to think if another station were in existence
<lb/>on which to spend a part of the year - it might tend to
<lb/>the furtherance of the gospel. Here we have tried every mode 
<lb/>of illustration I could think of. But though sometimes we
<lb/>see symptoms which encourage I feel afraid they may
<lb/>look upon the whole affair as one which will always
<lb/>be carried on here whether they heed it or not. <persName>Sebitoane</persName>
<lb/>a chief a little north of the Lake is called a <term type="tribe">Letibele</term> but seems
<lb/>to speak somewhat like the <term type="tribe">Bamapela</term> - He has a large
<lb/>tribe &amp; is enlarging it still more by killing neighbouring
<lb/>chieftains &amp; occupying their places among their people - He
<lb/>lifted the <term type="tribe">Bakwain</term> cattle - not <persName>Mosilikatse</persName> .- but before
<lb/>surrounding the town he gave orders to his people, to spare
<lb/>the children of <persName>Mocoasele</persName> - <persName>Sechele</persName>'s father who was then
<lb/>dead. <persName>Sechele</persName> had been knocked down by a <foreign xml:lang="und">molamu</foreign> but
<lb/>not speared. When they saw him in the morning they
<lb/>took him to <persName>Sebitoane</persName> - Who thanked them for sparing
<lb/>him - Taking him with him to the <term type="tribe">Bamangwato</term>, the 
<lb/>then chief <persName>Kame</persName> offered to redeem <persName>Sechele</persName> with a large
<lb/>bag of beads he had purchased from the <term type="tribe">Malokane</term> - <persName>Sebitoane</persName>
<lb/>asked <persName>Sechele</persName> if he was quite willing to go with him. If he was
<lb/>he would treat him as his son &amp;c. but if not he would 
<lb/>allow him to go. <persName>Sechele</persName>'s mother was <term type="ailment">foot sore</term> so
<lb/><persName>Sechele</persName> said to him you see my mother is unable to 
<lb/>go any farther and though you offer to treat me kindly
<lb/>in your country I should like to live in my own land
    
       

	<pb n="0008" facs="liv_000672_0008"><!--pb/@n='4v'--></pb>
<lb/>Let me save my mother &amp; return I shall consider that kindness
<lb/>enough. <persName>Sebitoane</persName> said very well since you <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> like to come
<lb/>to me, take these nine head of cattle &amp; return — He has one of
<lb/><persName>Sechele</persName>'s brothers with him now &amp; often asks for <persName>Sechele</persName> and
<lb/>the latter feels very anxious to visit his former benefactor.
<lb/>When we go he sends a present to him by us. Seven men
<lb/>have come from the Lake inviting us to come. We may
<lb/>find an open door there though the Eastern door seems shut
<lb/>Am glad <persName>Robert</persName><!-- figure of line inside a rectangle here, ks --> seems to give himself so heartily to the cause
<lb/>of <persName>Christ</persName> &amp; humanity. That<supplied cert="high">'</supplied>s the thing - the day is coming 
<lb/>and maybe near when he whom his Lord approveth <del type="strikethrough">will</del>
<lb/>will have <del type="strikethrough">the</del> approbation of the Universe - Dillydallying
<lb/>potbellied predikants will have no distinctive buttonholes
<lb/>then. You will see the paper I have penned for the 
<lb/><placeName><settlement type="city">Cape Town</settlement></placeName> Mail- I must request you to look over it
<lb/>And if you think it wrong rub out - Nemo (nobody) the signature
<lb/>may perhaps be blotted out if you dislike it. Also the address
<lb/>If it may be put in without ― Having no <w>acquaintance<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>ship</w> with the editor and feeling inclined to write elsewhere
<lb/>which I intend still to do I thought a scrap for the
<lb/>Mail ought to be sent now. I thought the Advertizer
<lb/>but you seem to prefer the Mail - At first I thought of 
<lb/>sending my views to <persName>Robert</persName> but after giving him a
<lb/>screed I came to the conclusion that a bit written with 
<lb/>more care would suit the purpose better and the sooner
<lb/>it goes to the public the better for the subject will lose
<lb/>interest quickly. But should you think it had
    
        

	<pb n="0009" facs="liv_000672_0009"><!--pb/@n='5r'--></pb>
<lb/>3 sheet
<lb/>first to him it can be sent. As you will be in possession
<lb/>of more recent information you will be able better to judge
<lb/>Can you shew me the bit <persName>Robert</persName> put in about <unclear cert="low">Burrman</unclear><!-- really no idea whether this is a person or tribe, ks -->
<lb/>I did not furnish about the affair here - of which you have
<lb/>heard an improved edition. <persName>Mary</persName> will have told you some of
<lb/>it. When <persName>Isak</persName> ran off. I rejoiced in my inner man
<lb/>and almost prayed may he never return - <persName><unclear cert="medium">Hesse</unclear></persName> came up 
<lb/>&amp; told us her mother wanted to cut her throat. I thought a
<lb/>little &amp; the same thought occurred to me as to you but then
<lb/>again if I did not go it would not look kind to <persName>Paul</persName>
<lb/>so down I went &amp; proposed as she wished to go to Hell
<lb/>that she should come near &amp; put her hand in the fire for
<lb/>a while to try how she liked it. This made her quiet
<lb/>and she afterwards denied having sought a knife</p>
<lb/><p>I should not put in another word merely because the
<lb/>one used was like another word of an obscene meaning but I
<lb/>should feel inclined to alter foreign words if they had any approach
<lb/>to such. <foreign xml:lang="und">Masete</foreign> I should write <unclear cert="medium">mast</unclear>. <foreign xml:lang="und">Mareta Marita</foreign> But it is
<lb/>a point of very little importance for only those who are lightly disposed
<lb/>will in reading the words of God mistake their meaning. these
<lb/>two words occurred to be remarked on in my presence but that
<lb/>was among pure heathen - happening to hear them remarked on
<lb/>was the reason I thought they ought to be mentioned to you but
<lb/>this may never happen again. My attention was called to
<lb/><foreign xml:lang="und">lōpa</foreign> in the same way but we have no word to substitute
<lb/>for <foreign xml:lang="und">lōpa</foreign> and it is not so like as the others - <foreign xml:lang="und">hetola</foreign> to dye
<lb/><foreign xml:lang="und">Mehetola</foreign> is the name of the plant - I think allied to <foreign xml:lang="und">Moijo</foreign>

	<pb n="0010" facs="liv_000672_0010"><!--pb/@n='5v'--></pb>
<lb/>I shall look for a sample for you.</p>
<lb/><p>I have not had time to look carefully at the Pilgrim - cannot
<lb/>pretend I am going back in Sitchuana for many words in it I never
<lb/>knew and cannot get them now. they are not used here &amp;
<lb/>some are used in different senses, here from what they are in the 
<lb/>pilgrim. think you have been pretty successful in expressing the
<lb/>meaning - but I <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice> speak with critical authority, <foreign xml:lang="und">setloeñ</foreign>
<lb/>you have at the end of one of the hym<add place="above">n</add>lets instead of <foreign xml:lang="und">lotoeñ</foreign> - 
<lb/>cuacoa or cuacua for find <add place="inline">˄</add><add place="above"><foreign xml:lang="und">humana humanoa</foreign> as common in the <placeName><region>East</region></placeName> might do</add> means to spring up as grass
<lb/>or an eruption on the <term type="bodypart">skin</term>. "his Jewels were not <hi rend="underline">found</hi>"
<lb/>many other words occurred to me in reading it which I 
<lb/>found difficulty in &amp; which I meant to ask explanations
<lb/>of but have forgot them - &amp; <foreign xml:lang="und">tloangáne e slle</foreign> for instance
<lb/>is a puzzler to us here we cannot make it out ― the
<lb/>accents seem to shew us that your tones are different
<lb/>out at <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> from here - <foreign xml:lang="und">Moéti sepéla héta
<lb/>mocoéri - toegétsa tsiéco - khétse</foreign> are all pronounced with
<lb/>the simple e here. Let me know if you remember whether
<lb/>these words are really pronounced as I have spelled them with
<lb/>the é as in clerk for I have got into the way of pronouncing
<lb/>them all in the <term type="tribe">Sequain</term> way &amp; of course if ever I come
<lb/>out you will hear me speak as if I were an <placeName><settlement type="city">Aberdeen</settlement></placeName><unclear cert="low">area</unclear>
<lb/>man - the Poco is very prettily done in <placeName><country>England</country></placeName><foreign xml:lang="und"><unclear cert="low">bopecoc</unclear></foreign>
<lb/>the errors as well as the beauties of it <del type="strikethrough">it</del> Why not revise
<lb/>the pilgrim &amp; send it to <placeName><country>England</country></placeName> too-? and let your time
    
       

	<pb n="0011" facs="liv_000672_0011"><!--pb/@n='6r'--></pb>
<lb/>be occupied in what <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice> be done in <placeName><country>England</country></placeName> viz translating
<lb/>A little difference in the price would perhaps defray all the <w>diff<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-erence</w> in the doing it yourselves &amp; having it done by printers
<lb/>But this I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> know - I merely suggest what in your
<lb/>willingness to work may not have occurred to you. If it
<lb/>can be done it would to me appear the best way to do the
<lb/>first edition yourselves and let the rest be done in <placeName><country>England</country></placeName>
<lb/>Life is short &amp; the work of translation is long - I send you
<lb/>the gospels I have of the <term type="tribe">Sesuto</term> - and you may judge whether
<lb/>my idea of <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lennie</persName>'s fountain was wrong Never did
<lb/>spiteful critics get such a kick on the <term type="bodypart">posterior</term>s as has
<lb/>been the fortune of <persName>Edwards</persName> &amp; <persName>Inglis</persName>. And the worst of it is
<lb/>they can now only say as the man did who was <add place="below">˄</add><add place="above">being</add> kicke<gap extent="1" unit="chars" agent="stain"/><supplied cert="high">d</supplied>
<lb/>down stairs - "one <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice> help what is done behind one's <term type="bodypart">back</term>"
<lb/>and the only comfort even their friends can give them
<lb/>must be "you have yourselves alone to blame"- Very minute
<lb/>things are under the Divine <choice><sic>controll</sic><corr>control</corr></choice> and we ought
<lb/>to recognize his hand in all the good bestowed on us
<lb/>We ought to be thankful that even our sworn enemies 
<lb/>cannot hurt a hair of our <term type="bodypart">head</term>s nor a fibril of our
<lb/>good name but by Divine permission</p>
<lb/><p>I have run on a good way before I <choice><sic>percieved</sic><corr>perceived</corr></choice> the thread
<lb/>of my letter was the accounts. four door locks are
<lb/>charged at 6<choice><abbr>/</abbr><expan>shillings</expan></choice> each or /24<!-- not sure if L really means 24 pence here or ifhe has put the solidus in the wrong place?, ks --><del type="strikethrough">dollars</del> for the whole - We
<lb/>got three on a former occasion for 12<choice><abbr>/</abbr><expan>shillings</expan></choice> Hope they
    
       

	<pb n="0012" facs="liv_000672_0012"><!--pb/@n='6v'--></pb>
<lb/><choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> become dearer by being kept like some kinds of wine ᅳ
<lb/>you had better put the gun locks sent by mistake into my account &amp;
<lb/>at my price. It was <hi rend="underline">door</hi> locks I asked for then - I see several cases
<lb/>put in which I do not know - probably they are now at <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName>
<lb/>&amp; will come by <persName>Mary</persName>. We shall need corn. I have not added up 
<lb/>your doing it twice will be enough.</p>
<lb/><p><persName>Sechele</persName> sends three really splendid tiger Karosses to <placeName><settlement type="city">Birmingham</settlement></placeName>
<lb/>two to the ladies who sent the chairs not as payment but as <foreign xml:lang="und">tebogolo</foreign> for
<lb/>their friendship to one whom they knew not  - the third is for <persName><unclear cert="medium">eomogolu</unclear></persName>
<lb/>of the smiths who made the gun - <unclear cert="low">either</unclear><persName>Parker</persName> or <persName>Topping</persName> or <persName>Lowden</persName>
<lb/>as a thanks offering for doing his gun so well and to ask friendship so
<lb/>that if he can obtain the price he may buy three double barreled rifles
<lb/>10 to the <del type="strikethrough">bob</del> not now - but when he gets the price All this entirely of his <add place="below">own accord</add></p>
	<ab>
<lb/><persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi><choice><abbr>R.</abbr><expan>Robert</expan></choice> Moffat</persName>
<lb/><hi rend="underline"><placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName></hi></ab>

			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>