<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P5 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000762">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to William Thompson</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to William Thompson, 6, 20 September 1852</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London, UK</pubPlace>
				<publisher>University College London</publisher>
				<date>2012</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000762</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">University of London. School of Oriental and African Studies; CWM/LMS/Livingstone Wooden Box, item 66</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0284</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Thompson, William, 1811-1889</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date from="1852-09-06" to="1852-09-20">6, 20 September 1852</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kuruman</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2013-12-15</date>
				<name xml:id="AM">Anne Martin</name>Initial transcription and XML encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2013-12-23</date>
				<name xml:id="HFB">Heather F. Ball</name>Proofreading and additional XML encoding.
            
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000762_0001"><!--pb/@n='1r'--></pb>
<lb/><!-- The number 66 appears at top left hand corner, I do not think this is Livingstone's hand AM --><p rend="right"><placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName><date when="1852-09-06">6<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> September
<lb/>1852</date></p>
<lb/><p><persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi><choice><abbr>W.</abbr><expan>William</expan></choice> Thompson</persName></p>
<lb/><p>My Dear Sir</p>
<lb/><p>Having by means of a sound constitution survived
<lb/>tedious drawl through the <placeName><region>Colony</region></placeName> I crossed the <placeName><geogName type="river">Orange River</geogName></placeName>
<lb/>at <placeName><settlement>Priestcar</settlement></placeName> - a spot which has been selected for a mission
<lb/>station by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Alheit</persName> of <placeName><settlement type="village">Scheit fontein</settlement></placeName>. The enormous
<lb/>weight on my <choice><orig>waggon</orig><reg>wagon</reg></choice> soon after that told on one of the
<lb/>wheels and down came the elegant <term type="nationality">Dutch</term> vehicle. The <term type="nationality">African</term>
<lb/>coach and ten, on to its marrow bones. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hughs</persName> kindly
<lb/>lent a wheel and by the assistance of himself and some
<lb/>of my old patients I managed to crawl to this place about
<lb/>10 days ago. I was sometimes vexed with myself for
<lb/>having loaded up so much but when I reach the places
<lb/>where I could offload it gave me sincere pleasure to hand
<lb/>the goods to the owners. I was disposed to blame myself
<lb/>most when we had to offload at the bottom of acclivities and
<lb/>carry the boxes up ourselves. I am now detained here getting
<lb/>my wheel mended.</p>
<lb/><p>I had written another letter to you and mentioned a number
<lb/>of conjectures respecting <persName>George</persName> but his arrival at <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName>
<lb/>today renders my surmisings as valuable as conjectures
<lb/>usually are. I could not understand what should have
<lb/>prevented him coming up to me on the way and after
<lb/>waiting here a week I began to suspect he had got into
<lb/>mischief by going to <placeName><settlement type="town">Beaufort</settlement></placeName>. He has been at more expense
<lb/>than I have - and I had to spend upwards of £50 in the way.
<lb/>We shall now help him on. I waited for him as soon as I
<lb/>got a spot which possessed forage, but when he did not turn
<lb/>out I concluded he must have taken another road. I
<lb/>came here ten days before him.</p>
<lb/><p>Now that I can calmly look back on my sojourn among
<lb/>the natives who live in a hollow under <placeName><geogName type="mountain">Table mountain</geogName></placeName> and
<lb/>who <choice><sic>dailly</sic><corr>daily</corr></choice> and nightly inhale effluvia known only to the initiated
<lb/>in the mysteries of Sanatory reform, I do remember them</p>
	<ab>
<lb/>I had a fine medical library - and many good works on general subjects - the former was my pride &amp; a
<lb/>great comfort. I have got lightened - and will move so much more easily now. You will hear of my
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> yet - they are not broken spirited <term type="tribe">Hottentots</term> that attack sealed many a
<lb/><choice><sic>boer's</sic><corr>Boer's</corr></choice> doom.    
</ab>


	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000762_0002"><!--pb/@n='1v'--></pb>
<lb/><p>with feelings of compassion. Poor creatures, living in a state
<lb/>of utter respectability - exchanging their <unclear cert="medium">how</unclear> dye do's - their noddings
<lb/><choice><sic>curstyings</sic><corr>curtsyings</corr></choice> and ministerial breakfasts and all the while to carnivori
<lb/>The cannibals I may say of the Law &amp; state &amp; Puseyite church ready
<lb/>to spring upon them and devour them. They are obliged to live &amp;
<lb/>walk as circumspectly as Elephants among well covered pitfalls
<lb/>I do pity you from my heart. I could not breathe freely
<lb/>till I got over the <placeName><geogName type="river">Orange River</geogName></placeName></p>
<lb/><p>Well, that is a fine letter from his <persName>Riverence Calderwood</persName>
<lb/>I look upon it with mingled feelings of scorn and shame. With
<lb/>scorn when I think of an English Professor of Christianity so
<lb/>unutterably mean as to join in the hue and cry against a
<lb/>poor <term type="tribe">Hottentot</term>, and so dead to the shame of infamy as to
<lb/>confess at the same time that it has been his practice
<lb/>to act the part of a common informer. A salaried
<lb/>Government spy.- I blush up to the ears when I
<lb/>read his confession (after spending years in the service
<lb/>of our society) that he does not know the language
<lb/>sufficiently well to know exactly the statement of a
<lb/>native without an interpreter. Is it not disgraceful
<lb/>to find the gospel of <persName>Christ</persName> proclaimed in a <hi rend="underline">patois</hi>
<lb/>called "school <term type="tribe">Caffre</term>"? We must not lose sight of this
<lb/>confession. It is good that he makes it though that
<lb/>and other statements ought to cover him with lasting
<lb/>infamy. A man who could write as he has done
<lb/>will do more. This is not his last letter nor
<lb/>his last stab at the cause of truth &amp; righteousness</p>
<lb/><p>You see how the Government officials feel towards
<lb/>the defence of <persName>Botha</persName>. In <placeName><country>Scotland</country></placeName> counsel is provided
<lb/>for the most depraved criminals at the expense of the
<lb/>state. This Reverend Commissioner would have us
<lb/>believe that such defence "tends to break down important
<lb/>moral distinctions" - that its tendency is to cause the
<lb/>whole of <term type="nationality">Scottish</term> society to be suspected for we have
<lb/>criminals there out of every class. From Commissioners
<lb/>who can play the fool for £600 per annum with the
<lb/>bible in one hand &amp; the sambok in the other. Good Lord delivers <add place="below">us</add></p>

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000762_0003"><!--pb/@n='2r'--></pb>
<lb/><p>The copies of <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Read</persName>'s letters have not reached any of the <w>miss-
<lb break="no"/>ionaries</w> up here.. The Reports all did - I have made arrangements
<lb/>for the delivery of your letters. Have <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> two notes from
<lb/>you. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>Moffat</persName>'s <term type="bodypart">head</term> is still affected. Nothing he has tried
<lb/>has the least effect on it. The Translation goes on briskly
<lb/>notwithstanding. <persName>Edwards</persName> has left his station and the
<lb/>people of <placeName><settlement type="village">Mabotsa</settlement></placeName> have come over to <persName>Sechele</persName>. The Boers are
<lb/>reported by an individual who came here two days ago to be
<lb/>encamped at <placeName><settlement type="village">Mabotsa</settlement></placeName>. They contemplate rooting out <persName>Sechele</persName>
<lb/>and wait only till two or three of their party return from the
<lb/>Lakes They fear if an attack is made now that <persName>Sechele</persName>'s people
<lb/>fleeing Northwards would meet their friends and of course -
<lb/>treat them as they <add place="below">^</add><add place="above">now</add> hope to do the <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term>. they may find it
<lb/>more difficult to subdue <persName>Sechele</persName> than they dream of. But their plan
<lb/>is to secure the whole country to themselves and prevent traders
<lb/>and travellers from going beyond them. One of <persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Robertson</persName>'s
<lb/>converts called <persName>Chief commandant Pretorious</persName> was <unclear cert="medium">feasted</unclear>
<lb/>the other day not far from <placeName><settlement type="village">Boomplaats</settlement></placeName> where the battle
<lb/>was fought. They drunk the memory of <persName>Major Hogg</persName> in solemn
<lb/>silence but forgot the memory of the brave men who <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="hole"/>
<lb/>butchered at <placeName><settlement type="village">Boomplaats</settlement></placeName> by this same <persName>Pretorius</persName>. Is it
<lb/>right or is it not for the <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> to make the country
<lb/>too hot for this man's party - after he strikes the first
<lb/>blow? I shall be there soon and must give an opinion
<lb/>on the point. What would you advise? If it is right for <term type="tribe">Hottentot</term>
<lb/>Levies to fight against the <term type="tribe">Caffres</term> it is right for <term type="tribe">Caffres</term> &amp; <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term>
<lb/>to fight against the enemies of their country. I doubt if it is right to fight <add place="below">at all</add></p>
<lb/><p><persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Ross has gone to see his people again at <placeName><settlement type="town">Tauns</settlement></placeName>. He came along</persName>
<lb/>with me from <placeName><settlement type="town">Griqua Town</settlement></placeName> as far as <placeName><geogName>Daniel's Kuil</geogName></placeName>. He will    
<lb/>return by way of <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName>. The Doctors have not written any
<lb/>of the <choice><orig>bretheren</orig><reg>brethren</reg></choice> for a long time. <persName>Major Hogg</persName> will have some idea
<lb/>now as to whether the reports he circulated anent a certain person
<lb/>were true or false. We shall all soon be hushed in the still &amp;
<lb/>peaceful <unclear cert="medium">Hades</unclear>. All this bother &amp; bluster &amp; blarney will <choice><sic>recieve</sic><corr>receive</corr></choice>
<lb/>a quietus before many years in as far as the present actors
<lb/>are concerned. What a hush takes place as the shades of death
<lb/>close around one. God grant that when we have finished our
<lb/>work we may be hushed to eternal rest on <persName>Abraham</persName>'s bosom</p>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000762_0004"><!--pb/@n='2v'--></pb>
<lb/><p>Kind love to your sister <persName>Ralph</persName> &amp; <persName>Jessie</persName>, I <choice><sic>wont</sic><corr>won't</corr></choice> mention <persName>Willie</persName>
<lb/>because he did not come to help me. I tried your plan on one
<lb/>ox and he became a beauty &amp; so tame. All the <choice><sic>boers</sic><corr>Boers</corr></choice> wanted to
<lb/>exchange him &amp; poor fellow he was drowned in the <placeName><geogName type="river">Orange River</geogName></placeName>
<lb/>Three fell into a muddy place on a Saturday evening. We all worked
<lb/>the whole night trying to get them out of the sloughy bank and as the
<lb/>morning dawned the finest of the whole lot expired. You may guess how
<lb/>eagerly we toiled when I mention that when daylight appeared I thought
<lb/><supplied cert="high">it</supplied> was only about 12 o'clock. I have not yet begun to write but have
<lb/><!-- The next 2 lines are highlighted by a vertical line and a tick in the left margin AM -->not lost sight of the project. I have not been idle. A correct and lucid
<lb/>analysis of the language engages my attention and has taken up all
<!-- a horizontal line across the whole page appears under this line and separates out the text written at 180°AM -->
<lb/>my spare time - I have devoted a whole evening to you - your
<lb/>notes were good but very short you will someday write a longer
<lb/>I hope. Poor <persName>Botha</persName>. The sentence is terrible. It is worse than
<lb/>death. Poor fellow. -- the wicked shall not always triumph
<lb/>By same post I send a letter for my brother containing <persName>Sandillah</persName>s
<lb/>speech to <persName>Renton</persName>. to be printed in <placeName><country>America</country></placeName>. All we learn of
<lb/>the <term type="tribe">Caffre</term> war is one sided. We must hear both sides
<lb/>It is well <persName>Sendillah</persName> speaks out so nobly. Bringing out converts
<lb/>to assist the <term type="nationality">English</term> is infamous - We must either preach
<lb/>passive resistance or fighting for our own countrymen <persName><choice><abbr>D.</abbr><expan>David</expan></choice><choice><orig>Livingston</orig><reg>Livingstone</reg></choice></persName></p>
	<ab><!-- This passage is written at 180 degrees from the text preceding it HB 12-23-13 -->
<lb/>Two parties of Boers are gone <persName>Sebitoané</persName> wards. they will be cut off <add place="above">by <persName>Sechele</persName>'s people</add>. One of these
<lb/>parties would plunder me if they met me - so I think it well to wait here till
<lb/>they are out of my way or killed. It is trying to wait but God's good Providence
<lb/>has detained me so long just to prevent me falling into the very worst of the strife &amp; losing <add place="below">everything</add></ab>
	<ab>
<lb/><date when="1852-09-20">20<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi></date> You will see by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName>'s to you the doings of <persName>D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Robertson</persName>'s dearly beloved
<lb/><choice><orig>bretheren</orig><reg>brethren</reg></choice>. I mourn over my books &amp; medicines <supplied cert="high">&amp;</supplied> instruments. Please say nothing
<lb/>about my losses or some good Samaritan will forthwith send me odd numbers of
<lb/>the Evangelical Mag. the pictures extracted - "Alleine's Alarm". without the title page. An odd volume <add place="below">Charnocks sermons &amp;c</add><!-- a horizontal line across the whole page appears under this line AM --></ab>
	<ab>
<lb/>Many thanks for the <unclear cert="low">Poalter &amp; O'Niel</unclear> books
<lb/>doubly precious now. I send <persName>Sandillah</persName>'s speech
<lb/>to be printed in <placeName><country>America</country></placeName>. Please notice if
<lb/>it comes to you also two letters for <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">rs</hi><choice><abbr>L.</abbr><expan>Livingstone</expan></choice></persName></ab>
	<ab>
<lb/><hi rend="underline">Prepaid</hi>
<lb/><persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi><choice><abbr>W<hi rend="sup underline">m</hi></abbr><expan>William</expan></choice> Thompson</persName>
<lb/>Church Square
<lb/><hi rend="underline"><placeName><settlement type="city">Cape Town</settlement></placeName></hi><!-- To the left of the address someone other than Livingstone has written "2. Language" and below this "p.4."; a large number "8" is superimposed in red ink over the address itself AM --></ab>

			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>