<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000561">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Benjamin T. Pyne</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Benjamin T. Pyne, 6 June 1844</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2007-11-29</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000561</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Private owner</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Pyne, Benjamin T., 1798/9-1880</persName></bibl><!-- this is addresed to Benjamin Pyne not Benjamin T Pyne - this may well be father and son-->
				<bibl xml:id="where">Mabotsa</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1844-06-06">6 June 1844</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0103</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2007-11-29</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Initial Transcription by Caroline Overy
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2008-09-10</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>Initial Proof by Chris Lawrence
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000561_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1r'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Mabotsa</placeName> 6 June 1844</p>
<lb/><p>My Dear Friends</p>
<lb/><p>I sent off three letters for you about three 
<lb/>months ago and when I was in a sadly distressed state on account of 
<lb/>having suffered <unclear cert="low">hurt</unclear> in the jaws of a lion. About the time we 
<lb/>came here we were surrounded by an unusual number of lions 
<lb/>many were killed but attacks continued to be made daily and the natives 
<lb/>were beginning to lose heart, and no sooner was it made known 
<lb/>that cattle had been killed during the night than all our work at the 
<lb/>water course was immediately suspended; Feeling vexed with these 
<lb/>misfortunes on one occasion when a lion killed 9 sheep on a 
<lb/>hill opposite our house I contrary to my usual custom went 
<lb/>with them in order to encourage them to put him to death and I 
<lb/>paid dearly for it for the lion on being wounded rushed down 
<lb/>upon and hit three of us badly, mine was worst for he broke 
<lb/>the left arm bone in several places &amp; twelve large gashes were 
<lb/>made some of them reaching down to the fractures. <persName><unclear cert="low">Mebalse</unclear></persName>
<lb/>our native assistant ran forward to rescue me but his gun 
<w>miss-<lb break="no"/>ed</w> fire and he got severely wounded in the thigh. The lion then attacked 
<lb/><term type="tribe">a makhatla</term> &amp; bit is shoulder but this was his last deed of 
<lb/>mischief for in doing so another <term type="tribe">makhatla</term> pitched a spear 
<lb/>into the monster's heart. <persName><unclear cert="low">Mebalse's</unclear></persName> wounds healed in about 
<lb/>a month after their infliction but mine were three before I could 
<lb/>use the arm in the least. I had a long trial of patience. <choice><reg>O</reg><orig>o</orig></choice>ur 
<lb/>hut being quite unfinished the natives built me a hut and 
<lb/>in that hut I had many a wearisome day &amp; night. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he wounds 
<lb/>discharged so excessively I was reduced to a mere skeleton and 
<lb/>had not strength to make the least movement on any couch 
<lb/>and not being able to secure the bones myself every motion 
<lb/>of the body caused them to grate on each other so as to prevent 
<lb/>union &amp; retard the healing of the wounds<reg>.</reg> But through 
<lb/>great mercy I have recovered well beyond my utmost expectations &amp; 
<lb/>my arm is both straight &amp; firm. It was a great affliction 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000561_0002"/><!--pb/@n='1v'-->
<lb/>But the Lord mingled much kindness with its severity and now 
<lb/>I can only praise him for his goodness &amp; sparing mercy. May 
<lb/>the spared life be devoted to the glory of my great Deliverer<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he <term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term> are at present erecting new villages on 
<lb/>the site of the mission and we shall commence the erection 
<lb/>of a school immediately in order to have the power of 
<lb/>collecting both children &amp; adults in all weathers. We have 
<lb/>nothing of interest to relate respecting them. It is only midnight 
<lb/>gloom in their minds their affections are all on the earth 
<lb/>&amp; a thought never glances heavenward. But notwithstanding 
<lb/>their selfishness which is supreme I begin to love them more 
<lb/>than ever. I soon forgot to think of them as of a different 
<lb/>complexion and feel towards them as fellow immortals who 
<lb/>if they don<reg>'</reg>t soon accept mercy must be lost eternally &amp; 
<lb/>O that they would but listen to the glad tidings. It would 
<lb/>satisfy them more thoroughly than all the world of goods. 
<lb/>We hear that the Lord is blessing his word at <placeName>Lattakoo</placeName>
<lb/>twentythree were lately added to the church. I wish we could 
<lb/>say we saw even three beginning to think about their 
<lb/>souls &amp; eternity. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey are degraded beyond conception 
<lb/>they seem to have sunk as far as human nature can - 
<lb/>there seem to exist some evidences of animal worship at 
<lb/>some former periods, as they are all called by some animal 
<lb/>thus for instance <del type="strikethrough">the</del><term type="tribe">Batlapi</term> literally translated is <hi rend="underline">they</hi> (of the) 
<lb/><hi rend="underline">Fish</hi>, <term type="tribe">Bakwain</term><hi rend="underline">they</hi> (of the) <hi rend="underline">Crocodile</hi>, <term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term><hi rend="underline">they</hi> of 
<lb/>the <hi rend="underline">monkey</hi>, <term type="tribe">Bachuene</term>, they of the Baboon. While 
<lb/>the <term type="tribe">Barolongs</term> if asked by what they swear invariably 
<lb/>answer "we dance to iron". And in hunting if they happen 
<lb/>to kill a khoodoo a magnificent animal of the antelope 
<lb/>species always make loud lamentations before they 
<lb/>begin to <del type="strikethrough"><unclear cert="low">skin</unclear></del> flay it as "yo yo yo we have killed our Father 
<lb/>yo yo yo &amp;c<reg>"</reg> &amp;c believing if they neglect this some of their 
<lb/>number will die in consequence. All the other tribes swear 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000561_0003"/><!--pb/@n='2r'-->
<lb/>by the animal after which they are called, never kill or eat 
<lb/>it &amp; sometimes won<reg>'</reg>t even look at it, saying that animal 
<lb/>is the friend of their race<reg>.</reg> But if I am not wrong in my 
<lb/>conjecture even this form of worship has degenerated so 
<lb/>that now only the vestiges remain &amp; all their affections are 
<lb/>given to the gratification of earthly propensities<reg>.</reg> O that the 
<lb/>Holy Spirit may work mightily on these dark minds &amp; turn 
<lb/>them from the service of their lusts to the pure service of 
<lb/>the Great God of Heaven &amp; of earth<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>Of all the seeds you gave me none vegetated except the 
<w>sun-<lb break="no"/>flower</w> and now it is planted at <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName>, the reason of the 
<lb/>deficiency of vegetative power I don<reg>'</reg>t know perhaps it was 
<lb/>sea air that destroyed it. I long much for an opportunity 
<lb/>to send you a box, but all my endeavours have as yet been 
<lb/>in vain. We have chinese oats without <add place="below">^</add><add place="above">any</add> husk and 
<lb/>Egyptian corn (a few grains of it were once shewn 
<lb/>me by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pyne</persName><reg>)</reg> grows well. It being better adapted 
<lb/>for boiling than the Bengal corn we have it <del type="strikethrough">planted</del> sown 
<lb/>yearly. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>here are other things which might be of use if I 
<lb/>could only get them sent. I shall however still be 
<lb/>on the look out &amp; I hope I shall yet succeed.</p>
<lb/><p>Hoping soon to hear from you I shall conclude this 
<lb/>short letter with very affectionate regards to all your 
<lb/>family &amp; yourselves<reg>.</reg> Yours ever</p>
<lb/><p>David Livingston</p>
<lb/><p>I have written <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wright</persName> of <placeName>Ongar</placeName><reg>.</reg></p>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000561_0004"/><!--pb/@n='2v'-->
<lb/><p>
<address>
<addrLine>Care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">d</hi></hi> D<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi><choice><sic>Phillip</sic><corr>Philip</corr></choice></persName><placeName>Cape Town</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><persName>Benjamin Pyne Esq</persName><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">re</hi></hi></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>Ongar Essex</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><hi rend="underline">England</hi></addrLine>
<addrLine><hi rend="underline">single</hi></addrLine>
</address>
</p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>