<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted from a TEI P5 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000501">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Benjamin T. Pyne</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">David Livingstone</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London, UK</pubPlace>
				<publisher>University College London</publisher>
				<date>2012</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000501</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Bodleian Library of Commonwealth and African Studies at Rhodes House, MSS.Afr.s.141, fol. 7-8</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">0046</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient">Benjamin T. Pyne</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date">22 December 1841</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kuruman</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="und">Undetermined</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2011-09-20</date>
				<name xml:id="AJS">A.J. Schmitz</name> initial transcription and XML encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-01-06</date>
				<name xml:id="HFB">Heather F. Ball</name> proofreading.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-01-12</date>
				<name xml:id="AW">Adrian S. Wisnicki</name> editing.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-09-15</date>
				<name>Heather F. Ball</name> second XML editing.
            
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000501_0001"><!--pb/@n='7r'--></pb>
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName><settlement type="town">Kuruman</settlement></placeName><date when="1841-12-22">22<hi rend="sup">d</hi><choice><abbr>Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi></abbr><expan>December</expan></choice> 1841</date></p>
<lb/><p>My very dear friends</p>
<lb/><p>Afraid lest when you hear of the reception
<lb/>of a letter from me by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Cecil</persName> you should think I had forgotten you
<lb/>I hasten to send you one too &amp; hope although it is of a later date
<lb/>it will be favoured with a more speedy passage than the
<lb/>other.<space dim="horizontal" extent="3" unit="words"/>I am now quite recovered from the effects of a
<lb/>long journey I made in company with <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edwards</persName> into the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName>
<lb/>and lest you should feel anyway concerned about my comforts
<lb/>I may mention that I have as many as I can desire; <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
<lb/><choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> are excellent people <space dim="horizontal" extent="1" unit="chars"/>The longer I live with them I like them
<lb/>the better. Perhaps you will be pleased to hear I was not permitted
<lb/>to commence housekeeping here. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi><choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> insisted that they
<lb/>should take all of the trouble of lodging me &amp;c. And although I felt loathe
<lb/>to put them to any additional trouble I was fairly compelled to it
<lb/>They likewise entertain Good old <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hamilton</persName> in the same manner 
<lb/>Another friend! whom you know has not conducted himself in the 
<lb/>most amiable manner to myself, is behaving in rather a strange
<lb/>sort of way to our <choice><orig>bretheren</orig><reg>brethren</reg></choice> here. Indeed I <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice> help thinking he
<lb/>is what you in <placeName><country>England</country></placeName> call a sort of imbecile. But he had
<lb/>ability enough to vex me thoroughly on sundry occasions. It will
<lb/>&amp; I hope has done me good notwithstanding the nauseousness of
<lb/>the draughts</p>
<lb/><p>Our journey was very long for this is a country of prodigious
<lb/>extent &amp; the people live far apart from each other. We however
<lb/>visited some who had not previously been visited by missionaries
<lb/>Traders have been much farther than we &amp; they endure more
<lb/>fatigue in search of ivory than we do in endeavouring to
<lb/>gather in immortal souls to the Saviour's Kingdom. But I 
<lb/>hope this <choice><sic>wont</sic><corr>won't</corr></choice> be said again with truth: We hope to do 
<lb/>more for souls after this than the men of the world for gain
<lb/>I intend soon to go into the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName> again. &amp; I perhaps will
<lb/>go farther than in this last Journey. for although we travelled 
<lb/>about 700 miles we were not more than 250 directly 
<lb/>North.<space dim="horizontal" extent="2" unit="words"/>Circumstances compelled us to go in the hottest
<lb/>season of the year, but you <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice>understand<add place="below">^</add><add place="above">what</add> heat of Sun
<lb/>means by feeling his summer rays in <placeName><country>England</country></placeName>; When we
<lb/>came even here although the difference in latitude is
<lb/>not great. It felt quite cool &amp; pleasant compared to the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName>
<lb/>the sun was "indeed <unclear>A</unclear>ngry Angry" <add place="above">a native expression</add> in the wide wide waterless
<lb/>&gt; plains of that region - <space dim="horizontal" extent="1" unit="words"/>I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> want to magnify my
<lb/>sufferings or call them such for I bore it I thought quite 
<lb/>as well as the natives. I only wish to give you an
<lb/>idea of the country I am to consider my own hereafter. It was
<lb/>really intolerably hot. The very flies sought the shade &amp; the
<lb/>enormous centipedes coming out by mistake I suppose from
<lb/>their holes were roasted to death on the burning sand</p>
	<cb/>
	<ab>
<lb/>I have seen several of the <term type="tribe">Bechuana</term> chiefs &amp; my candid opinion of them all except one is they are a set of hereditary downright 
<lb/>asses &amp; it is no scandal to say so for generally they are much more insignificant in every <gap agent="illegible" extent="3" unit="chars"/><unclear cert="medium">respect</unclear> than to <unclear cert="high">poorest</unclear>
<lb/>of the people. They are good for nothing but <space dim="horizontal" extent="2" unit="words"/>begging</ab>


	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000501_0002"><!--pb/@n='7v'--></pb>
	<ab>
<lb/><date when="1842-01-04"><choice><abbr>Jany</abbr><expan>January</expan></choice> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1842</date> No opportunity seems likely to occur of sending this but I leave it with <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hamilton</persName> I am 
<lb/>about to start for a distant part of the country Yours Affectionately <persName><choice><abbr>DL</abbr><expan>David Livingstone</expan></choice></persName> I expect letters from you <!-- Should Yours Affectionately be coded as a closer? HB 12/28/11 -->
<lb/>&amp; <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moore</persName> when I return 
	</ab>
<lb/><p>Water is very scarce towards the north But there is plenty of game
<lb/>both large &amp; small near all the watering places, so we usually 
<lb/>got something to eat as well as drink at them. And then if
<lb/>you saw the mirth &amp; laughter of the natives when cutting up an 
<lb/>animal you should feel perhaps more strongly the meaning of
<lb/>the expression "rejoicing as in the day of slaughter" then you have
<lb/>before - <space dim="horizontal" unit="chars" extent="1"/>Great numbers of the natives always turned <unclear cert="medium">out with</unclear>
<lb/>us from every village in order to get a share of whatever might 
<lb/>be killed. &amp; It did not matter although we killed nothing for the 
<lb/>first 40 or 50 miles. If they got after that a backful of meat 
<lb/>they returned rejoicing in their good success. Sometimes at night
<lb/>an amusing circumstance occurred putting as sudden a stop to
<lb/>their laughing roasting &amp; stewing, as if a thunderbolt had fallen 
<lb/>amongst them. The approach of a wild animal towards
<lb/>our fires, then there was such a rushing for spears guns &amp;c  
<lb/>the belly was entirely forgotten in our anxiety to do some valorous
<lb/>action - but courage was <del type="cancelled">not</del> never at night (fortunately for us) 
<lb/>put to the test. If it had it might have been found wanting</p>
<lb/><p>We saw all the large game of this country except the Elephant
<lb/>&amp; we saw abundance of marks where he had recently been. They
<lb/>must have immense power for large "camel thorn trees" 
<lb/>a kind of mimosa with wood so hard it <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice> be worked by 
<lb/>our chisels &amp;c. were lying twisted down to the ground, or split
<lb/>down the centre in order to allow them to eat the branches at the 
<lb/>top. They must have great power of digestion too for the 
<lb/>branches they had eaten were as thick as my thumb &amp; 
<lb/>covered with large strong thorns more than an inch in length
<lb/>The Giraffe is very beautiful &amp; so are the Zebra &amp; ostrich
<lb/>but the Rhinoceros is like a huge pig; we got one Zebra
<lb/>as large as <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> P</persName><choice><sic>s</sic><corr>'s</corr></choice> grey mare &amp; the meat was very good -- </p>
<lb/><p>But the people will be more interesting <supplied cert="high">to</supplied> you than <unclear cert="medium">wild</unclear> beasts 
<lb/>Although I believe the latter are greater in number than the 
<lb/>former.<space dim="horizontal" extent="2" unit="chars"/>They are quite a timid race of people, &amp; there is
<lb/>not the least danger to be apprehended by any European 
<lb/>traveling amongst them.<space dim="horizontal" extent="1" unit="words"/>They can be cruel enough
<lb/>to each other but are very much afraid of the "whites"
<lb/>The terrible effects of the guns of a few <choice><sic>boers</sic><corr>Boers</corr></choice> has contributed more
<lb/>than anything else to produce this fear of us &amp; now through the 
<lb/>whole country they have an impression that "whites" are decidedly 
<lb/>their superiors - <space dim="horizontal" extent="1" unit="words"/>Everywhere we were received with respect 
<lb/>but more especially by those who had never seen a white face 
<lb/>before. My hair was in their eyes a very curious affair indeed 
<lb/>and the wife of one of the chiefs very innocently put up her hand 
<lb/>to my nose to make herself sure by the sense of feeling that it really 
<lb/>was so far elevated from the level of my face as it appeared to 
<lb/>be &amp; were not like her own little flat thing. When  told of   
<lb/>the creation it seemed strange to them how one father should 
<lb/>have some children with such sharp noses white skins &amp; 
<lb/>eyes that can see everything while others had flat noses 



	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000501_0003"><!--pb/@n='8r'--></pb>
<lb/>short hair &amp; their skins like pots - <space dim="horizontal" extent="1" unit="words"/>About praying to God they had <!-- Does "God" need to be coded? HB 1/10/12 -->
<lb/>many strange notions. Because we kneeled &amp; bowed down our head they 
<lb/>thought our God must surely be in the ground. <space dim="horizontal" extent="1" unit="words"/>One woman told me 
<lb/>when I was looking at some of them drawing water out of a deep well 
<lb/>that she would pray to God after this. <space dim="horizontal" extent="1" unit="words"/> The nature of her prayers 
<lb/>I suppose will be like that of one of her countrymen who told me a 
<lb/>day or two afterwards when he &amp; I were returning from shooting 
<lb/>a Rhinoceros that he had prayed for success in getting game 
<lb/>before we went &amp; now the prayer was answered. We sometimes 
<lb/>had to exert ourselves considerably in pursuit of game to supply the 
<lb/>wants of our people. It was no easy matter in the midst of such 
<lb/>heat. some people might blame a missionary assuming the 
<lb/>character of a huntsman but if they knew the toil connected 
<lb/>with it they would never suspect he did it from motives of 
<lb/>pleasure -</p><space dim="horizontal" extent="2" unit="words"/><p>They are very superstitious. We had 8 with 
<lb/>us from the <term type="tribe">Bo-quain</term> tribe. (<term type="tribe">Bakuain</term>) who come for the purpose 
<lb/>of trading with an <choice><sic>elephants</sic><corr>elephant's</corr></choice> tooth &amp; a few skins they had got 
<lb/>one of them a hearty openhearted youth who had been a 
<lb/>soldier of the notorious Marauder <persName>Moselekatsi</persName> &amp; had with his 
<lb/>own hands killed 3 men, attached himself to me as a particular 
<lb/>friend of mine (we have in almost every village a particular 
<lb/>friend and although the chief burden of the friendship rests upon 
<lb/>us we encourage it for when arriving at a village our 
<lb/>friend is sure to turn out with a bowl of porridge, milk or 
<lb/>boiled beans which <del type="strikethrough">we</del><add place="above">is</add> really most acceptable after <choice><sic>livin</sic><corr>living</corr></choice>
<lb/>chiefly on meat for some time) As I liked this hearty 
<lb/>fellow I allowed him to ride sometimes. But one day I requested  
<lb/>him to bring me a human bone lying near. With an exclam<supplied>-</supplied>
<lb/>-ation of horror he replied, "My friend how can you ask me 
<lb/>to do that. How can I love you after this. Nobody but <unclear cert="medium">bewitchers</unclear>
<lb/>use human bones. I am afraid you are one." And from 
<lb/>that time he never would even look into my <choice><orig>waggon</orig><reg>wagon</reg></choice><add place="below">he traveled about 200 miles after that on foot</add></p>
<lb/><p>In order to try him I promised to reward him if he should bring it 
<lb/>but he declared he would not do it Although I should give him 
<lb/>as much as he had agreed for with <persName>Mr E.</persName> to go as servant 
<lb/>to <persName>Graham</persName>'s town &amp; back again, first going home to his own 
<lb/>country to ask his <choice><sic>father s</sic><corr>father's</corr></choice> consent, see his wife &amp; child 
<lb/>&amp; then return. The whole distance he offered to travel 
<lb/>being about 1500 miles - He was quite friendly in all other 
<lb/>respects, a most obliging fellow but that he could not get 
<lb/>over at all ---- </p><space dim="horizontal" extent="2" unit="words"/><p>I am sorry I said the baby's clothes 
<lb/>were not the thing for me. I hope you did not think me 
<lb/>saucy. I know in <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Phi<add place="above">llips</add></persName> hands they will be applied to good 
<lb/>purpose &amp; even in my own hands they would have been 
<lb/>of considerable use. I should have liked to have had one suit 
<lb/>of them now for a child that has been named not <persName>David <choice><abbr>L.</abbr><expan>Livingston</expan></choice></persName><!-- Should "Livingston" have the "e" on the end? HB 1/10/12 -->
<lb/>but <persName><foreign xml:lang="und">Monari</foreign> Livingston</persName>, or <persName>Master <choice><abbr>L.</abbr><expan>Livingston</expan></choice></persName> &amp; very likely they will add 
<lb/>the word for D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> yet so my poor little black representative will 
<lb/>have a handle to both ends of his name. I may mention for the 



	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000501_0004"><!--pb/@n='8v'--></pb>
<lb/>benefit of the young folks. The condition of the females is very degraded <unclear cert="low">indeed</unclear>
<lb/>they are sold for oxen &amp;c, when mere children to be wives to those who 
<lb/>perhaps have several already. The men care not how many they have 
<lb/>for as the women sow the corn &amp; cultivate all the other articles of cons-
<lb/>-umption as well as build the houses; The more wives the more corn &amp;c. 
<lb/>and when they are old or a little ugly from disease they are put away 
<lb/>&amp; must shift for themselves by digging up roots until they perish 
<lb/>from hunger or are devoured by wild beasts. Do your young 
<lb/>people value their privleges? I am sure if they for one night only 
<lb/>heard the dismal howling of the wolf or were once wakened up with 
<lb/>a start by the horrid roar of the lion, they would never forget 
<lb/>them &amp; I think they would pray more earnestly for the spread of 
<lb/>the gospel into these dark places of the earth - A poor little 
<lb/>girl was brought to me at one village she had been enduring intense  
<lb/>pain in her eyes from a certain disease for about a month  
<lb/>and now they had both burst. During all that time she had no 
<lb/>comforts neither by night nor by day. Although I had to adopt 
<lb/>severe measures to stop the disease. She never complained, And 
<lb/>this was a solitary case amongst many. Many both men &amp; 
<lb/>women were so ill they could not crawl to the <choice><orig>waggon</orig><reg>wagon</reg></choice>. They 
<lb/>have no comfort here &amp; they have no hope of anything better in the 
<lb/>world to come - I could fill a letter. many letters telling you about 
<lb/>their sorrows but this will suffice. Pray for the outpouring 
<lb/>of the spirit upon our feeble labours that they may result in 
<lb/>turning many of these heathen to the Lord --- You have I hope 
<lb/>heard from <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>Drummond</persName>. Please let me know how the lad 
<lb/>goes on. In expectation that I shall soon hear from you 
<lb/>by letters long since sent.</p><p rend="right">I am yours Affectionately <persName><choice><abbr>D</abbr><expan>David</expan></choice> Livingston</persName></p>			
	
	<div>
	<cb/>
<lb/><p>I have heard from <persName>T W S Taylor</persName> &amp; we have heard <unclear>8</unclear> missionaries 
<lb/>were set apart as designated in <placeName>Barbican Chapel</placeName> for <placeName><bloc><choice><abbr>S.</abbr><expan>South</expan></choice> Africa</bloc></placeName>
<lb/>&amp; <placeName><country>India</country></placeName>. <unclear>&amp;</unclear> I wish to hear if <persName>Moore</persName> &amp; <persName>Inglis</persName> are coming by 
<lb/>but patience, Please direct by way of <persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Phillip</persName></p>				
	</div>
	<div><!-- Should this section be in the middle of the lines 15 and 16 as it appears on the page? HB 1/10/12 --><!-- Also, the date written above the text is missing, but I am unsure where to add it HB 1/10/12 -->
<lb/><p><del type="strikethrough">Care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Phillip</persName><hi rend="underline"><placeName type="settlement">Cape Town</placeName></hi></del></p>
<lb/><space dim="vertical" extent="3" unit="lines"/>
	<milestone unit="column" n="1"/>
<space dim="vertical" extent="3" unit="lines"/>
<lb/><p><hi rend="underline">Single sheet</hi></p>
	<milestone unit="column" n="2"/>
<lb/><p><persName>Benjamin T. Pyne<choice><abbr>Esq<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi></abbr><expan>Esquire</expan></choice></persName>
<lb/><placeName>Wildingtree</placeName>
<lb/><placeName>Ongar</placeName>
<lb/><placeName>Essex</placeName>
<lb/><placeName><choice><abbr>S.B.</abbr><expan>South Britain</expan></choice></placeName></p>
	<milestone unit="column"/>
	</div>
			
			</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>