<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000587">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Robert Moffat 1</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Robert Moffat 1, 6 June 1845</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Robert Moffat 1, 6 June 1845</title>
				<author>Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
				<publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
				<date>2017</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000587</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">University of London. School of Oriental and African Studies; CWM/LMS/Africa/Odds - Livingstone, Box 4-04</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0125</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Moffat, Robert 1, 1795-1883</persName>; </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1845-06-06">6 June 1845</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Mabotsa</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="und">Undetermined</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2012-11-16</date>
				<name xml:id="KS">Kate Simpson</name>Initial transcription and XML encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-03-25</date>
				<name xml:id="AM">Anne Martin</name>Proofreading
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2013-06-16</date>
				<name xml:id="HFB">Heather F. Ball</name>Additional encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2016-06-09</date>
				<name>Anne Martin</name>Final Review
            
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000587_0001"><!--pb/@n='1r'--></pb>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">1 sheet</p>
<lb/><p rend="right"><space extent="7" unit="words"/><placeName><settlement type="village">Mabotsa</settlement></placeName> <date when="1845-06-06">6 June 1845</date></p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">My dear Father</p>
<lb/><p><space extent="3" unit="words"/>We <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> <bibl>your several communications</bibl> by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
<lb/>Cumming</persName> on Saturday last, a bitter cold day having ice standing on all the pools 
<lb/>in the morning and as <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Greig</persName> was preparing to leave on the same day as 
<lb/>he, (Tuesday) we had not a <choice><sic>moments</sic><corr>moment's</corr></choice> time to answer yours <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> Monday
<lb/>night. I sat up nearly the whole night in order to give you some particulars
<lb/>anent <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edwards</persName>' charges, &amp;c. But another opportunity being about to
<lb/>present itself in the person of <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Milligan</persName> I sit down to talk a little more
<lb/>leisurely than I could do on the former occasion. We are heartily glad
<lb/>at the departure of <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Greig</persName> but as he is only three days gone we cannot
<lb/>yet rejoice with very great confidence as the fellow may come stalking
<lb/><choice><sic>accross</sic><corr>across</corr></choice> our path again. We liked <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cumming</persName> very much. He is now
<lb/>fairly on his way to the <term type="tribe">Bamangwato</term>. He seems just the right sort of
<lb/>person for exploring so far as courage goes &amp; I hope he will come safely back
<lb/>Matters go on in much their usual way here, the meetings are not full
<lb/>a certain number seem always to come &amp; others only when greater efforts
<lb/>for their attendance are made, they sit with much more sedateness
<lb/>than formerly, but as yet I see not the least evidence of any change in
<lb/>their habits. Last Sunday, afternoon we had the smallest meeting we have
<lb/>had since our return in <date when="1845-03">March last</date>. The reason was the feast of harvest
<lb/>fell on that day or rather the preparations for it were made for its <w>cele-
<lb break="no"/>-bration</w> next morning. A Divine power is certainly requisite for their
<lb/>conversion. I fear that influence will not be granted so long as the
<lb/>present state of feeling exists between <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> &amp; myself. This consideration
<lb/>makes me more than willing to leave the station to himself, for from what
<lb/>I know of his quarrel with <persName>Hume</persName>. ours will not soon terminate. If this
<lb/>were my only motive I should be deeply grieved for then I could not expect
<lb/>the Divine blessing anywhere But I know that I had a desire to be the
<lb/>means of carrying the <bibl>gospel</bibl> to another tribe before I knew anything of the
<lb/>state of feeling which had existed. And when I asked myself the question
<lb/>whether I were not in anyway influenced by a desire to get quit of a <w>peculiar<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>tempered</w> colleague it seemed to me then that his peculiarities only rendered
<lb/>it less desirable to remain than it otherwise might have been. There are
<lb/>other feelings in my mind now but I hope &amp; pray that if parted I may
<lb/>be able to forgive as I hope to be forgiven. I however shall feel no
<lb/>respect for <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> aged though he is, and feeling none, none will be
<lb/>expressed. It is probable I shall adopt the same course I adopted (not soon
<lb/>enough) with respect to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ross</persName>. I shall not speak about him: When
<lb/>we came to <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> I began it &amp; continued it for three months but
<lb/>foolishly departed from it when informed that an opposite course had been
<lb/>adopted towards me. I have forgiven him &amp; <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> <choice><abbr>R.</abbr><expan>Ross</expan></choice></persName> from my heart and
<lb/>I fear to hear any of their statements now lest all the bitter feelings
<lb/>I once had should return against the injurious speeches uttered again
<lb/>&amp; again by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <supplied cert="high">Ross</supplied></persName> &amp; <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Ross</persName>. I have often spoken in bitter anger but now
<lb/>feel sorry I had not more philosophy or rather <term type="faith">Christian</term> meekness
<lb/>&amp; forbearance. For an investigation of the charges brought against
<lb/>me by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <supplied cert="high">Edwards</supplied></persName> &amp; <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Edwards</persName> I feel very desirous for an impartial



	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000587_0002"><!--pb/@n='1v'--></pb>
<lb/>investigation in the presence of the <choice><orig>bretheren</orig><reg>brethren</reg></choice>. If I could come I certainly would
<lb/>now write to you officially by this opportunity to demand a <orgName>committee</orgName> meeting
<lb/>But the probable circumstances in which my dear partner will then be
<lb/>placed convince me that I need no revelation from heaven in order
<lb/>to pronounce that it is clearly not my duty to go out. I should be loath 
<lb/>besides to leave the station without any one on it but <persName>Mebaloe</persName>
<lb/>My leaving the station is I am convinced that which <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> desires, but that
<lb/>very desire and the version he will afterwards give of my leaving present
<lb/>the greatest obstacles to the following out of my own desire, <unclear cert="low"><choice><abbr>reg</abbr><expan>regarding</expan></choice></unclear> to go
<lb/>to another tribe. I will not leave, unless <add place="below">˄</add> <add place="above">in</add> the decision of the <orgName>committee</orgName>
<lb/>there is something to <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice> that my leaving involves no acknowledgement
<lb/>of guilt. In my heart &amp; before Him who knows my heart I am
<lb/>not conscious of having up to the time of our interview given him any
<lb/>just cause of offence Now I will not whatever others may think
<lb/>do that which would imply that such consciousness did exist. Ought the
<lb/>meeting of <orgName>committee</orgName> not to be here? Certain statements could
<lb/>be better investigated here than anywhere else. For instance <persName>Mebaloe</persName>'s
<lb/>garden. It is not a hundred paces yet. And then the assertion that I went
<lb/>to <orgName>natives</orgName>. Who are these? One <orgName>native</orgName> <term type="occupation">deacon</term> was the only individual
<lb/>to whom I mentioned it previous to speaking to <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> <choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> &amp; to <hi rend="underline">his</hi> <add place="above"><unclear cert="medium">Mapoleane</unclear></add> wife
<lb/>afterwards and to no other. If <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>E</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> asserts I did anything else than what
<lb/>I have related to you, it is either by mistake of malice utterly untrue
<lb/>It is entirely untrue that I accused him of feelings of revenge in
<lb/>excluding the woman His own way of relating this story <choice><orig>shews</orig><reg>shows</reg></choice>
<lb/>that it is so. When asked about the exclusion he denied it. I believed
<lb/>him but urged that something should be done in it as the woman had 
<lb/>a wrong impression of what had been done, she evidently understood
<lb/>exclusion. Now as the object of discipline was the good of the offender
<lb/>as well as the purity of the <orgName>church</orgName>. Let us remove this wrong impression
<lb/>Let her be subject to discipline so that she may not go on in sin
<lb/>He replied that he would do right &amp; not care what impression was
<lb/>produced, I replied that we ought to be careful not to produce a
<lb/>wrong impression lest our good be evil spoken of ᅳ that in
<lb/>discipline especially we ought to be careful not to produce the
<lb/>impression that we acted out of private revenge and that we ought
<lb/>even to have a good report from those who were without
<lb/>He replied but she is within and then as he had repeatedly
<lb/>done before, that he did not feel at liberty because the affair had
<lb/>happened in his own house &amp;c. It is utterly untrue that I
<lb/>ascribed feelings of revenge to him. He denied that he had excluded
<lb/>at all. I believed him &amp; every act of mine afterwards <choice><orig>shewed</orig><reg>showed</reg></choice>
<lb/>that I did so, this case as <del type="strikethrough">in</del> the case of the garden was handed
<lb/>over to me, and I solemnly declare I thought that in both cases
<lb/>I had done the very things he wished me to do. I thought I had obliged 
<lb/>him in the case of <persName>Mapoleane</persName> up to the time of our interview
<lb/>by taking a <choice><sic>disagreable</sic><corr>disagreeable</corr></choice> subject off his hands. And my thoughts 
<lb/>were the very same about the garden up to the receipt of <bibl>your
<lb/>
<lb/>



	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000587_0003"><!--pb/@n='2r'--></pb>
<lb/>letter</bibl> on Saturday last, I nevertheless could in justice have ascribed feelings
<lb/>of revenge to him about the <term type="foodstuff">meat</term>, or what feelings the expressed resolution
<lb/>that <persName>Mapoleane</persName> should get no more of his <term type="foodstuff">meat</term> indicate But I never
<lb/>did to my recollection ascribe anything improper to him on any occasion
<lb/>previous to our interview, nor did I ever say or do anything which
<lb/>I thought could offend him. In the case of the garden he came to me
<lb/>and said something like what he gave in version <choice><abbr>N<hi rend="sup">o</hi></abbr><expan>Number</expan></choice> 2. and that <w>some<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-thing</w> to me implied that he had not given satisfaction to all <orgName>parties</orgName>
<lb/>and he wished me to interfere and give a larger piece of ground, so
<lb/>as to effect a good understanding. To do this I remember <w>distinct<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-ly</w> I was decidedly averse, &amp; said that I thought the amount he then
<lb/>stated was quite enough, I was then walking about But a <w>consider<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-able</w> time elapsed before I did anything. A considerable time I say for
<lb/>an interval elapsed sufficient to convince <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> that a great
<lb/>number of <orgName>Kurumanites</orgName> would not come to live with him as <!-- Does "Kurumanites" get coded as a tribe or nationality? HB 6-17-13 --><!-- I don't think it's either - have used orgName AM -->
<lb/>he expected. I think it was the return of <persName>Merupe</persName> with the <choice><orig>waggon</orig><reg>wagon</reg></choice>
<lb/>that made him first doubt the affections of the <orgName>Kurumanites</orgName> <!-- Same note for "Kurumanites" HB 6-17-13 -->
<lb/>We had conversations on the subject and we both agreed that
<lb/>those who had come first ought to have the largest share &amp; that
<lb/>ground ought not to be kept for those whom he expected. At
<lb/>least two months had elapsed after what he related to you. And he 
<lb/>had spoiled the lower part of the water ditch before I did anything
<lb/>in it. I had previously thought of having my garden below his
<lb/>but when I saw that the ditch was useless in a portion or
<lb/>nearly all of his and quite impracticable all below it I <w>prop<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-osed</w> that he should shift up a little. I did not tell him
<lb/>the principal reason, but <choice><orig>shewed</orig><reg>showed</reg></choice> him that the ground was
<lb/>better as you ascend. He said he had fixed and I might do
<lb/>or go where I liked. <persName>Mebaloe</persName> &amp; <persName>Kobopure</persName> were next to him
<lb/>above so I proposed to <del type="strikethrough">him</del> <add place="above">them</add> to remove to oblige me. Both
<lb/>readily consented, so when I took <persName>Mebaloe</persName>'s garden I must
<lb/>of necessity measure off a garden for both him &amp; <persName>Kobopure</persName>
<lb/>Mine was &amp; is equal to all <persName>Mebaloe</persName>'s &amp; part of <persName>Kobopure</persName>'s
<lb/>I remember distinctly saying. It seems none of our <orgName><placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName>
<lb/>friends</orgName> are coming <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> they see whether we die or not. We
<lb/>need not keep land for them till then. I measured off 80
<lb/>paces, and asked if he were satisfied. <persName>Kobopure</persName> complained
<lb/>of more trees in the new than his former. I said then take
<lb/>farther than the 80 paces if you can pick it But you will
<lb/>never pick it all. He then went forward about 20 paces
<lb/>more and I asked if he were satisfied, &amp; he replied in the affirmative
<lb/>Now it occurs to me if <persName>Mr <choice><abbr>E</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> is such a bold <choice><sic>out spoken</sic><corr>outspoken</corr></choice>
<lb/>man why did he never say one word to me implying dissatisfaction 
    
    

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000587_0004"><!--pb/@n='2v'--></pb>
<lb/>there are several questions I should like to put to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> one of them is.
<lb/>On what occasions did he interfere between the <orgName>natives</orgName> &amp; me. If he says 
<lb/>he ever did except in the one case of appeal which I related and
<lb/>to which I put a stop at once he tells what is decidedly untrue ᅳ When
<lb/>I was ill, he is quite right in saying that the men were sent to him
<lb/>What had they to do with me then? They were more of men than trouble 
<lb/>me with <choice><sic>any thing</sic><corr>anything</corr></choice> but sweet <term type="plant_foodstuff">reed</term>, <term type="foodstuff">beer</term>, and their own kind 
<lb/>sympathizing company more than I liked too sometimes - there
<lb/><choice><sic>were</sic><corr>was</corr></choice> only one batch of seven men employed while I was able 
<lb/>to work. These were asked for by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> and I now recollect
<lb/>he asked for them in my heinous way "<hi rend="underline">I</hi> want<hi rend="underline">"</hi>. By the by
<lb/>there was a fine row with these same men's wages in which
<lb/>had I been so disposed I could have interfered to advantage
<lb/>But I defended him when they asserted he cheated them Now 
<lb/>these same men finished the ditch &amp; the house. I had no
<lb/>more to do with these works after I was bitten. When I went
<lb/>out the first time to see <persName>Mary</persName>, the walls of the school were built
<lb/>in my absence. So we never worked conjointly except for
<lb/>a very short time &amp; with that same one batch of seven
<lb/>men whom he asked <add place="above">for</add> with the "ego" Now what he means by
<lb/>saying the men we asked were always sent to him, <hi rend="underline">Always</hi>
<lb/>what does the <hi rend="underline">always</hi> mean? We never did on one
<lb/>occasion ask for men conjointly. If the men whom I
<lb/>employed on my own works were sent to him first he may
<lb/>thank me for calling him "<foreign xml:lang="und">co mogolu</foreign>" for that but I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice>
<lb/>believe they ever were. But now I am blamed for calling him
<lb/>an old man. About the letters I think too he mistakes, they
<lb/>may have gone occasionally first to him But this I know
<lb/>I have sometimes sent them when I saw his name &amp; not mine
<lb/>which I believe happened at least once. After my return
<lb/>from my first visit to <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> I am certain they always
<lb/>came to me first But it would have been all quite right
<lb/>had the paltry circumstance not puffed up the poor old
<lb/>man's self importance. <choice><sic>Dont</sic><corr>Don't</corr></choice> mistake the tone of
<lb/>my voice when I say if grey hairs may catch at 
<lb/>every straw to bolster up its own importance surely
<lb/><hi rend="underline">I-I-I-I</hi> may do the same. Indeed if <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>E</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> really believed
<lb/>he was of 1/20 part of the importance he wishes you to understand 
<lb/>he is he would not be in such a dreadful fright lest it should
<lb/>be annihilated. I know however that if it is destroyed it
<lb/>will not be by anything that I have said or will say to his
<lb/>disadvantage</p>

	<pb n="0005" facs="liv_000587_0005"><!--pb/@n='3r'--></pb>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">2 sheet</p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">I cannot accuse myself of having behaved in the way he mentioned to
<lb/>you. Previous to our interview he had no just cause of offence and
<lb/>yet his first sentence which I took down in his presence was
<lb/>"your conduct has been dishonest dishonourable &amp; mischievous"
<lb/>there never has occurred an instance of conduct so base between
<lb/>one <term type="occupation">missionary</term> &amp; another. I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> believe there is another instance
<lb/>on record" &amp;c. Now I should like to hear these words poured out <!-- Not exactly sure about the coding here, but from what I can see zoomed in, it looks like an end quote (that doesn't match a beg. quote) and etc. abbrev. HB 6-17-13) -->
<lb/>with the <term type="animal">lamb</term> like meekness tears &amp; groans he assumed before
<lb/>you. To all this and a great deal more in the same strain
<lb/>I returned only a fair explanation of the whole of my conduct
<lb/>with my motives for acting as I did. He then went on talking
<lb/>of his honesty &amp;c. and accused me of the opposite ᅳ To this I only
<lb/>replied O <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> talk so much of your honesty. It puts one so
<lb/>much in mind of <persName>Inglis</persName>. "I must have an apology said he for
<lb/>certain words you made use of", "It is true you made a sort of
<lb/>apology but I have no right to be satisfied with that"
<lb/>He then mentioned the words, I <hi rend="underline">then &amp; then only</hi> made use
<lb/>of words which you may find fault with, for all his
<lb/>hidden anger of which I had in the note been informed by
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> <choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> came back to my mind &amp; ranged side by side with
<lb/>his boasts of honesty. And I told him of it but I used no
<lb/>epithet such as "you are an old man." I said you informed
<lb/>me that you thought I wished to drive things all my own way
<lb/>At that very time I was endeavouring to uphold your character
<lb/>in the eyes of the <orgName>natives</orgName>, for when you were weak enough
<lb/>to endeavour to make yourself <del type="strikethrough">an</del> <add place="above">a source of</add> appeal I was refusing
<lb/>to be one against you. These same seven men (one of
<lb/>whom refused to obey me &amp; went to you), declared to me that
<lb/>they had been cheated, and asked why I had brought a man
<lb/>like you with me, I said no you are not cheated, you <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice>
<lb/>yet understand wages. One said but all the people who
<lb/>come from the southward tell<del type="strikethrough">s</del> us that man is Satan
<lb/>Now I was defending your character and telling them never
<lb/>to come again to me to say a word against <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edwards</persName>
<lb/>at the very time you thought I was <add place="inline">˄</add> <add place="above">wishing to</add> driv<del type="strikethrough">ing</del><supplied>e</supplied> things all my own
<lb/>way. You insolently told me I added to let the watercourse
<lb/>alone, &amp; you would carry it on for I was always <w>cont<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-radicting</w> you. Well you got it all your own way
<lb/>&amp; from the point at which I was bitten by the <term type="animal">lion</term>, it
<lb/>had all to be <choice><sic>digged</sic><corr>dug</corr></choice> over again I said all this but
<lb/>no more on that subject &amp; I shall repeat it
    
    

	<pb n="0006" facs="liv_000587_0006"><!--pb/@n='3v'--></pb>
<lb/>I was then accused of having engaged <persName>Mebaloe</persName> privately. To this
<lb/>I replied (but not before he had accused me of holding the sentiment
<lb/>that no one should have authority over him but myself) that he
<lb/>knew of my requesting you to give <persName>Mebaloe</persName> a public charge to make
<lb/>no difference between him &amp; me. And that my sentiments were that
<lb/>no one should have authority over a <orgName>native</orgName> who <add place="below">˄</add> <add place="above">had</add> none over
<lb/>his own temper. You <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> are an example of what I mean
<lb/>and the proof is you never speak out notwithstanding all your
<lb/>boasts of honesty unless your temper boils over &amp; compels you
<lb/>I then asked why he had not spoken to me as an honest outspoken
<lb/>man would have done before going to another to <choice><sic>introdroduce</sic><corr>introduce</corr></choice>
<lb/>for him a subject into the <orgName>committee</orgName>. I <add place="above"><choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice> prove</add><del type="strikethrough">don't know</del> that
<lb/>you did but it has always looked so to me. He denied it
<lb/>point blank. I then gave him another instance of his
<lb/>honesty. But I never said one word about his temper
<lb/>or his honesty <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> the subject was introduced by himself
<lb/>He charged me first with bad temper by saying "my temper
<lb/>was my ruin," which from him tickled me not a little
<lb/>Every statement I made was introduced by himself But
<lb/>why does he shift the ground of <choice><sic>controvery</sic><corr>controversy</corr></choice> from the
<lb/>case of <persName>Mapoleane</persName> &amp; this nonentity sentence to what took
<lb/>place entirely at the interview. I assure you I did not
<lb/>say one word calculated to exasperate <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> after I had
<lb/>been informed that he had written to all the <choice><orig>bretheren</orig><reg>brethren</reg></choice> on
<lb/>the subjects before speaking to me. And had I not been
<lb/>quite confounded by the unexpected explosion it is
<lb/>probable I should have given him a great deal more
<lb/>When coming away from the interview he asked me if I objected
<lb/>to any statement in his <bibl>epistle</bibl> to the <orgName>Directors</orgName>. I said it had
<lb/>got a twist through the whole of it &amp; that my proceedings
<lb/>with respect to the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName> had had no reference to him for
<lb/>as he might remember he did not know <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> long after my
<lb/>resolution with respect to this station whether or not to use
<lb/>his own phrase he should still be <persName>Moffat</persName>'s lackey. Had he
<lb/>not delivered <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> <choice><abbr>E</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName>'s message concerning her writing to
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> <choice><abbr>M.</abbr><expan>Moffat</expan></choice></persName> I should have been able to bear most of what he
<lb/>said But that with impeachment of my veracity <unclear cert="medium">in</unclear>
<lb/>what he knows to be the truth was rather beyond me
<lb/>In conclusion on this subject I may state that whatever charges
<lb/>refer to a period antecedent to our interview I protest that
<lb/>except in the one case (of nonentity) about which I was informed
<lb/>by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> <choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> I was not conscious of ever having offended 

    

	<pb n="0007" facs="liv_000587_0007"><!--pb/@n='4r'--></pb>
<lb/>either in word or deed. And that I should be informed immediately
<lb/>if I ever did offend in either word or deed, was my pointed request
<lb/>on that occasion. It is scarcely fair on <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> to jumble all together
<lb/><choice><abbr>viz.</abbr><expan cert="high">videlicet</expan></choice>. what passed at the interview &amp; everything else he can think of.</p>
<lb/><p>I feel most anxious to have an unravelling before <choice><orig>bretheren</orig><reg>brethren</reg></choice>
<lb/>but I must be guided by what you think best as to going or staying
<lb/>I feel very unwilling to <hi rend="underline">go out to</hi> a meeting and yet I feel very anxious
<lb/>to be present at it. It cannot however be at that time if called
<lb/>for my accommodation. December or January either would
<lb/>prevent my going quite. I may say again that I am even more
<lb/>willing than I was at last <orgName><choice><abbr>com.</abbr><expan>committee</expan></choice></orgName> meeting to go to another tribe. I
<lb/>should prefer <persName>Sechele</persName> to the <term type="tribe">Bahurutse</term> but should be content
<lb/>to go to the place where there is most hope of doing good. <persName>Bube</persName>
<lb/>has always professed great friendship &amp; when here last week asked me
<lb/>if I would not come &amp; live with him; <persName>Sechele</persName>, we met on
<lb/>the path leading up to his town, &amp; after saluting <persName>Mary</persName> he said, Have
<lb/>you come to teach us? I shall come to <placeName><settlement type="village">Mabotsa</settlement></placeName> &amp; take you
<lb/>away from <persName>Moseelele</persName><!-- unsure whether this is the person or the place? ks --> &amp; make you my <term type="occupation">teacher</term>. When we talked
<lb/>to him afterwards on many other subjects we found that he always 
<lb/>said just what a sensible man in his circumstances would <add place="below">˄</add> <add place="above">be expected to</add> say
<lb/>He never said like <persName>Bube</persName> &amp; others. O I like the word of God, &amp;c.
<lb/>But when he told us that he intended removing to a fountain called
<lb/><placeName><geogName type="fountain">Kolobeñ</geogName></placeName> as soon as he heard that the <term type="tribe">Matibele</term> intended to come
<lb/>that way no more, or were defeated, in order to get a <term type="occupation">missionary</term>
<lb/>His reasons were a <term type="occupation">missionary</term> could help him in sickness
<lb/>mend his gun, teach him to read, &amp; <foreign xml:lang="und"><unclear cert="medium">'inthuta botlale</unclear></foreign><!-- African phrase, ks --> He seems
<lb/>very fond of improvements and altogether a more likely subject
<lb/>than any I have seen. He &amp; <persName>Moiloe</persName> resemble each other in
<lb/>many respects. I did not like to propose anything lest it
<lb/>should seem like anxiety on my part to go to him. If you
<lb/>come as you <add place="above">mention</add><del type="strikethrough">intend</del> before august the proposal would come
<lb/>much better from you. I long to be away from all <foreign xml:lang="und">khañ</foreign><!--african word?, ks-->
<lb/>If I get in there <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>E</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> will be clever if he can hook me into
<lb/>another scrape. ᅳ the worst I fear here in leaving without
<lb/>giving to them any sort of what they will consider a
<lb/>plausible explanation, is anger on account of appearing
<lb/>to leave in discontent or if my residence were as near as <persName>Bube</persName>
<lb/>I fear blame might be attached to me (if they removed nearer to
<lb/>that locality) as having used improper influences to induce
<lb/>them to that step. They will not come near <persName>Sechele</persName>. But
<lb/>it might be different with <persName>Bube</persName> or <persName>Moiloe</persName>. I think
<lb/>it would be right to make provision against the

    

	<pb n="0008" facs="liv_000587_0008"><!--pb/@n='4v'--></pb>
<lb/>possibility of blame. Certain remarks made by <orgName>natives</orgName> but to 
<lb/>which I never return an answer induce me to believe that some
<lb/>talk has taken place other than what a wellwisher to the cause should
<lb/>like to hear. For instance repeated allusions to the gardens as mineᅳ
<lb/>As having known me first &amp;c, without any connection; and one
<lb/>said "Do you know what we said in the <foreign xml:lang="und">peecho</foreign>. (I did not know
<lb/>there had been a <foreign xml:lang="und">pico</foreign>) "<persName>Mosielele</persName> said you were his father and if
<lb/>you left this place so would he." I made no reply, but it has
<lb/>made me think since. What can induce them to speak of the
<lb/>gardens as mine when I have invariably declared that they are
<lb/>not mine but those of the <term type="occupation">teachers</term> for the time being for ever
<lb/>But I leave this subject You will <choice><sic>percieve</sic><corr>perceive</corr></choice> that 
<lb/><persName>Sechele</persName> would perhaps be the most eligible situation
<lb/>It would be 2<choice><orig>ₑ⁄₂</orig><reg>1/2</reg></choice> days distant and as there is enmity
<lb/>between the <term type="occupation">chiefs</term> &amp; between <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>E</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> &amp; one of them we should
<lb/>not probably trouble each other</p>
<lb/><p>The plough met with an accident, in getting the mould
<lb/>board broken off <choice><sic>accross</sic><corr>across</corr></choice> by the hinder bolt. An unseen
<lb/>root was the cause. another <choice><orig>⅓</orig><reg>1/3</reg></choice> of it has since been broken
<lb/>off by another hidden root But it continued to plough
<lb/>very well <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> this evening when the foot board was broken
<lb/><choice><sic>accross</sic><corr>across</corr></choice> by the first bolt. I have put a strong band
<lb/>from the iron which <choice><sic>recieves</sic><corr>receives</corr></choice> the share round a portion
<lb/>of the wood, &amp; it is now on its legs again. We employed
<lb/>men to root out the trees &amp; they <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> seem to have acted
<lb/>conscientiously for we have found stumps which held 8 <term type="animal">oxen</term>
<lb/>covered over with mould. Your band is a <unclear cert="medium">fail me</unclear>
<lb/><unclear cert="low">never</unclear>, the iron does for everything. Will you favour
<lb/>me with the measurement horizontally of the distance between
<lb/>the end of the foot board &amp; the tail end of the mould board
<lb/>I think I must have given the mould board too great
<lb/>a lateral set for though well supported it broke off.
<lb/>Can I fall heir to the other mould board belonging to <unclear cert="medium">this</unclear>
<lb/>plough. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> made a "<foreign xml:lang="und">Tutlua</foreign>"<!-- african word, ks --> plough last year &amp; he has it yet
<lb/>I think I shall be able to make a good one next time for
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Milligan</persName> gave me an idea of the shape. We have got 5<choice><orig>ₑ⁄₂</orig><reg>1/2</reg></choice>
<lb/>buckets of <term type="plant_foodstuff">wheat</term> sown. manured the land by making a
<lb/>Kraal &amp; shifting it, highland fashion. Have you any <term type="plant_foodstuff">pease</term>
<lb/>or <term type="plant_foodstuff">beans</term> to spare for seed. I never saw the "<term type="plant_foodstuff">Cobbet's corn</term>"
<lb/>you gave me. We have <term type="plant_foodstuff">Mangold Wurzel</term> &amp; <term type="plant_foodstuff">carrots</term> growing
<lb/>well but the <term type="plant_foodstuff">potatoes</term> were nipped off by frost. I thought
<lb/>of putting up a smithy Do you think it would be proper in
<lb/><space dim="horizontal" extent="10" unit="words"/>present circumstances</p>

	<pb n="0009" facs="liv_000587_0009"><!--pb/@n='5r'--></pb>
<lb/><p>I have bought of <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Milligan</persName> <term type="animal">sheep</term> &amp; <term type="animal">goats</term> &amp;c. to the
<lb/>amount of Five Pounds and as <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cumming</persName> has proposed
<lb/>selling some things to us on his return, such as <term type="plant_foodstuff">coffee</term> &amp;c
<lb/>I prefer keeping the money I have here for that purpose
<lb/>So I send an order on you which I hope you will be kind
<lb/>enough to <del type="strikethrough">defray</del> honour discount or whatever ought
<lb/>to be done. If you ever send for tools will you order a
<lb/>large saw for me? that strong hand-saw you kindly
<lb/>gave is completely bent in sawing up trees for planks
<lb/>I see nothing will do but the large pit saws for
<lb/>that purpose. I hope you did not forget the <term type="occupation">smiths</term>
<lb/>bellows. If I leave this they will be indispensable for a 
<lb/>new station</p>
<lb/><p>I intended to have written the <orgName>Directors</orgName> by this 
<lb/>opportunity on the subject of <persName>Mokoteri</persName>, the ly<gap extent="6" unit="chars" agent="hole"/>
<lb/>of that affair you will find by what I say will <gap extent="6" unit="chars" agent="hole"/>
<lb/>with the <orgName>committee</orgName>, I shall let you have it and with 
<lb/>it <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ashton</persName><supplied cert="high">'</supplied>s &amp; your advice <add place="below">˄</add>, <add place="above">me</add> "Get out of it the best
<lb/>way you can." I shall state my belief as an individual
<lb/>that it would be improper to employ <persName>Mokoteri</persName> in any way
<lb/>whatever in the mission, that belief being founded on
<lb/>the testimony of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> ____ ____ ____ ___ which I <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> as
<lb/>true in the first <orgName>committee</orgName>. And also on the consideration
<lb/>that <del type="strikethrough">it would be</del> <add place="above">it is</add> <add place="below">˄</add> <add place="above">in general</add> improper for one <term type="occupation">missionary</term> to
<lb/>give countenance to a <orgName>native</orgName> when that countenance might
<lb/>be construed into opposition or condemnation of his
<lb/><choice><orig>bretheren</orig><reg>brethren</reg></choice>. Witness the same case in the hands of <unclear cert="medium"><persName>Inglis</persName></unclear> at
<lb/><placeName><settlement type="town">Bethelsdorp</settlement></placeName> And then as being a man of yesterday I
<lb/>shall politely hand it over to the "collective wisdom"
<lb/>of which we all entertain a high opinion ᅳ
<lb/>I should have written now. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.</persName> has come before I
<lb/>anticipated. I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> understand what you mean by, being
<lb/>"in it." the <orgName>Directors</orgName>, <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ashton</persName>, <persName>Inglis</persName> &amp; you are in
<lb/>it &amp; ought to get out of it But I have not been in it yet
<lb/>except as part of a <orgName>committee</orgName>. Perhaps I ought to be called
<lb/>a nothing or neer do well or thing of yesterday because<gap agent="illegible" extent="1" unit="words"/>
	<cb rend="vertical"/>
<lb/><orgName>Directors</orgName> in your &amp; my own views are to <gap extent="15" unit="chars" agent="hole"/><choice><sic>recieving</sic><corr>receiving</corr></choice> our unit<gap extent="9" unit="chars" agent="hole"/>my. We shall
<lb/>see what the <orgName>committee</orgName> will say of <hi rend="underline">me</hi> whose testimony <gap extent="4" unit="chars" agent="hole"/> set at nought just as well <gap extent="3" unit="chars" agent="hole"/> yours, unless you
<lb/>mean to address yourselves to me I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> understand the advice "get <hi rend="underline">out</hi> of it". If I were a <term type="occupation">director</term> it would do</p>

	<pb n="0010" facs="liv_000587_0010"><!--pb/@n='5v'--></pb>
	<ab>
<lb/><date when="1845-06-18">18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June</date> Please observe the bill I have given
<lb/>is Eleven Pounds Sixteen shillings Not Five Pounds
<lb/>as stated within. The increase was for <term type="animal">cows</term></ab>
	<ab>
<lb/><persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> <choice><abbr>R.</abbr><expan>Robert</expan></choice> Moffat</persName>
<lb/><space extent="1" unit="words"/><hi rend="underline"><placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName></hi></ab>
	<ab>
<lb/><space extent="1" unit="words"/>Please send a bit of old copper for soldering
<lb/>See how attentive I am to rid you of your rubbish</ab>
<!-- Extra notes inserted vertically in the top margin by Robert Moffat dated Mabotsa 6th June 1845: 'The third sheet to be answered as it contains a libel & makes me an enemy to an important department of Missionary labour RM Mr L wants light' -->
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>