<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P5 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000507">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Manning Prentice</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Manning Prentice, 8 April 1842</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London, UK</pubPlace>
				<publisher>University College London</publisher>
				<date>2012</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000507</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">University of London. School of Oriental and African Studies; CWM/LMS/Livingstone Wooden Box, item 19</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0052</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Prentice, Manning</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1842-04-08">8 April 1842</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">[Bakwain Country]</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2012-04-17</date>
				<name xml:id="AJS">AJ Schmitz</name>Initial transcription and XML encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-09-18</date>
				<name xml:id="KS">Kathryn Simpson</name>Proofreading
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-10-08</date>
				<name xml:id="HFB">Heather F. Ball</name> XML editing.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2016-05-01</date>
				<name xml:id="AM">Anne Martin</name>Final Review
            
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000507_0001"><!--pb/@n='1r'--></pb>
<lb/><p rend="right"><space extent="10" unit="words"/><date when="1842-04-08">8<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> April 1842</date></p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">My dear <persName>Manning</persName></p>
<lb/><p><space dim="horizontal" extent="12" unit="chars"/>I feel much pleasure in commencing an epistle to you but 
<lb/>whether you will feel as much in perusing it is another question, The place 
<lb/>whence I now write you is the residence of <persName>Bubi</persName> one of the <term type="tribe">Bakwain</term> <term type="occupation">chiefs</term> 
<lb/>The town is situated on the top of a hill which forms part of a pretty extensive 
<lb/>range and from its height it feels much pleasanter than in the plains below 
<lb/>Round the bottom and through a deep defile which separates this from another 
<lb/>part of the range runs a river not very large but superior to the <w>contem<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-ptible</w> thing that runs past <placeName><settlement  type="town">Ongar</settlement></placeName>. In this country such a stream is 
<lb/>invaluable for <term type="occupation">irrigating</term> the land. I came here for the purpose of 
<lb/>assisting a <orgName>native</orgName> <term type="occupation">teacher</term> to commence operations and likewise to 
<lb/>perfect myself in the language by cutting myself off from all <orgName>European</orgName> 
<lb/>conversation. A great deal of intercourse being necessary on account 
<lb/>of the want <supplied cert="high">of</supplied> any <bibl>dictionary</bibl> except such as every one constructs 
<lb/>for himself. After we commenced school for the children I wished 
<lb/>to lead out some water to <term type="occupation">irrigate</term> a garden for <persName>Pomore</persName>. (The <term type="occupation">teacher</term>) 
<lb/>And when I explained that this was my way of making rain and 
<lb/>how far superior it was to their enchantments all were quite 
<lb/>delighted with the idea. The <term type="occupation">chief</term> sent as many men as I needed &amp; 
<lb/>we proceeded to operations in the best way we could.  We have raised 
<lb/>a huge dam of earth &amp; stones and dug a canal which will water many 
<lb/>gardens. And the whole of the labour has been performed by themselves 
<lb/>for I was unable after the first day to stimulate them as I wished, on 
<lb/>account of having got both <term type="bodypart">legs</term> &amp; <term type="bodypart">arms</term> severely <term type="ailment">sunburned</term>. And 
<lb/>that too although most of the time immersed in the water 
<lb/>the <term type="occupation">digging</term> was performed by sharpened sticks. When they came to a 
<lb/>large stone too large to lift out they had just to dig round it so it is quite 
<lb/>of a zig zag form. The earth was lifted out in handfuls &amp; carried to 
<lb/>the dam in their karosses, a wooden bowl or <term type="animal">tortoise</term> shell. After nearly 
<lb/>completing it a tornado came down &amp; swept a great portion of our 
<lb/>work away, but after looking a little with rueful countenances 
<lb/>they commenced again with all their might. I have been the
<lb/>more astonished at the industry of these wild ignorant <orgName>heathen</orgName>, as    
<lb/>the early <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> could never get them to work. At <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName>
<lb/>the <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> have been obliged to perform most of the manual 
<lb/>labour themselves. Working even for wages was almost out of 
<lb/>prospect of a future <del type="cancelled">benefit</del><add place="above">benefit</add> held out before them. I have no 
<lb/>doubt but you could have managed the business much better 
<lb/>I did not even think of it when I left home, (So I should imagine 
<lb/>that many things of a like nature will occur to you and if 
<lb/>you can gain their attention and affection you will do great 
<lb/>good among them) I am quite ignorant of the scientific way 
<lb/>of <term type="occupation">irrigation</term>. It was almost all guess work &amp; with a trembling 
<lb/>heart I watched <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> I saw the water assume its new course</p>

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000507_0002"><!--pb/@n='1v'--></pb>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">You can by ingenuity lead the <orgName>people</orgName> but one can never force them. They 
<lb/>are mere children and although they have the passions of men thay are as 
<lb/>easily pleased as babies. <choice><orig>Shew</orig><reg>Show</reg></choice> one a looking glass &amp; he will almost go 
<lb/>into convulsions laughing at his own image. But if you are habitually kind 
<lb/>to any one in particular you will spoil him &amp; get the envy of the rest. He 
<lb/>immediately thinks he has a right to what he gets &amp; becomes impudent. To this 
<lb/>the <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> here never knew an exception. You require therefore 
<lb/>to study their characters a little and then there is no difficulty in guiding them 
<lb/>you must expect disappointments among them for they are an <w>exceeding<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-ly</w> selfish <orgName>race</orgName> &amp; it by no means leaves them entirely when they become 
<lb/><orgName>Christians</orgName>, to this however there are exceptions. The <orgName>people</orgName> here are 
<lb/>more simple &amp; know less of vice or at least the vices of <orgName>Europeans</orgName> than 
<lb/>those further to the <placeName><region>South</region></placeName>.  They <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> hate the <bibl>gospel</bibl> because they <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice>
<lb/>know it. I think they are not so greedy either. Towards the <placeName><region>South</region></placeName> if 
<lb/>one follows you into the field he will ask payment for it May even 
<lb/>the children after having enjoyed in play with the children of the <term type="occupation">missionary</term> 
<lb/>will sometimes come and demand payment for the same. Part of the 
<lb/>reason of this may be the manner in which they treated the first <term type="occupation"><w>mission<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-aries</w></term> induced them to give to almost everyone who asked. They live in danger 
<lb/>of their lives &amp; durst not say a sharp word to them. Here I have ventured 
<lb/>on a different plan<del type="strikethrough">t</del> I pay all baneful debt mere begging I <w>discour<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-age</w> by speaking out in pla<gap agent="illegible" extent="2" unit="chars"/><supplied cert="high">in</supplied><add place="inline">˄</add><add place="above">terms</add> from the <term type="occupation">king</term> downwards. They begin <!-- I think the illegible coding should be switched to strikethrough? HB 10/8/12 -->
<lb/>now to understand that I am not to be imposed on, the other day the 
<lb/><term type="occupation">king</term> came &amp; begged something. I answered <persName>Bubi</persName> you know I hate beggars 
<lb/>He disappeared in an instant. Some <orgName>natives</orgName> from a tribe about 
<lb/>100 miles south of this came on a visit while the dam was in progress 
<lb/>&amp; told the <orgName>people</orgName> that they ought to demand payment for that 
<lb/>work. Next day when they began to be tired they told me what the 
<lb/>strangers had said, adding that the <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> at <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> always 
<lb/><del type="strikethrough">demanded</del><add place="above">gave</add> payment &amp; they did not mean to work without. I told 
<lb/>them it was all kindness in one to <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice> them how to do such a 
<lb/>work &amp; instead of my paying them they ought to pay me but as they 
<lb/>were discontented we should drop it instantly. I left them immediately 
<lb/>as it was only to try me they felt sorry they had proceeded so far 
<lb/>and came begging I should not cease to <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice> them how to work 
<lb/>the <term type="occupation">king</term> himself joining them saying I must not think of leaving 
<lb/>them alone it was just their foolishness. Perhaps these little incidents 
<lb/>will let you see what sort of <orgName>people</orgName> you will have to deal with.
<lb/>It is not so much the present as the future we have to look to. We    
<lb/>must stimulate them to industry. Giving without making them feel 
<lb/>that they have earned what they receive has a very bad effect 
<lb/>it makes them covetous &amp; does not tend to advance their civilization 
<lb/>This is the effect of all these clothes sent out by kind friends in 
<lb/><placeName><country>England</country></placeName>. If it were in the power of the <term type="occupation">missionary</term> to dispose 
<lb/>of these articles for payment in labour they would be a benefit 
<lb/>to the <orgName>people</orgName> But they are to be distributed &amp; the distribution  
<lb/>however conducted is the cause of heart burnings without end 
<lb/>amongst all both rich &amp; poor. Even <persName>Mahura</persName> the <term type="occupation">chief</term> of the <term type="tribe"><unclear cert="low">Batlape</unclear></term>
<lb/>grumbled because he did not get some of the clothes sent out for the</p>

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000507_0003"><!--pb/@n='2r'--></pb>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent"><orgName>poor of <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName></orgName>. When you come therefore much of plans whereby 
<lb/>you will make them benefit themselves. A <term type="occupation">trader</term> can do more for the 
<lb/>mere civilization than a <term type="occupation">missionary</term>. The <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> deny this but it is 
<lb/>to me quite apparent. The <orgName>natives</orgName> here never imitate the <term type="occupation">missionaries</term>. (I <unclear cert="medium">mean</unclear>
<lb/>at <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName>) We have Christianized but the <orgName>natives</orgName> have preferred to 
<lb/>imitate the <orgName>Griquas</orgName> who have a remnant of the customs of the <term type="nationality">Dutch</term>  <orgName><choice><sic><orig>boor</orig></sic><corr>Boor</corr><reg>Boer</reg></choice></orgName>
<lb/>There is only one square house in <placeName><settlement type="village"><choice><abbr>K.</abbr><expan>Kuruman</expan></choice></settlement></placeName> besides those of the <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> &amp; 
<lb/><term type="occupation">traders</term> &amp; that was built by a <orgName>Hottentot</orgName> &amp; is now uninhabited. All the <!-- I have forgotten are we marking up Hottentot as tribe?, ks, 18.9.12 -->
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> live in their old beehive huts as they did in the beginning. At 
<lb/><placeName><settlement type="village">Moteeto</settlement></placeName> there is not one <orgName>native</orgName> house square. And only now they are 
<lb/>beginning at <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Helman</persName>'s to erect a few square houses. I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> know 
<lb/>what is best to be done. I should think our chief hopes be in the infant 
<lb/>schools <space dim="horizontal" extent="10" unit="chars"/>Here I could build <persName>Thomas</persName> a house for a few <choice><abbr>lbs</abbr><expan>pounds</expan></choice>
<lb/>of beads &amp; would certainly begin if I knew his intentions but I have 
<lb/>not had a single line from him, If I were certain he would come 
<lb/>I could place it in a sufficient state of forwardness for his <w>recept- 
<lb break="no"/>-ion</w> soon after his arrival but I am quite in the dark. I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> like 
<lb/>to begin one although it would not be great trouble while mixing with 
<lb/>people to learn the language But perhaps I am speaking <choice><sic>to</sic><corr>too</corr></choice><w>confid<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-ently</w>. I have not yet tried <term type="occupation">housebuilding</term> though I succeeded pretty 
<lb/>well in <term type="occupation">irrigation</term>. You must take care &amp; never let your temper 
<lb/>get soured on beholding the ingratitude of the <orgName>natives</orgName>. You will be tried 
<lb/>but rather be a stoic than otherwise. You ought to have a plow &amp; above 
<lb/>all a smith<supplied cert="high">'</supplied>s apparatus if you can work a little in that way. But these 
<lb/>things are not so absolutely necessary as the first <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> would 
<lb/>had you to believe. They were indeed for them but I have been unable 
<lb/>to see that they are so to us, A good stock of medicines. These have <gap extent="4" unit="chars" agent="blotting"/><supplied cert="high">been</supplied>
<lb/>exceedingly serviceable to me but <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName> will say the <choice><sic>smiths</sic><corr>smith</corr></choice> bellows 
<lb/>above everything. For this part &amp; all before us beads are the only coin 
<lb/>so as many of these as you can bring. You may either purchase these 
<lb/>in the <placeName><region>Colony</region></placeName> or in <placeName><country>England</country></placeName> I suppose they are cheaper at home than in 
<lb/>the <placeName><region>Colony</region></placeName>. They are the only circulating medium, tin vessels, knives 
<lb/>snuffboxes must do instead of money, money itself <choice><sic>wont</sic><corr>won't</corr></choice>, small looking 
<lb/>glasses, here &amp; nearer to <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> handkerchiefs. I did not like to give
<lb/>beads at first &amp; so great was my prejudice against them I brought none 
<lb/>to <placeName><settlement type="village"><choice><abbr>K.</abbr><expan>Kuruman</expan></choice></settlement></placeName> but I cannot now help thinking that they look much the better of a 
<lb/>few round their dirty <term type="bodypart">necks</term> &amp; <term type="bodypart">arms</term>.<space dim="horizontal" extent="6" unit="chars"/>You need not fear the langua<gap agent="cutoff" extent="2" unit="chars"/><supplied cert="high">ge</supplied>
<lb/>it is easy. I have found no difficulty with it &amp; I am no great genius at the
<lb/>languages. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName> represents it exceedingly difficult &amp; it was so to him 
<lb/>but it will never be so to any one else. The only difficulty in it is the <w>jumb<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>ling</w> way of speaking it many of the <orgName>natives</orgName> have. With those who speak it 
<lb/>well one finds no difficulty in understanding. It was indeed a great work in 
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>M</abbr><expan>Moffat</expan></choice></persName> to reduce it to writing &amp; no one can understand it fully but himself 
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hamilton</persName> is always quoted by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>M</abbr><expan>Moffat</expan></choice></persName> as never having acquired the 
<lb/>language but the reason is quite plain. He never once made an effort 
<lb/>He has the <term type="nationality">Dutch</term> will, is an easy soft sort of good man, uses an <term type="occupation">interpreter</term> 
<lb/>&amp; thus content with his crutch goes on in the old way. <choice><sic>Dont</sic><corr>Don't</corr></choice> fear it</p>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000507_0004"><!--pb/@n='2v'--></pb>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">It would be well for <persName>Thomas</persName> if he were ordained or had his A.M.<!-- unsure of the abbv, could it be assistant missionary?, ks, 18.912 --> You <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice>
<lb/>conceive <choice><sic>how how</sic><corr>how</corr></choice> much heartburning there has been among the <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> 
<lb/>on the subject of ordination. Those who look down on those who are 
<lb/>not ordained. Both you &amp; <persName>Thomas</persName> must feel yourselves thoroughly underpaid an<gap agent="cutoff" extent="1" unit="chars"/><supplied cert="medium">d</supplied>
<lb/>You must not take the opinions of anyone as your guide but examine for 
<lb/>yourselves &amp; act accordingly. Choose friends with whom you can assimilate 
<lb/>of whatever society they may be &amp; let the narrowminded touchy people pass b<gap agent="cutoff" extent="1" unit="chars"/><supplied cert="high">y</supplied>
<lb/>This is what I am determined to do. I will never <choice><sic>asociate</sic><corr>associate</corr></choice> with a <orgName><placeName><settlement type="city">London</settlement></placeName>
<lb/><choice><abbr>Soc.</abbr><expan>Society</expan></choice> man</orgName> because he is such, but with amiable <orgName>Christians</orgName> wherever I can 
<lb/>find them ᅳ  A number of the <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> are unordained <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName>

<!-- Text interrupted by postal information; continues after break at bottom of page HB 10/8/12 -->
	<cb/>
<lb/><persName>Edwards</persName>, <persName>Hamilton</persName> <persName>Hughs</persName>. I do not attach any importance to ordination 
<lb/>I only wish all had been ordained it would have prevented some from <w>desp- 
<lb break="no"/>-ising</w> others who remain without that ceremony having been performed 
<lb/>on them. Please Remember me very kindly to <persName>Thomas</persName>: <persName><unclear cert="medium">Firons</unclear></persName>, &amp; 
<lb/><persName>Miss Ridley</persName> if you see her at anytime. I have just got one <bibl>letter from 
<lb/>home</bibl> since I left, but I hope to find <bibl>letters</bibl> at <placeName><settlement type="village"><choice><abbr>K</abbr><expan>Kuruman</expan></choice></settlement></placeName> in June or July when I 
<lb/>return. Will you write a long <bibl>letter</bibl>? There is no need for teetotalism 
<lb/>here, they make <term type="foodstuff">beer</term> but it does not intoxicate. it only causes sleep &amp; 
<lb/>profuse sweating. At <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> however they make intoxicating <term type="foodstuff">beer</term> of <term type="foodstuff">honey</term></p>
	<ab/>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent"><del type="strikethrough">Care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Phillips</persName><space dim="horizontal" extent="5" unit="chars"/><placeName><settlement type="city">Cape Town</settlement></placeName></del></p>
<lb/><p rend="center"><persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Manning Prentice</persName></p>
<lb/><p>1842<space dim="horizontal" extent="3" unit="words"/><placeName>Violet Hill</placeName></p>
<lb/><p rend="right"><space dim="horizontal" extent="2" unit="words"/><placeName><settlement type="town">Stowmarket</settlement></placeName></p>
<lb/><p rend="right"><space dim="horizontal" extent="3" unit="words"/><placeName><region>Suffolk</region></placeName></p>
<lb/><p><hi rend="underline">single sheet</hi><space dim="horizontal" extent="2" unit="words"/><placeName><country>England</country></placeName></p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>