<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000695">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Benjamin T. Pyne</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Benjamin T. Pyne, 4 March, 2 August 1850</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2009</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000695</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0225</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2009-04-04</date>
				<name xml:id="initials">SM</name>Initial Transcription by 
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000695_0001"/><!--pb/@n='01'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Kolobeng</placeName> 4<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">th</hi></hi> March</p>
<lb/><p>1850 </p>
<lb/><p>My Very Dear Friends 
<lb/>I am ashamed to remember that your last 
<lb/>letter is still unanswered although it has been by us for 2 or 3 
<lb/>months. My wife will bear none of the blame in that respect 
<lb/>imitating <persName>Mrs P</persName>. after she got my scolding. I was quite proud 
<lb/>when I found it has some effect and wish <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> P</persName> would touch 
<lb/>up my better half occasionally too. We could work to each 
<lb/>other's hands nicely. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he reason why I did not answer it 
<lb/>sooner was I have till tonight been going on under the 
<lb/>impression that I had answered it long ago, but <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>L</persName> insists 
<lb/>I have not. Mary's was a beautiful and most 
<w>interest-<lb break="no"/>ing</w> letter. She takes after her mother. I cannot possibly 
<lb/>answer her now as we are going to the North in a few days 
<lb/>and are busy <del type="strikethrough">now</del> preparing. If she will excuse me I shall 
<lb/>write during the journey and send it off as soon as we return 
<lb/>the box about which you advised us came to hand two 
<lb/>days ago. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>nd it afforded us a great amount of pleasure 
<lb/>but pleasure is not all - the contents are are all really useful 
<lb/>Mary says <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>P</persName> has anticipated all her wants and provided 
<lb/>for them with the kindness of a mother. It is impossible to 
<lb/>specify the different articles - they are so numerous. I was 
<lb/>nearly out of shirts and did not know what to do for the journey 
<lb/>for last time I went every washing wearing one or two of 
<lb/>my stock through the middle. Half a dozen from my mother in 
<lb/><placeName>Scotland</placeName> &amp; yours have quite set me out. I have not looked 
<lb/>over all the articles, but you must accept our hearty &amp; 
<lb/>sincere thanks for the whole. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he seeds I am sorry to say 
<lb/>were spoiled, they seem to have been put up too moist &amp; 
<lb/>and were gone bad probably your climate is not dry enough 
<lb/>for putting up in tins. If you try again it may be well 
<lb/>to put them up simply in brown paper. Our garden is useless from want of water. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he olive plants around 
<lb/>our table are the only vegetables that seen to thrive here<reg>.</reg>

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000695_0002"/><!--pb/@n='02'-->
<lb/>We had a pleasant visit from <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Freeman</persName>. He came a 
<lb/>few days before 49 fled &amp; left a few days after 50 began. We 
<lb/>outlandish people forgot to wish him a happy new year. We 
<lb/>have no holidays - but I thought we might have so planned 
<lb/>a trip of about a days journey to a cave. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he Bakwains 
<lb/>would not go near it. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey have a tradition that some people 
<lb/>went in &amp; never came out. One called <persName>Kobokoe</persName> went in 
<lb/>and was never seen again - Flocks of sheep were some 
<lb/>times seen near its mouth but when one went near they ran 
<lb/>in. His old people thought I should never return and <persName>Sechele</persName> said 
<lb/>he would go in if I did. We took a lantern - a line &amp; ladder<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>It is on the face of a hill about 600 feet high. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he waggon with 
<lb/>wife &amp; children stood at the bottom and the firm believers in old tales 
<lb/>looked at us <add place="above">ascending</add> with awe. I thought it might be a mile in length but 
<lb/>alas it was not 20 yards deep. We went in &amp; spoke to those 
<lb/>who had the <unclear cert="low">hardihood</unclear> to follow (some boys were among the number) on the follies of the old system, and that all their other tales were 
<lb/>equally absurd. It seems to have been a fountain of water 
<lb/>in ancient times - I crept to the extremity &amp; deposited a <unclear cert="low">father 
<lb/>Mathew</unclear> &amp; token and a bullet, and when the old men denied 
<lb/>that we had entered we replied go to the end of it and you will 
<lb/>find these. O that they were wise. We went from thence 
<lb/>about two miles &amp; visited the spot where with Bube I led 
<lb/>out the stream. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>here lay the stones we had lifted up &amp; 
<lb/>the serpentine form of the water course was still easily traced 
<lb/>but no gurgling stream ran by - the drought has dried up all 
<lb/>the Bakwain streams. After spending a day among these 
<lb/>scenes we returned much pleased with our trip. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he 
<lb/>children having had the hooping cough was the thing that prompted 
<lb/>me to this excursion. I forgot to say that all have not been 
<lb/>so superstitious for some one had cut down a tree at the door 
<lb/>way &amp; must have seen into the end of it. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he young branches 
<lb/>which were now young trees shewed that he must have 
<lb/>done many years ago. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his is a long digression &amp; I have 
<lb/>been led away by the word holiday. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>Freeman</persName><unclear cert="low">remembers</unclear>

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000695_0003"/><!--pb/@n='03'-->
<lb/>wish us a happy &amp;c. He was much pleased with <persName>Sechele</persName> &amp; 
<lb/>wishes him to go to England. I had no idea that he would care 
<lb/>about curiousities or I should have had some collected together 
<lb/>the great difficulty of transmitting anything to the coast deters me 
<lb/>from collecting. He got a few horns of animals &amp;c here - left 
<lb/>me a fine prospect glass &amp; some hooks. His visit was very 
<lb/>agreeable indeed. He had an apparatus for the Daguerrotype 
<lb/>and tried hard to take me but something in our water prevented. 
<lb/>Had you seen it you would perhaps have thought me rather 
<lb/>unclerical with masterchions  if that is the way to spell it. 
<lb/>I am becoming loyal now like <persName>Prince Albert</persName> but this is to prevent 
<lb/>my lips being burned by the sun. We were sorry the visit 
<lb/>was so short and, our accomodation is so poor - 
<lb/>the object of the deputation was to reduce the expensditure from <add place="above">£</add>
<lb/>to £4000. Something this ought to be effected by allowing the 
<lb/>members of the old colonials stations to support the gospel among 
<lb/>themselves. Others that if we let the hottentots alone they would 
<lb/>sink into their former state. We are the only society which does 
<lb/>attend to the wants of the coloured population the Wesleyan &amp; 
<lb/>Dutch reformed attend exclusively to the whites. Now these worthy 
<lb/>men excuse themselves from attending to the blacks because we 
<lb/>do. "It would be unbrotherly to try &amp; take them out of our hands" 
<lb/>the thing goes round in a circle then the hottentots being 
<w>provid-<lb break="no"/>ed</w> with the gospel free of expense, are not likely 
<lb/>to act as free 
<lb/>independent Christian men. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey are in tutelage perpetually 
<lb/>and the society is a sort of go cart to them. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his would be 
<lb/>little if they were not unconsciously the barrier which 
<lb/>prevents the flow of the stream of benevolence to the 
<lb/>real heathen lands. <persName>N<hi rend="sup">r</hi>F.</persName> has taken up <persName>D<hi rend="sup"/>r</persName> Philips<reg>'</reg>
<lb/>idea that the colonial stations must be kept up for ever 
<lb/>and aye, and though we expected much from his visit 
<lb/>it is not likely to be of much service in as far as an 
<lb/>onward movement is concerned. He was much pleased 
<lb/>with the prospect beyond us and said it ought to be kept 
<lb/>open for our society. We are now going in a weary 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000695_0004"/><!--pb/@n='04'-->
<lb/><unclear cert="low">weary of</unclear>600 miles in order to see if there is any good locality for 
<lb/>a mission. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he children will probably be the better of the trip and I hope 
<lb/>so will the mother. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he natives in there had never any idea of the 
<lb/>value of ivory and now there is quite a rush into that region 
<lb/>of Grequees and Bechuanas and Whites: it is our <placeName>California</placeName> but 
<lb/>more will come away disappointed than joyous. 3 English 
<lb/>men left us yesterday. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>wo are officers from <placeName>India</placeName> and the 
<lb/>third a young man who has traversed <placeName>N &amp; S. America</placeName> and 
<lb/>published a book on the latter. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey were accompanied part 
<lb/>of the way by a gentleman called <persName>Nichols</persName> who came out from 
<lb/><placeName>England</placeName> to "discover the Lake" but before he had travelled many 
<lb/>days. He said why this is terrible. One can<reg>'</reg>t get anything to eat 
<lb/>I shall return to my wife. He brought the young traveller all 
<lb/>the way from <placeName>England</placeName> in order to sketch the Lake for him 
<lb/>they have gone off in high glee but they don<reg>'</reg>t know the weary 
<lb/>way before them. I pity my poor wife, but I can not leave 
<lb/>her here. And she is quite willing to go. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> T</persName>was 
<w>accompan-<lb break="no"/>ied</w> by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName> &amp; his daughter <persName>Ann</persName>. <persName>Sechele</persName> has brought 
<lb/>a waggon and will accompany us to <persName>Sebitoane</persName> who 
<lb/>formerly saved his life. We shall form a party of 30 or 40 
<lb/>and having some good shots among them we shall probably 
<lb/>be well supplied with game. Pray for us and that that 
<lb/>the way may be prepared for the spread of the gospel. We 
<w>as-<lb break="no"/>cend</w> a large river coming down from the North about 
<lb/>200 miles. Would <persName>Bernaird</persName> like to go &amp; <persName>Morland</persName> to gather 
<lb/>some seeds. <persName>Robert</persName> is quite pleased to go but will be tired 
<lb/>long before he sees <placeName>Kolobeng</placeName> again. I wrote a long letter 
<lb/>to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Taylor</persName> for a projected periodical he told me of 
<lb/>but suppose it has never come to anything - a note 
<lb/>enclosed in the box near the seeds is I am sorry to say 
<lb/>totally illegible except 4 lines - "acknowledge it by 
<lb/>some message." &amp; then something about <persName>Morland</persName> &amp; seeds 
<lb/>the moisture from the seeds has destroyed it<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>

	<pb n="0005" facs="liv_000695_0005"/><!--pb/@n='05'-->
<lb/>Very sorry to hear by our friend <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Sewell</persName> that <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>P</persName> has 
<lb/>suffered much from poor health, but hope she has by 
<lb/>this time been restored to her usual health. And that the 
<lb/>affliction has answered the end intended by Him who 
<lb/>sent it. We are favoured with pretty fair health in 
<lb/>this climate. <choice><orig>t</orig><reg>T</reg></choice>he country around us is beautiful but 
<lb/>very dry. <choice><orig>t</orig><reg>T</reg></choice>he <placeName>Kolobeng</placeName> is quite dried up except in pools 
<lb/>here &amp; there. I don<reg>'</reg>t remember whether I introduced our 
<lb/>youngest <persName>Thomas Steele</persName> to your acquaintanceship. He 
<lb/>according to <persName>Grandfather Moffat</persName> "is a noble fellow" "the 
<lb/>finest infant he ever saw" His weaning commenced 
<lb/>today. He is always ready for fun. My man Friday is very 
<lb/>proud of the black hat and his visage becomes it well 
<lb/>it only wants a shade or two to be of ther same colour. <choice><orig>t</orig><reg>T</reg></choice>he 
<lb/>naval cap nearly fits your humble servant at the 
<lb/>head of the medical profession in the <placeName>Bokone</placeName>. We got 
<lb/>a few apples yesterday from <placeName>Kuruman</placeName>. <choice><orig>t</orig><reg>T</reg></choice>hey vividly 
<lb/>brought to my recollection some I got from you for 
<lb/>shipboard. I planted the seeds of them but they did not 
<lb/>suceed. I shall enclose a few seeds in this of 
<lb/>a kind of hibiscus from which the people at the 
<lb/>lake make their nets. <choice><orig>t</orig><reg>T</reg></choice>he flower is rather pretty - the 
<lb/>mebaic very strong. <choice><orig>t</orig><reg>T</reg></choice>hose in your tin - smelt so 
<lb/>strongly when opened as to make me turn away 
<lb/>my head and I am not easily moved by a twingle 
<lb/>of the olfactory nerve. Have heard from <persName>Moore</persName>
<lb/>lately at <placeName><del type="strikethrough">Colchester</del></placeName><placeName>Congleton</placeName>. Very kind regards 
<lb/>to Mary. I began to fear she was dead and she may 
<lb/>set me down as good as defunct for not writing her now<reg>.</reg>

	<pb n="0006" facs="liv_000695_0006"/><!--pb/@n='06'-->
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L</persName> very tired with the long journey of 1200 miles 
<lb/>shall write you at length very soon<reg>.</reg> Excuse the 
<lb/>great blunder of taking this with us, instead of 
<lb/>leaving it. Kind love to all the family every one<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Believe me dear friends 
<lb/>Yours ever Affectionately 
<lb/><persName>D Livingston</persName></p>
<lb/><p rend="left"><persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L</persName> writes with me 
<lb/>
in love &amp; thanks </p>
<lb/><p>
<address>
<addrLine>Care of the <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>D<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi>Philip</persName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName><hi rend="underline">Cape Town</hi></placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><persName>Benjamin Pyne Esq<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">re</hi></hi></persName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>Wildingtree</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>Ongar Essex</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>England</placeName></addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<lb/><p>2<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">d</hi></hi> August - this letter was finished long ago but by 
<lb/>mistake was not posted. It went with us to the Lake &amp; 
<lb/>we have just returned. I am very sorry for it but an opportunity 
<lb/>occurs and I gladly embrace it. <choice><orig>t</orig><reg>T</reg></choice>wo of the children 
<lb/>had fever at the Lake but God in mercy raised 
<lb/>them up. Our people too who had it were spared 
<lb/>while one English gentleman died &amp; two of their people<reg>.</reg></p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>