<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000572">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to George Drummond</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to George Drummond, 21 November 1844</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2008-08-27</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000572</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0112</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2008-04-02</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>Initial Transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000572_0001"/><!--pb/@n='19r'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Mabotsa</placeName>
<lb/>21 Nov 1844 </p>
<lb/><p>My Dear <persName>Brother Drummond</persName></p>
<lb/><p>Your welcome and excellent letter written 
<lb/>at some queer outlandish place where it seems <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Chisholme</persName> among 
<lb/>other good deeds is doing the needful towards augmenting the worlds 
<lb/>population found me in my monkish all a few days ago as happy 
<lb/>as any of you domesticated animals and (miserbile dictu) first on 
<lb/>the eve of becoming one myself. Tempus intanta &amp;c. But 
<lb/>I cannot leave the batchelor life without a sigh. What infatuation 
<lb/>you labour under to rejoice after having <add place="above">had</add> your nose held to the 
<lb/>"grindstone" for such a length of time and what infatutation I am 
<lb/>under myself. In love!! words yea thoughts fail so I leave it to your 
<lb/>imagination &amp; recollection -- I am it seems after all to be 
<lb/>hooked to <persName>Miss Moffat</persName> (<persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffats</persName> first daughter) in about three 
<lb/>weeks hence. I am just finishing my house. It is something like 
<lb/>your own I suppose <add place="above">one</add> rather more primitive. 52 feet in length &amp; 
<lb/>20 broad, containing a study bedroom &amp; parlour - , &amp; pantry, kitchen 
<lb/>apart from the house. It is stone do you think? Nay but 
<lb/>a much easier material to mould. viz. plastic rind. We dash 
<lb/>it about a foot thick and then cut it straight with a spade 
<lb/>and such is the heat of the luminary that <persName>Fairbrother</persName> won<reg>'</reg>t call 
<lb/>the sun over our heads before two hours you would wonder 
<lb/>where the water has gone. Indeed one hours exposure makes 
<lb/>it difficult <unclear cert="low">Dent</unclear> We are up walls in no time after the 
<w>found-<lb break="no"/>ation</w> is laid and they are as hard as brick almost. Let <persName>Moore</persName>
<lb/>good dear fellow know of my marriage. It will comfort all 
<lb/>your hearts to know I am become as great a fool as 
<lb/>any of you. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he pickle he was in at the time he wrote 
<lb/>the note predictates something in the population line I suppose 
<lb/>But he did not mention among his other duties the washing of 
<lb/>the baby's <unclear cert="low">unmentionables</unclear>. He won<reg>'</reg>t stick in the world nor will 
<lb/>I if I can help it. </p>
<lb/><p>Now after the above nonsense I must give you something 
<lb/>better if I can. And first of all I must tell you that this 
<lb/>station has been recently formed by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edwards</persName> &amp; myself 
<lb/>&amp;c <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> E</persName> came out 20 years ago for the Kurrichane &amp; 
<lb/>is the only one of 7 with the same destination who ever 
<lb/>saw the locality. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he Kurrichane mountains lie about 30 
<lb/>miles South east of us, the people among whom we have 
<lb/>taken up our residence are called <term type="tribe">Bakhatta</term> a tribe of <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>
<lb/>which works in iron &amp; wood, the founderies are of the 
<lb/>most original description, <unclear cert="low">fae</unclear> similies of that of the old 
<lb/>Tukal coin. What you say of the Samsons applies in all 
<lb/>it is farce to them, desire for property is a predominant 
<lb/>feature in their character, greedy &amp; mean beyond calculation 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000572_0002"/><!--pb/@n='19v'-->
<lb/>Indeed they seem to make conscience of begging, and though refused 
<lb/>if the refusal is in a joculent or friendly manner they don<reg>'</reg>t 
<lb/>seem to take it ill. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey have chased their conscience and had 
<lb/>they gone away without making a <unclear cert="low">trial</unclear> they would have perhaps 
<lb/>felt its stings. Deceitful, liars to a man and as proud as 
<lb/>Lucifer if they think you are under any sort of obligation 
<lb/>or dependant for anything <del type="strikethrough">in</del> them. I should say in general 
<lb/>we ought to place but little dependance on a native <choice><sic>untill</sic><corr>until</corr></choice> we 
<lb/>get him into Heaven, and as a rule of conduct Let us 
<lb/>act with uniform kindness to them expecting that at one 
<lb/>time or other they will repay it with ingratitude, perhaps 
<lb/>insult. It will be a great misfortune if we (as some have) 
<lb/>allow our tempers towards them to become <unclear cert="low">soured</unclear> or 
<lb/>disgusted. I know one who has placed confidence on 
<lb/>many and having been ungratefully treated his talk regarding 
<lb/>them would savoured badly if reported any where. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he case 
<lb/>is instructive. I have tried as much as possible to avoid 
<lb/>making the conduct of others to me any part of my rule 
<lb/>of conduct to them and have got on comfortably sometimes 
<lb/>when others got broken heads (much grief) Our chiefs are 
<lb/><!--TODO A line break is missing in the next little while -->generally an imbecile race. "gawks" &amp; "Sandy Macfarlanes" their power is of the fended sort. And they are exceedingly 
<lb/>jealous of our approaches. Everything we do is thought 
<lb/>to be an attempt to draw people to our party &amp; pawn 
<lb/>the "Boguera" or circumcision is more (or rather entirely) a 
<lb/>national civil right than religious observance. It takes 
<lb/>place every four or five years &amp; all of nearly the same 
<lb/>age one subjected to it. Those <add place="above">who</add> have gone to the circumcision 
<lb/>together are bound into a cohort under one of the chiefs sons 
<lb/>or brothers for ever afterwards &amp; have to under service 
<lb/>go wherever he is sent, do whatever he likes under pain 
<lb/>of death <choice><sic>untill</sic><corr>until</corr></choice> that event takes place, this ceremony 
<lb/>was looked upon by the early missionaries  as sinful, 
<lb/>they keep it secret as a measure &amp; perhaps this was one 
<lb/>portion of the reason why the missionaries came to the 
<lb/>conclusion. You will perceive that war proclaimed against 
<lb/>this ought easily be interpreted as war against the feud as 
<lb/>system which exists &amp; it was so, and thus jealously for 
<lb/>the existing form of government was very extensively 
<lb/>engendered, this has been a great hindrance to the spread 
<lb/>of christianity. Each chief is absolute lord of his people 
<lb/>business without his consent, this was the state of 
<lb/>matters out at <placeName>Kuruman</placeName> &amp; vicinity when the mission 
<lb/>began - it is not so now. But it is so here. <persName>Mahura</persName>the chief of the <term type="tribe">Battapi</term>was very much opposed 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000572_0003"/><!--pb/@n='20r'-->
<lb/>to the gospel <choice><sic>untill</sic><corr>until</corr></choice> lately, and so long as he continued so, No 
<lb/>one living near hiom embraced the gospel. He has lately become 
<lb/>more favourable &amp; <persName>M<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Ross</persName> has gone to live with him &amp; we 
<lb/>have hopes of good being the result, told you notice that <persName>Mr 
<lb/>R</persName> mentioned in the report that he had been "the first to get 
<lb/><persName>Mahura</persName> to listen to this gospel" this was a lapus loungue with 
<lb/>a vengeance after <persName>M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">r</hi></hi> Moffat</persName>, <persName>Hamilton</persName> &amp;c had preached to 
<lb/>him so long. But we must be charitable &amp; hope against hope 
<lb/>that it was true. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he French missionaries have been 
<lb/>very successful among the <term type="tribe">Basontos</term> to the eastward of us 
<lb/>and a great deal under God has been among the influence 
<lb/>of an enlightened but unbelieving chief, he had never 
<lb/>like the others thrown obstacles in the way, on the contrary 
<lb/>has encouraged  the people to attend to the instruction 
<lb/>of the missionaries. Our chief is a real Johnny Raw 
<lb/>but he is kind as yet &amp; civil &amp; encourages the people 
<lb/>to attend our meetings. You speak of the expedition 
<lb/>to endeavour to make peace. Had you been here 
<lb/>church members would not have been deemed acknowledgement 
<lb/>of the teachers as chiefs &amp; a certain attack would have 
<lb/>been made. Churches here are notwithstanding all on 
<lb/>efforts regarded still as sort of political communities 
<lb/>you seem to have been shocked by the indecency of the 
<lb/>dress of the males. A short apron reaching half way down 
<lb/>the thigh is the <term type="tribe">Bechuana</term> female dress when working. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he 
<lb/>men nondescriptive <unclear cert="low">alveays</unclear> and the <term type="tribe">Caffres</term> go 
<lb/>stark naked. I have seen the men stand in the presence 
<lb/>of European females with as little consciousness of 
<lb/>impropriety or shame as G. D. does without trousers 
<lb/>on. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he <term type="tribe">Matibele</term> all go in puris naturalis &amp; are 
<lb/>&amp; all of them wonder what makes us thrust our pins 
<lb/>"into bags which can only <!-- TODO linbreak missing somewhere in this line? -->hinder us from running fast" Your language seems a curious pointless one, the mouth 
<lb/>can<reg>'</reg>t get a hold of so many vowels, you say "I thank 
<lb/>you for your advice, this in situana is "Kia gu 
<lb/>itunelela ka enutla kakololo ea gago, I <add place="above">do</add>thee thank for 
<lb/>by means of advice of thine. How different the two tongues<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>We have much circumlection to express a very simple idea 
<lb/>and have to make use of words frequently which have very 
<lb/>little meaning. Witness the above "for by means of "or on accent of 
<lb/>I now do thank your for all yours &amp; hope I have profited by it 
<lb/>the hand writing however is beyond my power. I am getting worse 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000572_0004"/><!--pb/@n='20v'-->
<lb/>and worse the more I write &amp; don<reg>'</reg>t know where I shall end. You of 
<lb/>course have heard of <persName>Radford's</persName> death. He wrote me the most affecting 
<lb/>letter I ever <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice>. It came in a box of medicine he sent &amp; that 
<lb/>arrived long after I knew he was dead. He told me the state of his lungs 
<lb/>&amp; with the full consciousness of his approaching dissolution said 
<lb/>"Now write soon as I won<reg>'</reg>t be here to <choice><sic>recieve</sic><corr>receive</corr></choice> it." Salome Coal 
<lb/>too &amp; <persName>Miss Marshall</persName>. I have <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> letters from <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> C</persName> &amp; <persName>Metomatree</persName>
<lb/>often<reg>.</reg> At the latter place they were lamost dispairing of hearing from 
<lb/>you ere you first arrived &amp; when it did it caused great joy <reg>.</reg>
<lb/><persName>Prentice</persName> a <placeName>Plymouth</placeName> brother is gone to the wall as far as mission 
<lb/>are concerned. Poor <persName>Catharine</persName>, she has not enjoyed the maroned 
<lb/>state here. In perpetual pain &amp; unable to stand without support 
<lb/><gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/> well &amp; of <persName>Fison</persName> I hear nothing<reg>.</reg></p><anchor xml:id="envelopePosition" type="positionMarker"/>
<lb/><p>You say if <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/> children pulling my coat tails &amp;c could not take the <unclear cert="low">breeks</unclear>
<lb/>off a <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/> could you? I don<reg>'</reg>t know when I have had a coat on my 
<lb/>back I wear jackets. &amp; I say if you were as near <placeName>Egypt</placeName> as we are 
<lb/>you would have worse plagues than children only a great deal smaller<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>How is with respect to native agency? I have £50 at my disposal 
<lb/>if I like some or most of it from persons I never saw for native 
<lb/>teachers, I have not yet been able to appropiate more than £12 
<lb/>on account of paucity of suitable individuals. I cannot 
<w>con-<lb break="no"/>scientiously</w> recommend unsuitable. I have thought perhaps you 
<lb/>may be more favourably situated for that mode of propogating 
<lb/>the gospel &amp; a lot of ladies &amp; gents in <persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>Woodlands's</persName> church having 
<lb/>sent lots of things now on their way here and guessing me to mention 
<lb/>waht may be useful in order to assist me. if you wish it I 
<lb/>feel inclined to direct some of their benevolence to you &amp; friend 
<lb/><persName>More</persName> I don<reg>'</reg>t know if I should succeed as I am not 
<lb/><addSpan spanTo="#p20v-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='side of envelope'--></addSpan>reasonably acquainted with a single individualof them 
<lb/>but it is always well to set people in the way of the 
<lb/>good. I intend writing to them tomorrow by way of 
<lb/>taking their pulse on the subject and you may be 
<lb/><anchor xml:id="p20v-01"/><addSpan spanTo="#p19r-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left hand margin'--></addSpan>you may be sure I shall  give you a character worth <unclear cert="low">7&amp;</unclear> sixpence any day. If you see a fair prospect of doing 
<lb/>good by a native teacher and apart from your own station let me know if you please. I think the last point 
<lb/><anchor xml:id="p19r-01"/><addSpan spanTo="#p19v-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left hand margin'--></addSpan>desirable to be attended to in order to be able to tell them of the amount of good done &amp; thus stimulate others to support &amp; 
<w>individ-<lb break="no"/>nalize</w> their own labourers at the throne of grace. Have you seen <unclear cert="low">Marrnonisio Kilmarhock facts?</unclear></p><anchor xml:id="p19v-01"/><addSpan spanTo="#p20r-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left hand margin'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
Williams</persName> has been ill since he went to <placeName>England</placeName> &amp; I fear he won<reg>'</reg>t get better. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his prevents his fond project 
<lb/>of a Welsh magazine. If however I hear again I shall let you know <reg>.</reg>Peace and mercy be with you &amp; wife &amp; children 
<lb/>give her my most affectionate salutations<reg>,</reg> D.L. </p><anchor xml:id="p20r-01"/><!-- Confirm to value (and id value of this anchor) as it is a duplicate value to an addSpan used above. If it is another addSpan on the same page, then call it p19r-02 --><addSpan spanTo="#p19r-02" place="margintop" rend="right"><!--addSpan/@place='top right of page 19r-01'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p>Don<reg>'</reg>t address me Rev &amp; M.D. too 
<lb/>say either <persName>D <hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi>L</persName> or <persName>Rev D<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">r</hi></hi>L</persName>. if you say Rev D<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> that would be equal 
<lb/>to D.D. which I am not<reg>.</reg></p><anchor xml:id="p19r-02"/><!-- TODO: Not new coding -->
<ab type="envelope">
<address>
<addrLine>Rev <hi rend="sup">d</hi>George Drummond</addrLine>
<addrLine>Falealopei Sasaii</addrLine>
<addrLine>Navigation Islands</addrLine>
<addrLine>South Seas</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>