<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2017-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000504">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Benjamin T. Pyne</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Benjamin T. Pyne, 11 March, 17 May 1842</title>
				<author>Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
                <authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
                <publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
                <pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2017</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000504</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Royal Geographical Society (Great Britain); Archives, DL 2/6/1</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0049</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Pyne, Benjamin T., 1798/9-1880</persName>; </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date from="1842-03-11" to="1842-05-17">11 March, 17 May 1842</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Tropic Capricorn, Long. 28° 10' E</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change> 
				<date>2009-04-28</date> 
				<name>Caroline Overy</name>Initial Transcription by Caroline Overy
			</change>
			<change> 
				<date>2017-06-20</date> 
				<name>Kate Simpson</name>Proofreading 
			</change>
			<change> 
				<date>2017-06-22</date> 
				<name>Adrian S. Wisnicki</name>Proofing and Formatting 
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000504_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1r'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><space extent="24" unit="chars"/><placeName><region>Tropic of Capricorn</region></placeName>, <choice><abbr>Long.</abbr><expan>Longitude</expan></choice> 28º 10′ <choice><abbr>E,</abbr><expan>East</expan></choice>
<lb/><space extent="50" unit="chars"/><date when="1842-03-11">11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> March
<lb/><space extent="56" unit="chars"/>1842</date></p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent"><space extent="2" unit="chars"/>My very dear friends
<lb/><space extent="17" unit="chars"/>You will see by the date if this that I am coming nearer 
<lb/>you, I am not quite certain whether I am actually on the <placeName><region>Tropic</region></placeName> but by a 
<lb/>dead reckoning carried on from the last observation I had an opportunity 
<lb/>of taking I am very near it, if not perhaps a few miles on the northing 
<lb/>of it. <space extent="3" unit="chars"/> I am at present with <persName>Bubi</persName> one of the <term type="occupation">chiefs</term> of the <term type="tribe">Bakwain</term> or 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bakone</term> as it is sometimes spelled. I have come for the purpose of helping 
<lb/>a <orgName>native</orgName> <term type="occupation">teacher</term> to commence operations amongst them &amp; as far as we 
<lb/>have proceeded with them we have found all to our wishes. A great cause 
<lb/>of <choice><sic>thankfullness</sic><corr>thankfulness</corr></choice> to him who thus opens up our way amongst a fickle people.</p> 
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">I read one of your letters on <date when="1842-03-06">Sunday</date> evening last &amp; it brought back to my 
<lb/>recollection many pleasing thoughts - It was so full of kindness I resolved to 
<lb/>devote the only remaining large sheet of paper at present with me to you - 
<lb/>But I fear I cannot give you anything like the ideas of this country which the 
<lb/>actual presence in it gives - It is prodigiously large, &amp; I think there are 
<lb/>far more wild animals than human beings in it - During our long 
<lb/>journey hither we came to no village except one &amp; that did not contain 
<lb/>500 of a population But every day we were sure of seeing large herds of 
<lb/>different kinds of game - In travelling - there is not much to excite interest 
<lb/>one has to keep near the waggon not so much for conveyance as defence
<lb/><term type="animal">Lions</term> abound, they seldom however <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice> themselves in the day but make 
<lb/>a disagreeable noise at night - the <term type="animal">Rhinoceros</term> is exceedingly like a gigantic <del type="cancelled"><term type="animal">pig</term></del> 
<lb/><term type="animal">pig</term> both in his motions &amp; general appearance But I need not begin to 
<lb/>describe animals, I may however mention that one loses much of the 
<lb/>feelings with which we think of them while in <placeName><country>England</country></placeName>, even on <term type="animal">serpents</term> 
<lb/>&amp; the enormous <term type="insect">centipedes</term> disgusting at first from their size &amp; length I 
<lb/>now look with indifference &amp; like the <orgName>natives</orgName> I walk among the long grass 
<lb/>as tall in some parts as myself without the least apprehension - I am very
<lb/>much astonished at the change which has taken place on my mind in so 
<lb/>short a time, had anyone told me of it beforehand I could not have credited it 
<lb/>for the first one I nearly trod upon 6 or 7 feet in length almost petrified 
<lb/>me - By thinking of this change you will understand how inhabitants of 
<lb/>tropical climates can live just as well as you do in <placeName><country>England</country></placeName> <w>notwithst<supplied>-</supplied>
<lb break="no"/>anding</w> all the reptiles which would destroy our comfort if more sensitive <del type="strikethrough">on the</del></p>
<lb/><p>I intend remaining here for 6 weeks &amp; then proceeding still further to the North 
<lb/>in order to visit other tribes still more distant, they are so few &amp; far 
<lb/>scattered it will be impossible or rather impolitic for the people at home 
<lb/>to supply them with <orgName>European</orgName> <unclear cert="low"><term type="occupation"><choice><abbr>Miss<hi rend="sup">s</hi></abbr><expan>Missionaries</expan></choice></term></unclear> <space extent="3" unit="chars"/> If one were stationed here all 
<lb/>the best portions of his time would be occupied in travelling towards the
<lb/><placeName><region>Colony</region></placeName> for supplies &amp; <term type="animal">oxen</term> will be pretty well worn out before reaching 
<lb/><placeName>Kuruman</placeName>. Native teachers are the only hope &amp; unless we can open up 
<lb/>a route to <placeName>Delagoa Bay</placeName> or some other on the West Coast<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>I have with me an excellent man as <term type="occupation">teacher</term>, today he began school for 
<lb/>the children - the <term type="occupation">chief</term> himself collecting them for him <space extent="2" unit="chars"/> I could not go near 
<lb/>to see how he was getting on for if I had only looked at the little naked 
<lb/>brats an instant dispersion of the whole school would have taken place, their 
<lb/>terror at the sight of a white face though mine scarcely merits that <w>appel-
<lb break="no"/>ation</w> now is extreme - Even girls of 10 years scream with terror if brought 
<lb/>forcibly by their parents for medicine - <space extent="3" unit="chars"/>this <term type="occupation">chief</term> is the most sensible 
<lb/>I have seen among chiefs of <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> - He is not considered <hi rend="underline">legally</hi> <term type="occupation">chief</term> 
<lb/>but by his own abilities has drawn around him a number of people 
<lb/>equal to that of the legal <term type="occupation">chief</term> - This latter a greedy nasty fellow is very 
<lb/>anxious to fight but being afraid to try alone has been soliciting and in 
<lb/>different quarters against <persName>Bubi</persName> - In order to defend himself better <persName>Bubi</persName>
<lb/>has recently taken up his residence on a hill about <measure>600 feet high</measure> - &amp; <w>surrou-
<lb break="no"/>nded</w> on all sides by rocky precipitous approaches - It is about <measure><choice><orig>½</orig><reg>1/2</reg></choice> a mile 
<lb/>broad</measure> at the top - I outspanned at the bottom but he came down &amp; pressed 
<lb/>me to ascend on another side where the ascent was less steep - Here then 
<lb/><addSpan spanTo="#longadd-1" corresp="#p.01-01" place="marginleft"/>He lives so far in the desert almost without walls they are unable to attack him - He sent ambassadors to them &amp; his own brother murdered 
<lb/>them - Again he sent others who passed his brother by another route <space extent="3" unit="chars"/> those to whom they went assured him that they were friendly to him 
<lb/>told him to leave the desert, come out &amp; sow <term type="plant_foodstuff">corn</term> - (his own ardent wish as he may get nothing but roots &amp; the flesh of his <term type="animal"><term type="foodstuff">cattle</term></term> where he is) And  
<lb/>at the same time they were purchasing <term type="animal">horses</term> in order to attack him - His object in sending to me is to ascertain<anchor xml:id="longadd-1"/>

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000504_0002"/><!--pb/@n='1v'-->
<lb/>on a cool spot I shall remain a little - <space extent="2" unit="chars"/>My presence will probably deter the other fellow 
<lb/>from attempting anything - <persName>Bubi</persName> feels this &amp; is perhaps more kind than he 
<lb/>in other circumstances might be - He brings <term type="foodstuff">milk</term> to me morning &amp; evening 
<lb/>himself - Just now sent a huge pot of <term type="foodstuff">beer</term> &amp; when I proposed to him yesterday 
<lb/>to pay for the <term type="foodstuff">milk</term> &amp;c - I received, he said, "No, drink my <term type="foodstuff">milk</term> &amp; eat 
<lb/>my <term type="foodstuff">corn</term> &amp; let your heart feel pleasant so long as you remain &amp; <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> say 
<lb/>anything about payment" I <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice> hear of it" Some of his people went with 
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edwards</persName> &amp; <unclear cert="low"><persName>S</persName></unclear> to <unclear cert="low"><placeName><settlement><choice><abbr>K</abbr><expan>Kuruman</expan></choice></settlement></placeName></unclear> - There received me with great joy, the wild bursts of 
<lb/>laughter by which they testified it was very gratifying - and what to me was 
<lb/>amusing was the enquiry some of them put respecting an old <term type="animal">ox</term> of mine left 
<lb/>behind to rest himself, "Where is <term type="animal">Canute</term>?" &amp;c" I suppose their affection is 
<lb/>about as strong for the <term type="animal">oxen</term> as for myself, the <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> are devotedly 
<lb/>attached to cattle - <space extent="4" unit="chars"/> My establishment consists of a <term type="occupation">Driver</term> &amp; <term type="occupation">Leader</term> - the 
<lb/>latter is necessary because no reins are used - He goes before &amp; leads the two front <term type="animal">oxen</term> 
<lb/>the <term type="occupation">Driver</term> manages to propel the ponderous machine by guiding &amp; thrashing the animals 
<lb/>with a whip as long as a fishing rod - He is the commander in chief &amp; presides at 
<lb/>meals &amp;c. and his orders are implicitly obeyed - He cooks, washes shirts &amp; is the 
<lb/>sort of <term type="occupation">valet</term> of the owner of the waggon -<space extent="2" unit="chars"/> Mine is a heathen but the most 
<lb/>energetic obliging fellow I have seen amongst them, more so indeed than most 
<lb/>of the <term type="faith">Christians</term> - I took him on account of his energy &amp; hope to be useful 
<lb/>to him -  He is besides a famous <term type="occupation">Nimrod</term> &amp; we never want a supply of 
<lb/>meat if I only allow him powder &amp; shot. My leader is a Christian &amp; an 
<lb/>amiable man - when a boy he was driven out of his own country by <persName>Moselekatze</persName>
<lb/>He requested to come with me because he was poor &amp; wanted to make a 
<lb/>little money to buy a <term type="animal">cow</term> - A few beads to assist him in trading for <term type="animal">foxes</term> 
<lb/>skins has made him very grateful - <space extent="2" unit="chars"/> My <orgName>native</orgName> <term type="occupation">teacher</term> <persName>Pomore</persName> is 
<lb/>the son of an old heathen <term type="occupation">chief</term> &amp; has considerable influence wherever he 
<lb/>goes - He is a good man &amp; far before most of his countrymen in knowledge</p>
<lb/><p>He has resolved to bring his wife &amp; children here as soon as the <term type="plant_foodstuff">corn</term> is cut
<lb/>It being still green was the cause he left her behind when we set out
<lb/>All his <choice><sic>fathers</sic><corr>father's</corr></choice> family are <term type="faith">Christians</term> &amp; when they became so one after another It was 
<lb/>a great affliction to the old man - He looked upon them as dying &amp; now they are all dead 
<lb/>as he expresses it - He says sometimes his heart sweats &amp; he should like to be a 
<lb/><term type="faith">Christian</term> but how can he give up his wives - (he has 3 or 4) Last year he came 
<lb/>to this part of the country seeking another &amp; being much annoyed by his sons who 
<lb/>accompanied him for the purpose of trading, preaching wherever they came
<lb/>He at last proposed to precede them to the next town - He came to this &amp; the next 
<lb/>village &amp; told the people that some men would soon follow who would begin &amp; talk <w>nonse-
<lb break="no"/>nse</w> But they must not believe them it was all lies - <space extent="1" unit="chars"/>When his last son <persName>Moffat</persName> went 
<lb/>to <placeName><settlement type="town">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> for the purpose of being admitted to the church, the old man manifested violent anger 
<lb/>and in addition to sending off a <term type="occupation">messenger</term> to bring him back by force went about <unclear cert="low">steaming</unclear>
<lb/>at a great rate against Believers for three days - But at length fearing his other dead sons 
<lb/>would be offended with him, he went to them privately &amp; said "you know my sons that I 
<lb/>am a man of the world - It is necessary for me to make this <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice> in order to please 
<lb/>my fellow <term type="occupation">chiefs</term> still in heathenism - Never mind me but go on praying as before  
<lb/><choice><sic>Dont</sic><corr>Don't</corr></choice> stop for me or anything I may say or do - Such is old <persName>Seretse</persName> <space extent="2" unit="chars"/> father of my friend <persName>Pomore</persName>
<lb/>Another man <unclear cert="low"><persName>P.s. Sawaat</persName></unclear> constitutes the whole of my establishment - You will think I 
<lb/>have enough to support But it is not so difficult to support them here as it is at 
<lb/>home - Although it is much more so here than in <placeName><country>India</country></placeName> the abundance of game is 
<lb/>a great help - Everything is eaten except the <term type="animal">wolf</term> between whom &amp; the <orgName>natives</orgName> a most 
<lb/>determined enmity exists because he is the enemy of their <term type="animal">cattle</term> - The <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>
<lb/>never eat <term type="foodstuff">fish</term> &amp; hold them in the greatest detestation - Perhaps this owing to those 
<lb/>of <placeName><geogName type="river">Kuruman River</geogName></placeName> being deleterious <del>in</del><add place="over-text">to</add> <del type="cancelled"><unclear cert="medium">quality</unclear></del> most stomachs, they are disgusting -
<lb/>looking things, having a broad flat head &amp; a kind of beard &amp; without scales - On 
<lb/>our way here we halted on the banks of a stream containing three parts, as <unclear cert="low"><persName>T</persName></unclear>
<lb/>asserted that fish always even in small quantity acted as emetics to him &amp; other 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> I took out a few with a pin in order to try the experiment on him 
<lb/>again He ate them with relish &amp; no <term type="ailment">vomiting</term> took place - I think if the <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>
<lb/>knew the difference of the different kinds they would soon add another article 
<lb/>to their already large bill of fare - Certainly they are preferable to the flesh of <term type="animal">Rhinoceros</term>
<lb/>They are perfectly tame having never been troubled by the <unclear cert="high">arts</unclear> of the angler - <space extent="2" unit="chars"/>I at one time 
<lb/>intended to make a collection of insects &amp;c. for <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> <unclear cert="low">P</unclear>.</persName> but after some further endeavours 
<lb/>I am obliged to give up the idea - the butterflies are very beautiful but my fingers are too 
<lb/>clumsy for them &amp; the heat is so great that when dead they are quite brittle &amp; the jolting 
<lb/>of the waggon makes them crumble to powder - She must therefore excuse me on that 
<lb/><unclear cert="medium">hand</unclear> - I shall endeavour to send some other things not so frail as insects, the box 
<lb/>for the college I have sent - There was an opportunity for one only but I have told 
<lb/><persName>Professor Owen</persName> I shall entrust yours to his care by the next opportunity - It will be 
<lb/><addSpan spanTo="#longadd-2" corresp="#p.02-01" place="marginleft"/>the truth - If I should say come out He will come with his people directly. But I <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice> bid him now - He would be safe with me so 
<lb/>long as I continued on the spot but if I went any where else the others would attack him immediately - Such is the terror inspired by <anchor xml:id="longadd-2"/>

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000504_0003"/><!--pb/@n='2r'-->
<lb/><date from="1842-06" to="1842-07">June or July</date> before I reach <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> &amp; it may be some time after that before an 
<lb/>opportunity occurs of sending - Of course this letter remains by me till then - I hear 
<lb/>nothing but Sita<add place="above">h</add>uana &amp; hope to make more progress toward the attainment of the 
<lb/>language in this - than when mixing with <orgName>Europeans</orgName> I read addresses long ago 
<lb/>in it but of course full of imperfections - It is a poor language except in what relates 
<lb/>to <term type="animal">cattle</term> &amp;c. Energy is expressed chiefly by reputation, the loudness of the tone &amp; gestures more 
<lb/>or less violent according to its intensity - You may understand the meaning of a <unclear cert="high">far</unclear>
<lb/>by the way the speaker elevates his voice <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> it is lost in a rough sort of breathing 
<lb/>straining the eyes in the direction spoken of &amp; repeating the word for it incessantly</p>
<lb/><p>Theological terms have all to be constructed for them &amp; <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> they have learned their 
<lb/>meaning, It is all Greek to them - <space extent="1" unit="chars"/> If I should speak to the people here in this 
<lb/>language used in the <bibl>New Testament</bibl> scarcely one in this whole tribe would 
<lb/>understand what I said - &amp; believe not one <space extent="2" unit="chars"/> They are all children &amp; are as easily 
<lb/>amused as they - A few buttons or beads <unclear cert="low">puts</unclear><gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="illegible"/> the wisest among them into 
<lb/>extremes <space extent="2" unit="chars"/> As a whole they are exceedingly ungrateful, mean to the last degree
<lb/>Liars for the sake of lying &amp; the most disobeying selfish nation on the face of the 
<lb/>earth - The <term type="faith">Christians</term> <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> lose this character when they make a profession - There 
<lb/>are exceptions however you must remember but they are few &amp; far between</p>
<lb/><p>If you are habitually kind to anyone you are sure to spoil him - the <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> 
<lb/>never knew an exception to this - He becomes impudent &amp; <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="blot"/>  &amp; a slanderer
<lb/>We have therefore to labour for this good with a certainty of getting no thanks 
<lb/>for them - Those who are nearest <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> are the worst - Believers at 
<lb/>a distance on receiving a visit from us receive us with great joy &amp; it 
<lb/>is really a pleasure to meet them &amp; it is so with friends in heathen towns 
<lb/>but still the chief expense of the friendship devolves on the stranger - By <unclear cert="low">working</unclear>
<lb/>on their character as expressed above (the universal testimony by all the <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> 
<lb/>I have met in this country confirms it) I have found no difficulty in getting on 
<lb/>well with them I scarcely ever propose anything to those with whom I have to 
<lb/>do without pointing out the personal advantage - make stops in dispensing 
<lb/>favours, never ask one to do anything because he can do it better if there is a 
<lb/>poor person who can do it in any way &amp; who would esteem employment a 
<lb/>favour- All those I have now with me are obliging in the greatest degree, I 
<lb/>have not been obliged to reprove one of them &amp; the chief reason is I allow 
<lb/>them to carry their little stocks of merchandise in the waggon &amp; give them an 
<lb/>opportunity of trading when we come to a village by remaining a day or two at it 
<lb/>&amp; if a very good bargain offered, they know they can make a draught <w>before<supplied>-</supplied>
<lb break="no"/>hand</w> on their wages to secure it - Besides the <term type="foodstuff">tea</term> you so kindly gave
<lb/>is occasionally produced on a wet day or after a fatiguing <choice><sic>days</sic><corr>day's</corr></choice> work 
<lb/>a cup of <term type="foodstuff">tea</term> has wonderful effect on their tempers or when we get a 
<lb/>large animal &amp; then they eat &amp; laugh all day long, suppose it is Sunday 
<lb/>&amp; we have got a good fat wild <term type="animal">horse</term> the day before, the pot is never cool 
<lb/>one large potful disappears one after another all the day - In these cases
<lb/><term type="foodstuff">bread</term> is never thought of, the lean is <choice><orig>dipt</orig><reg>dipped</reg></choice> in the fat &amp; down it goes</p>
<lb/><p>Different modes of cooking are continually in process &amp; during the intervals 
<lb/>of eating someone begins a hymn in which all <unclear cert="medium">form</unclear> but a concert of 
<lb/><term type="animal">screech owls</term> might be denominated the "music of the spheres" compared to 
<lb/>it - Spelling books are also in request but it seems only to ease their consciences 
<lb/>these are occasionally taking up - These are our company - <persName>Pomore</persName> is 
<lb/>not quite so bad as the others  But it would be a great offence indeed if 
<lb/>temperance were insisted on I should be scandalized over the <del type="strikethrough"><unclear cert="low">old</unclear></del> whole country 
<lb/>as one who starved my people &amp; instead of being anxious to go with me 
<lb/>I should find it difficult to get a complement for the waggon -</p>
<lb/><p>I have lately become acquainted with some excellent friends. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> <persName><unclear cert="low">Lempe</unclear></persName>
<lb/>of the <term type="nationality">French</term> mission - They are as polite as we think the <term type="nationality">French</term> &amp; amiable 
<lb/>&amp; kind even to a fault - The same may be said of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> <persName>Helmore</persName> of <placeName><settlement type="village">Likation</settlement></placeName>. 
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> L.</persName> is at <placeName><settlement type="village">Mohito</settlement></placeName> about <measure>35 miles</measure> from <placeName><settlement type="village"/></placeName> - they were lately most anxious 
<lb/>I should take up my abode with them for 3 or 4 months  the time during which <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r Edwards</hi></persName>
<lb/>is on a visit to the <placeName><region>Colony</region></placeName> - But I preferred coming here - Both of them speak <choice><abbr>Eng</abbr><expan>English</expan></choice>. well 
<lb/>but I can converse with the children only by means of Si<add place="above">th</add>uana</p>
<lb/><p><date when="1842-05-17">17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> May 1842</date> Perhaps you may dislike this patchwork like letter but I have just to 
<lb/>write as I have opportunity - I hope therefore you will excuse me - After finishing 
<lb/>what is above, I was busied for a month directing the people how to lead out the water 
<lb/>of their river, &amp; after that was finished on one side I left this &amp; proceeded to the <placeName><region>North</region></placeName> 
<lb/><choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> I arrived within 2 days <space extent="1" unit="chars"/> of the <term type="tribe">Bamangwato</term> - my route skirted the <placeName><geogName type="desert">Great Sandy 
<lb/> desert</geogName></placeName> which lies to the West of this <space unit="chars" extent="2"/> the sand completely exhausted the strength of the <term type="animal">oxen</term> 
<lb/>3 of them were sick &amp; one died - If any of the others failed I saw my waggon must 
<lb/>stand still - There was no water nearer than <choice><orig>½</orig><reg>1/2</reg></choice> a day before us &amp; behind us nearly a whole 
<lb/>day - I directed our people to endeavour to take them back &amp; remain at that water <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice>
<lb/>I should return from the <term type="tribe">Bamangwato</term> - <space extent="2" unit="chars"/> We were received with great kindness 
<lb/>by the <term type="occupation">chief</term> <persName>Sekomi</persName> &amp; in addition to a present of an <term type="animal">elephant</term><supplied cert="high">'</supplied>s tusk in value sufficient 
<lb/>to pay <persName><unclear cert="low">Pomore</unclear></persName>'s salary the first half year - I have him for myself &amp; this is a 
<lb/><addSpan spanTo="#longadd-3" corresp="#p.03-01" place="marginleft"/>guns of the <orgName>Boers</orgName> none of them dare think of attacking a tribe where a white man lives - <space unit="chars" extent="2"/> this <term type="occupation">chief</term> sent me an <term type="animal">ox</term> as a present 
<lb/>which fills up the vacancy caused by the loss of the other, his name is <persName>Sebechwe</persName> <space unit="chars" extent="2"/> the ch sounded gutturally as in Scotch lo<hi rend="underline">ch</hi><anchor xml:id="longadd-3"/>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000504_0004"/><!--pb/@n='2v'-->
<lb/>is the hand of our Father providing - <space extent="2" unit="chars"/> I had no authority from the Directors but thinking 
<lb/>good could be done I could not want their sanction but rather suffer the loss myself  
<lb/>but loss it <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice> be called for it is spent in the service of him from whom are all 
<lb/>that I have &amp; to him all should be dedicated - I ought to have said in addition to the <choice><abbr>Ele-</abbr><expan>Elephant</expan></choice> 
<lb/>tusk I lived on his bounty for a fortnight - This town is larger than any I have 
<lb/>seen in this country but the huts are miserably small  We lived in one as large as 
<lb/>the <term type="occupation">chiefs</term> &amp; three of us could not sleep in it without kicking each other unless the fire was out</p>
<lb/><p>I then visited the <term type="tribe">Bakaa</term> another portion of the <orgName><term type="tribe">Bechuana</term> nation</orgName> &amp; they are in bad 
<lb/>repute among the other tribes so much so some of the <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> who accompanied me 
<lb/>refused to go to them - The reason is a few years ago they poisoned a <term type="occupation">trader</term> 
<lb/>&amp; his people in order to get his waggons &amp;c - They heard by one of <persName>Sekomi</persName><supplied cert="high">'</supplied>s people 
<lb/>that I was on the way to visit them &amp; the whole tribe fled my presence - they said 
<lb/>to him that foreigner must be coming to kill us on account of the waggons we 
<lb/>destroyed - There were only three who had courage to look me in the face at my first 
<lb/>entrance into the town - the <term type="occupation">chief</term> &amp; two others but after I had sat &amp; talked a while with 
<lb/>them the others ventured to come from their hiding places - If anyone ought to have 
<lb/>feared it ought to have been myself but I was quite amused with this terror instead 
<lb/>of being terrified myself - When the others came near I could not help feeling sad 
<lb/>for I saw pieces of gun locks hung round their necks &amp; other things which I am 
		
<lb/><addSpan spanTo="#longadd-4" corresp="#p04-01" place="marginright"/><!--addSpan/@place='right side of fol.2v folded into envelope, and left margin of fols 1r, 1v, 2r'--><!--Mike, is this correct--><persName>Sekomi</persName> sent 5 men with me to <placeName><settlement type="village"><choice><abbr>K.</abbr><expan>Kuruman</expan></choice></settlement></placeName> in order to see the white men &amp; bring
<lb/>him back a faithful report of all the wonderful things I had told him of - 
<lb/>When I came back here I found an embassy of 16 men from a 
<lb/><term type="occupation">chief</term> of the <term type="tribe">Wanketze</term> who lives in the desert <measure>200 miles</measure> West of this, the 
<lb/>tribes to the Southward wish to plunder him of his <term type="animal">cattle</term> &amp;c<anchor xml:id="longadd-4"/>

<lb/>
		<address corresp="#envelopePosition">
			<addrLine><space extent="10" unit="chars"/><del type="strikethrough">Care of the <persName><choice><abbr>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi></abbr><expan>Reverend</expan></choice> <choice><abbr>D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi></abbr><expan>Doctor</expan></choice> Phillip</persName>, Church Square,</del></addrLine>
			<addrLine><space extent="40" unit="chars"/><del type="strikethrough"><hi rend="underline"><placeName><settlement type="town">Cape Town</settlement></placeName></hi></del></addrLine>
			<addrLine><space extent="15" unit="chars"/><persName>Benjamin T. Pyne</persName>, <choice><abbr>Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi></abbr><expan>Esquire</expan></choice></addrLine>
			<addrLine><space extent="30" unit="chars"/><placeName>Wildingtree</placeName>, <placeName><settlement type="town">Ongar</settlement></placeName>,</addrLine>
			<addrLine><space extent="29" unit="chars"/><placeName><region>Essex</region></placeName>. <hi rend="underline"><placeName><country>England</country></placeName></hi></addrLine>
			<addrLine><hi rend="vertical"><date when="1842-03-11">March 11 / 42</date></hi></addrLine>
			<addrLine><hi rend="underline">single sheet</hi></addrLine>
		</address>
		
<lb/>sure belonged to these unfortunate visitors - one had a piece of the waggon sail 
<lb/>round his head &amp; another a piece of a tin jug attached to his ear - They <choice><orig>shewed</orig><reg>showed</reg></choice> 
<lb/>considerable uneasiness <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> they got a bowl of <term type="foodstuff">porridge</term> cooked for me &amp; saw me 
<lb/>eating of it heartily - this seemed to give them more satisfaction anything I had 
<lb/>before said - Next day I assembled them &amp; told them of the Blood which cleanses them 
<lb/>from all sin - I earnestly hope some of these murderers may yet turn to that <unclear cert="low">penus</unclear>
<lb/>fountain of mercy - <persName>Pomore</persName> was then taken with <term type="ailment">fever</term> &amp; so ill I feared we should 
<lb/>not remain long together, &amp; to add to the difficulty I had given away all the medicine 
<lb/>I had brought with me - A copious bleeding relieved him considerably when it 
<lb/>was at its height - The <term type="tribe">Bakaa</term> felt great anxiety on his account as in the 
<lb/>event of his death they would be blamed by the neighbouring tribes. All their 
<lb/><orgName>native</orgName> remedies were put into requisition but the <term type="ailment">fever</term> ran its course &amp; left 
<lb/>him very weak - I then left him &amp; <add place="below">˄</add><add place="above">having</add> requested <persName>Sekhomi</persName> to send men for one of 
<lb/>my <term type="animal">oxen</term> - When they arrived I sent them on for <persName>Pomore</persName> - We then bid <persName>Sekomi</persName>
<lb/>farewell &amp; instead of riding myself I had the pleasure of walking about <measure>70 miles</measure> <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="illegible"/>
<lb/>the side of my <term type="occupation">servant</term> &amp; the sand is very much like snow under <gap extent="5" unit="words" agent="illegible"/></p><anchor xml:id="p.04-01"/>

			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>