<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000576">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Benjamin T. Pyne</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Benjamin T. Pyne, 28 January 1845</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>16-03-2010</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000576</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0114</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>16-03-2010</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>Transcribed by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000576_0001"/><!--pb/@n='01'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Kuruman</placeName> 25 January 1845 </p>
<lb/><p rend="left">My very Dear Friend </p>
<lb/><p>I have again the pleasure of announcing 
<lb/>the safe arrival of two letters from you and to say they 
<lb/>were welcome would be only saying that which you 
<lb/>already know, <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> P's</persName> I shall answer by itself, and hope 
<lb/>each will keep the other company <choice><sic>accross</sic><corr>across</corr></choice> the wide gulph 
<lb/>which intervenes in the same summer yours did. How 
<lb/>affecting the intelligence yours conveys, and how instructive 
<lb/>the time in short. Let us work with our might while we 
<lb/>are continued here. About the same I <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice>
<lb/>a letter from <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Williams</persName> and we too has departed, he 
<lb/>has the means of establishing a Welsh Missionary 
<lb/>Magazine and his letter contained earnest entreaties for 
<lb/>correspondence for it. I shall begin immediately 
<lb/>&amp; furhish the needful as far as my abilities go. I 
<lb/>wish I were more able to furnish intelligence. I have 
<lb/>been so busy of late I could not do anything and 
<lb/>what was all the fuss about do you think only about 
<lb/>being married. I am sorry I had not an opportunity 
<lb/>of telling you before this for it was settled long to me. It was 
<lb/>a few months since &amp; I had to build a house after 
<lb/>I was engaged. Well I am hooked now &amp; <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Drummond</persName>
<lb/>will no longer have it in his power to excuse 
<lb/>me of being a monk. By the way I am glad you 
<lb/>have heard from him and &amp; that our dear departed 
<lb/><persName>Miss Marshall</persName> heard it before she died. He says to 
<lb/>me "reverse her memory" &amp; utters many affectionate 
<lb/>things respecting her, <!--mike: squiggle--> who can speak otherwise 
<lb/>respecting her, I never heard that to which you 
<lb/>refer &amp; am sure she never had any thoughts 
<lb/>such as those presented to her by - As for myself 
<lb/>I never thought myself good enough to aspire so high 
<lb/>I may mention that my wife is in bodily appearance 
<lb/>very much like her  only a great deal stouter<reg>.</reg>

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000576_0002"/><!--pb/@n='02'-->
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>O</persName> gives me a copy of a letter <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> from <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
<lb/>Moore</persName> during the time he was writing to me. It runs 
<lb/>thus Dear <persName>Chisholm</persName>, My hands are so full having to 
<lb/>cook fetch water, sweep rooms &amp;c &amp;c that I have only 
<lb/>time to say I hope you are enjoying the presence of our 
<lb/>beloved saviour &amp; prospering abundantly in your 
<lb/>work. My heart deserves that you may never 
<lb/>labour in vain here alas everything goes wrong. The 
<lb/>French have deposed the queen &amp; taken full poss 
<lb/>ession of the Island. Write me by <persName>Cap<hi rend="sup">n</hi> Scott</persName> I am yours 
<lb/>truly <persName>Joseph Moore.</persName><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D</persName> says you can draw your 
<lb/>own inferences from it. It seems a flag of 
<lb/>distress truly - the union Jack upside down &amp; no 
<lb/>mistake But I must not crow over poor <persName>Joseph </persName>
<lb/>for I too am married I am at present at 
<lb/><placeName>Kuruman</placeName> but intend leaving a week or two for 
<lb/><placeName>Mabotsa</placeName>, this place begins to assume an air of 
<lb/>prosperity and this chiefly by the residence of 
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName>. He has toiled manually ever since he 
<lb/>came, building repairing thatching improving in 
<lb/>everything &amp; makes me see that a great deal 
<lb/>can be done when one's heart is in this work, His 
<lb/>excellencies make the differences of those who 
<lb/>had the care of the station more apparent<reg>.</reg> But I 
<lb/>must not praise now that he is my father 
<lb/>in law<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>At <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName> matters go on pretty well<reg>.</reg> But I 
<lb/>don<reg>'</reg>t expect to remain there long. The sphere is 
<lb/>too small for the missionaries, as I am the 
<lb/>younger I propose to go to the Bakwains of 
<lb/>either <persName>Bubi</persName> or <persName>Sechele</persName>. If I remained at <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName>
<lb/>the utmost I could hope for would be the part of 
<lb/>introduction of the gospel to a tribe while by going 
<lb/>to another it would be an introduction of the 
<lb/>gospel wholly by my intrustrmentalility the additional 
<lb/>labour &amp;c does not weigh anything in the 
<lb/>calculations so I think I shall go as soon as poss<reg>.</reg></p>

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000576_0003"/><!--pb/@n='03'-->
<lb/><p><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Inglis</persName> makes a very poor figure in the language<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>While <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
Ashton</persName> preaches fluently &amp; very correctly indeed 
<lb/>He <add place="above">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>I</add> visited us at <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName> But has taken no steps for 
<lb/>forming a station or doing anything else. He remains 
<lb/>at <placeName>Gruqua Town</placeName> I wish he would devote himself 
<lb/>to something when so much is needed. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> I.</persName> has 
<lb/>been much troubled with ophalmia,&amp; so has her 
<lb/>little daughter, all blue eyes are in the country very 
<lb/>subject to it, in this respect it resembled <placeName>Egypt</placeName>
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> I's</persName> obtuseness in the language will be against his 
<lb/>future usefulness for to be useful one has to excel 
<lb/>in more respects than a minister at home. If 
<lb/>a native excels a missionary in any work He 
<lb/>does not listen as attentively to his instructions as 
<lb/>he otherwise would<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>We had a party of English hunters up in the 
<lb/>interior lately one the son of a clergyman and 
<lb/>himself a candidate for holy orders offered to 
<lb/>call on any of my friends in <placeName>England</placeName> &amp; tell 
<lb/>what he had seen of me, you may guess of 
<lb/>what I thought his character made when I 
<lb/>did not give him a single address, I have lately 
<lb/>had a channel opened up for my transmitting 
<lb/>parcels to the <placeName>Cape</placeName>, <persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wallich</persName>the <placeName>East India</placeName>
<lb/>companys' superintendent of Botanical gardens 
<lb/>at <placeName>Calcutta</placeName> authorizes me to put any expenses 
<lb/>I choose to his charge. This, far sending him 
<lb/>the edible roots &amp; prints of the poor Bakalah 
<lb/>are of the desert, I shall avail myself of 
<lb/>his kindness by sending something first 
<lb/>to you. Give my kind regards to <persName>Mary</persName>
<lb/>and all your family <persName>Benjamin</persName>, <persName>Marland</persName>
<lb/><persName>Bernard</persName> &amp; the other who may have by this time 
<lb/>come, (the Queen is going on at a dreadful 
<lb/>rate. In these my <persName>Mary</persName> writes Ever Affectionately </p>
<lb/><p>Yours <persName>D. Livingston</persName></p>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000576_0004"/><!--pb/@n='04'-->
<lb/><p>P.S. I enclose the specimen for the album which 
<lb/>you requested<reg>.</reg> Give that which will suit 
<lb/>her character. I did not intend to convey any 
<lb/>reproof or ought else in that which I wrote 
<lb/>for you formerly I never hint if a subject 
<lb/>is worth talking about I talk out &amp; never 
<lb/>by a side wind so I did not mean you </p>
<lb/><p>
<address>
<addrLine>Care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Phillip</persName><placeName>Cape Town</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><persName>Benjamin Pyne Esq<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi></persName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>Wildingtree</placeName><placeName>Ongar</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>Essex</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine>2 sheets </addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<lb/><p>When I spoke of the teeth of a saw writing 
<lb/>However since you draw my attention to it so I 
<lb/>must say I the application might be made 
<lb/>But I never would be made by such 
<lb/>a wretched hand as mine excuse me saying this 
<lb/>It is always really &amp; truly most acceptable 
<lb/>you must just write in the way you 
<lb/>can, most sorely write often &amp; long </p><addSpan spanTo="#p.04-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left margin of fols 04-01'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p>long what from you &amp; never fail 
<lb/>to answer yours &amp; never will 
<lb/>Believe me yours affectionately</p><anchor xml:id="p.04-01"/>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>