<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000652">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to William C. Oswell</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to William C. Oswell, 10 April 1848</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>08-04-10</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000652</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Auckland Libraries; MS. 116</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Oswell, William C., 1818-1893</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kolobeng</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1848-04-10">10 April 1848</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0184</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2010-05-21</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>Intial Transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000652_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1r'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Kolobeng</placeName>
<lb/>10<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> April 1848 </p>
<lb/><p>My Dear <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Oswel</persName></p>
<lb/><p>Your favour of July last containing a communication 
<lb/>from our friend <persName>Vardon</persName> reached its destination a short time ago. It was 
<lb/>extremely welcome and afforded us much pleasure. I only wish mine 
<lb/>may yield a tithe of what yours imparted. It set my mind at ease 
<lb/>on several points. I had concluded that my note had miscarried - 
<lb/>that you had gone to <placeName>England</placeName> - &amp; was on the eve of writing to 
<lb/><persName>Vardon</persName> for your address. In addition to the plasure of perusal 
<lb/>the prospect of another visit allows us to indulge the pleasures 
<lb/>of hope. And our position in this out of the world region has taught 
<lb/>us to make the most of this source of employment. On one point 
<lb/>I feel a little sorry, and though engaged in building a new house 
<lb/>I hasten to remove the impression from your mind which my 
<lb/>letter seems unfortunately to have produced. I suspect the wording 
<lb/>of my epistle has been <del type="strikethrough">read</del> far wrong to induce you to conclude I doubted 
<lb/>your accuracy in the nothing of the Limpopo. I do not recollect 
<lb/>my words but I remember having a conversation with you on the 
<lb/>point before my mind in perusing it, in which you remarked 
<lb/>if the River really did come round as far south as the <placeName>Aegoa Bay</placeName>
<lb/>it would be one of the most remarkable rivers in the world. Having 
<lb/>ascertained that it really does come very far south I felt anxious to 
<lb/>set you right in your idea of the unprobability of such a roundaboit 
<lb/>course. If I appeared to throw discredit on the Morthing it makes 
<lb/>I must have alluded (in my own mind) to Arkthought mao &amp; I 
<lb/>am very sorry the blunder has caused you uneasiness. <persName>N<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> A</persName> left 
<lb/>me a sketch but I relied on yours and indeed that information furnished 
<lb/>by you and <persName>Capt<hi rend="sup">n</hi> M</persName> is the only knowledge I posess on that part of the 
<lb/>course of the River. I never was East of the Balai in the same latitute 
<lb/>My knowledge of the Lulipolo was gained in the Latitute of <placeName>Choumane</placeName>
<lb/>and Southwards (a little) I believe <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Murray's</persName> rights to have been 
<lb/>pretty correct and from  your account that the Limpolo goes 
<lb/>as far North as that tribe I see no reason to dissent - But whatever 
<lb/>may be the Southing it makes It comes round again to very nearly 
<lb/>the latitude of the <placeName>Choumane</placeName>. The latter however (the junction) 
<lb/>I did not see. It was pointed out to me in the distance. In going from 
<lb/>this to the <placeName>Bamapela</placeName> our course is not quite straight. We have to make 
<lb/>some southing to avoid some ranges of hills. We crossed to <placeName>Marikoe</placeName> then 
<lb/>its source, but course was then North East for 9 days and there lies 
<lb/>the <placeName>Limpolo</placeName> again after having traversed the course you know 
<lb/>the first two crossings are by <placeName>Lundungo</placeName> the main direction of 
<lb/>the whole must however be at those parts North West. I imagine 
<lb/>its course may be some what of the following shape <!--Mike: diagram-->there exists a range of very high hills North East 
<lb/>of the <placeName>Bamapela</placeName> these may be the obstacle to its 
<lb/>finding its way to the sea farther north but this 
<lb/>is merely conjecture. Do not I entreat you imagine that 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000652_0002"/><!--pb/@n='1v'-->
<lb/>doubted the candour with which you made your observations. I supposed 
<lb/>that your observations had been dicated by a mass of magnetic rocks 
<lb/>eastward of <placeName>Choumane</placeName>. Arkwrights certainly were by some means 
<lb/>or other but now I believe it is quite possible yours in respect to 
<lb/>nothing may be correct by supposing that the river makes a great 
<lb/>bend. It certainly come round very far south whatever it may 
<lb/>have done in the north. </p>
<lb/><p>I have written <persName>Captain Steele</persName> very fully about about my projected journey lakewards<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Our removal to <placeName>Kolobeng</placeName> has deferred it but I had proposed to go 
<lb/>next month and had your letter not come to hand I would in a probability 
<lb/>have proceeded. I wait now for you if I hear of no one else having 
<lb/>his face in that direction. <persName>Sechele</persName> whom you know if a mixture 
<lb/>of good &amp; evil has for a considerable time past exhibited most of the 
<lb/>former quality on his character. He would accompany me himself 
<lb/>and as he has a considerable amount of regard for you it is probable 
<lb/>he will do the same when you come. I heard him lately saying that 
<lb/>you &amp; <unclear cert="low"><persName>Olson</persName></unclear> exceeded all other travellers and when I told him that you 
<lb/>intended another visit he seemed much pleased &amp; requested me to 
<lb/>return your salutationsas that is possible on paper. His conduct 
<lb/>to us &amp; to others has been for a long time better than we hoped for in 
<lb/>a native - is a great reader according to his means - has perused 
<lb/>the Testament &amp; all the other parts of the Bible printed three times 
<lb/>and is found of general informationthe innate African 
<w>greed-<lb break="no"/>iness</w> may not not be diminished to others but it to us for he 
<lb/>invariably offers to pay for what he gets from us. We are infinitely 
<lb/>better here than where we were formerly, the hutonegs have been 
<lb/>a sore drain on the salary but we are devoutly thankful that we are 
<lb/>away from <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName>. We have had and still have much hard work 
<lb/>but feel in good spirits. We can irrigate now. Have good water - 
<lb/>A great blessing in <placeName>Africa</placeName>. People talk of nightingales &amp; poets turn 
<lb/>up their eyes to ?? I thank they call her because they have 
<lb/>nothing else to do But if all the songsters in the world I like best to
<lb/>
        hear the merry frogs tantalus like up to their chins in water. Esop 
<lb/>must have been an African for he speaks tenderly of these same 
<lb/>musicians. We are about 40 miles West N. West of <placeName>Chouname</placeName>. 
<lb/>the spot I mentioned as due west of our old place did not afford a 
<lb/>good prospect for native produce so we went down the stream a 
<lb/>little. If no mishap occurs we shall be able to supply you with 
<w>com-<lb break="no"/>ment</w> year - so you must not purchase much in the colony. If we 
<lb/>have it &amp; shall write &amp; let you know. You must allow us to 
<lb/>furnish you with at least corn &amp; potatoes. When we came hither 
<lb/><persName>Sechele</persName> of his own accord built the school &amp; his people made the 
<lb/>watercourse &amp; dam in exchange for some assistance in erecting 
<lb/>a square house for their chief - these works saved some expenses 
<lb/>which had we been in <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName> must have been incurred. Poor 
<lb/>Mabotsa <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> E</persName> quarrelled with Mosielele soon after we left - the difference 
<lb/>was never made up &amp; scarcely a single Mokhatea either adult or 
<lb/>child ever comes near him for instruction. We feel very sorry for 
<lb/>this for we worked hard there in matters were looking favourable<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>If you wished to come through Mabotsa again you know the route<reg>.</reg>We go by a path West of the station leaving the old path at <placeName>Maritsane</placeName>
<lb/>we enter the hills near <placeName>Motsenekatze</placeName> &amp; come along by the high hills 
<lb/>directly west of the reedy part of <placeName>Mitoane</placeName> where <persName>Baba</persName> was killed 
<lb/>on your spoor. We come close  by a large table hill which is visible 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000652_0003"/><!--pb/@n='2r'-->
<lb/>from <placeName>Choumane</placeName> containing plenty of Black buck. We sent out 
<lb/>waggon lately by the Western path which the Gruguas always take 
<lb/>on account of the game. Either of these I should prefer if a sportsman 
<lb/><persName>Cumming</persName> took your spoor last year with 15 horses 18 dogs &amp; a hottentot 
<lb/>Venus - a species of solace I suppose. He spent some considerable time 
<lb/>in hunting a new buck which he resolved to call A. Ronalyni in honour 
<lb/>of himself. I thought it entirely new untill I described it to two boers 
<lb/>I heard them declare it was the Bushbuck of the colony. I have no 
<lb/>doubt it is the same you shot &amp; lost among the reed - viz the same 
<lb/>as you mention. <unclear cert="low">fine</unclear> white stripes like the Khoodoo &amp; about 20 
<lb/>small <add place="above">white</add> spots on the hip - horns of male like those of the goat here. &amp; 
<lb/>a darkish belly, hoops prettily curved <add place="above">towards</add> this. I felt sorry you had not 
<lb/>secured it but do no regret now. If no one <add place="above">un</add> moreover <persName>Cumming</persName>
<lb/>before he gets to the colony. I shall send you a portion of newspaper 
<lb/>with the puff he is sure to put in. He passed the Barilaka I could 
<lb/>not ascertain from him how far  but believe it must have 
<lb/>been 7 or 9 days beyond at most. He gave the Lumpopo a little more 
<lb/>herd south than you - a very little however, says he killed 33 elephants 
<lb/>a great number of hippopotomi. Went to some hills West of the 
<lb/>river to hunt putokuane  - was successful - and so were the tsetse 
<lb/>for he wrote to us from beyond the junction of the votsave for 
<lb/>the loan of oxen. One solitary mare &amp; two oxen with a dog or two 
<lb/>attested what the fly can do. One of his hottentots was snatched away 
<lb/>from the fire one evening by a lion &amp; devoured a few paces from 
<lb/>the waggon. <persName>Cumming</persName> killed it next day. We will never think 
<lb/>the Lake. Not he, unless somebody tells him that he may get wary 
<lb/>lying on the ground there. He is by far the keenest trader we have 
<lb/>seen in <placeName>Africa</placeName>. When he sees an elephant he does not become excited 
<lb/>with the idea of sport. He says in his heart "there goes £25" I could not 
<lb/>help pitying him when he made the confession - feels anxious to obtain 
<lb/>a fastu &amp; uncertain too whether he will come up again. I think his 
<lb/>necessaries will drive in again but it will be  to the Lumpopo 
<lb/><del type="strikethrough">again</del>. I mention this much concerning him that you feel at ease 
<lb/>on his future course. </p>
<lb/><p>I feel confident that <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ashton</persName> has <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> the sum you mention, if 
<lb/>he had not I should have heard it from him when at <placeName>Kuruman</placeName> I distinctly 
<lb/>remember that he stated the manner in which you settled about the rifle 
<lb/>he thought a money transaction would be the most <gap extent="8" unit="chars" agent="illgblDel"/>
<lb/>&amp; therefore said he I proposed it to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> O.</persName> I shall ask him however <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
<lb/>Hume</persName> has been in <placeName>Graham's town</placeName> for some time past. I shall 
<lb/>deliver your message by first opportunity &amp; it will probably reach 
<lb/><placeName>Kuruman</placeName> as soon as he - your kind gift to me was brought 
<lb/>to us in August last, the rogues however had taken as much 
<lb/>benefit out of it during the two years they kept it from me as to render 
<lb/>him useless for some time after I got him - the sickness began 
<lb/>early this season and he fell a victim to my great sorrow. We got by 
<lb/>him several eilads &amp; Kaveels. I had always doubts about his identity, he 
<lb/>had a bay mane &amp; tail now you mentioned that these points were black 
<lb/>they deny the saddle. It may howeveryet turn out when no longer 
<lb/>usable. We felt the more sorry to part with the poor animal  as it was 
<lb/>in our minds closely associated with yourself. As I am on a four footed 
<lb/>subject I may mention that <persName>Roberts</persName> cow has calved <add place="above">a heffer calf</add> &amp; both cow &amp; 
<lb/>you have given us. <persName>Robert</persName> runs about now &amp; speaks a little in both  
<lb/>languages, his sister helps him occasionally in the 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000652_0004"/><!--pb/@n='2v'-->
<lb/>matrimonial music we enjoy. If you heard them both at it you would 
<w>con-<lb break="no"/>sider</w>  that <persName>Selkirk</persName> talked nonsense when he said something about science 
<lb/>is shocking to me. I am building a new house at present. I burned the 
<lb/>old house &amp; school lest a boer might take up his residence in them. This 
<lb/>brings to my mind the Boor expedition to <persName>Mosilikatze</persName>. It was a mere foray 
<lb/>for cattle &amp; they suceeded in carrying of a number but the Matibele recaptured 
<lb/>them &amp; killed a great number of their native auxilaries, the expedition 
<lb/>ended by their attacking one of their assistant tribes - the Bamapela - and 
<lb/>carrying off a great number of children &amp; sheep. I saw in my late journey 
<lb/>many Bamapele children in their houses kept in a kind of slavery. The 
<lb/>Boers generally are indignent until the party which acted treacherously 
<lb/>with a friendly tribe - they have had some meetings on the subject. But 
<lb/>I need not trouble you with Boor politics. The above is the report given 
<lb/>by the boors themselves &amp; the native report agrees with it, the Boors generally 
<lb/>intend an expedition against <persName>Moszilikatze</persName> in May next, they crossed the 
<lb/><placeName>Limpopo</placeName> somewhere about  x <persName>Cumming</persName> did not see their spoor 
<lb/>so I conclude he did not go very much further than yourselves. <persName>Mosilikatze</persName>
<lb/>lives not very far from the Limpopo. It would be dangerous to go very 
<lb/>far down the River on the northern bank. One might fall in with 
<lb/>Matibele &amp; be mistaken for a boer. </p>
<lb/><p>As I have but little space now I must say a word on the course to the 
<lb/>Lake one route is N. W. from this for a considerable part of the way &amp; 
<lb/>waggons can go on till within 8 days of the water - the other has more 
<lb/>northing &amp; passes by Sekhomi, this is the preferable route as waggons can perform the whole distance. Sekhomi is unwilling that any one 
<lb/>go past him for his ivory comes from the tribes situated there 
<lb/>but we should not ask his leave. We should go through north from 
<lb/>Masihue or Koribelo. Please bring a nautical Almanack with you. 
<lb/>Five shillings in London. But 15 at the <placeName>Cape</placeName>. I have requested <persName>Captain 
<lb/>Steele </persName> to bring any periodicals he can lay his hands on. Any old 
<lb/>Reviews Scientific  journals - <hi rend="underline">not new.</hi> Maybe left here rather than 
<lb/>be consigned to luniber homes at home. If you can take in the Edinburgh or 
<lb/>Blackwood  while at home. Please do not leave them behind you 
<lb/>If you wonder at my impudence  But I am a caffre - the seeds have 
<lb/>not arrived yet but will in due time I have no doubt . I thank 
<lb/>you infrequently for them - the ?? seeds did not vegetate here<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>
<address>
<addrLine>Care of the <persName>Rev. D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Philip <placeName>Cape Town</placeName></persName>
<lb/><persName> W, Oswell  Esq</persName><hi rend="sup underline">re</hi>
<lb/>India</addrLine>
</address>
</p><addSpan spanTo="#addEnd-2v" place="end"><!--addSpan/@place='sheet folded to make envelope. Envelope test on the middle of fo. 2v'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p>Saw two genuine Banyanis. Roots coming down 
<lb/>a lot of fibrils at the end of each descending branch all 
<lb/>ready to do duty in the ground. <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">rs</hi>L</persName> joins 
<lb/>with me in very affectionate salutations. </p>
<lb/><p>Ever yours <persName>D Livingston</persName></p><anchor xml:id="addEnd-2v"/>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>