<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000803">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Thomas Maclear</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Thomas Maclear, 29 September 1853</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2008-10</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000803</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">National Library of Scotland; MS. 10768, ff. 10-11</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0323</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Maclear, Thomas, 1794-1879</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1853-09-29">29 September 1853</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Sekeletu's Town</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2008</date>
				<name xml:id="initials">CO</name>Initial Transcription by Caroline Overy
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000803_0001"/><!--pb/@n='10r'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Town of Sekeletu</placeName>, <placeName>Linyanti</placeName> 29<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> September</p>
<lb/><p rend="right">1853</p>
<lb/><p><persName>Thomas Maclear</persName> Esq<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">re</hi></hi></p>
<lb/><p rend="center">My Dear Sir</p>
<lb/><p>Enclosed you will <choice><sic>percieve</sic><corr>perceive</corr></choice> a mass of 
<lb/>manuscripts with which I take the liberty to trouble you. The <unclear cert="medium">faggot</unclear> contains 
<lb/>observations made at different parts of the country and I venture to 
<lb/>send them such as they are because you mentioned that you preferred 
<lb/>such to those which have passed through the adulterating process of an 
<lb/>African calculation. If you read them backwards like Hebrew viz. 
<lb/>beginning with the fifth or sixth <del type="strikethrough">page</del><add place="above">sheet</add> I shal feel obliged for 
<lb/>then you will be able to see the reason why I sent such 
<lb/>poor things as those made from the <term type="tribe">Bamangwato</term> Northwards<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I found or thought I found that our Longitudes of last 
<lb/>journey were all wrong, our waggon stand instead of being in 
<lb/>26º is not more than 23º 48′ or 50′. But I have not so much 
<lb/>confidence in my calculations as to assert this without serious 
<lb/>misgivings. When I found that the Boers had destroyed my 
<lb/>celestial map - I set off to work on the Lunars and persevered 
<lb/><choice><sic>untill</sic><corr>until</corr></choice> I think I have mastered the methods given in <persName>Thomson's</persName>
<lb/>Tables perfectly, I made many obsevations between <placeName>Kuruman</placeName>
<lb/>and this but working with the inverting telescope chiefly I placed 
<lb/>no value on them. My chief aim was to acquire as much 
<lb/>facility with it as with the small telescope, I have succeeded 
<lb/>in this too, but when i found out longitudes were wrong 
<lb/>I felt nsorry I had not written down all my observations. 
<lb/>Those I have put down are from the <term type="tribe">Bamangwato</term> Northwards 
<lb/>and were made in trying to work with the sextant fixed on 
<lb/>a stand with a movable joint. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey are very precise but 
<lb/>the time required to get the mercury into the right position in 
<lb/>turning from one object to another, and above all this difficulty 
<lb/>of getting the instrument adjusted to the different angles in which 
<lb/>Lunars are observed rendered this effort after many trials 
<lb/>abortive. I thought however that you may be able to 
<lb/>make something of them, perhaps determine whether the Long. 
<lb/>of the <term type="tribe">Bamangwato</term> is right. I worked out many here before 
<lb/>coming to the conclusion that 26º was wrong, and a new 
<lb/>idea has lately entered my head which makes me fear 
<lb/>that <persName>M<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Morton</persName> may be right after all. <gap extent="3" unit="words" agent="editorialDecision"/>

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000803_0002"/><!--pb/@n='10v'-->
<gap extent="1" unit="pages" agent="editorialDecision"/>

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000803_0003"/><!--pb/@n='11r'-->
<gap extent="0.5" unit="pages" agent="editorialDecision"/></p>
<lb/><p>One of the slave merchants wished me to go westward in 
<lb/>his company. He was as kind to me when I was up at the <term type="tribe">Barotse</term>
<lb/>as he could be, influenced probably by a letter from the <persName>chevalier 
<lb/>Du Pratt</persName>. <choice><reg>B</reg><orig>b</orig></choice>ut the sight of gangs of poor wretches in chains 
<lb/>was so much against the grain I resolved to proceed alone<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>He could speak no language, but Portuguese. We managed 
<lb/>to make a jargon. I caught all the owrds resembling latin 
<lb/>added other Latin terms to these and when very much at a 
<lb/>loss stuck in some big rough Dutch word to eke out the 
<lb/>sentence. It is so wonderful how seeon one believes he understands 
<lb/>what is said, <persName>Cumming</persName> thought he could speak Sechuana 
<lb/>when he knew about four words. I have heard him call out 
<lb/>"Rhinoceros" when he wanted his servant to beat the oxen and 
<lb/>he thought he must be understood because the whip was made 
<lb/>of rhinocerous skin. Pardon this gossip and</p>
<lb/><p>Believe me yours </p>
<lb/><p>most Truly </p>
<lb/><p>David Livingston</p>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000803_0004"/><!--pb/@n='11v'-->
<gap agent="editorialDecision"/><!-- envelope -->
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>