<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000526">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to George Drummond</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to George Drummond, 20 June 1843</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>20-12-07</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000526</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0071</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>20-12-07</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Initial Transcription by Caroline Overy
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000526_0001"/><!--pb/@n='14r'-->
<lb/><p><placeName>Kuruman</placeName> 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June 1843 </p>
<lb/><p>My Dear Friend</p>
<lb/><p>I <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> your most welcome &amp; long expected letter a few days 
<lb/>ago, and I assure you my heart was made white by its perusal. I am 
<lb/>glad you have at length arrived at a sphere of labour &amp; that there is a 
<lb/>prospect of your labour being crowned with success. May you have 
<lb/>an <unclear cert="low">sanction</unclear> from the Holy one that many sinners may through your 
<lb/>instrumentality be baptized with the holy Ghost sent down from Heaven<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>But while I am glad to hear of your prospects I feel sorry that you 
<lb/>have some <del type="strikethrough"><gap agent="illgblDel"/></del> pain in that you are not engaging in full cooperation 
<lb/>of your dear partner in life. The debility of which you spoke 
<lb/>I hope however is by this time removed and you may now be 
<lb/>both vigorously prosecuting the great work for which we have 
<lb/>been sent to the Heathen. I a not going to give you medical 
<lb/>advice at such a distance but you could easily manufacture 
<lb/>a shower <unclear cert="medium">bath</unclear> which if used when you are not sensible 
<lb/>of either chill or fatigue I have no doubt would benefit you 
<lb/>both. You must present my Christian love to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> D</persName> &amp; 
<lb/>her little<persName>Jean</persName>. I mention it now lest as I am this old 
<lb/>batchelor I should forget it at the end. <persName>Inglis</persName> is married &amp; 
<lb/>now on his way up here, so is <persName>Moore</persName> &amp; now on his way 
<lb/>to your quarter, <persName>Prentice</persName> is married to <persName><unclear cert="medium">Catrine</unclear></persName> &amp; has a child 
<lb/>I believe he gor her because he <unclear cert="low">inferred she</unclear> a missionary 
<lb/>now he is stuck up in his <unclear cert="medium">fathers counting</unclear> house at 
<lb/><placeName>Stowmarket</placeName> &amp; <persName>John <unclear cert="medium">Hay</unclear></persName> is expected home to be noosed to 
<lb/><persName>Lucy</persName>. Thus you see the world goes on and all my good 
<lb/>example is lost upon it. O Tempores O mores! You 
<lb/>thought I should turn foolish at the Cape What nonsense 
<lb/>man<reg>.</reg> Do you think I would take a thing in hand &amp; 
<lb/>not carry it through<reg>.</reg> But I suppose I must give in 
<lb/>directly for I shall get a few of the wise sayings og 
<lb/><persName>Magregor</persName> before long.</p>
<lb/><p>I am happy to hear your are succeeding with the  
<lb/>language. I had to speak long before I knew what to 
<lb/>say. Colics came in by dozens &amp; sore bellies by the score &amp; if I did not help them they were sure to help me, I then 
<lb/>set <unclear cert="low">off N</unclear> left all European society, went far north 
<lb/>&amp; beyond every other white man in order to learn the 
<lb/>different dialects of the language, this latter I partially 
<lb/>effected &amp; now i can speak so as to be understood 
<lb/>by any of them. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he language of the other tribe however is 
<lb/>that in which I am most expert, I can preach in it with nearly the same ease as i can speak 
<lb/>English<reg>.</reg> But still I have something to learn, I cannot 
<lb/>apply all the words I know at the exact time when 
<lb/>I wish to use them. By the above course I have 
<lb/>been made acquainted with the customs &amp; modes of thinking 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000526_0002"/><!--pb/@n='14v'-->
<lb/>of the people better than if I had remained as one station, and 
<lb/>there being but a very slender assistance to be to be derived from the 
<lb/>language used in the testament the above course was absolutely 
<lb/>necessary. During my first visit to the Interior I went as 
<lb/>far as North East as far as Lat 22ยบ S. Long 29ยบ E. &amp; visited many 
<lb/>tribes who had never before seen a white face. By 
<lb/>means of native teachers with me I was enabled in a poor 
<lb/>was to proclaim the message od mercy. That tour 
<lb/>lasted 4 months &amp; now I am just returned from another 
<lb/>of a like duration. But this is a weary wide wide country &amp; the people are scattered over it at immense distances from each other, I could give you many 
<lb/>anecdotes of wild beasts if you were a lover of such 
<lb/>stuff but as I know you are not I would fain 
<lb/>give you something more profitable. I have not been 
<lb/>allowed to attempt anything of a permanent nature in 
<lb/>consequence of an interdict of the Directors, they forbade information of any new station <choice><sic>untill</sic><corr>until</corr></choice> the whole 
<lb/>mission should be organized, this  organization was 
<lb/>to take place after the arrival of <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName> &amp; the 
<lb/>other bretheren &amp; means simply, a committee is to be 
<lb/>got up by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.</persName> in opposition to the former 
<lb/>state of things by <persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Phillip</persName>. A committe it is to be 
<lb/>alias a presbetery. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his is as much against the grain 
<lb/>with me as the bishoprick is, But if it will advance 
<lb/>the cause I wont spend time quarelling. I have not 
<lb/>the least confidence in the wisdom either collective or 
<lb/>individual of our S. African bretheren. There has been 
<lb/>too much <unclear cert="medium">jarring</unclear> &amp; now a committee the result of a <unclear cert="medium">jar</unclear>
<lb/>It does not bode well. I shall give it the go by if I 
<lb/>see nonsense springing up. O that <unclear cert="medium">none</unclear> of my life 
<lb/>may be spent in vain <unclear cert="low">jangling</unclear> after I have had 
<lb/>such an opportunity of devoting it to him who 
<lb/>died to save me.</p>
<lb/><p>This mission has been pretty successful among 
<lb/>the <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>, But a stranger coming here would 
<lb/>not know it. Indeed he wold feel disappointment 
<lb/>if he had not read the accounts published respecting it<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey are far below the Hottentots in point of 
<w>civiliz-<lb break="no"/>ation</w> &amp; general information as well as morality<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Of a church composed of more than 300  don't know 
<lb/>half a dozen of whom I could say with confidence 
<lb/>the man appears to have consacrated himself to 
<lb/>the Redeemer. But notwithstanding <supplied reason="illegible">this</supplied> the change 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000526_0003"/><!--pb/@n='15r'-->
<lb/>among them upon the whole has been wonderful. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he 
<lb/>difference which exists between professed believers &amp; 
<lb/>the professed heatheb is such as to make one feel there 
<lb/>there must be something more than outward conformity 
<w>notwit-<lb break="no"/>hstanding</w> all the darkness &amp; perversity with which it is 
<lb/>asociated.<choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he pure heathen are as degraded in soul 
<lb/>body &amp; spirit as it is possible to <choice><sic>concieve</sic><corr>conceive</corr></choice> the human
<lb/><del type="strikethrough"> mind</del><add place="above">ity</add><!--TODO MH: 'ity'. DL wrote 'human <lb/>mind' and then changed it to 'humanity'. --><!-- TODO SM: Email jpg of this page to me so I can check something out --> to be &amp; nothing but the Holy Spirit can produce any 
<lb/>the least change in such characters. Very soon I 
<lb/>expect to depart for the interior &amp; assist in the 
<w>form-<lb break="no"/>ation</w> of a station at the <term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term> tribe. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey are the  
<lb/>iron smelters of whom <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Campbell</persName> heard but 
<lb/>was not permitted to see &amp; they are situated very 
<lb/>near the spot where he faced round to go away 
<lb/>home. It is also near the spot where <persName>Mosilkatse</persName>
<lb/>was seen by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName>. you will read an 
<lb/>account of him in <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M's</persName> book. You will see numerals in that book, for instance the 
<lb/>immense armies of <persName>Mosilikatse</persName>, cut off a few 
<lb/>cyphers always then you will have the truth<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I do not wish to say a word against <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M</persName> but 
<lb/>in his love for the good cause he sometimes <supplied reason="damage">mistates</supplied>. 
<lb/>He always calls thousands what others who were with 
<lb/>him call hundreds.  I hope he will be still <gap agent="damage" extent="1" unit="words"/>
<lb/>useful than he has been. Indeed I have no doubt 
<lb/>he will if he has not been spoiled in England<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Is it true that Good <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Williams</persName> was spoiled by the 
<lb/>people in E? We fear for <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.</persName> It is not every 
<lb/>one who can drink of the cup of flattery &amp; not get 
<lb/>"top heavy"<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>I have heard from the <persName>Pynes</persName> frequently, also 
<lb/>from <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Cecil</persName> &amp; other friends whom you know<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Wee <persName>Thomas <gap agent="illegible"/></persName> wrote this shabby thing had no 
<lb/>time to write to any one but <persName>Catrine</persName>. Is he a 
<w>mission-<lb break="no"/>ary</w> as she expected? <persName>Birt</persName> lost his wife a few 
<lb/>weeks ago by the overturning of his waggon, 
<lb/>mine was overturnd twice during my late journey 
<lb/>&amp; yet I am spared, may my spared life be devoted to Him who spares it. <persName>Fairbrother</persName> is still at 
<lb/><placeName><unclear cert="medium">Springhill</unclear></placeName> &amp; is expected to go out to <placeName><unclear cert="low">Benares</unclear></placeName>, <persName>Parker</persName>
<lb/>is at <placeName>Homerton</placeName> &amp; <persName>Jock Bradford</persName> is at the scalpel<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Poor dear <persName>Moore</persName> my heart is sore when I think 
<lb/>of him. He wished to come out here &amp; I groaned 
<lb/>for it But it was selfishness on my part he 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000526_0004"/><!--pb/@n='15v'-->
<lb/>will be more useful where he is young. Blessings upon 
<lb/>the head of Joseph &amp; on the crown of the head of him 
<lb/>who is separated from his bretheren. I shall write 
<lb/>you again before long &amp; you <choice><sic>you</sic><corr>no text</corr></choice> must do the  
<lb/>same to me, then we shall have a letter in <supplied reason="damage" cert="medium">advance</supplied>
<lb/>&amp; there wont be such a long gap in our 
<w>corresp-<lb break="no"/>ondence.</w> By the Bye, I have thought of you, <unclear cert="low">then</unclear>
<lb/>you will not be unwilling to give some <gap agent="hand"/>
<lb/>information to a projected Welsh periodical which 
<lb/>is to be chiefly devoted to missionary matters. Tell me  
<lb/>&amp; I shall give your name to the Editor. If you will 
<lb/>supply a letter occasionally it will be translated &amp; 
<lb/>published &amp; may advance the cause of our blessed saviour<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p><persName>Salome Cecil</persName> is very ill of some complaint of the liver<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>You have probably heard of <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wright's</persName> death, I mean <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
<lb/>Wright</persName> of <placeName>Ongar</placeName>. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wright</persName> of <placeName>Griqua Town</placeName> ia also 
<lb/>dead. He was an able &amp; efficient missionary, &amp; his 
<lb/>place will not soon be filled up<reg>.</reg> May we who are 
<lb/>spared be enabled to work while we are able &amp; glorify 
<lb/>Our Father in Heaven. My very kind regards to 
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> D.</persName> &amp; believe me ever yours most affectionately 
<lb/><!-- TODO SM: Email jpg of this page --><!-- TODO MH: Check transcription/coding of this section -->I shall be content if you address me just D Livingston 
<lb/>as I write <unclear cert="low">there without any ???</unclear> &amp; to the care of <persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Phillip</persName> Cape Town.</p>
<lb/><p><!--TODO SM: Envelope needs coding with addSpan/anchor-->Care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">d</hi></hi> D<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Phillip</persName><hi rend="underline">Cape Town</hi></p>
<lb/><p><persName>Rev<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">d</hi></hi> George Drummond</persName></p>
<lb/><p><placeName>Island of Savaii</placeName></p>
<lb/><p><hi rend="double-underline">South Seas</hi></p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>