<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_002572">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to John Kirk 2</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to John Kirk 2, 26 June 1871</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2009-04-04</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_002572</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 1971</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2009-04-04</date>
				<name xml:id="initials">SM</name>Initial Transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_002572_0001"/><!--pb/@n='81v'-->
<lb/><p>To <persName>D<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">r</hi></hi>Kirk</persName> from <persName>D. Livingstone</persName> 26<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> June 1871 </p>
<lb/><p>On this page I intended to put an Arabic dismissal of the <unclear cert="low">sin slaving</unclear>
<lb/>I use it now to say please do not be offended with <unclear cert="low">palavers</unclear> - I am really 
<lb/>reduced to beggary notwithstanding all the bountiful provisions you 
<lb/>with immense difficulty made for me and that too almost entirely by the 
<lb/>villany of the unmitigated drunken blackgaurd <persName>Shareef</persName>. His <unclear cert="low">banality</unclear> a British subject is in part to blame for he must have known his habits 
<lb/>and his brandy when they imposed him on us. He is reported to have bought 
<lb/>ivory with my goods and this ivory ought to be stopped at the Custom house 
<lb/>as is done in the case of Arabs till he as funds - If <persName>Sayed bin Majid</persName> sends the 
<lb/>list of goods left by <persName>Shareef</persName> you will judge the extent of loss. If not 
<lb/>the case had better wait till I return. Remember that the list contaning 
<lb/>12 Frasilahs sam sam and the watch is that destroyed by <persName>Shareef</persName> - I have 
<lb/>that of Samsam 6 Frasilahs and think as he refused it to Digumbe it 
<lb/>hidden: I feel sore most of all about the watch though it is hard 
<lb/>to be living from hand to mouth in beggary which my Bamian slaves 
<lb/>sixteen months in dover and idleness <unclear cert="low">calming</unclear> my supoosed from five 
<lb/>to seven dollars per month - they are underpaid  out of the Arabs but so they 
<lb/>one of us and of honesty. I go West of this to <placeName>Lomane</placeName> 30ยบ then buy a 
<lb/>canoe if <persName>Dugumbe</persName> will advance the give and go south to the watershed 
<lb/>and form fountains - <persName>Dugumbe</persName> is very friendly and a gentleman with 
<lb/>exploring enterprise which than any other. He is going to sow and be 
<lb/>here at <placeName>Nyangne</placeName> in three years sending every now and then to <placeName>Ujiji</placeName>letters sent to him will be safe <reg>.</reg> His <unclear cert="low">mople</unclear> will bring some 
<lb/>goods for one from <placeName>Ujiji</placeName> and I shall share liberally with him 
<lb/>I ought have mentioned that a dyke of basalt or other igneous rock 
<lb/>cuts across the river 4 days off the canoe this and the immense body 
<lb/>of water is jammed rushing through the gutting ends which are not parallel 
<lb/>and form whirlpools in which canoes rell round &amp; round 
<lb/>hopelessly <gap extent="4" unit="words" agent="damage"/>or would have near 
<lb/>foremost in this and a cataract below - and as Makololo to the hills 
<lb/>I thought next of going up river to <placeName>Kamolondo</placeName> the broad part of 
<lb/><placeName>Webb<reg>'</reg> Lake</placeName> river at another cataract intervenes so I go due 
<lb/>West on foot on the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> day of New &amp; about 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> July. In this am able 
<lb/>of old and you will see how my mind is confused. I should be 
<lb/>turning up <placeName>Lomame</placeName> from <placeName>Lualaba</placeName> I should probably merit 
<lb/>some basaltic dyke in the ascent for such dykes run among us 
<lb/>across country - here I have the chance of cutting from <unclear cert="low">the lake</unclear>
<lb/>I had to pay the carriers of <persName>Shereef</persName> brandy<reg>,</reg> from <persName>David Livingstone</persName>
<lb/>bust to lest his own trade in ivory was what he followed shamelessly<reg>.</reg></p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>