<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000605">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Benjamin T. Pyne</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Benjamin T. Pyne, 1 January 1846</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2004-04-07</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000605</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0143</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2009-04-07</date>
				<name xml:id="initials">SM</name>Initial Transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000605_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1r'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Chonuane</placeName> 1<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">st</hi></hi> January /46 </p>
<lb/><p>My Very Dear Friends 
<lb/>I wrote you some months ago <del type="strikethrough">but</del>
<lb/>but was favoured with the means of transmission only 
<lb/><del type="strikethrough">last</del><add place="above">two</add> weeks ago. We are famishing for want of news from 
<lb/>the South having had no arrivals from <placeName>Kuruman</placeName> for 
<lb/>many months, and as the next best to <choice><sic>recieving</sic><corr>receiving</corr></choice><add place="above">myself</add> I begin 
<lb/>something to be <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> by you. It is a wearisome thing 
<lb/>to listen for months to the news of this dark region 
<lb/>without anything to turn our thoughts away to the world 
<lb/>of light &amp; civilisation. After the first two sentences 
<lb/>were penned an instance of what we have to listen 
<lb/>to perpetually occured in the arrival of two messengers 
<lb/>from a chief concerning his gun, somebody is 
<lb/>tailor to her Majesty But I am gun mender to all - the 
<lb/>tribes <del type="strikethrough">sen</del> &amp; their sovereign in the interior. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he 
<lb/>chief of the Bamangueto sent all the way here for 
<lb/>assistance in that particular, and I am sure 
<lb/>you would smile if you heard the supplicating 
<lb/>tone assumed by that as well as other potentates 
<lb/>when their guns are "dead" <reg>.</reg>And the authoritative 
<lb/>tone I assume in threatening to withold any aid if 
<lb/>one drop of human blood is ever shed by fire arms<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>In <persName>Sekhomi's</persName> case I threaten if he attacks the 
<lb/>Bakaas (As he recently attempted to do) I shall not 
<lb/>only refuse aid but prevent white men 
<w>sell-<lb break="no"/>ing</w> guns to him to him for all time to come. As they 
<lb/>are aware we possess some influence with our 
<lb/>countrymen - these threats make them almost turn 
<lb/>pale lest we put them into execution. I think 
<lb/>I told you in my last that <persName>Sechele</persName> the chief 
<lb/>to whom we have transferred our more stated 
<lb/>labours refrained from attacking the murderers 
<lb/>of his father "because he would not break 
<lb/>his promise to his missionary"<reg>.</reg> We had recently 
<lb/>at <placeName>Chonuane</placeName> a number of visitors from a 
<lb/>very numerous tribe to the E.S.E. of us, they are 
<lb/>of the Toolah or Matibele race and came 
<lb/>to sell leglets of brass manufactured by themselves 
<lb/>many of them had clocks of cotton cloth 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000605_0002"/><!--pb/@n='1v'-->
<lb/>they have seen the sea &amp; describe all that region as densely 
<lb/>populated. An old one eye doctor asked me if I were one of the 
<lb/>beings who go in ships and have eyes behind as well as 
<lb/>before, and on my exhibiting my head, he began gravely 
<lb/>to inform me that such creatures were actually in 
<lb/>existence. ! O when will these regions feel the influence 
<lb/>of the Sun if Righteousness. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he articles you kindly 
<lb/>sent me and for which if I have not thanked you 
<lb/>before I most heartily do, are very useful 
<lb/>indeed on occasions such as the above they 
<lb/>are very anxious to obtain a little thing or two 
<lb/>to shew they have been to the white man; and 
<lb/>when we have a little influence over them 
<lb/>we can use it in the prevention of wars &amp; 
<lb/>bloodshed. A party of Korranas attacked a village 
<lb/>about 12 miles from <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName> while I was at 
<lb/><placeName>Chounane</placeName> &amp; <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L</persName> at <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName>, they killed three 
<lb/>people &amp; took away their cattle<reg>.</reg><persName>Mosheu</persName> the 
<lb/>person mentioned in <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat<reg>'</reg>s</persName> work took 
<lb/>the cattle from the depradators &amp; sent them 
<lb/>back to the proper owners: I went to <placeName>Chouname</placeName>
<lb/>in order to prevent something of the sort there 
<lb/>in company with a son of <persName>Sir William Cumming</persName>
<lb/>to <placeName>Forres</placeName><reg>.</reg> As he is a real highlander he had 
<lb/>a great inclination to follow the marauders 
<lb/>in order to retake the cattle. He was on a hunting 
<lb/>expedition in the <placeName>Banyamgmato</placeName> country and 
<lb/>though deserted by all his people there brought 
<lb/>out £800 worth of ivory. <persName>Mebaloe</persName> went 
<lb/>in to help him when we heard of his misfortune 
<lb/>and found him with a broken axle, I made a 
<lb/>new one for him and he generously gave 
<lb/>at a low price coffee &amp;c sufficient to serve 
<lb/>us for nearly two years to come. As he has 
<lb/>been in the army &amp; is well bred we enjoyed his 
<lb/>company. Only thank Mary. <choice><reg>H</reg><orig>h</orig></choice>e gave us a few 
<lb/>numbers of "Punch". Did I not enjoy the 
<lb/>jokes on the poor River and that sort of thing<reg>.</reg>

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000605_0003"/><!--pb/@n='2r'-->
<lb/>We have been dependent on <placeName>Kuruman</placeName> for all our supplies <choice><sic>untill</sic><corr>until</corr></choice>now 
<lb/>when after a great deal of work &amp; expense I got my garden into 
<lb/>bearing order and from 5 1/2 buckets of wheat we reaped 166 
<lb/>by leaving I must begin the same thing over again but we are 
<lb/>now providentially supplied for a long time to come <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> P's</persName>
<lb/>turnips do well, the clover &amp; rape seed I have not yet tried but 
<lb/>the oats still retain their vegetative power - the turnips are 
<lb/>a most valuable accession to our articles of diet<reg>.</reg> We 
<lb/>thank you sincerely for them. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he cows here do not 
<lb/>eat Lucerne I don<reg>'</reg>t know whether they eat clover but 
<lb/>we shall try. Each cow gives just about a glass of 
<lb/>milk morning &amp; evening during winter: I am half or 
<lb/>quarter of a farmer now. A Scotch gentleman gave 
<lb/>me many hints when here lately indeed had he not 
<lb/>come we might through sheer ignorance have lost 
<lb/>our crop. He promised to send us seeds &amp;c from 
<lb/><placeName>Scotland</placeName> and another gentleman from <placeName>India</placeName> promised 
<lb/>to send lots of all sorts from <placeName>India</placeName>. All desire me 
<lb/>to write them but I must attend to my old friends 
<lb/>before those more recently known. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cumming</persName> is delighted 
<lb/>with the climate &amp; country and talks of colonizing us 
<lb/>highlanders. A great charm to him in it is abundance 
<lb/>of game. He himself shot 29 elephants and other kinds 
<lb/>of wild animals <del type="strikethrough">are</del> without number<reg>.</reg> He had 2 
<lb/>lions in the number of his trophies. Lately while 
<lb/>walking over from <placeName>Chouname</placeName> to <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName> during the 
<lb/><choice><sic>the</sic><corr>no text</corr></choice> night (a distance of 45 miles) in consequence of 
<lb/>the illness of my rib. We came near to two of these 
<lb/>animals. As I &amp; two of the people were in advance 
<lb/>we sat down to wait for the other two who had 
<lb/>fallen behind. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he lions then began to roar very 
<lb/>near us, which made us light up a fire immediately<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>We were so tired we all fell asleep in about 5 minutes 
<lb/>but having been awakened before day break we went 
<lb/>on &amp; when it was quite light we came close upon 
<lb/>two very large animals which quitely moved off 
<lb/>this was well for it was then raining so fast 
<lb/>we were wet wading ankle deep &amp; the gun would not 
<lb/>have fired. We went close by an enormous herd 
<lb/>of buffaloes the same morning.</p>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000605_0004"/><!--pb/@n='2v'-->
<lb/><p>I do not remember whether I thank <persName>Bernard</persName> for his bullets 
<lb/>but I believe I spoke about a pistol. I should now feel 
<lb/>more obliged by a thermometer made for the purpose 
<lb/>of measuring from the boiling point of water at the 
<lb/>level of the sea. Newman 122 Regent St. is the 
<lb/>maker most approved and as my better half intends to 
<lb/>trouble <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> P.</persName> to <choice><sic>to</sic><corr>no text</corr></choice> select some gown pieces for her the 
<lb/>instrument may be put to the same account. If 
<lb/>well I shall send a bill to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> P</persName> about april next part of it is 
<lb/>for dresses &amp; part for the assistance of my parents. We 
<lb/>both admire <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> P<reg>'</reg>s</persName> taste so much <add place="above">exhibited</add> in the things sent<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><anchor xml:id="envelopePosition" type="positionMarker"/>
<lb/>We proceed to the impudence above refered to. We need 
<lb/>strong drak coloured prints But <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L</persName> will give the necessary 
<lb/>information. She is a good deal of an African in 
<lb/>complexion a stout stumpy lady so you will 
<lb/>have no difficulty in selecting the proper sort of 
<lb/>thing after this explanation. In my next I shall 
<lb/>give you more missionary information that this 
<lb/>contains. Kind regards to all. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hanks to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> J</persName>
<lb/>for the great trouble he took in the case of the last bill<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>If I have not mentioned all the articles <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> it 
<lb/>is not because I feel nothing in the way of gratitude
<addSpan spanTo="#p1r-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left hand margin of p01'--></addSpan>I do not know what to do with the dress sent for <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Edwards</persName>. I did a great deal for her &amp; <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> E.</persName> Indeed the latter 
<lb/>was permitted to occupy the post of missionary in the interior entirely by my consenting to going in his company<reg>.</reg>But no sooner was he made a full missionary than he<anchor xml:id="p1r-01"/><addSpan spanTo="#p2r-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left hand margin of p01'--></addSpan>became offended because he was not also my superior<reg>.</reg>As he has a most unfortunate temper I think he
<lb/>would compel her to return it<reg>.</reg>He forced her against her sense of duty to leave <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName> for the <unclear cert="low">pleasure</unclear>of being confined <add place="above">in <placeName>Matita</placeName></add> in order that might not assist on that occasion<reg>.</reg><anchor xml:id="p2r-01"/><addSpan spanTo="#p1v-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left hand margin of p01'--></addSpan><persName><unclear cert="low">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ross</unclear></persName> is doing well at <placeName><unclear cert="low">Tauns</unclear></placeName>. A great many believers have collected under the wily old chief <persName>Bahura</persName> and many 
<lb/>conversions are taking place since. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R</persName> finds great difficulty in managing her little unruly members. 
<lb/><persName>Mr Inglis</persName> has begun with Bahruotse &amp; I hope he will succeed<reg>.</reg></p><anchor xml:id="p1v-01"/>
<lb/><p>
<address>
<addrLine>Care of the <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>D<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi>Philip</persName>
<lb/><placeName><hi rend="underline">Cape Town</hi></placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><persName>Benjamin Pyne Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi></persName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>Wildingtree</placeName>, <placeName>Ongar</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><hi rend="underline"><placeName>Essex</placeName></hi></addrLine>
<addrLine><hi rend="underline">single</hi></addrLine>
</address>
</p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>