<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_002659">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to John McRobert</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to John McRobert, 14 July 1843</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2007</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_002659</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Private owner</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0079</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>McRobert, John, 1793/4-1876</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1843-07-14">14 July 1843</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kuruman</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
				<language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2007-05-09</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Intial Transcription by Caroline Overy
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2007-06-08</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>Proof by CL
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_002659_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1r'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><space extent="6" unit="words"/><placeName>Kuruman</placeName> 14<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> July 1843</p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">My Dear Brother in Christ</p>
<lb/><p>I thank you for the good but little bit you 
<lb/>appended to the excellent letter of your partner<reg>.</reg> And I now take a 
<lb/>separate sheet in order to provoke you to do the same. I do not 
<lb/>remember to have seen you but if you studied at Glasgow we 
<lb/>must often have been near each other &amp; very likely we have looked 
<lb/>on each others countenance in our attendance at the Academy 
<lb/>lectures of <persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wardlaw</persName>, 1836-7. But that is of little 
<lb/>importance compared to the community of feeling which I trust we 
<lb/>possess. Our hearts are drawn to the same centre of attraction 
<lb/>and they long to see the benefits of the great Redemption 
<lb/>realized by all the human family, &amp; you make me glad 
<lb/>by telling me of the progress of the good cause in Scotland 
<lb/>and I wish I could give you as encouraging news from Africa<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Here however the chariot of the gospel goes on but slowly<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>We have other materials to work upon than you, the people with 
<lb/>whom you deal know immediately what you wish to be at<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>But here the minds of the people are so earthly when we 
<lb/>become acquainted with their modes of thinking it almost makes 
<lb/>us believe we have not got humanity to deal with, our nature 
<lb/>cannot sink lower that it has done in the case of <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term><reg>.</reg>
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>heir foolish hearts are darkened - their minds &amp; conscience 
<lb/>are defiled. As a nation they are the greatest cowards in 
<lb/>the world. Afraid to speak of death and yet if they can kill 
<lb/>without danger of being killed they glory in murder. In 
<lb/>some of the Interior tribes I have seen men with from 30 to 
<lb/>40 scars - the marks of incisions made after each murder 
<lb/>had been committed. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey did not seem sorry for it 
<lb/>but with an air of triumph have asked me to count 
<lb/>the scars as if they were highly meritorious in having so many<reg>.</reg>

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_002659_0002"/><!--pb/@n='1v'-->
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he females are the tillers of the ground &amp; have all the heavy burdens 
<lb/>assigned to them. A man is not ashamed to say he cannot carry a 
<lb/>weight but his wife can &amp; he will go &amp; tell her to do it - their ideas 
<lb/>of medicine are that all good is done &amp; evil is prevented by witchcraft<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Hence they imagine that whatever way we use the medicine it will 
<lb/>have the same effect. If a child refuses to drink medicine they will 
<lb/>pour it on its head or drink it themselves. If their guns miss 
<lb/>fire they ask medicine to heal them &amp; <persName>Sechele</persName> chief of the <term type="tribe">Bakwain</term>
<lb/>lately wanted me to give him some to make him run fast in 
<lb/>hunting. He shewed me a piece of root which he used for 
<lb/>that very purpose. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>heir music too is still in an state of 
<lb/>embryo. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>wo notes are all they possess and I have heard them 
<lb/>droning away at them through the whole night. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>heir language 
<lb/>too is as simple as possible &amp; very easily learned. It is an 
<lb/>original tongue &amp; in this respect somewhat resembles the Hebrew<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I know more than a dozen words in it which very nearly 
<lb/>resemble the Hebrew one of which I may mention as it has caused 
<lb/>me to believe the Septuagint rendering of Manna is the right one 
<lb/>Mang yo? What is <del type="strikethrough">it</del> this? <choice><reg>I</reg><orig>i</orig></choice>s just what the <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> would 
<lb/>say if placed in the same position as the Israelites when they 
<lb/>exclaimed <foreign xml:lang="he">מן הר</foreign> What is it? But of course these instances in 
<lb/>which it resembles that language are only accidental - All our 
<lb/>theological terms have been recently coined &amp; are not understood 
<lb/>by the natives generally. Some the manufacture a very 
<lb/>clever missionary are curious enough and I could give you 
<lb/>some amusement by them were they not associated with 
<lb/>a great disadvantage to the speedy progress of our cause. I 
<lb/>shall give you a specimen of a word as good as could have 
<lb/>been adopted in order to shew you the difference existing between 
<lb/>our work &amp; yours. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he word for soul is one used for 
<lb/>the breath, air or steam of a pot. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he same I believe as in 
<lb/>other languages but should we proceed to speak of it as 
<lb/>the man without a number of explanations very likely our 
<lb/>address would be interrupted by shouts of laughter. "What does 
<lb/>the man mean by talking about steam? can we eat it, is it 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_002659_0003"/><!--pb/@n='2r'-->
<lb/>food that <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">he</add> tells us so much about it"? <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his is not a difficult term to 
<lb/>explain to them but some of the others are as unlike the idea we intend 
<lb/>to convey as is the sound of a waggon wheel, this Theological language 
<lb/>is a great hindrance. It requires a long course of training before they 
<lb/>are brought to the state in which you can appeal to them on the 
<lb/>subject of religion with the assurance that they are not taking 
<lb/>up our words in an opposite sense from what we intend<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>We know that the spirit is always in the word and that if presented 
<w>accord-<lb break="no"/>ing</w> to His mind he will render it effectual<reg>.</reg> But the earthly sense 
<lb/>in which the natives have always used the words constitutes a great 
<lb/>barrier to our doing so. If that influence is necessary any 
<lb/>where and it is absolutely so everywhere how much more 
<lb/>so here, where the minds of men are so deplorably degraded, nothing 
<lb/>will <choice><sic>peirce</sic><corr>pierce</corr></choice> through this thick crust of ignorance which envelopes 
<lb/>their souls but the power of the Almighty. Let us have your 
<lb/>prayers for the manifestation of that power<reg>.</reg> But you 
<lb/>would require to be here to feel the utter hopelessness of our cause 
<lb/>without it.</p>
<lb/><p>I have occupied so much space with these details 
<lb/>I have very little room for anything else<reg>.</reg> But you may feel 
<lb/>interested in our modes of operation in itinerary. We have no 
<lb/>railways here<reg>.</reg><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he weary lumbering Dutch waggon drawn by 
<lb/>oxon; a pack ox or our own lower extremities are the only 
<lb/>modes of conveyance. When we arrive at a village &amp; wish to 
<lb/>have a regular service we are obliged to ask the chief to collect 
<lb/>his people, the place of concourse is the enclosure for the 
<lb/>cattle, sitting down among them we begin by an address generally 
<lb/>on one subject to which we confine ourselves as long as they 
<lb/>seem attentive to what is said. If we speak on more than 
<lb/>one subject they generally forget all we have said. And 
<lb/>after the address we have prayer, if they have been accustomed 
<lb/>to hear the gospel we sing but if not that is omitted, those 
<lb/>who wish to depart then go away <del type="strikethrough"><unclear cert="low">and</unclear></del> with those who 
<lb/>remain we get into conversation on the subject of the address 
<lb/>and I believe more good is done by conversations than by 
<lb/>formal addresses. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey seldom ever object to what we 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_002659_0004"/><!--pb/@n='2v'-->
<lb/>have told them<reg>.</reg> But many of them are bitter opponents to the gospel<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he old especially are our bitter enemies, they cannot bear the idea 
<lb/>of parting with their younger wives nor the impurities to which 
<lb/>they have long been accustomed<choice><reg>.</reg><orig>,</orig></choice> Of the old however there is 
<lb/>as great a proportion converted as of the young, perhaps the proport 
<lb/>of the former is greater, it is certainly such as to strike one from 
<lb/>England with surprise. I believe in England the conversion of the old 
<lb/>who have long rejected the gospel is rare<reg>.</reg> But here they have not 
<lb/>become gospel hardened &amp; perhaps this may account for the fact 
<lb/>of their frequent conversion -</p>
<lb/><p>I lately saw in the country of the <term type="tribe">Bamangwato</term> a son of <persName>Conrad Buys</persName>
<lb/>a runaway dutch boer who did immense mischief to the early 
<lb/>missionaries. His father is dead &amp; all his children 7 in number are 
<lb/>either dead or in slavery to the <del type="strikethrough"><unclear cert="medium">other</unclear></del> natives, the mother of the lad 
<lb/>I saw was a native, he is in a wretched condition, speaks 
<lb/>the language &amp; is dressed as a native. He has forgotten all 
<lb/>about God &amp; Jesus, but remembers his father was accustomed 
<lb/>to read a book kneel down to pray yet has forgot every 
<lb/>word of dutch. His father was a most abandoned character<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>But like the rest of the Dutch boers he had it seems a portion 
<lb/>of our genuine <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">Scotch</add> church going formality<reg>.</reg> I felt sad as I 
<lb/>looked on this poor relict, the seed of evil doers shall 
<lb/>never been renowned.</p>
<lb/><p><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he church here is in rather a low state just now and 
<lb/>has been so for many months. We have had no stirrings 
<lb/>among us since the commencement of the commotions in 
<lb/>the Interior<reg>.</reg><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he rumours of wars seemed to occupy the 
<lb/>minds of the natives to the exclusion of anything better. We 
<lb/>hope the arrival of the new bretheren with <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName> may 
<lb/>prove a season of revival, they are now in the Colony<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>But it is a long way off from this outlandish quarter<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>May you enjoy the presence of your Saviour &amp; with Him 
<lb/>every Temporal &amp; Spiritual blessing is the prayer of 
<lb/><seg rend="right">yours affectionately D Livingston</seg></p><!--<pb n="Additional"/>-->

	<pb n="0005" facs="liv_002659_0005"/><!--pb/@n='2v'-->
<ab type="envelope">
<address>
<addrLine>Care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Phillip</persName></addrLine>
<addrLine rend="right"><!-- CODIC: align right but it looks like crap online --><hi rend="underline">Cape Town</hi></addrLine>
<addrLine><space extent="3" unit="chars"/><persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> J. M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>Robert</persName></addrLine>
<addrLine><space extent="3" unit="words"/><!-- CODIC: align right but it looks like crap online --><placeName>Cambuslang</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><space extent="4" unit="words"/><!-- CODIC: align right but it looks like crap online --><hi rend="underline">Glasgow</hi></addrLine>
</address>
</ab>

<!--
<p>Glasgow <lb/>12 <unclear cert="low">Feb 1843</unclear></p>
<p>SHIP LETTER</p>
-->
	<pb n="0006" facs="liv_002659_0006"/><!--pb/@n='2v'-->
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>