<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2017-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000633">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Benjamin T. Pyne</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Benjamin T. Pyne, 31 May 1847</title>
				<author>Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
                <authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
                <publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
                <pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2017</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000633</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Royal Geographical Society (Great Britain); Archives, DL 2/6/1</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0168</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Pyne, Benjamin T., 1798/9-1880</persName>; </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1847-05-31">31 May 1847</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kuruman</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2009-04-20</date>
				<name xml:id="initials">Sharon Messenger</name>Initial Transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2017-06-22</date> 
				<name>Kate Simpson</name>Proofreading 
			</change>
			<change> 
				<date>2017-06-22</date> 
				<name>Adrian S. Wisnicki</name>Proofing and Formatting 
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000633_0001"/><!--pb/@n='01'-->
<lb/><p rend="no-indent"><space extent="2" unit="words"/><add place="inspace">A little girl called Agnes the name</add>  <placeName>Kuruman</placeName>31 <hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">st</hi></hi> May 1847 
<lb/><space extent="4" unit="words"/><add place="inspace">of my mother has taken up her abode with us for 
<lb/><space extent="12" unit="words"/>a time. May we</add> 
<lb/><space extent="1" unit="words"/>My very Dear Friends <space extent="2" unit="words"/><add place="inspace">feel she is lent <unclear cert="low">hither</unclear> up for God</add></p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent"><space extent="5" unit="words"/>Your favour of Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 19 has just now been placed 
<lb/>in my hands and though these are trembling I begin to do what I have 
<lb/>been doing most of the past day viz "strike while the 
<lb/>iron is hot." What have you seen doing say you? Are you 
<lb/>turned blacksmith? We thought you were a missionary well 
<lb/>I am and I was mending my intinerators or waggon wheels  which
<lb/>are rather the worse of having travelled some thousands 
<lb/>of miles. Could <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pyne</persName> weld a band or tire? If here we 
<lb/>could teach him<reg>.</reg> I shortened all nine <unclear cert="low">one</unclear> &amp; Sauls too without 
<lb/>any teaching whatever but this smacks of boasting. Yet 
<lb/>people are not ashamed at home to be called the "working 
<lb/>clergy" &amp; why should we stickle to call ourselves so? 
<lb/>We have been here nearly three months waiting till a 
<lb/>unit could be added to the world<reg>'</reg>s population, there are some 
<lb/>symptoms of the event transpiring tonight. We shall never 
<lb/>wait so long for another. It is a great trial of patience 
<lb/>to us but some things convince us that there are many 
<lb/>others quite beyond our control. I need not say that we 
<lb/>feel always thankful for your letters. I think I had better say 
<lb/>it once for all. And now I must begin and thank you 
<lb/>for your great kindness in attending to our <hi rend="underline">orders</hi> you 
<lb/>think the obligation all on your side. As I am requested to 
<lb/>tell you your mistakes you must put this down as N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> first 
<lb/>the obligation is certainly all on our side. N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> consists 
<lb/>in having put yourselves to trouble about the pistol &amp; N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
<lb/>consists in having put your letters &amp; I suppose those of the children 
<lb/>into the box &amp; not into the post office. I cured a Griqua of 
<lb/>a very troublesome complaint -  He appeared very grateful &amp; 
<lb/>took charge of my <del type="strikethrough">horse</del><add place="above">mare</add>. One given by <persName>Capt<hi rend="sup">n</hi> Steele</persName> during the 
<lb/>sick season. A token of gratitude he rode <add place="above">it</add> till its back was so 
<lb/>much ulcerated I never got any more good out of it. I lately 
<lb/>sent for the two foals which belonged to it and my grateful 
<lb/>patient will not deliver them up even though I offer to pay 
<lb/>him for his trouble. I think you will put me down as 
<lb/>brother to this gentleman as N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 4<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> for my impudence. We 
<lb/>had a hearty laugh over this Griqua's gratitude and as it elicited 
<lb/>another from <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName> I shall give it you with the expression of my 
<lb/>conviction that these sort of things seem necessary to the present 
<lb/>order of things. If there were no ungrateful persons we should not 
<lb/>know the value of gratitude. If there were no false friends we 
<lb/>should not feel the value of true ones - even nonsense as you will 
<lb/>call this seems necessary to make us feel the value of sense 
<lb/>just in the same way that we never feel the value of water 
<lb/>till we travel in <placeName>Africa</placeName>. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.</persName> was once fortnightly invited 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000633_0002"/><!--pb/@n='02'-->
<lb/>to <placeName>Griqua Town</placeName> - the people were in expectation of being attacked by parties 
<lb/>of <unclear cert="low">banditti</unclear> which infested the country at that time. He went and assisted 
<lb/>them by his counsel and as they had no ammunition gave them all his own 
<lb/>stock viz 400 ball cartridges. For this they expressed unbounded gratitude<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>When his people were bringing his cattle to the yoke some of them trode on the 
<lb/>corner of a garden but ate nothing of the produce - the Griquas in 
<lb/>counsel assembled sentence <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M</persName> to pay a fine of 16 dollars.<persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.</persName>
<lb/>wished him not to pay it but as he says to this day it was such a funny 
<lb/>instance of the most intense ingratitude - he could not spoil the story 
<lb/>by refusing<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>We have not yet <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> a box which you mentioned as having 
<lb/>sent for our own use, some time previous to a <del type="strikethrough">large</del> bale containing 
<lb/>patch work shawls, thread, calico,  and other things equally acceptable 
<lb/>for the shirts I thank you most sincerely &amp; believe <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs </hi>L</persName> has done the 
<lb/>same for the whole. I did not speak about the box in the my last 
<lb/>because I had the hope that it might reach us ere we left this but 
<lb/>it having been despatched at some period previous to that of the parcel 
<lb/>we begin to fear it may be lost. If it comes to hand we shall 
<w>ack-<lb break="no"/>knowledge</w> it immediately. We feel sorry for its loss, but must 
<lb/>try to feel resigned to many things very disagreeable to flesh &amp; blood - 
<lb/>If the pistol comes to hand it will be very useful. A gun is heavy 
<lb/>yet it must always be borne about wherever one goes. Lately 
<lb/>or either when returning from our last journey to the Eastward 
<lb/>I retired a little down a deep gully by the banks of the <placeName>Marikoe</placeName> - there 
<lb/>is no privacy in a waggon - well I was standing leaning on my 
<lb/>gun when long past went a pallah about three yards in from 
<lb/>and presently a wild dog a large spotted wild looking thing in hot 
<lb/>pursuit. It however started when it came to the spot on which 
<lb/>I stood &amp; leaped backwards &amp; forwards as if uncertain whether to bite 
<lb/>or not yet uttering a sort of howl as much to say its intentions 
<lb/>were not over pacific - my gun missed fire &amp; I confess I felt 
<lb/>fear enough to produce trepedation which caused me to miss 
<lb/>when the gun did go off. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he people soon scared it off. A few 
<lb/>days previous to this event I saw some <choice><sic>haartebeests</sic><corr>hartebeests</corr></choice> in the evening 
<lb/>and ran a little way from the waggon in order to have a steak 
<lb/>out of them but they went in a direction opposite to that of the 
<lb/>waggon so I turned &amp; was following on the waggon trail or tract 
<lb/>when happening to look behind a tree there I saw an immense lion 
<lb/>with his attention taken up looking after the waggon which had 
<lb/>probably awakened him out of a dream. I could have shot him 
<lb/>with great ease but preferred slipping away out of sight among 
<lb/>the trees and then at double quick march made for the waggon 
<lb/>the insecurity induced by perpetual occurances such as these 
<lb/>makes one feel anxious for pistols or a pistol about the person 
<lb/>always. Your kindness will not be unprofitable. Nor is it 
<w>un-<lb break="no"/>appreciated</w> - I told you in my last that I was ashamed that you 
<lb/>had got the little things sent by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Greig.</persName> I did not believe he would 
<lb/>ever deliver them and therefore picked up a few things of no 
<lb/>value in order to get off when he proferred his services to 
<lb/>take them - the hair I cut off <persName>Machose's</persName> head a long time ago 
<lb/>for you - she was then the wife of <persName>Bube.</persName> A very kind woman 
<lb/>and now wife of <persName>Khase</persName> - the larger curls are from the head 
<lb/>of another wife of <persName>Bube</persName> whose name I forget<reg>.</reg></p>

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000633_0003"/><!--pb/@n='03'-->
<lb/><p rend="no-indent"><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey were intended as specimens of Bechuana hair. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he small bag has 
<lb/>if I remember rightly medicine in it these are worn round the neck as 
<lb/>charms and <del type="strikethrough">that particular one</del> sent was thrown into a <add place="above">believers</add> woman's house 
<lb/>in order to bewitch her. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he little box is what was worn in a slit in the 
<lb/>ear of one of <persName>Mosilikatze's</persName> warriors<reg>.</reg> It is a snuff box. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he larger one was 
<lb/>worn on the arm of a native of the Bamangwato - use the same - What 
<lb/>you call a piecer is a Sitchuana needle. All their sewing is done by these - a hole is made 
<lb/>and then the thread of split tendon inserted in the same way as shoemakers do with their 
<lb/>awls. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he carved bones are the <term type="tribe">Bechuana</term> dice used in divinations - if you go 
<lb/>to hunt one sits down &amp; throws these on the ground &amp; from the position they 
<lb/>assume tells whether any game will be killed. If I had known he would 
<lb/>have delivered them I should certainly sent some things worth going so far<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I have several curiosities at <placeName>Choumane</placeName> which have been preserved 
<lb/>for some years. For <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> P.</persName> we recently sent a box containing bulbs 
<lb/>seed &amp; karrosses to <placeName>Glasgow</placeName>. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName> got it forwarded for us. We 
<lb/>knew of <persName>John Moffat</persName> going home but in an unaccountable 
<lb/>manner forgot to bring your articles. I have been so often disappointed 
<lb/>&amp; have so often disappointed you I shall say nothing now, but you 
<lb/>will hear from him if he arrives<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>We were much pleased by the visit last year of <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Oswell</persName> an Indian gentleman. He 
<lb/>visited us in the year preceding the company with a Scotch gentleman called <persName>Murray</persName>
<lb/>the latter visited the Mission house &amp; gave a missionary with 
<lb/>whom I was connected the character of a "an ill natured brute". <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hat missionary 
<lb/>had said many things hard &amp; bitter against us to him. I never uttered a sentence 
<lb/>against him. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hat was all the gain he reaped for abusing me to a stranger<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>M.</persName> said so many kind things about me at the mission House I should 
<lb/>be an egotist if I repeated them. But here I am again to scold you<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Why you wish me to be egotistical - you wish me to tell you more 
<lb/>about myself. Whoever heard the like. &amp; <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L</persName> and <persName>Robert</persName> too. - the 
<lb/>latter is growing very finely since we came here - but I am sure if you 
<lb/>heard some of the squalls he makes during the night you would 
<lb/>be ready to apply the rod to his tail instead of writing about him<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Both <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L</persName> &amp; self are well - We were very lean when we came but our visit 
<lb/>has improved our bodily state<reg>.</reg><persName>Robert</persName> was a skeleton but is now plump 
<lb/>trying to walk &amp; talk. </p>
<lb/><p>I have forgot whether you ever mentioned that <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wright</persName> had <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> my 
<lb/>letters. Please thank her sincerely for her kindness. It will be many months 
<lb/>before we <choice><sic>recieve</sic><corr>receive</corr></choice> the articles you have sent. If you instructed the clerk 
<lb/>at the Mission House to send by way of <placeName>Algoa Bay</placeName>. Care of <persName>Joshua Kemp Esq</persName>
<lb/>the parcels might come sooner &amp; be cheaper than by way of the <placeName>Cape</placeName><reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I am sorry to hear of the continued attacks of indisposition to which you are 
<lb/>subject. Colds may frequently be avoided by regulating the amount of 
<lb/>fluid taken into the system. If you intend to expose yourself to cold at any 
<lb/>time you ought to refrain as much as possible from drinking. If you 
<lb/>were expecting to go out in the evening one cup of tea instead of two would 
<lb/>lessen the probability of your <choice><sic>recieving</sic><corr>receiving</corr></choice> a check to the perspiration. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he 
<lb/>pores of the body would not have so much fluid to dispose of - A 
<lb/>very good cough mixture may be made by purchasing at <placeName>Apothecaries Hall</placeName>
<lb/><placeName>London</placeName> or anywhere where you can get pure medicines - Carbonate 
<lb/>of Potash, Liquorice Root, Gentian Root - syrup of poppies &amp; 
<lb/>almond emulsion of each an ounce - Boil a quarter of the drugs &amp; 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000633_0004"/><!--pb/@n='04'-->
<lb/>roots an hour in as much water as will fill a wine bottle <del type="strikethrough">nearly</del> - add 
<lb/>when cold a teaspoonful of the Potash or <unclear cert="low">wafer</unclear> 1/4 of the ounce of all the 
<lb/>other ingredients <add place="above">shake this bottle</add> &amp; take a tablespoonful occasionally - you may sweeten 
<lb/>it if you like sweets with honey &amp; you cannot poison yourself 
<lb/>with the ingredients - it is difficult to prescribe for persons at a distance 
<lb/>the above is good where there is no inflammation. </p>
<lb/><p>We have heard from  <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>Drummond</persName> lately and one or two or the 
<lb/>number. Reporters reached us too. The scientific portion made me blush 
<lb/>I mean that part and tho probable information of the Islands. Only think of men 
<lb/>believing that a flood or a <unclear>transcending</unclear> of them could trail down 
<lb/>Capes after them formed of solid everlasting granite. <placeName>Table mountain</placeName>
<lb/>for instance is an immense mass of <add place="above">old</add>granite with <unclear cert="low">never</unclear> sort shot up 
<lb/>through many fizzures &amp; at such a <unclear cert="low">temperature</unclear> that it transformed the 
<lb/>sandstone <unclear cert="low">at the</unclear> top into schist and <unclear cert="low">get out south senworthies I think</unclear>
<lb/>all this were boulder or pebble rolled down from <placeName>Timbuctoo</placeName> the 
<lb/><unclear cert="low">fields of Lilias Mills</unclear> are worth a chart load of the scientific dreams<reg>.</reg></p>

<addSpan spanTo="#p.04-01" place="marginright"><!--addSpan/@place='right hand margin of p.04-01'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">extremely <unclear cert="low">handy</unclear> (?) had they fitted her - they were too small &amp; are now 
<lb/>worn by her sister. We have been favoured with a little 
<lb/><space extent="2" unit="words"/>daughter. Mother &amp; child both doing well. No word of the box so 
<lb/><space extent="2" unit="words"/>we conclude it lost. We thank you for it although it has not come<reg>.</reg></p><anchor xml:id="p.04-01"/>

<lb/><p><address><addrLine><del type="strikethrough">Care of <persName>D<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Philips</persName> <placeName>Cape Town</placeName></del></addrLine>
<addrLine><persName>Benjamin Pyne Esq<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi></persName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>North Weald</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>Ongar</placeName>. <placeName>Essex</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine>S.B. </addrLine></address></p>
<lb/>

<lb/><p>All here are pretty well - <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hamilton</persName> very frail. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName> busy 
<lb/>translating <unclear cert="low">karah</unclear>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>here is not much done at present among 
<lb/>the  people - the <unclear cert="low">contensions</unclear> for some time back have been <unclear cert="low">dead</unclear>. 
<lb/>We mourn over the apparent deadness. May God serve his own 
<lb/>work. A sister of <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L</persName>is to be married this month in London - I do 
<lb/>not know her intended. He has a good character but his letters seem 
<lb/>to indicate a sort of peevishness such as prevents me wishing you 
<lb/>to make his acquaintance. If <persName>Robert Moffat</persName> comes your way 
<lb/>he will visit you we have a better opinion of him - <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L</persName>desires me 
<lb/><space extent="1" unit="words"/>to say that a pair of stays (alias pincers) you kindly sent would have </p>

			
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>