<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000705">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Margaret Sewell</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Margaret Sewell, 9 September 1850</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2007-09-04</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000705</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">National Library of Scotland; MS. 20312, ff. 12-13</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0235</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Sewell, Margaret</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1850-09-09">9 September 1850</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kolobeng</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2007-09-04</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Intial Transcription by Caroline Overy
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2008-02-02</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>Proof by Chris Lawrence
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000705_0001"/><!--pb/@n='12r'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Kolobeng</placeName> 9<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> September 1850</p>
<lb/><p>My very Dear Friend</p>
<lb/><p>I wrote you about six months ago and having been 
<lb/>absent from home for more than four months lately I could not of course 
<lb/>address you again. But you have often been in my remembrance. I 
<lb/>have been reminded again and again of your kindness when reading 
<lb/>the Banners you kindiy sent us. And more than once I have wished 
<lb/>I had had an opportunity of thanking you for them<reg>.</reg> In this however 
<lb/>there was a good deal of selfishness for I feared that as you had 
<lb/><choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> no thanks you might, disgusted with my ingratitude, have 
<lb/>sent them somewhere else. I did not advert to them particularly in 
<lb/>the letter I sent acknowledging the receipt of the parcel in which they 
<lb/>were. And the reason was I did not know what a treat they contained<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Now however I thank you most sincerely and beg a continuance of the 
<lb/>same favours. <persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Campbell</persName> is really a fine fellow I hope he may 
<lb/>long be spared to the world. I have had no letter or parcel from you 
<lb/>lately. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his is a disappointment for I expected one at least when 
<lb/>I returned from the Lake. From the <persName>Pynes</persName> I am sorry to hear of 
<lb/>your indisposotion but hope you are again restored to health. Be 
<lb/>sure &amp; let me know if your illness has in any way impaired your 
<lb/>bodily vigour. I love to remember you skipping out of the parlour 
<lb/>or springing up to ring the bell as nimbly as ever did the little 
<lb/>Frenchman <persName>Courvoisier</persName><reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>Have only recently returned from revisiting the Lake. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he reason
<lb/>we have for bending our thoughts in that direction is the <term type="tribe">Bechuana</term>
<lb/>mission having been shut up into a kind of cul de sac. On the East 
<lb/>by the Boers they have prohibited any missionary instructing the 
<lb/>natives<reg>.</reg> A French missionary <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fredoux</persName> of <placeName>Motito</placeName> lately attempted 
<lb/>to follow on my trail to visit the <term type="tribe">Bamapela</term> but was forcibly 
<lb/>driven back by a party of armed boers, forbidding us to speak to the Gentiles 
<lb/>that they may be saved - they truly know not what they do. By far 
<lb/>the largest portion of the <term type="tribe">Bechuana</term> people live in that direction<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>On the West we have a country without water &amp; hitherto deemed impassable 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000705_0002"/><!--pb/@n='12v'-->
<lb/>and as the desert extends round to the North East we must either have confined 
<lb/>our attention entirely to a few tribes or bully the Boers. I am sincerely thankful 
<lb/>that God has given us an entrance into the far North for when the <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>
<lb/>see that we cannot go to others they become extremely careless about the 
<lb/>benefits we try to impart. It is rather a favour for them to attend to our 
<lb/>instructions - not <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">a favour</add> for us to impart them without fee or reward. And O 
<lb/>they are as a people slow of heart to believe - patience long continued 
<lb/>patience must be <choice><sic>practiced</sic><corr>practised</corr></choice> here. Hope deferred has been a frequent visitor 
<lb/>to me since I saw you. I cannot work away at other things if I have 
<lb/>not real missionary work too. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his set me away again to the Lake 
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L</persName> and children &amp; <persName>Sechele</persName> accompanied me. When we got to the <placeName>Ngami</placeName>
<lb/>we found the <term type="ailment">fever</term> raging. A <term type="ailment">fever</term> I suppose not very unlike that 
<lb/>which cut up the Niger expedition. It seems destined by Providence 
<lb/>to keep the Intertropical Africa for the black races alone. No boer could 
<lb/>live in there. It cuts off stout people first and they are generally very much 
<lb/>so. A party of Englishmen went in and a young artist &amp; a Hottentot servant 
<lb/>died of <term type="ailment">fever</term>. A trader too called <persName>Wilson</persName> who resides at <placeName>Kolobeng</placeName> was brought 
<lb/>to a stand still by all his people &amp; himself being siezed by it. He got a 
<lb/>terrible squeeze from the king of terrors and lay for several days more 
<lb/>dead than alive. Our children played in the Lake as if they had 
<lb/>been used to water from infancy or as ducklings do. <choice><reg>B</reg><orig>b</orig></choice>ut two 
<lb/>of them had <term type="ailment">fever</term> and were nearly cut off. God was gracious to us 
<lb/>our people had it too - and I had to become driver in order to get 
<lb/>away from the focus of malaria. We spent two very pleasant 
<lb/><choice><reg>S</reg><orig>s</orig></choice>undays with the <term type="tribe">Botasana</term> But the <term type="ailment">fever</term> &amp; <term type="ailment">fly</term><!--ailment or vector--> prevented our going 
<lb/>on to <persName>Sebitoane</persName>. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L</persName> would have preferred waiting for me <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="blotting"/>
<lb/>at the <term type="tribe">Botasana</term> while I went forward on ox back but I could not 
<lb/>leave after the <term type="ailment">fever</term> began. We must find a salubrious settlement 
<lb/>in some of the regions beyond and I have some hopes that we will 
<lb/>find such for the <placeName>Teoge</placeName> which falls into the lake at the North West 
<lb/>runs very rapidly and probably descends from an elevated region<reg>.</reg> 
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he <placeName>Ngami</placeName> is low as compared with <placeName>Kolobeng</placeName>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hen we must 
<lb/>have a passage to the sea on either the East or west coast<reg>.</reg> You 
<lb/>will understand this necessity when I tell you that here we are 
<lb/>270 miles North East of <placeName>Kuruman</placeName> and the lake is 600 miles beyond 
<lb/>this. If spared to effect this we should then probably be allowed to 
<lb/>introduce the gospel into a large &amp; populous region of at least equal 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000705_0003"/><!--pb/@n='13r'-->
<lb/>importance to the entire <term type="tribe">Bechuana</term> mission. I hope to go in again next 
<lb/>year and will make perhaps a twelve months sojourn there<reg>.</reg> Don<reg>'</reg>t forget 
<lb/>me in your prayers. I shall try &amp; write you again but that may be 
<lb/>my last. It is well to be always prepared. May He remember us both who 
<lb/>said I will never leave thee nor forsake thee. </p>
<lb/><p>We were favoured with a little <persName>daughter</persName> seven days after reaching 
<lb/>home. We have a pair of each now. 2 boys &amp; a like number of girls. 
<lb/>Behold the fruits of matrimony which you always advocated<reg>.</reg><persName>Robert</persName>
<lb/>is now speaking to me with all his might and turning round my 
<lb/>face occasionally when he sees my thoughts are quite away in 
<lb/><placeName>57 Aldersgate St</placeName>. How is <persName>Charles</persName>? I could not find time to write 
<lb/>him as I intended but you must be kind enough to give him 
<lb/>my kind remembrance and good wishes. And your son &amp; daughter 
<lb/>in India how do they get on. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey have population enough without 
<lb/>travelling far. China seems to attract a great deal of attention now<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Robert Moffat</persName> lately visited his parents at <placeName>Kuruman</placeName> - he is a 
<lb/>Gov<hi rend="sup">t</hi> land surveyor at between £300 &amp; 400 per annum. Seemed <unclear cert="low">enough</unclear>
<lb/>to benefit Africa but the mode of life he has adopted does not seem 
<lb/>well calculated for that end. What a poor set you are in England<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Can<reg>'</reg>t pay your secretaries decently. And then so suspicious of the <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/>
<lb/>You don<reg>'</reg>t seem to know that the Directors of our society give smaller 
<lb/>salaries than those of any other society<reg>.</reg> 38 Wesleyan missionaries 
<lb/>cost about £3000 more per annum than an equal number 
<lb/>of ours do. Then such a scurvy meeting as that at Leeds passing 
<lb/>resolutions such as 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. Directors the mission churches must be free 
<lb/>independent self governed &amp;c. 2. Why do you allow free independent 
<lb/>churches to do as they like in reference to Gov<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grants for 
<lb/>education. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he directors poor fellows must proclaim freedom 
<lb/>&amp; coercion with the same breath. I am a voluntary but if 
<lb/>I proclaimed a certain church independent &amp; self governed I would 
<lb/>never think of grumbling because that church acted out its <choice><sic><w>indep-<lb break="no"/>endance</w></sic><corr>independence</corr></choice> both in reference to Gov<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grants &amp; everything else. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hen pretending 
<lb/>they were only sifting affairs after "a lapse of 50 years" though only two 
<lb/>years had elapsed since there was quite enough of sifting and poking<reg>.</reg> 
<lb/>What would they have? Remove our suspicions and then we shall 
<lb/>contribute Won<reg>'</reg>t we. Ough. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey parted with a stroking of each other backs 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000705_0004"/><!--pb/@n='13v'-->
<lb/>and puffing about the "excellent spirit which pervaded this meeting" Bah<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>Wishing you every blessing - many thanks for the Banners and a wish 
<lb/>that you may send more. Believe me Ever yours</p>
<lb/><p rend="center">very affectionately</p>
<lb/><p>David Livingston</p>
<ab type="envelope">
<address>
<addrLine><del type="strikethrough">Care of <persName>Rev. W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Thompson</persName><placeName> <hi rend="underline">Cape Town</hi></placeName></del></addrLine>
<addrLine><space extent="3" unit="words"/><persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">rs</hi> Sewell</persName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>57 Aldersgate St</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine>London</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>