<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000515">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Margaret Sewell</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Margaret Sewell, 14 July 1842</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2007-08-15</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000515</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">National Library of Scotland; MS. 656, ff. 97-98</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0060</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Sewell, Margaret</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1842-07-14">14 July 1842</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kuruman alias Lattakoo</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2007-08-15</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>Intial Transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2008-03-03</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>Proof by Chris Lawrence
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000515_0001"/><!--pb/@n='97r'--> 
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Kuruman</placeName> alias<placeName> Lattakoo</placeName> 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> July 
<lb/>1842 </p>
<lb/><p>My very dear friend </p>
<lb/><p>I assure you I am very sorry to hear 
<lb/>by your (4) letters that you have not got any of those which 
<lb/>I have from time <add place="above">to time</add> written you. I am afraid you have 
<lb/>thought me unmindful of all that <add place="above">you</add> have &amp; are kindly 
<lb/>doing for me. But I hope you recollected what I asked 
<lb/>of you when parting, "that if at any time you did not 
<lb/><choice><sic>receive</sic><corr>recieve</corr></choice> letters you might be sure some good reason 
<lb/>prevented me." <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his however is what I did not 
<lb/>calculate upon, I only thought of being myself prevented 
<lb/>from writing &amp; not of defects in the transmission<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>I write again although I have nothing new to add 
<lb/>more than I put in the one I wrote in the interior &amp; 
<lb/>sent about a month ago. I have a request to make however 
<lb/>and I am sure that if you can with propriety you will gladly oblige 
<lb/>me. I have an excellent friend here <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edwards</persName>, a most worthy 
<lb/>man and more useful among the <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> than any one I 
<lb/>know. He however is not ordained, came out as an <unclear cert="low">artizan</unclear>
<lb/>&amp; schoolmaster, is an excellent workman &amp; in connexion with 
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName> used to do all the printing. Since <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat's</persName> return 
<lb/>to <placeName>England</placeName><choice><reg>h</reg><orig>H</orig></choice>e has been the sole pastor of the church &amp; during these 
<lb/>years more members have been added to the church than at any 
<lb/>former period, and according to the testimony of <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hamilton</persName>
<lb/>its affairs have been conducted by him with very great 
<lb/>wisdom &amp; prudence, now after having acted the part of a full 
<lb/>missionary for 4 years &amp; always as such in either one capacity 
<lb/>or another it seems attempts have been made by some here 
<lb/>&amp; others at home to deprive him of the privilege of being anything 
<lb/>more than a mere printer under <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName>, this mission 
<lb/>is to be made a completely clannish affair (perhaps one of the 
<lb/>reasons <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> M</persName> wanted to get me noosed down at <placeName>Ashton</placeName>)<reg>.</reg> Now 
<lb/>I am sure the Directors are not aware of the value of <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edwards</persName>

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000515_0002"/><!--pb/@n='97v'--> 
<lb/>as a missionary as they would not sanction his degradation <del type="strikethrough">if</del>
<lb/><del type="strikethrough">Mr</del> All I beg of you is if you think it consistent with propriety 
<lb/><del type="strikethrough">to</del> if at any time in conversation with <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Tidman</persName>, to drop a 
<lb/>remark expressive of my opinion of <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> E</persName>. as a fellow labour whom 
<lb/>I much esteem &amp; admire on account of his devotedness &amp;c. 
<lb/>Of course it would not do to introduce the subject purposely for 
<lb/>that object so that he could see what you were driving at<reg>.</reg> But 
<lb/>it might happen that the subject of this mission might be the 
<lb/>theme of your conversation &amp; then it could be done<reg>.</reg> But 
<lb/>you know better than I do about what is proper in the 
<lb/>case. I write with freedom &amp; I ask the favour because 
<lb/>it is not for myself and the only way I can see in 
<lb/>which I can help a truly efficient minister of the gospel<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I think it may be of importance to his cause that <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
<lb/>Tidman</persName> be acquainted with the opinions of one who has 
<lb/>been in the house &amp; witnessed both public &amp; private conduct 
<lb/>of the individual in question for nearly a twelve month<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Ho I say, you there sitting at your desk &amp; reading this 
<lb/>scrawl, you must pack up immediately, &amp; come over here 
<lb/>for I am going to marry you. It's no joke for <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
<lb/>Ross</persName> has told the sisterhood here that I am in love 
<lb/>with a young widow in <placeName>London</placeName> called <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Sewell</persName>, so 
<lb/>you are done for, for I say it is true, and I am sure 
<lb/>you can<reg>'</reg>t object. Remember your own text, "It is not 
<lb/>good for man to be alone " there's scripture for 
<lb/>it. Come along then, no delay. N.B. Don<reg>'</reg>t forget 
<lb/>baby linens please But I forgot we can tear up my old 
<lb/>shirts for that purpose, then bring new shirts for me &amp;c &amp;c<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Don't be the death of me by refusing - </p>
<lb/><p>I have written <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> MacLehose </persName><unclear cert="low">oftener I believe</unclear> them 
<lb/>than he will thank me for them, I was in the key for 
<lb/><del type="strikethrough">with</del> writing one day &amp; I gave him a regular sermon 
<lb/>I am waiting with some anxiety to hear from him But 
<lb/>I fear I won<reg>'</reg>t be here to <choice><sic>recieve</sic><corr>receive</corr></choice> any thing for some 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000515_0003"/><!--pb/@n='98r'--> 
<lb/>months to come as I am again about to depart for the interior<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I am very much obliged to you for visiting my former home 
<lb/>I am now a vagabond on the face of the earth &amp; any where has 
<lb/>to be a home for me<reg>.</reg> But though it is only a bush at my head &amp; 
<lb/>a fire at my feet it is no sacrifice to me and that it is not 
<lb/>is mainly owing to my having been cradled in a rough bed since 
<lb/>infancy. I look back with both pleasure and gratitude to my 
<lb/>early days and to no portion of them do I recur with fonder 
<lb/>recollections than that in which those parents whom you saw 
<lb/>witnessed me struggling almost to desperation in order to amass 
<lb/>as much as kept soul &amp; body together while attending classes 
<lb/>in <placeName>Glasgow</placeName>. By toiling at manual labour through the day &amp; 
<lb/>at mental during a large portion of the night, I at length 
<w>succeed-<lb break="no"/>ed</w> in getting two sessions at the college. A happy time it was  &amp; if 
<lb/>I could begin life again, I should like to go through the very same 
<lb/>struggles. Indeed when through the advice of friends I applied &amp; 
<lb/>told I was accepted by the L.M.S. I felt somewhat sorry that 
<lb/>I could not continue in my career of independence and 
<lb/>hard <unclear cert="medium">face</unclear> without resisting what seemed to be the voice 
<lb/>of Providence. I wish you had seen my sisters you <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/>
<lb/>have had a better opinion of them than you have of <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/>me<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>I have got a letter from our excellent friend <persName>Watt</persName><reg>.</reg>
<lb/>He tells me of the love affair of <persName>Ingram</persName>. Better surely be a 
<lb/>batchelor than go mad like him. I am happy to hear of 
<lb/>the restoration of the health of <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Mather</persName>, I imagined she was 
<lb/>at home with you &amp; was fearing your heart would have 
<lb/>been filled with sorrow at receiving back a shattered 
<w>remn-<lb break="no"/>ant</w> of the daughter you sent away. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hanks to the Author 
<lb/>of all good for his great compassion &amp; kindness<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>I got a letter from <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Paterson</persName> &amp; one from the 
<lb/>excellent man we became acquainted with in <placeName>Rio Janeiro</placeName>
<lb/>the Bible is beginning to cause a stir there, &amp; during the week 
<lb/>my friend wrote me a furious article had appeared in the 
<lb/>public prints against all protestants in general &amp; him 
<lb/>in particular. It was very abusive &amp; stated that the writer 
<lb/>who by the bye is an archbishop is astonished to see with 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000515_0004"/><!--pb/@n='98v'--> 
<lb/>what avidity all classes of the people whose ignorance is notorious 
<lb/>&amp; the priests who are if possible still more ignorant receive the 
<lb/>bible from this missionary. My friend remarks neither priests 
<lb/>nor people will thank him for the compliment. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he most 
<w>resp-<lb break="no"/>ectable</w> people in <placeName>Rio</placeName> receive the word of God thankfully. I hope 
<lb/>the time will soon come when the Brazilians will no longer 
<lb/>be held in the bonds of superstition, I told <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Mac</persName>. this 
<lb/>friend would gladly furnish papers for his magazine if he 
<lb/><anchor xml:id="envelopePosition" type="positionMarker"/>should only state to him his willingness to receive them 
<lb/>but I don<reg>'</reg>t know whether our dear <placeName>Glasgow</placeName> friend has 
<lb/>received the letter which contained the information, <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> I 
<lb/>Spaulding</persName> tells me he has not yet heard from <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M</persName>. 
<lb/>As this is a love letter you must if you please burn it 
<w>imm-<lb break="no"/>diately.</w> Your letters are most acceptable<reg>.</reg> Please write soon 
<lb/>to your affectionate <persName>D. Livingston</persName></p>
<ab type="envelope">
<address>
<addrLine><del type="strikethrough">Care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Phillip</persName><placeName> <hi rend="underline">Cape Town</hi></placeName></del></addrLine>
<addrLine><persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Sewell</persName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>57 Aldersgate Street</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>London</placeName></addrLine>
</address>
</ab>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>