<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription-alt.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2017-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000496">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to James Maclehose</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to James Maclehose, 8 December 1841</title>
				<author>Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
                <authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
                <publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
                <pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2017</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000496</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">National Library of Scotland; MS. 656, 76-79</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0041</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Maclehose, James, 1811-1885</persName>; </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1841-12-08">8 December 1841</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kuruman</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2008-10-09</date>
				<name>Caroline Overy</name>Initial Transcription by Caroline Overy
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2017-05-08</date>
				<name>Kate Simpson</name>Proofread by Kate Simpson
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2017-06-14</date>
				<name>Adrian S. Wisnicki</name>Formatting Review by Adrian S. Wisnicki
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000496_0001"/><!--pb/@n='76r'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><space unit="chars" extent="38"/><placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> <date when="1841-12-08">8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> <choice><abbr>Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi></abbr><expan>December</expan></choice> 1841</date>  <add place="marginright" hand="#hand01"><hi rend="gray">76</hi></add></p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">My Dear Friend</p>
<lb/><p><space extent="16" unit="chars"/>Having lately travelled in company with <persName><choice><abbr>Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi></abbr><expan>Reverend</expan></choice> R. Edwards</persName> a distance 
<lb/><space extent="3" unit="chars"/>between <measure>6 &amp; 700 miles</measure> in the <placeName><region>interior</region></placeName> of this country and visited many tribes 
<lb/><space extent="3" unit="chars"/><term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> some never before seen by missionaries, I lose no time in 
<lb/>transmitting you some information respecting the state &amp; prospects of the 
<lb/>cause of Christ among them -</p>
<lb/><p>The <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> you are already aware are divided into a great many 
<lb/>distinct tribes or clans and they extend a great way into the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName></p>
<lb/><p>Many of them have not yet been visited by any <orgName>European</orgName>, the language 
<lb/>of the whole is however essentially the same varying less in proportion 
<lb/>to the extent of country they occupy than do the different dialects in 
<lb/>the provinces of our own empire - The feudal system of <w>govern-
<lb break="no"/>ment</w> <unclear cert="high">obtains </unclear> amongst them in all its glory and in many respects 
<lb/>they resemble the <orgName>Ancient Highlanders</orgName> - Each clan is governed by its 
<lb/>own <term type="occupation">chieftain</term> who comes into office by right of birth and although 
<lb/>hereditary succession produces just the same effects here as in more 
<lb/>civilized countries, each <term type="occupation">chief</term> looks upon himself as a wiser &amp; 
<lb/>better man than <del>all</del><add place="over-text">any</add> <add place="above">of</add> his tribe and superior to all his contemporaries</p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">He has the power of life &amp; death - the administration of the laws and 
<lb/>many prerequisites of office - Although he has <term type="occupation">councellors</term> who in 
<lb/>public assemblies are allowed by law to use the greatest freedom 
<lb/>of speech towards him, yet all the people are in a state of abject 
<lb/>subjection to his authority - <space extent="4" unit="chars"/> The different tribes possess with 
<lb/>respect to each other feelings similar to those of the <term type="occupation">chiefs</term> to their 
<lb/>fellows - One tribe calls itself a race of kings &amp; superior to all 
<lb/>others while a neighbouring tribe indulges the same lofty pretensions 
<lb/>to superior dignity in the scale of humanity - This clannish pride 
<lb/>has fortunately vanished considerably during the last 10 years or so 
<lb/>but previous to that period it stood at such a height. It was 
<lb/>hardly possible for <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> to endure it - No foreigners were 
<lb/>could be equal in  point of wisdom &amp;c. to the royal <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> - <w>conseq<supplied>-</supplied>
<lb break="no"/>uently</w> to deal with them a large stack of patience &amp; self denial 
<lb/>were <del type="strikethrough">requisite</del> <add place="above">needed</add> and these seem to have been possessed in the requisite 
<lb/>degree by <persName>Read</persName>, <persName>Hamilton</persName> &amp;c. Those devoted pione<add place="above">e</add>rs of this Mission 
<lb/>who have now grown <del type="cancelled">old</del><add place="above">grey</add> in their work of faith &amp; labour of love 
<lb/><unclear cert="high">At present</unclear> only the remnants of this haughty spirit prevail
<lb/>Very few consider themselves equal to foreigners and we can 
<lb/>now travel through the whole country without fear of molestation</p>
<lb/><p>The question now becomes one of interest, to what is this <w>favor<supplied>-</supplied>
<lb break="no"/>-able</w> change to be attributed? And to us whose prejudices are on the 
<lb/>side of the gospel it would be pleasant could we place it to the 
<lb/>account of the operation of that mighty agent But when we 
<lb/>take a retrospective glance at the events which have transpired 
<lb/>in this country within the last 20 years and examine the state 
<lb/>&amp; feelings of those who have been most in contact with <w>Missi<supplied>-</supplied>
<lb break="no"/>-on's</w> and those also who on account of their distance know nothing 
<lb/>at all about these things We shall be compelled to give the credit 
<lb/>of the change to an instrumentality far less to be admired
<lb/>But while we cannot feel any complacency in the instrument -</p>
<lb/><cb rend="vertical"/>
<lb/><addSpan spanTo="#p.76r" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left margins of fols 76r, 76v, 78r, 78v'--></addSpan><p rend="no-indent">and it has only been by long argument &amp; bringing forward the facts of the case in as gentle a way as I could that 
<lb/>that I have succeeded in making them feel that our best mode is just to follow in the same tract as that in which the 
<lb/>others have been so eminently blessed - they are now both wishing they had it in their power to plant</p>

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000496_0002"/><!--pb/@n='76v'-->
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">or the operations We cannot help adoring the superintending Providence of 
<lb/>Him who has in all ages &amp; countries carried on his purpose right through 
<lb/>heart of human wickedness &amp; canstantly brought good out of evil</p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">And since in this country a great good has followed the horrid scourge 
<lb/>of war <del type="strikethrough">they</del><add place="above">are</add> we <del type="strikethrough">not be</del> justified in turning our eyes with intense interest 
<lb/>to another large portion of the world, long shut against the gospel, where 
<lb/>war is now actually in progress, and confidently expect that however 
<lb/>unjustifiable the pretext for that may be, it will eventually turn out 
<lb/>for the advancement of that <del type="cancelled">place</del><add place="above">kingdom</add>  which consists of righteousness &amp; 
<lb/>peace. <add place="inline" rend="small"><space extent="7" unit="chars"/>The finder of the <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> rendered them one once nearly as insensible to the 
<lb/><space extent="15" unit="chars"/>gospel as the laws in China now do hurt successive scourges have humbled them <add place="below">greatly</add></add></p>
<lb/><p>At a time when pride &amp; arrogance were rampant amongst the <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>
<lb/>a large swarm of marauders more savage than they came pouring 
<lb/>down <add place="below">˄</add><add place="above">from the interior</add> upon those nearer to the <placeName><region>Colony</region></placeName> - Their cruelties &amp; successes 
<lb/>spread terror though the whole country, one tribe fell before them 
<lb/>after another <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> they were thought invicible by the thousands 
<lb/>of fugitives who flocked towards the South; But a few mounted 
<lb/><orgName>Griquas</orgName> with guns succeeded in <unclear cert="high">routing</unclear> the whole with immense 
<lb/>slaughter of the invaders &amp; scarcely any loss to themselves</p>
<lb/><p>By &amp; Bye came another swarm  more dreadful than the former 
<lb/>under <persName>Moselekatsi</persName>, they spared none except the young men who 
<lb/>were capable of being soldiers - the old men with the women &amp; children 
<lb/>were all cruelly butchered. As in the former case those who <add place="below">˄</add><add place="above">could</add> escape 
<lb/>fled in terror in this direction and <persName>Moselekatsi</persName> following came 
<lb/>with <del type="cancelled">2</del><add place="above">2</add> weeks of <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName>, there, having ventured to capture the 
<lb/>waggons of some <orgName>Boers</orgName> &amp; put some of them to death he aroused 
<lb/>the vengeance of their relatives who although a mere handful in 
<lb/>number <unclear cert="high">routed</unclear> &amp; compelled him to retire far into the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName>. These 
<lb/>successive defeats of powerful marauders have contibuted more towards 
<lb/>producing an impression of the superiority of <orgName>Europeans</orgName> than anything 
<lb/>else - This applies more especially to the tribes who have not been 
<lb/>subjected to the scourge of <orgName>European</orgName> warfare - What the effect is on
<lb/>the minds of the people of <persName>Moselekatsi</persName> I have not had an opportunity 
<lb/>of ascertaining - Most probably they are "chafed in their minds" 
<lb/>and the possibilty of our intercourse with them may for a long 
<lb/>time be retarded</p>
<lb/><p>Those tribes which in the time of danger flocked around the 
<lb/>mission stations have <del type="strikethrough">mostly</del><add place="above">all</add> retired, not so far inland as they 
<lb/>formerly were. The terror of <persName>Moselekatsi</persName>'s name is still <w>every-
<lb break="no"/>where</w> fresh in their minds preventing <unclear cert="medium">the</unclear><del type="strikethrough">return northwards</del>. But 
<lb/>there is one unfortunate feature in the character of all the tribes 
<lb/>who have been within the sphere of missionary operations 
<lb/>they know somewhat of the requirements of the gospel but 
<lb/>they are all decidedly averse to it, those tribes who have 
<lb/>never been near <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> always behaved with more respect 
<lb/>&amp; kindness than those who had. At a point <measure>250 miles</measure> nearly 
<lb/>directly north, the people had never before seen a white face - 
<lb/>There they were all we could expect a savage nation to be, &amp;  
<lb/>forcibly reminded us of those in a similar state in the <placeName><region>South Seas</region></placeName>
<lb/><space extent="2" unit="chars"/>here was no begging, no <unclear cert="high">noisy</unclear> impudence but</p><!-- kate to here -->
<lb/><cb rend="vertical"/>
<!--pb/@n='76v'-->
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">some of our <orgName>native</orgName> <term type="faith">Christians</term> in these newly visited tribes - It is really a great pity that this spirit of rivalry 
<lb/>&amp; opposition sprung up between the two Missions - Fear instead of rejoicing at the spread of the gospel</p>

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000496_0003"/><!--pb/@n='77r'-->
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">After <add place="below">˄</add> <add place="above">having</add> overcome their fears <add place="above">sufficiently</add> <del type="strikethrough">of our first approach, sufficiently</del> they gazed <add place="marginright" hand="#hand01"><hi rend="gray">77</hi></add>
<lb/>in astonishment at everything they saw &amp; then brought presents of <term type="foodstuff">milk</term> &amp;c. 
<lb/>When we went into the town the women peeped past the corners <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice>
<lb/>we approached nearer &amp; when they fled into the houses - the children screamed 
<lb/>in terror - and the very <term type="animal">dogs</term> wanted not to bark but were as <w>precip<supplied>-</supplied>
	<lb break="no"/>-itate</w> in their flight as if they had seen a <term type="animal">lion</term>, (the <term type="occupation">chief</term> of this 
<lb/>place too was the most sensible of this kingly tribe I have seen among<add place="above">st</add> 
<lb/>them - for in general they are regular fools) Another tribe which 
<lb/>received us courteously we found busily employed in the manufacture 
<lb/>of large wooden bowls, each bowl being hollowed out from the 
<lb/>section of a large tree, costs an immense deal of labour - In addition 
<lb/>to this they were smelting iron for knives spears axes &amp;c</p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">The manufacture seemed in its crudest state - Indeed it seems 
<lb/>in their hands to be exactly in that state I suppose <persName>Tubal Cain</persName> 
<lb/>left it - <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he furnace is built of clay, two leathern bags 
<lb/>with clay tubes to enter the furnace, a piece of the bark of a tree 
<lb/>bent upon itself, and a huge stone grasped in both hands 
<lb/>constitute the bellows, tongs, hammer &amp; another stone the anvil 
<lb/>of these antediluvian <del type="cancelled">workers</del><add place="above">artificers</add> in iron, the ore in abundance 
<lb/>they find in the neighbouring mountains - To make up 
<lb/>for their want of knowledge in the manufacture &amp; frequent 
<lb/>accidents in burning the iron to a cinder, they have  
<lb/>many superstitions such as abstinence from connubial 
<lb/>intercourse for several months during which they work
<lb/>the iron &amp;c. &amp;c. There are also manufactures of <del type="cancelled">brass</del> copper &amp;
<lb/>tin amongst them but these have more superstitions still
<lb/>Indeed the further we went towards the north we found 
<lb/>superstition increasing &amp; probably it does increase <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice>
<lb/>we reach the region where idols are worshipped</p>
<lb/><p>All whom we visited far in the <placeName><region>interior</region></placeName> treated us with great 
<lb/>respect &amp; listened attentively to the preaching of the gospel, this <choice><abbr>att<hi rend="sup">n</hi></abbr><expan>attention</expan></choice>
<lb/>of course can be attributed to nothing but the effect of novelty
<lb/>But I am persuaded they are much more likely to receive the 
<lb/>gospel than those who live within <measure>100 or 150 miles</measure> of this 
<lb/>&amp; Who generally now merit the appellation of scorners &amp; refectors of the truth</p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">You may be surprised to hear that this state of matters exists amongst those 
<lb/>who lately lived near mission stations - But what else can be expected 
<lb/>from heathens in their sins only occasionally hearing a detached sermon 
<lb/>or two - <del type="strikethrough">If we</del> Before we can reasonably hope for much success 
<lb/>the truth must be brought to bear repeatedly on the mind of the same 
<lb/>individual - the heathen are in a totally different position from 
<lb/>people at home - there, a single sermon may convert But here 
<lb/>it is hardly possible for the truth to find its way through the thick 
<lb/>darkness which shrouds the mind of the <orgName>natives</orgName> by any means but 
<lb/>a continually pouring it upon them - And after all our chief 
<lb/>hope is in the young, but little comparatively can or has been 
<lb/>done with the old - You must not imagine from the style of 
<lb/>the foregoing remarks that I in the least disparage the labours 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000496_0004"/><!--pb/@n='77v'-->
<lb/>of the devoted bretheren who have long laboured amongst these people <unclear cert="medium">the</unclear> it 
<lb/>has not been from any defect in their preaching that the unfortunate state 
<lb/>of the tribes immediately beyond us has resulted - It has been from the 
<lb/>want of means to carry on more extensive operations - their efforts 
<lb/>for want of more agents have been too much confined to one spot 
<lb/>Occasionally visits have been made to the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName> But for want of 
<lb/>others to supply their places at the station these attempts have been too 
<lb/>desultory in their nature to result in <del type="cancelled">m</del> much good - It would 
<lb/>require many <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> at different points in the country 
<lb/>before the great body of the people can be influenced,  this <unclear cert="medium">defining</unclear>
<lb/>for want of <term type="occupation">labourers</term> still exists and unless the society can send out 
<lb/>some more <term type="occupation">labourers</term> there is only one <add place="below">˄</add><add place="above">other</add> hope left. I mean 
<lb/>the employment of <term type="occupation"><orgName>native</orgName> agents</term> by private <term type="faith">Christians</term> at home</p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">To ascertain if you can do anything at all for us in this respect 
<lb/>is my object in writing to you - I don't expect you to publish 
<lb/>this though you were kind enough to request me to write some 
<lb/>for that purpose - It is too full of inaccuracies for that - But 
<lb/>I hope you may find it convenient to do something with the <gap agent="illgble" extent="1" unit="words"/><w>inform-
<lb break="no"/>-ation</w> it contains <space extent="2" unit="chars"/> - <space extent="4" unit="chars"/>To <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice> the advantage of <orgName>native</orgName> agency amongst these 
<lb/>people <add place="below">˄</add><add place="above">I mention</add> a fact which every day stares me in the face - It has all along 
<lb/>been the practice of the <placeName><settlement type="town">Griqua town</settlement></placeName> <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> to employ <orgName>native</orgName> <term type="occupation">teachers</term> 
<lb/>as soon as they were capable of doing anything in the work, this <del type="strikethrough">plan</del>
<lb/>plan was not thought advisable by the bretheren here, the consequence 
<lb/>has been the <orgName><placeName><settlement type="town">Griqua</settlement></placeName> Mission</orgName> has augmented and stretched out on every 
<lb/>side <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> now they have more than 20 <orgName>native</orgName> <term type="occupation">agents</term> at work &amp; all 
<lb/>the people *<add place="marginleft" rend="vertical">* The <orgName><placeName><settlement type="town">Griqua Town</settlement></placeName> Mission</orgName> has an immense number of <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> under instruction, many more 
<lb/>than this mission</add><!-- Can someone check the preceeding, ks --> on <del type="cancelled">three</del><add place="above">2<choice><orig>½</orig><reg>1/2</reg></choice></add> sides of <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> are under their instruction 
<lb/>viz. South &amp; <choice><abbr>S.</abbr><expan>South</expan></choice> East &amp; West <add place="below">˄</add><add place="above">&amp; some far to the North West</add> and the <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> can now do little 
<lb/>else than <add place="below">˄</add><add place="above">itinerate &amp;</add> superintend them -<space extent="2" unit="chars"/> We have an open door left for us 
<lb/>only towards the North - During the period of prosperity <del type="strikethrough">the</del> of the 
<lb/><orgName><placeName><settlement type="town"><choice><abbr>G.</abbr><expan>Griqua Town</expan></choice></settlement></placeName> Mission</orgName>, this stood almost stock still <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName>
<lb/>went to <placeName><country>England</country></placeName>, finding the current there strongly in favour of 
<lb/><orgName>native</orgName> agency he appears to have changed his views a little for he  
<lb/>wrote back again instructing the bretheren here to make a trial 
<lb/>of two. These are stationed one at a village <measure>16 miles</measure> off 
<lb/>Northwards the other much farther to the North East &amp; now 
<lb/>although it is only a few years since they were appointed 
<lb/>each has many more members under him than on 
<lb/>the station here. And they are more consistent in their 
<lb/>walk and so kind to each other it is quite a treat to visit 
<lb/>them after living sometime with those here - The chief accessions 
<lb/>to the church have also been from their ministry, and 
<lb/>indeed this was to be expected for the truth seems to find its 
<lb/>way to the heart much sooner from their lips than 
<lb/>from a foreigner - In their hands it is divested of that 
<lb/>peculiar strangeness which always attaches to foreigners 
<lb/>in every country but more especially among the uncivilized
<lb/>That <orgName>native</orgName> <term type="occupation">teachers</term> have been planted amongst the tribes which 
<lb/>are now the avowed enemies of the gospel who only 

	<pb n="0005" facs="liv_000496_0005"/><!--pb/@n='78r'-->
<lb/>could have instructed the children <add place="below">˄</add><add place="above">to read</add> &amp; brought home the truths of the <add place="marginright" hand="#hand01"><hi rend="gray">78</hi></add>
<lb/>gospel repeatedly in their own simple affectionate way. We 
<lb/>might now have beheld a very different race of people, - at 
<lb/>present most of them would refuse a <orgName>native</orgName> <term type="occupation">teacher</term>, I mean those 
<lb/>with <measure>100 miles</measure> of us but not so with the tribes beyond
<lb/>They would gladly receive them not however because the <term type="occupation">chiefs</term> 
<lb/>love the gospel Of this they are entirely ignorant But simply 
<lb/>because they imagine as yet that it would be a good thing 
<lb/>to have the <orgName>whites</orgName> as their friends &amp; it would add to their 
<lb/>importance a little - They are not yet contaminated by <term type="occupation">traders</term> 
<lb/><orgName>Griquas</orgName> &amp;c. But they soon will be if something is not 
<lb/><del type="cancelled"><unclear cert="low">arra</unclear></del> done for I found in <add place="below">˄</add><add place="above">each of</add> three tribes 2 persons who 
<lb/>had been infected with the <term type="ailment">venereal disease</term> from a <orgName>Griqua</orgName> 
<lb/>who lately visited them; O I wish much &amp; in this wish the 
<lb/>bretheren <persName>Hamilton</persName> &amp; <persName>Edwards</persName> cordially <del type="strikethrough">agr</del> join, that <del type="cancelled">I</del>
<lb/>we could place some of our <term type="faith">Christians</term> amongst these people 
<lb/>that the blessings of <term type="faith">Christianity</term> &amp; civilization may be given 
<lb/>them before the further spread of some of the worst <w>accomp<supplied>-</supplied>
<lb break="no"/>-animents</w> of more refined society, there is enough of disease 
<lb/>amongst them already, many a sad case I saw without 
<lb/>the power of contributing effectually to the relief of the sufferer 
<lb/>on account of the shortness of our visit - I had no 
<lb/>idea previously that disease existed to such an extent in
<lb/>uncivilized life - At one small town I had about 40 really 
<lb/>bad cases brought to me, some scarcely able to crawl, the 
<lb/><term type="occupation">chief</term> himself was laid up of <term type="ailment">ophthalmia</term> &amp; some of the 
<lb/>cases in the houses were really the personifications of 
<lb/>abject misery - Some come great distances for my 
<lb/>medical advice, they fully appreciate the value of medicine 
<lb/>for bodily maladies O that the Spirit may be poured out <figure><figDesc>blue National Library of Scotland stamp</figDesc></figure>
<lb/>upon them to make them value before it is too late the Great 
<lb/><term type="occupation">Physician</term> of souls. As it is however I could travel to 
<lb/>any distance in the character of a <term type="occupation">medical man</term> &amp; be <w>every<supplied>-</supplied> 
<lb break="no"/>where</w> well received, but in that capacity chiefly, they quite  
<lb/>beseiged my waggon when in the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName>, this liberty of 
<lb/>access I should be glad to employ for any friend who 
<lb/>should feel it his duty to employ a <orgName>native</orgName> <term type="occupation">teacher</term> - If you 
<lb/>know anyone willing to contribute so much more than 
<lb/>they are already doing to the cause of Christ, I can assure 
<lb/>them they employ a most efficient mode of spreading 
<lb/>the gospel for during the first few years of a 
<lb/>mission at least by teaching the children to read &amp; 
<lb/>preaching in their own way in which there are 
<lb/>imperfections, they do as much to remove prejudice 
<lb/>&amp; spread scriptural knowledge as can be effected by 
<lb/>any x<orgName>Eu<add place="above">r</add>opean</orgName>. I know no better way of comme-</p>
<!--pb/@n='78r'-->
<lb/><cb rend="vertical"/>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">All the K <term type="occupation"><choice><abbr>miss<hi rend="sup">s</hi></abbr><expan>missionaries</expan></choice></term> looked upon themselves as aggrieved by the other extending so as to take most of the people away from them
<lb/>It must be confessed that we have always been far inferior to the other mission - I <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice> account for in any other way than 
<lb/>laying it to the account of <orgName>native</orgName> agency - this however is strictly confidential &amp; only for your own information</p>
               

	<pb n="0006" facs="liv_000496_0006"/><!--pb/@n='78v'-->
<lb break="no"/><p rend="no-indent">ncing the work amongst these people than this. Its efficiency 
<lb/>has been most abundantly testified both at <placeName><settlement type="town">Griqua Town</settlement></placeName> &amp; 
<lb/>here &amp; I may add too in the <placeName><region>South Sea islands</region></placeName> - I should 
<lb/>most gladly incur all the fatigue &amp; expense of taking them to 
<lb/>their destinations, help them afterwards as much as in my 
<lb/>faithful account of all that has been done - I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> 
<lb/>know what more I could do but if anything more were needed 
<lb/>I should not I hope be wanting in my attentions to his or her wishes</p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">These <orgName>native</orgName> <term type="occupation">teacher</term> <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> engage in the work without sacrifice 
<lb/>£10 is by no means sufficient for the support of one in this 
<lb/>country but they take it thankfully &amp; some of them work 
<lb/>most assiduously - <space extent="2" unit="chars"/> Usually they have to spend some <unclear cert="medium">time</unclear>
<lb/>in hunting &amp;c. but at these times they employ another &amp; pay 
<lb/>him for his labour - During these hunting excursions they 
<lb/>penetrate far into the country &amp; we have lately ascertained 
<lb/>they are not unmindful of their obligations even when far 
<lb/>removed beyond the reach of their <term type="occupation">teachers</term> &amp; fellow <term type="faith">Christians</term>
<lb/>They sometimes collect the <orgName>natives</orgName> of villages together &amp; tell them 
<lb/>of the way of life &amp; salvation by Jesus Christ</p>
<lb/><p>The country to the North abounds in game, the <term type="animal">Lion</term>, <term type="animal">Elephant</term>, 
<lb/><term type="animal">Rhinoceros</term>, <term type="animal">Giraffe</term> <term type="animal">Zebra</term> &amp; many kinds of <term type="animal">antelope</term> But when 
<lb/>we come within the <placeName><region>Tropics</region></placeName> the heat is excessive, paricularly 
<lb/>in the summer months at which period we visited it</p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">Water is scarce and it was only by following the tracts of 
<lb/>the <term type="occupation">hunters</term> to the different wells that we succeeded in 
<lb/>accomplishing our journey - there is a tribe called the 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bakalihari</term> who live quite in the desert, they have scarcely 
<lb/>any fountains, no cattle &amp; subsist by snaring wild animals 
<lb/>and eating roots - Providence in a peculiar way supplies 
<lb/>the place of water to these sons of the desert - A species 
<lb/>of <term type="plant_foodstuff">bitter melon</term> grows abundantly on many parts of the 
<lb/>sandy plains which contains a considerable portion of sap 
<lb/>There they collect &amp; making incisions into it bitter juice 
<lb/>exudes into their vessels &amp; by it they manage to quench 
<lb/>their thirst - It is a poor substitute <del type="cancelled">for</del> But these 
<lb/>hardy fellows prize their liberty so much nothing 
<lb/>will induce them to quit what appears to us a miserable 
<lb/>mode of existance - Probably they have, like the 
<lb/><term type="people">Laplanders</term> with their <term type="plant_foodstuff">sowthistle</term> &amp; smokers with their 
<lb/><term type="plant_foodstuff">tobacco</term> <add place="below">˄</add><add place="above">become</add> so accustomed to their little <term type="plant_foodsuff">melons</term> they 
<lb/>taste sweetly to them. They are much afraid of the other <term type="tribe">Bechuananas</term>
<lb/>scarcely ever came to the waggons although our people ran after them 
<lb/>and invited them to come &amp; see the white people, they were afraid</p>
<!--pb/@n='78v'-->
<lb/><cb rend="vertical"/>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">Please remember me to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Sewell</persName> &amp; <persName>Charles</persName> when you write. Let me know if she received my letters 
<lb/>&amp; if you have done anything with respect to <placeName><settlement type="city">Rio</settlement></placeName>. I am yours affectionately <persName><choice><abbr>D</abbr><expan>David</expan></choice> Livingston</persName><anchor xml:id="p.76r"/><!--Mike is this addspam correct, none of it on p 77r or 77v--></p>

	<pb n="0007" facs="liv_000496_0007"/><!--pb/@n='79r'-->
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">of being treated by us as they frequently are by their fellow <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> <add place="marginright" hand="#hand01"><hi rend="gray">79</hi></add>
<lb/>who frequently seize them &amp; reduce them to a kind of <orgName>slavery</orgName></p>
<lb/><p><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Watt</persName> tells me the <placeName><settlement type="city">Glasgow</settlement></placeName> churches were preparing clothing for the 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>, these are good but unfortunately they always produce 
<lb/>heart burnings amongst the people - We <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice> give to all &amp; those who 
<lb/><choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> yet imagine we are partial &amp; have favourites - It is of great 
<lb/>importance for the <term type="occupation">missionary</term> to appear as a Universal friend - If I had 
<lb/>clothes publicly committed to my trust, to be distributed publicly I should 
<lb/>consider it a calamity - The only way to avoid the evil is to do all 
<lb/>privately &amp; never give without making them work some to make 
<lb/>them feel they have earned what they have got. When things are 
<lb/>given gratuitously it takes away all the feeling of independency 
<lb/>and teaches them to become beggars without shame - Lately some 
<lb/>boxes were sent and although all the <add place="below">˄</add><add place="above">female</add> members of the church now 
<lb/>appear in <orgName>European</orgName> gowns which look much neater than the 
<lb/>skin gowns their own manufacture, yet it has caused a 
<lb/>great deal of heart burning - Even the reigning <term type="occupation">chief</term> a mean 
<lb/>speaking double faced dirty fellow, without honesty to appear 
<lb/>either on the side of the world or the <term type="faith">Christians</term> but conducts himself 
<lb/>one way with the one party &amp; another with the other, is grumbling 
<lb/>sorely because says he "these <term type="occupation"><choice><abbr>miss<hi rend="sup">s</hi></abbr><expan>missionaries</expan></choice></term> take the poorest of the people 
<lb/>&amp; make them <term type="occupation">kings</term>. Giving a man a suit of clothes <figure><figDesc>blue National Library of Scotland stamp</figDesc></figure>
<lb/>in this country makes him a <term type="occupation">king</term>! <space extent="3" unit="chars"/> I may mention here 
<lb/>one feature in the character of the <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>, they generally have 
<lb/>as much "blarney" as ever was possessed by every boy out of
<lb/><placeName><region>Cork</region></placeName>, my Father, my Lord, King, King of Kings, and even the <unclear cert="low">name</unclear>
<lb/>of the Deity were addressed to us in the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName> and even here
<lb/>it is not uncommon in requesting a favour to do so with some 
<lb/>of these pompous titles But give a point blank refusal &amp; 
<lb/>the significant titles <term type="animal">dog</term>, <term type="animal">wolf</term>, <term type="animal">tiger</term>, <term type="animal">lion</term>, are given with just as 
<lb/>much grace as the former. <space extent="7" unit="chars"/>It is amusing to hear them 
<lb/>sometimes, you are niggardly, speedy, whovever marries 
<lb/>you will get a <term type="animal">wolf</term> &amp;c &amp;c</p>
<lb/><p>I have seen <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi></persName> &amp; <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> W. Phillips</persName> &amp; liked them particularly 
<lb/>the latter very much, they are now somewhere in the <placeName><region>Colony</region></placeName>
<lb/>he is surveying some of the mission stations, marking out 
<lb/>gardens for the people, learning the language &amp;c<reg>.</reg> He did not 
<lb/>like the church at <placeName><settlement type="city">Cape Town</settlement></placeName> &amp; the church did not admire him
<lb/>The feeling in his mind is not to be wondered at, the Church has 
<lb/>used the good old <persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi></persName> most shamefully - Abominably, indeed 
<lb/>when we reflect how much he has done for them, (<unclear cert="medium">Having</unclear>
<lb/>taken by the hand &amp; raised from indigence to <del type="strikethrough">I</del> affluence those 
<lb/>very men who insult him at every church meeting) they 
<lb/>ought to be reprobated by all the world - No doubt he has 
<lb/>had faults &amp; who has not? but these must have been 
<lb/>heinous indeed to justify so much abuse thrown on a 
<lb/>genuine philanthropist - He has now risen beautifully 
<lb/>above it all &amp; notwithstanding their conduct seeks still nothing 

	<pb n="0008" facs="liv_000496_0008"/><!--pb/@n='79v'-->
<lb/>but their good &amp; edification. <space extent="4" unit="chars"/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Calderwood</persName> has accepted a call from <unclear cert="low">them</unclear>
<lb/>greatly surprised at it are all who know him. We hope he has not got tired 
<lb/>of the heathen but sometimes they <choice><sic>dont</sic><reg>don't</reg></choice> look so interesting in reality as they 
<lb/>do in anticipation</p>
<lb/><p>If you <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice> do anything in the way of <orgName>native</orgName> agency, could you turn the 
<lb/>attention of some of the donors of clothes to the fact that a present of a 
<lb/>few spectacles for some old women who by great labour have 
<lb/>taught themselves to read but are now from want of sight losing 
<lb/>the benefit of their industry, would be peculiarly acceptable. Those 
<lb/>at 1/ a pair would do quite well - If you send anything - Please do 
<lb/>so care of <persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Phillip</persName> at the <placeName><region>Cape</region></placeName> via <persName><choice><abbr>Rev</abbr><expan>Reverend</expan></choice> T. Atkinson</persName>, <placeName><settlement type="town">Calesberg</settlement></placeName>
<lb/>I have mentioned this to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Taylor</persName> - O How much I should like to <unclear cert="medium">have</unclear></p><anchor xml:id="envelopePosition"/><!--mike, is this right - does it need another line break-->

<ab>
<address corresp="#envelopePosition"><!--is this envelope coding correct-->
<addrLine><del type="strikethrough">Care of <persName><choice><abbr>Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi></abbr><expan>Reverend</expan></choice> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Phillip</persName>, <placeName>Church Square, Cape Town</placeName></del></addrLine>
	<addrLine><del type="strikethrough"><hi rend="red large">2/4</hi></del></addrLine>
<addrLine><persName>M<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> James Maclehose</persName></addrLine>
<addrLine><space extent="12" unit="chars"/><placeName>83 Buchanan St.</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><space extent="14" unit="chars"/><placeName>Glasgow</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><hi rend="underline">2 sheets</hi><space extent="16" unit="chars"/>N.B.</addrLine>
</address></ab>

<lb/><p rend="no-indent"><persName>Inglis</persName> for my fellow labourer, I hope he will be sent hither</p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">Please let me know the price of <persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Smith</persName>'s work on <placeName><bloc>Africa</bloc></placeName>, you need 
<lb/>not consult <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName> on the subject of <orgName>native</orgName> agency - His views may 
<lb/>have altered, I hope they have But the many differences which have 
<lb/>sprung up between him &amp; the <placeName><settlement type="town">Griqua Town</settlement></placeName> men - I fear will still induce 
<lb/>him to look more coldly on this mode of operation than he otherwise 
<lb/>would. their bickerings have been most unfortunate &amp; deeply are they 
<lb/>to be lamented for they are all excellent men But they still go on 
<lb/>the bretheren<del type="strikethrough">&amp;</del> here <add place="below">˄</add><add place="above">are at <unclear cert="high">variance &amp; war</unclear></add> with those at <placeName><settlement type="town"><choice><abbr>G.</abbr><expan>Griqua Town</expan></choice></settlement></placeName> &amp; <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>M.</abbr><expan>Moffat</expan></choice></persName> with their letters &amp; <del type="cancelled">c</del> <w>com-
<lb break="no"/>mittee</w> in <placeName><settlement type="city">London</settlement></placeName> &amp;c. I may be mistaken in my fears, I shall be 
<lb/>glad if I am. But when I came here the bretheren here <del type="strikethrough">the b</del> possessed 
<lb/>the same feelings respecting the subject as <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>M.</abbr><expan>Moffat</expan></choice></persName> had when he left</p> 




			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>