<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000871">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Arthur Tidman</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Arthur Tidman, 12 October 1855</title>
				<author>Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
				<publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
				<date>2017</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000871</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">University of London. School of Oriental and African Studies; CWM/LMS/Livingstone Wooden Box, item 91</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0389</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Tidman, Arthur, 1792-1868</persName>; </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1855-10-12">12 October 1855</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Linyanti, River Chobe</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="la">Latin</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2013-07-01</date>
				<name xml:id="AM">Anne Martin</name>Initial transcription and XML encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2013-12-11</date>
				<name xml:id="HFB">Heather F. Ball</name>Proofreading and additional XML encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2016-10-01</date>
				<name>Anne Martin</name>Final Review.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2016-10-01</date>
				<name xml:id="AW">Adrian S. Wisnicki</name>Review of final page.
            
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000871_0001"><!--pb/@n='1r'--></pb>
<lb/><!-- The number "91" appears in the left hand margin of the 1st line - I do not think this is in Livingstone's hand AM --><p rend="right"><space extent="2" unit="words"/><placeName><settlement type="town">Linyanti</settlement></placeName>, on the <placeName><geogName type="river">River Chobe</geogName></placeName></p>
<lb/><p rend="right"><space extent="2" unit="words"/><date when="1855-10-12">12<hi rend="sup underline"/>th</date> October 1855.</p>
<lb/>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">The <persName>Reverend D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Tidman</persName></p>
<lb/>
<lb/><p rend="right">Dear Sir</p>
<lb/><p><space extent="6" unit="words"/>The excessive heat and dust which
<lb/>prevail previous to the commencement of the rainy season, have
<lb/>prevented my departure from the <placeName><settlement type="town">town of <persName>Sekeletu</persName></settlement></placeName> as I intended
<lb/>at the beginning of this month, in order to descend the <placeName><geogName type="river">Leeambye</geogName></placeName>
<lb/>or <placeName><geogName type="river">Zambesi</geogName></placeName>. And though often seized with sore longing for the end
<lb/>of this pilgrimage, the certainty that the present weather would soon
<lb/>lay me up with <term type="ailment">fever</term> at a distance from friends almost reconciles
<lb/>the mind to the delay. As I now possess considerable knowledge
<lb/>of the region to which I have devoted some years of toil, I will
<lb/>employ my present comparative <choice><sic>leizure</sic><corr>leisure</corr></choice> in penning a sort of
<lb/><bibl>report</bibl> which may enable you to form a clear idea of <placeName><region>intertropical
<lb/><placeName><bloc>Africa</bloc></placeName></region></placeName> as a <term type="occupation">missionary</term> field.</p>
<lb/><p>It may be advantageous to take a glance at the physical
<lb/>features of the country first, in order to be able to appreciate the
<lb/>nature of the obstacles which will <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">have to</add> be surmounted by those whom
<lb/>God may honour to introduce <term type="faith">christianity</term> into this large section
<lb/>of the <orgName>heathen</orgName> world The remarks made for this purpose must be
<lb/>understoo<supplied cert="high">d</supplied> as applying exclusively to the country between 18º and 10º
<lb/>South Latitude, and situated towards the centre of the continent. The
<lb/>region thus indicated may be described as an extensive plain, intersected
<lb/>in every direction by large rivers with their departing and re-entering
<lb/>branches. They bear on their bosoms volumes of water such as
<lb/>are totally unknown in the <placeName><region>South</region></placeName>. And never dry up as the <placeName><geogName type="river">Orange</geogName></placeName>
<lb/>and most <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">other</add> <orgName>African</orgName> rivers do. They appear as possessing two beds,
<lb/>one of inundation, and another cut out <del type="cancelled">in that</del> exactly like the <placeName><geogName type="river">Clyde</geogName></placeName>
<lb/>above <placeName><placeName><settlement type="village">Bothwell</settlement></placeName> bridge</placeName>. They overflow annually during the rainy
<lb/>season in the <placeName><region>North</region></placeName>. &amp; then the beds of inundation - the haughs or
<lb/>holms, are all flooded though as in the <placeName><region>Barotse valley</region></placeName> they may
<lb/>be more than 20 miles broad. The main body of the water still
<lb/>flows in the now very deep low water bed - but the rivers look
<lb/>more like chains of Lakes than streams. The country between this
<lb/>and <placeName><settlement type="town">Sesheke</settlement></placeName> was during the present year nearly all under water
<lb/>The parts which remained dry are only a few feet above the general
<lb/>level - and canoes went regularly from <placeName><settlement type="town">Linyanti</settlement></placeName> to <placeName><settlement type="town">Sesheke</settlement></placeName>, the
<lb/>distance being in a straight line more than 120 miles. It was
<lb/>an unusually wet year and the plains are not yet free from
<lb/>large patches of stagnant foul smelling water, though we expect
<lb/>the rains of another season to begin during the present month.
<lb/>The inundation, if I may judge from my own observation, is by
<lb/>no means partial. The exceptions are where outcropping rocks
<lb/>form high banks and there we have rapids and cataracts

       

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000871_0002"><!--pb/@n='1v'--></pb>
<lb/>which impede navigation and have probably always been the
<lb/>barriers to inland trade. When the supply of water from the <placeName><region>North</region></placeName>
<lb/>diminishes, the rivers are confined to the low water channels and
<lb/>even at their lowest are deep enough to prevent invasion by
<lb/><orgName>enemies</orgName> who cannot swim or manage canoes. Numerous
<lb/>Lakes of considerable size are left on the lately flooded meadows by
<lb/>the retiring rivers, and these are either fringed with <term type="plant">reeds</term> or covered
<lb/>with <term type="plant">mat rushes</term> - <term type="plant">Papyrus plants</term> - the <term type="plant"><term type="nationality">Egyptian</term> Arum</term> - the <term type="plant">Lotus</term> and
<lb/>other waterloving plants. They are always drying up but never dry
<lb/>ere the next wet season begins</p>
<lb/><p>The country over which the rivers never rise is rarely 200 feet
<lb/>higher than the holms. More frequently it is under 100 feet. In many
<lb/>parts there are plains so level the rain water stands for months
<lb/>together 6 or 8 inches deep. We waded <choice><sic>accross</sic><corr>across</corr></choice> some upwards of
<lb/>twenty miles broad and <term type="animal">fish</term>, <term type="animal">otters</term> and <term type="animal">water tortoises</term> appeared
<lb/>in numbers and quite at home among the grass bushes &amp; trees.
<lb/>These peculiarities result in a great measure from the form of
<lb/>that part of the continent to which our attention is directed
<lb/>It appears to be of a basin or trough form - the hollow is
<lb/>much more elevated certainly than the sea but it is considerably
<lb/>depressed in reference to two longitudinal ridges or fringes on
<lb/>its <placeName><region>Eastern</region></placeName> and <placeName><region>Western</region></placeName> sides. I was led to the recognition
<lb/>of this fact by contemplating the <placeName><geogName type="river">Lotembua</geogName></placeName> running in two
<lb/>and nearly opposite directions. Parting at the <placeName><geogName type="lake">Lake <unclear cert="low">Dilalo</unclear></geogName></placeName> the
<lb/><placeName><region>Northern</region></placeName> portion is discharged into the <placeName><unclear cert="low">Casai</unclear></placeName> and thence into the
<lb/><placeName><geogName type="ocean">Atlantic</geogName></placeName> by the <placeName><geogName type="river">Congo</geogName></placeName>. The <placeName><region>Southern</region></placeName> half disembogues into the
<lb/><placeName><geogName type="river">Leeba</geogName></placeName> and thence into the <placeName><geogName type="ocean"><placeName><bloc>Indian</bloc></placeName> Ocean</geogName></placeName> by the <placeName><geogName type="river">Zambesi</geogName></placeName>. The
<lb/>boiling point of water <choice><orig>shewed</orig><reg>showed</reg></choice> this takes place at the highest part
<lb/>of the basin. It is a sort of partition in it and both <placeName><region>North</region></placeName>
<lb/>and <placeName><region>South</region></placeName> of it all the feeders of the great draining rivers flow
<lb/>from both <placeName><region>Eastern</region></placeName> and <placeName><region>Western</region></placeName> ridges towards the centre of
<lb/>the continent. The general direction of the ranges of hills and
<lb/>the stratification of the rocks dipping down towards a central basin
<lb/>now much filled up by eruptive rocks I had noticed many
<lb/>years ago, and information <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> from <orgName>Arabs</orgName> of two
<lb/>Large shallow lakes within the <placeName><region>Eastern</region></placeName> ridge make me wonder
<lb/>I did not recognize what seems so self evident now. I advance
<lb/>the view to you now with the less diffidence inasmuch as
<lb/>I have just <del type="strikethrough">now</del> ascertained by the perusal of a speech of <persName>Sir
<lb/><choice><abbr>R.</abbr><expan>Roderick</expan></choice> Murchison</persName> before the <orgName><choice><abbr>R.Geog.Soc.</abbr><expan>Royal Geographical Society</expan></choice></orgName> that he promulgated the
<lb/>same idea so long ago as <date when="1852">1852</date>. I cannot imagine how he
<lb/><choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> that information but from his eminent scientific attainments
<lb/>it is certain to be from a reliable source. And as I reached the
<lb/>conclusion from <choice><sic>independant</sic><corr>independent</corr></choice> but very <unclear cert="low">jogtrot</unclear> observation, the
<lb/>view of that gentleman is surely correct.</p>
<lb/><p>I may have dwelt too long on the foregoing topic, but
<lb/>you will at once <choice><sic>percieve</sic><corr>perceive</corr></choice> it has a most important bearing

      

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000871_0003"><!--pb/@n='2r'--></pb>
<lb/>on our prospects. The great humidity produced by quick evaporation
<lb/>from such a vast expanse of water and marsh - the <choice><sic>exhuberant</sic><corr>exuberant</corr></choice>
<lb/><term type="plant">vegetation</term> caused by fervid heat and a perfect flood of light in a rich
<lb/>moist soil. And the prodigious amount of decaying <term type="plant">vegetable</term>
<lb/>matter annually exposed after the inundations to the fervid rays
<lb/>of the torrid sun, with a flat surface often covered with forest,
<lb/>and little wind except at one season of the year, all combine to
<lb/>render the climate far from salubrious for any portion of
<lb/>the human family. I really do not desire to deepen those dark
<lb/>colours in which the climate of certain parts of <placeName><bloc>Africa</bloc></placeName> have been <choice><sic>pourtrayed</sic><corr>portrayed</corr></choice>
<lb/>But in dealing even prospectively with that <choice><sic>sarced</sic><corr>sacred</corr></choice> thing human life,
<lb/>it is necessary to be conscientiously explicit. Take the experience
<lb/>of the <term type="tribe">Makololo</term> who are composed of <term type="tribe">Basutas</term>, <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> and the
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bamangwato</term>. They came from a dry climate, than which there
<lb/>are few more salubrious in the world. They have not been
<lb/>20 years in this quarter but so great has been the mortality among
<lb/>the men the tribe presents all the appearance of being destined at
<lb/>no distant day to extinction. I have heard <persName>Sebituane</persName> (<persName>Sebitane</persName>
<lb/><orgName>his own people</orgName> call him) and many others complain of the
<lb/>numbers of children who have been cut off by <term type="ailment">fever</term>. The women
<lb/>are less fruitful than formerly and ascribe the difference to the
<lb/>excessive operation of a natural phenomenon <gap agent="deletion" extent="1" unit="words"/> produced
<lb/>by the climate. This may explain why they are generally less subject
<lb/>to <term type="ailment">fever</term> than the men. The <term type="tribe">Barotse</term>, <term type="tribe">Batoka</term>, <term type="tribe">Bashikia</term> &amp;c. who
<lb/>belong to the true <orgName>negro</orgName> race now constitute the body of the tribe
<lb/>Then who can boast of being pure <term type="tribe">Makololo</term>. We considered the    
<lb/><gap agent="illegible" extent="2" unit="chars"/><supplied cert="medium">ar</supplied>istocracy &amp;c are a mere handful - the <orgName>negroes</orgName> differ from the <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>
<lb/><unclear cert="medium">in</unclear> being very prolific. Every village we entered in the <placeName><region>North</region></placeName> swarmed
<lb/>with children. This perhaps explains why notwithstanding all their
<lb/>wars, kidnapping, <orgName><orgName>slave</orgName> selling</orgName> and mortality by <term type="ailment">fever</term>. they are
<lb/>such an imperishable race. I supposed the mortality to be
<lb/>considerable among them because many with whom we formed
<lb/>acquaintanceship in going North were in their graves when we returned.
<lb/>But we saw many aged men there.</p>
<lb/><p>Having given the dark side of the picture first the impression
<lb/>may have been produced that it can have no other. Before deciding
<lb/>let me try and give the brighter phase as fairly. No one seeing the
<lb/><placeName><region>country around <placeName><settlement type="town">Linyanti</settlement></placeName> or <placeName><settlement type="town">Sesheke</settlement></placeName></region></placeName> could form an idea of what
<lb/>it becomes further <placeName><region>North</region></placeName>. The <placeName><region>Southeast portion</region></placeName> is the least desirable
<lb/>of the whole. For when we go beyond the <placeName><region>Barotse</region></placeName> the land gradually
<lb/>becomes more lovely <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> in <placeName><region>Londa</region></placeName> (<placeName><region>Lunda</region></placeName>) we reach an exceedingly
<lb/>well watered fruitful country. It is flat, but the luxurient
<lb/>loveliness of many a spot will remain in my imagination <w>for<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>ever</w>. As for the <placeName><region>Interior of <placeName><country>Angola</country></placeName></region></placeName> if <placeName><geogName>Eden</geogName></placeName> sent up so quickly
<lb/>such a rush of rank <term type="plant">vegetation</term> our progenitor must have found
<lb/>sufficient occupation in dressing it. The very thing to be dreaded</p>
	<cb rend="vertical"/><ab>
<lb/>It is necessary to qualify their experience a little in view of the general practice of smoking
<lb/>the <term type="plant">Cannabis Sativa</term> which in the form of <term type="plant">hackshisch</term> is nearly as injurious as <term type="plant">opium</term> among the <term type="people">Turks</term>
</ab>


	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000871_0004"><!--pb/@n='2v'--></pb>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">you think,<hi rend="large">*</hi> the miasmata from such luxuriance must be terrible. This is
<lb/>from the decay of a hundred thousand organisms every one of which <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">is</add> beautiful
<lb/>But the <placeName><settlement type="city">London</settlement></placeName> <orgName>Directors</orgName> surely have not been such unprofitable hearers of
<lb/>sanitary sermons, as to forget that they inhale perennially, effluvia, miasmata,
<lb/>poison! from millions of things almost everyone of which is too horrible to
<lb/>name.</p>
<lb/><p>The <term type="ailment">fever</term> is certainly the great bugbear of this field. But it must
<lb/>ever be borne in mind that it is the only one. There are few other
<lb/>diseases. No <term type="ailment">consumption</term>, nor <term type="ailment">scrofula</term>, nor <term type="ailment">madness</term>.<hi rend="large">*</hi> <term type="ailment">Measles</term>
<lb/>and <term type="ailment">smallpox</term> paid a passing visit some twenty years ago (singularly
<lb/>enough <term type="medicament">inoculation</term> was employed in the latter disease.) I have seen but
<lb/>one well marked case of <term type="ailment">hydrocephalus</term>, three of <term type="ailment">epilepsy</term> but none
<lb/>of <term type="ailment">cholera</term>, <term type="ailment">cancer</term> or <term type="ailment">hydrophobia</term>. <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">or <term type="ailment">delirium themeus</term></add> and many other diseases common     
<lb/>in <placeName><country>England</country></placeName>. "Silent friends" <foreign xml:lang="la">et id genus omne</foreign>, would here have light
<lb/>purses. The paucity of complaints renders people less gullible than with
<lb/>you. A person is very rarely suspected of malingering, and though we
<lb/>have the most implicit faith in medicine homeopathy never alters
<lb/>nor alleviates a single symptom. Indeed  Odyle, <unclear cert="low">Table</unclear>, <unclear cert="low">Twinny</unclear>, popular
<lb/>mesmerism are all the accomplishments of high civilization. The only
<lb/>exception is where a state of <choice><orig>extacy</orig><reg>ecstasy</reg></choice> allied to hypnotism is produced by
<lb/>violent action of the <term type="bodypart">voluntary muscles</term>. The individual pretending to the prophetic
<lb/><foreign xml:lang="la">afflatus</foreign>. The application or even threatened application of that which is
<lb/>recommended for the backs of children and fools produces instantaneous
<lb/>return to propriety. The most common diseases are <term type="ailment">inflammations</term>
<lb/>of different <term type="bodypart">organs</term> but neither these nor <term type="ailment">fever</term> should form a
<lb/>barrier to <term type="occupation">missionary</term> enterprise. I imagine they will not for those
<lb/>who wished to engage therein have never yet stipulated for a field
<lb/>in which death has absolutely no deaths in his quiver. I hope I am
<lb/>not estimating the prospect of subjection to frequent attacks of <term type="ailment">fever</term>
<lb/>too lightly for should <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> who are educated and sent out
<lb/>at great expense be cut off as soon as they enter on their labours
<lb/>by causes which might have been foreseen and avoided, great losses
<lb/>would be sustained by both the church and world. But can any
<lb/>unfavourable inference be drawn from my personal experience in
<lb/>respect of <term type="ailment">fever</term>? I believe decidedly not. It is true I suffered severe
<lb/>attacks of the disease no fewer than twenty seven times in the space of
<lb/>2<choice><orig>½</orig><reg>1/2</reg></choice> years, but it will readily be confessed that sleeping month after
<lb/>month with only a little grass and a horsecloth between me and the ground
<lb/>emitting so much moisture; dew is deposited so quickly on the glass
<lb/>roof of the artificial horizon if placed on a box and within it if placed
<lb/>on the trough on the ground. It is extremely difficult to observe the stars -
<lb/>exposure in comparative motion to the hot sun by day in a <choice><abbr>temp<hi rend="sup underline">e</hi></abbr><expan>temperature</expan></choice>
<lb/>generally upwards of 90º in the shade. (My poor <term type="animal">ox</term> <del type="cancelled">"Sinbad"</del> would
<lb/>never allow <del type="cancelled">the "old man of the sea"</del> to hold an umbrella!) - Drenching
<lb/>showers often making me deposit the watch in the <term type="bodypart">arm pit</term>.- the
<lb/>lower extremities wetted regularly two or three times every day by crossing
<lb/>marshy streams - and food in the <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">half</add> journey North and half passage
<lb/>south purely <orgName>native</orgName>, (with the exception of fine <placeName><country>Angola</country></placeName> sugarless <term type="plant_foodstuff">coffee</term>
<lb/>and that is composed of that <add place="above">article</add> which is sold in <placeName><country>England</country></placeName> as
<lb/>the lesser <term type="animal">bird</term> seed - <term type="plant_foodstuff">manioc</term> roots and meal, all of which

<cb rend="vertical"/>
<lb/><add place="marginleft"><note>* The great moisture does not appear so undesirable after 
<lb/>one has been pining as we did under a sky of brass <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> we 
<lb/><hi rend="underline">almost believed the Prince of the Pow</hi>er of the air had too much 
<lb/><hi rend="underline">of his own way there</hi></note></add>

<cb rend="vertical"/>
<lb/><add place="marginleft"><note>* 3 cases of <term type="ailment">mania</term>, one of <term type="ailment">puerpural insanity</term> &amp; one of <term type="ailment">senile 
<lb/>dementia</term> in 15 years do not require notice in a general statement</note></add>                  
      

	<pb n="0005" facs="liv_000871_0005"><!--pb/@n='3r'--></pb>
<lb/><!-- in both margins there is a vertical line highlighting the text from line 1 to the end of the paragraph i.e. line 19. I think this may be Livingstone's own work, as he refers to marking thus in lines 16/17. AM --><hi rend="underline">2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> sheet</hi>
<lb/>contain so very much starch the <term type="bodypart">eyes</term> become affected as in the case
<lb/>of animals fed on pure <term type="foodstuff">gluten</term> or amylaceous matter only. No ulcer was
<lb/>actually formed but this I attribute to being occasionally able to procure
<lb/>a <term type="animal"><term type="foodstuff">fowl</term></term> and some <term type="plant_foodstuff">maize</term> - these constitute rather a pitiful hygiene
<lb/>and few who follow will have to endure the like. These privations
<lb/>I beg you to observe are not mentioned as if I considered them
<lb/>in the light of <hi rend="underline">sacrifices</hi>. I think the word ought never to be mentioned
<lb/>in reference to anything we can do for Him who though he was rich
<lb/>yet for our own sakes became poor. But I supposed you could not
<lb/>well appreciate my experience at its true or rather no value, unless
<lb/>I stated the drawbacks to fair treatment of the animal economy I
<lb/>came into collision with. No unfavourable opinion surely can
<lb/>be formed from mine as to what the experience of one less exposed
<lb/>to the vicissitudes of the weather and change of diet, might be. I
<lb/>beg that in the event of publication the parts marked by a line on
<lb/>the margin may be suppressed. Unless I mentioned privately the foregoing
<lb/>circumstances it might be supposed I was speaking too lightly of a
<lb/>disease which has inspired so much terror</p>
<lb/><p>The <term type="ailment">fever</term> may be said to commence at the Latitude of <placeName><geogName type="lake">Lake 
<lb/>Ngami</geogName></placeName> (20º South) and extends to the equator or beyond it But from
<lb/><unclear cert="low">8</unclear>º South <choice><abbr>Lat.</abbr><expan>Latitude</expan></choice> it generally assumes the intermittent or least fatal form.<hi rend="large">*</hi>
<lb/>The <foreign xml:lang="la">sequelae</foreign> of this are enlargement of the <term type="bodypart">spleen</term> and great emaciation
<lb/>which after a considerable period end fatally. Abundant <unclear cert="medium">warning</unclear> is
<lb/>always given to seek cure by change of climate and we have not far to
<lb/>go, for a few  degrees of southing introduces into the dry, pure air of the
<lb/>desert and every step in that direction is made in the very remarkably
<lb/>healthy tract termed the <placeName><region>Interior of Southern Africa</region></placeName>. I have had the
<lb/>complaint in its severest forms and, when checked by exposure during
<lb/>its course <term type="bodyprocess">vomiting</term> of large quantities of blood ensued, yet I am aware:-
<lb/>of no organic affection as the result. Indeed I am as well now as ever
<lb/>I was in my life. The greatest inconvenience I was subjected to was
<lb/>being less energetic or quite useless for long periods as a <term type="occupation">missionary</term>.</p>
<lb/><p>One cause of the great mortality which prevails at certain times and
<lb/>particularly at the period of drying up of the inundations is the want
<lb/>of prompt though not heroic treatment. Neither <term type="occupation">doctors</term> nor patients
<lb/>hurry themselves. Though his services may not have been asked till danger
<lb/>appears, the <term type="occupation">medical man</term> must throw his dice first and spend hours
<lb/>of talking over that, then if it is late in the afternoon he will go and dig
<lb/>the roots tomorrow, and even then stirs not till the sun is well up. The
<lb/>treatment when once fairly in operation is undoubtedly that best adapted
<lb/>to overcome the disease for they set themselves assiduously to induce <term type="prescription">profuse
<lb/>and long continued action of the <term type="bodypart">skin</term></term>. By a combination of this <del type="strikethrough">and</del> with
<lb/>simultaneous but <term type="prescription">gentle stimulation of the <term type="bodypart">internal organs</term></term> which as well
<lb/>as the <term type="bodypart">skin</term> have ceased <term type="bodyprocess">secretion</term>, I have found no difficulty in relieving
<lb/>and ultimately curing every case submitted to my care. My <orgName>company of
<lb/>27 persons</orgName> were often attacked. (two of them being jaundiced appeared as if
<lb/>affected by something of the <term type="ailment"><placeName><region>West African</region></placeName> remittent</term>) but all were brought
<lb/>home in good health. With an equal number of <orgName>Europeans</orgName> it might
<lb/>have been otherwise. But I apprehend no great mortality among <term type="occupation">missionaries</term>

<cb rend="vertical"/>
<lb/><add place="marginleft"><hi rend="vertical"><note>* I would speak in a different tone if I believed this to be the <term type="ailment"><placeName><region>West African</region></placeName> Remittent</term>. That terrible disease seems to baffle 
<lb/>all medical means - I believe it occasionally becomes epidemic in the country mentioned. I have seen a few mild 
<lb/>cases - yet in the intervals we have a more salubrious field than the <hi rend="underline">church, <orgName>Baptist <term type="nationality">American</term></orgName> &amp; <orgName>United Presbyterian</orgName></hi>
<lb/><space extent="5" unit="words"/><term type="occupation">missionaries</term></note></hi></add>
               
      

	<pb n="0006" facs="liv_000871_0006"><!--pb/@n='3v'--></pb>
<lb/>- men of education and prudence who can if they will adopt proper <choice><sic>hygeinic</sic><corr>hygienic</corr></choice>
<lb/>precautions. Excuse me if I remind you this is more than the <orgName>natives of
<lb/><placeName><settlement type="city">London</settlement></placeName></orgName> can effect though liable to three if not four forms of <term type="ailment">fever</term>.
<lb/>Their breed will never be whitened by bone dust alum or sulphate of copper
<lb/>The detestable adulterations <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">of which</add> you are the victims are here unknown. And
<lb/>even though it may still be thought a disease sufficiently menacing the
<lb/>terrible ravages it committed among the <orgName>Northern or <choice><sic>Independant</sic><corr>Independent</corr></choice> <orgName>Boers</orgName></orgName> in
<lb/>its sweep it made a few years ago round the <placeName><geogName type="mountain">Cashan mountains</geogName></placeName> <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice>
<lb/>it is not to be regarded as an unmitigated evil. <persName>Radama</persName> called a
<lb/>complaint of the same nature one of his best <term type="occupation">generals</term>. Neither <term type="nationality">English</term> nor
<lb/><term type="nationality">French</term> <term type="occupation">soldiers</term> could be hounded on to a <orgName>caffre</orgName> war in <placeName><region>Madagascar</region></placeName> for <choice><sic>the
<lb/>the</sic><corr>the</corr></choice> especial benefit of "<orgName><placeName><region>Frontier</region></placeName> <term type="occupation">settlers</term></orgName>". It may appear ludicrous to
<lb/>look even askance to a <term type="ailment">Fever</term> for protection. I bear with the loss
<lb/>of my entire property - plundered as the very first act of the<del type="strikethrough">ir</del> <choice><sic>independant</sic><corr>independent</corr></choice>
<lb/>existence of the <orgName><placeName><region>Transvaal</region></placeName> <orgName>Boers</orgName></orgName> with very great composure for it would
<lb/>have cost me a world of time and trouble to have brought it here, but
<lb/>it is bitter to be told by the <orgName>Boers</orgName> who heard him that <persName>her Majesty's
<lb/><term type="occupation">commissioner</term></persName> said "they might do as they liked with the <term type="occupation">missionaries</term>"
<lb/>and then to have the additional insult by the <persName><placeName><region>Cape</region></placeName> <term type="occupation">Governor</term></persName> that "if
<lb/>we go into the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName> it must be at our own risk". If so, and it never
<lb/>yet has been at anything else, why appoint a <term type="occupation">consul</term> <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">at <placeName><settlement type="city">Bloemfontein</settlement></placeName></add> for which <placeName><country>England</country></placeName>
<lb/>must pay a handsome salary. Such gratuitous insults to loyalty
<lb/>and confessions of imbecility from <term type="occupation">commissioners</term> and <term type="occupation">Governors</term>
<lb/>were never dreamed of in <placeName><country>America</country></placeName> though they can go great lengths
<lb/>in some disreputable directions. We will not become disloyal
<lb/>though. On we intend to go as heretofore at our own risk. We have
<lb/>enlarged considerably the boundaries of <term type="nationality">British</term> commerce and have
<lb/>conveyed <del type="strikethrough">the</del> an impression to thousands of <orgName>Africans</orgName> of <term type="nationality">British</term> justice
<lb/>and honour. Witness <persName>Sechele</persName>'s faith in the <del type="strikethrough">justice</del><add place="above">character</add> of <persName>Queen Victoria</persName>
<lb/>on the strength of which he travelled from the vicinity of the
<lb/><placeName><region>Tropic</region></placeName> to <placeName><settlement type="city">Cape Town</settlement></placeName>, more than a thousand miles, certain if
<lb/>he could only get near enough to tell her his case would be
<lb/>attended to. And certainly it would have been, for <orgName>hundreds of
<lb/>of his children</orgName> reduced to hopeless <orgName>slavery</orgName> in direct violation
<lb/>of the treaty is no where else looked upon by <term type="nationality">British</term> <term type="occupation">statesmen</term>
<lb/>with indifference. At <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> I dissuaded him from the
<lb/>attempt to go to <placeName><settlement type="city">London</settlement></placeName>. "Will <persName>the Queen</persName> not listen to my story?"
<lb/>I could not say Nay. Well, <orgName><term type="nationality">English</term> <term type="occupation">officers</term></orgName> just returning from
<lb/>fighting with <term type="tribe">Basutas</term> - <orgName>his own family and friends</orgName>, with that
<lb/>love of fair play which distinguishes them, generously contributed
<lb/>upwards of £60. to defray his expenses to <placeName><country>England</country></placeName>. Let our
<lb/><term type="occupation">rulers</term> be entreated by all that is good to forbear allowing such
<lb/>noble minded men <del type="strikethrough">from</del> being employed (as the <term type="people">Russians</term> against
<lb/><orgName>Magyars</orgName>) in crushing men who have for years <choice><orig>shewn</orig><reg>shown</reg></choice> a devotion
<lb/>to their <term type="occupation">chiefs</term> only equalled not surpassed by <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">that of</add> the <orgName><term type="nationality">Scottish</term> Highlanders</orgName>
<lb/>to the <persName>Pretender</persName>. A <orgName>caffre</orgName> war presents no elements of honour <!-- persName: Charles Edward Stuart or "Bonnie Prince Charlie" -->
<lb/>and it is impossible for any one who loves the <term type="nationality">English</term> <term type="occupation">soldier</term>
<lb/>not to view with gloom the persevering efforts to get up another
<lb/><placeName><region>Natal</region></placeName>. Some <orgName>members of a commission</orgName> sitting there lately unblushingly
<lb/>advocate compulsory labour. Others removal of 100<supplied>,</supplied>000 <orgName>caffres</orgName> by 6000 <add place="below"><orgName>whites</orgName></add>


	<pb n="0007" facs="liv_000871_0007"><!--pb/@n='4r'--></pb>
<lb/>and this too though the <bibl>Recorder</bibl><!-- cannot be certain that this is a publication, but have assumed it is AM --> of the district declares that history does not
<lb/>present an instance in which so great security for life and property has
<lb/>been enjoyed. The killing modesty of the colony <orgName>bravadoes</orgName> becomes evident
<lb/>when you see the men who say, "I would drive the 100,000 over the border by
<lb/>force". "I would make a law to <choice><sic>compell</sic><corr>compel</corr></choice> them to give their <orgName>young men</orgName>
<lb/>to us to labour" described by another of the examined, as "generally men
<lb/>who came to the country in search of employment themselves". They cannot
<lb/>now dig but to beg for enrichment by a <orgName>Caffre</orgName> war they are not ashamed.</p>
<lb/><p>In regard to the people inhabiting this large and populous territory
<lb/>it is difficult in the absence of all numerical data to present a very precise
<lb/>idea. The tribes are large but divided into a great number of villages
<lb/>so thickly were these dotted over the country that in travelling in a straight
<lb/>line in which we could rarely see more than a mile on each side we
<lb/>often passed ten or twelve hamlets in a single day. Occasionally however
<lb/>we marched 10 miles without seeing any. In no part of the <placeName><region>South</region></placeName> I have
<lb/>visited is such a population seen. <placeName><country>Angola</country></placeName> contains 600<supplied cert="high">,</supplied>000 souls
<lb/>and <placeName><region>Londa</region></placeName> seemed more populous and of larger extent than it.
<lb/>The <placeName><region>Cape Colony</region></placeName> with 200<supplied cert="high">,</supplied>000 souls, possesses some hundreds of <term type="occupation"><w>mission-
<lb break="no"/>-aries</w></term> and other <orgName><term type="faith">Christian</term> <term type="occupation">instructors</term> and <term type="occupation">schoolmasters</term></orgName>, but it will
<lb/>bear no comparison with <placeName><region>Londa</region></placeName> as a <term type="occupation">missionary</term> field. The <placeName><region><term type="tribe">Makololo</term>
<lb/>territory</region></placeName> has several tribes <del type="strikethrough">of</del> <term type="tribe">Batoka</term>, <term type="tribe">Barotse</term>, <term type="tribe">Bashubia</term>, <term type="tribe">Banyeti</term>
<lb/><term type="tribe">Matlotlera</term> &amp;c. and there is no impediment to immediate occupation 
<lb/>by <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> and to such as aspire to the honour of being
<lb/><orgName><term type="occupation">messengers</term> of mercy</orgName> to the actual <orgName>heathen</orgName> there is no more inviting
<lb/>in <placeName><country>South Africa</country></placeName>. I am not to be understood as meaning that any
<lb/>of these people are anxious for the <bibl>gospel</bibl> - they are quite unlike the
<lb/>intelligent, enquiring <orgName>race in the <placeName><region>Punjaub</region></placeName></orgName>, or the vivaceous <orgName>islanders
<lb/>of the <placeName><geogName type="ocean">Pacific</geogName></placeName></orgName>. But there is not such callous indifference to religious
<lb/>truth as I have seen. nor yet that opposition which betokens
<lb/>progress in knowledge. But there is a large population and we are
<lb/>sure if the word of life is faithfully preached, in process of time
<lb/>many will believe. I repeat again that I know of no impediment
<lb/>to immediate efforts for their instruction. Every <term type="occupation">headman</term> and
<lb/><term type="occupation">chief</term> in the country would be proud of the visit or residence of a
<lb/><orgName>white man</orgName>. There is security generally for life and property. I left by
<lb/>mistake a pontoon in a village of <placeName><region>Londa</region></placeName> and found it safe 18
<lb/>months afterwards. Some parcels sent by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName> by means
<lb/>of <term type="tribe">Matibele</term> lay a whole year on an island in the <placeName><geogName type="river">Zambesi</geogName></placeName> near
<lb/><placeName><geogName type="waterfall">Mosioatunya</geogName></placeName>. It is true, it was believed that they contained medicine
<lb/>which might bewitch but regular rogues are seldom scared by such
<lb/>preservatives, the <term type="tribe">Balonda</term> are a friendly industrious race, and
<lb/>thousands of the <term type="tribe">Balobale</term> find an asylum among them from
<lb/>the <orgName><orgName>slave</orgName> <term type="occupation">dealing</term></orgName> propensities of their <term type="occupation">chiefs</term>. They seem to possess
<lb/>a more vivid conviction of their relation to the unseen world
<lb/>than any of the <orgName>southern tribes</orgName>. In the deep dark forests near
<lb/>their villages we always met with idols and places of prayer. The
<lb/>latter are spots about four feet broad and forty long kept carefully
<lb/>clear of <term type="plant">vegetation</term> and fallen leaves. They resemble garden walks

      

	<pb n="0008" facs="liv_000871_0008"><!--pb/@n='4v'--></pb>
<lb/>branching off from the common foot path and have two or three partitions
<lb/><choice><sic>accross</sic><corr>across</corr></choice> them of split sticks of grass and generally terminate at a tree. There
<lb/>in the still darkness of the forest night the <term type="occupation">worshipper</term> either male or female
<lb/>comes alone and prays to the gods (Batimo) or spirits of departed relatives
<lb/>and when an answer to the petition seems granted, <term type="foodstuff">meal</term> or other
<lb/>food is sprinkled on the spot as a thank offering. The <term type="tribe">Balonda</term>
<lb/>extend to 7º South <choice><abbr>Lat.</abbr><expan>Latitude</expan></choice> and their paramount <term type="occupation">chief</term> is always named
<lb/><persName>Matiamvo</persName>. There are many subordinate <term type="occupation">chiefs</term> all nearly <choice><sic>independant</sic><corr>independent</corr></choice>
<lb/>The <term type="tribe">Balobale</term> possess the same character but are more warlike yet no
<lb/>prudent <orgName>white man</orgName> would be in the least danger among them.</p>
<lb/><p>It seems proper to refer to the <term type="tribe">Chiboque</term> <term type="tribe">Bashinge</term> and <term type="tribe">Bangala</term>
<lb/>who treated us more scurvily than any I had previously met with
<lb/>in <placeName><bloc>Africa</bloc></placeName>. And in estimating their actions it will be but fair
<lb/>to <choice><sic>concieve</sic><corr>conceive</corr></choice> ourselves as placed in their circumstances. They have
<lb/>been visited by <orgName><orgName>slave</orgName> <term type="occupation">dealers</term></orgName> of colour, and the nature of the
<lb/>country precluding the use of vehicles the<del type="cancelled">y</del> <add place="above"><term type="occupation">merchants</term></add> are always obliged to hire
<lb/>40 or 50 <term type="occupation">carriers</term> whose <orgName>clannish</orgName> feelings are all on the side of the
<lb/>tribes mentioned. In any difficulty they are ready to save themselves
<lb/>by <del type="strikethrough"><unclear cert="medium">siding</unclear></del> abandoning their <term type="occupation">employer</term> on arriving at any village
<lb/>They tell how much he has been <unclear cert="low">wicked</unclear> at those already
<lb/>passed. The <term type="occupation">chief</term> sees he has but one man and a few personal
<lb/><orgName>slaves</orgName> with whom to deal and regulates his demands accordingly
<lb/>and the <term type="occupation">merchant</term> feeling his correct position as well as <add place="above">being</add> desirous
<lb/>to curry favour in order to induce him to part with <del type="strikethrough">their</del><add place="above">his</add> people
<lb/><del>Their</del><add place="above">his</add> sole source of importance, generally accedes to every demand.
<lb/>Real <term type="people">Portuguese</term> would not submit to the imposition but the <orgName>men
<lb/>of colour</orgName> they employ always do, and justify the squandering of their
<lb/><term type="occupation">employers</term> property on the ground that resistance would place in
<lb/>jeopardy the whole in going and a great part in returning, for nothing
<lb/>is easier in a densely wooded country than to abstract chainful after
<lb/>chainful of <orgName>slaves</orgName> - or kidnap straggling <term type="occupation">carriers</term> in the rear. The
<lb/>tribes have by this process imbibed the idea that they have as
<lb/>undoubted a right to these <unclear cert="medium">fines</unclear> as our good <term type="occupation">bishops</term> have to
<lb/>theirs. Could it therefore be otherwise than utterly disgusting to
<lb/>get the impudent answer from 2 <orgName>chartists</orgName> "who had only five guns"
<lb/>"We <choice><sic>wont</sic><corr>won't</corr></choice> pay for treading the earth of God our common
<lb/>father". They were indignant to behold an unblushing attempt
<lb/>to defraud the revenue and uttered shouts of most patriotic
<lb/>disgust. Could we have done less? Sometimes they levelled their
<lb/>guns at us and it seemed as if we must fight to prevent
<lb/>entire plunder and reduction to <orgName>slavery</orgName>. A quiet arrangement
<lb/>by which <term type="occupation">chief</term> and <term type="occupation">councillors</term> were quite within range of the <term type="occupation">spearmen</term>
<lb/>and our assertion that we were neither <orgName><term type="occupation">slavedealers</term></orgName> nor <term type="occupation">soldiers</term> &amp;
<lb/>would fight only after they had struck the first blow. It would
<lb/>have been dangerous to fire without killing for one being defenceless
<lb/>till the piece is reloaded, the enemy is encouraged by seeing a
<lb/>good chance before this can be effected. These were trying times, the
<lb/>more especially as I had no <unclear cert="medium">predilection</unclear> towards ending my <choice><sic>carreer</sic><corr>career</corr></choice>


	<pb n="0009" facs="liv_000871_0009"><!--pb/@n='5r'--></pb>
<lb/>as a "<term type="occupation"><unclear cert="low">soger</unclear></term>" But it cannot be said they acted unreasonably. Indeed
<lb/>considering their circumstances, and entire ignorance of our previous
<lb/>good conduct, unreasonableness cannot be said to be a more obstinate
<lb/>hereditary complaint in <placeName><bloc>Africa</bloc></placeName> than in <placeName><country>Ireland</country></placeName>. I thank God we did
<lb/>them no harm and no one need fear vengeance on our account
<lb/>A few more visits on the same principle would render them as
<lb/>safe as all other tribes, concerning which it may <supplied cert="medium">be</supplied> confidently stated
<lb/>that if one behaves as a gentleman, he will invariably be treated as
<lb/>such. Contrary conduct will give rise to remarks and treatment of scorn.</p>
<lb/><p>Reference has been made to the <term type="tribe">Barotse</term> <term type="tribe">Batoka</term> &amp;c. as of
<lb/>the true <orgName>negro</orgName> race which occupies the <placeName><region>interior of the continent</region></placeName>
<lb/>By their subjection to the <term type="tribe">Makololo</term> they have acquired considerable
<lb/>knowledge of the Sichuana language. We have thus a very
<lb/>important field open in a tongue into which the whole of the <bibl>sacred
<lb/>scriptures</bibl> will it is hoped soon be translated, and the time necessary
<lb/>for learning and reducing the <orgName>negro</orgName> language may not be so
<lb/>barren as is usually the case. The <term type="tribe">Barotse</term>, <term type="tribe">Batoka</term>, <term type="tribe">Balonda</term>,
<lb/>and <del type="strikethrough">Balonda</del><add place="below">^</add> <add place="above"><term type="tribe">Ambonda</term> dialects</add> (or language spoken by the <orgName>Angolese</orgName>) With those spoken
<lb/>in <placeName><region>Luba</region></placeName> &amp; beyond, as also those of people on the <placeName><region>East coast</region></placeName> are
<lb/>all undoubtedly cognate with the <term type="tribe">Bechuana</term> tongue and <orgName>Caffre</orgName>.
<lb/>The very considerable number of words exactly alike or only
<lb/>slightly varied in their inflexions can only be explained on
<lb/>that hypothesis for there has been no intercourse between
<lb/>these <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">tribes</add> at least for centuries past. Each of the <orgName>negro</orgName> tribes
<lb/>readily learns the language of the others. The <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>
<lb/>however often fail to acquire that of the <orgName>negroes</orgName> though living
<lb/>among them, yet <orgName>my companions</orgName> acquired it in <placeName><country>Angola</country></placeName> as
<lb/>readily as I could a smattering of Portuguese and failed entirely
<lb/>in the latter. <term type="ailment">Fever</term> prevented my learning more <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">of the Balonda</add> than the
<lb/><term type="occupation">interpreter</term> of a late <orgName><placeName><region>Cape</region></placeName> <term type="occupation">Governor</term></orgName> had of Sitchuana when
<lb/>he cooly told his <term type="occupation">employer</term> that, a language into which the
<lb/><bibl>Pentateuch</bibl> is fully and idiomatically expressed in a very great 
<lb/>number fewer words than it is in the Septuagint Greek.
<lb/>or verbose English, was not capable of certain remarks made
<lb/>by a <term type="tribe">Basuta</term> <term type="occupation">chief</term>. The influence of the <bibl>sacred scriptures</bibl> in
<lb/>the true <orgName>negro</orgName> language will be immense, If we call the
<lb/>actual amount of conversion the direct results of missions
<lb/>and the wide diffusion of better principles the indirect I have
<lb/>no hesitation in asserting that the latter are of infinite more
<lb/>importance than the former. I do not undervalue the importance
<lb/>of the conversion and salvation of the most abject creature
<lb/>that <term type="bodyprocess">breathes</term>. it is of overwhelming worth to him personally
<lb/>But viewing our work of wide sowing of the good seed
<lb/>relatively to the harvest which will be reaped when all

      

	<pb n="0010" facs="liv_000871_0010"><!--pb/@n='5v'--></pb>
<lb/>our heads are low there can I think be no comparison
<lb/>It seems necessary in pointing out a large new field and
<lb/>counselling its immediate occupation that I should advert
<lb/>to this subject. for we have been amused once and again of
<lb/>late with the <hi rend="underline">discovery</hi> that concentration of <term type="occupation">missionary</term>
<lb/>agency is what is needed, and not that sowing beside all
<lb/>waters which led you to send <persName>Morison</persName> and <persName>Milne</persName> to <del type="strikethrough"><placeName><country>China</country></placeName></del> be
<lb/>lost among 300<supplied>,</supplied>000<supplied>,</supplied>000 <term type="occupation">idolators</term>. And the <orgName>Church <term type="occupation">missionary</term>
<lb/>Society</orgName> to look to the <placeName><region>Antipodes</region></placeName> &amp; <placeName><region>Patagonia</region></placeName> <add place="above">&amp; <placeName><region>East Africa</region></placeName></add> with the full knowledge
<lb/>that charity begins at home. The question involves various
<lb/>elements which I have not the means of solving. I therefore speak
<lb/>with diffidence though any report within my reach during the
<lb/>last ten or twelve years seems to say. "<hi rend="underline">the more concentration
<lb/>the less success"</hi> i.e. If you increase <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> so that
<lb/>they bear a proportion of more than one to 2000 or 3000 of the
<lb/>population - in ten years the proportion of <orgName>communicants</orgName>
<lb/>will be very much less per man employed than if the proportion
<lb/>had been one to 20<supplied>,</supplied>000 of the people. I refer to <placeName><bloc>Africa</bloc></placeName> alone
<lb/>and as it has been held forth as an example of the good effects
<lb/>of concentration it is singular if you glance at the numbers
<lb/>of <orgName>communicants</orgName> &amp; numbers of <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> - the one is in
<lb/>inverse ratio to the other though it is believed that there
<lb/>is not much difference in the standards of admission.
<lb/>Time is more essential than concentration. Let the seed be sown and
<lb/>there is no more doubt of its vitality and germination than there is of the
<lb/>general spring &amp; harvest in the course of nature. Although I have not
<lb/>the most distant hope that we shall ever approach to anything like
<lb/>converting or "conversions to order" the subject merits attention <w>in-
<lb break="no"/>asmuch</w> as it may be elicited that there has been a great deal
<lb/>more done both directly and indirectly in <placeName><country>India</country></placeName> <del type="strikethrough">more</del> than men believe.
<lb/>Will it be out of place to recommend the subject to our
<lb/>friend <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Mullens</persName> of <placeName><settlement type="city">Calcutta</settlement></placeName>?</p>
<lb/><p>It might be premature to contemplate the probability of
<lb/>any results from the circulation of the <bibl>edition of the testament</bibl>
<lb/>which was furnished to <persName>Park</persName>. But the circumstances are
<lb/>somewhat similar seeing all the <orgName>Arabs</orgName> I have met with are
<lb/>able to read and write. We may accomplish that which
<lb/>he was not permitted to do. It will at all events be working
<lb/>in the right direction. Schemers though we may be there
<lb/>is this difference between us and the worldly wise, While they
<lb/>seem annoyed with our fanaticism we are really glad to
<lb/>see their schemes, whether of prison or sanitary reform
<lb/><orgName><placeName><geogName type="river">Niger</geogName></placeName> expeditions</orgName> or soup kitchens, and wish they would
<lb/>make another attempt at the commercial aspect of this field.
<lb/>The <orgName>Africans</orgName> are all deeply <unclear cert="medium">imbued</unclear> with the spirit of trade. We
<lb/>found great difficulty in getting past many villages. Every

      

	<pb n="0011" facs="liv_000871_0011"><!--pb/@n='6r'--></pb>
<lb/>artifice was employed to detain us that we might purchase our
<lb/>suppers from them. And having finished all the game they are
<lb/>entirely <choice><sic>dependant</sic><corr>dependent</corr></choice> on <term type="nationality">English</term> calico for clothing. It is retailed
<lb/>to them by inches. A small piece will purchase a <orgName>slave</orgName>. If
<lb/>they had the opportunity of a market they could raise on their
<lb/>rich soil abundance of <term type="plant">cotton</term> and <term type="plant_foodstuff">Zingolia beans</term> for oil. I
<lb/>cannot say they were lazy though they did seem to take the world
<lb/>easy - their hair was elaborately curled - many of their villages
<lb/>were models of neatness and so were their gardens &amp; huts. Many
<lb/>were inveterate <term type="occupation">musicians</term>, and made one remember how
<lb/>much of our <orgName>Anglo saxon</orgName> energy <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">is <choice><sic>expendeded</sic><corr>expended</corr></choice></add> in dress, &amp; in the howling of
<lb/>pianos. The men who went with me to <placeName><settlement type="city">Loanda</settlement></placeName> did so
<lb/>in order to open up a path for commerce and without any
<lb/>hope of payment from me. Though compelled to part with
<lb/>their hard won earnings in that city for food on our
<lb/>way home. I never heard a murmur - the report they gave
<lb/>of the expedition both <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">in</add> public and private and very kind
<lb/>expression towards myself were sufficiently flattering. A
<lb/>fresh <orgName>party</orgName> was dispatched with ivory under the guidance
<lb/>of an <orgName>Arab</orgName> from <placeName><geogName type="island">Zanzibar</geogName></placeName> and two days only given
<lb/>for preparation. And when they return or even
<lb/>sooner <orgName>my companions</orgName> are to start again. That
<lb/>their private opinions are in accordance with their
<lb/>public professions I have evidence in the number of volunteers
<lb/>who offer themselves to go to the <placeName><region>East</region></placeName> with me knowing I have
<lb/>not wherewith to purchase food even. And they are not an
<lb/>enthusiastic race either. There is not the least probability of
<lb/>any mere <term type="occupation">adventurer</term> attaining much influence among
<lb/>them. If the movement now begun is not checked by
<lb/>some untoward event the <orgName><orgName>slave</orgName> trade</orgName> will certainly come
<lb/>to a natural termination in this quarter. Our <unclear cert="low">outzers</unclear>
<lb/>have rendered <orgName>slaves</orgName> of so little value now on the coast
<lb/>The <term type="tribe">Mambari</term> purchase for domestic use alone and they
<lb/>can still buy in some of the <term type="tribe">Batoka</term> tribes only on account
<lb/>of the very high value put upon small pieces of clothing
<lb/>they could not come for <orgName>slaves</orgName> alone but the <term type="tribe">Makololo</term>
<lb/>feeling the value of the ivory which enables the <term type="tribe">Mambari</term> to
<lb/>make the trip have resolved to purchase it all. Commerce
<lb/>has the effect of speedily letting the tribes see their mutual
<lb/><choice><sic>dependant</sic><corr>dependent</corr></choice>. It breaks up the sullen isolations of <orgName>heathenism</orgName>
<lb/>It is so far good But <term type="faith">Christianity</term> alone reaches the very
<lb/>centre of the wants of <placeName><bloc>Africa</bloc></placeName> and of the world. The <orgName>Arabs</orgName>
<lb/>or <orgName>Moors</orgName> are great in commerce but few will say they
<lb/>are as amiable as the uncivilized <orgName>negroes</orgName> in consequence.
<lb/>You will see I appreciate the effects of commerce much
<lb/>but those of <term type="faith">Christianity</term> much more.</p>

	<pb n="0012" facs="liv_000871_0012"><!--pb/@n='6v'--></pb>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">Theoretically I would pronounce the country about the forks
<lb/>of the <placeName><geogName type="river">Leeba</geogName></placeName> and <placeName><geogName type="river">Leeambye</geogName></placeName> or <placeName><geogName type="river">Kabompo</geogName></placeName> and river of the 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bashukubompo</term>, as a most desirable central point for
<lb/>the spread of civilization and <term type="faith">Christianity</term> - and unfortunately
<lb/>I must mar my report by saying I feel a difficulty
<lb/>as to taking my children there, without their own intelligent
<lb/><choice><sic>self dedication</sic><corr>self-dedication</corr></choice> - I can speak for my wife and myself only
<lb/>we will go whoever remains behind.</p>
<lb/><p rend="center">Affectionately Yours</p>
<lb/><p rend="right"><persName>David Livingstone</persName></p>
<lb/>

<lb/><cb rend="vertical"/><ab rend="center"><persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Tidman</persName>
<lb/><space extent="1" unit="words"/><placeName>Mission House</placeName>
<lb/><space extent="2" unit="words"/><placeName>Blomfield <choice><abbr>St.</abbr><expan>Street</expan></choice></placeName>
<lb/><space extent="4" unit="words"/><hi rend="underline"><placeName><settlement type="city">London</settlement></placeName></hi>.</ab>


			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>