<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000562">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Arthur Tidman</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Arthur Tidman, 9 June 1844</title>
				<author>Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
				<publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
				<date>2017</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000562</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">University of London. School of Oriental and African Studies; CWM/LMS/Livingstone Wooden Box, item 27</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0104</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Tidman, Arthur, 1792-1868</persName>; </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1844-06-09">9 June 1844</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Mabotsa</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="U">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
            </handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2012-01-08</date>
				<name xml:id="DC">Danielle Cyphert</name>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-09-12</date>
				<name xml:id="MS">Matthew Stumpf</name>Proofreading.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-10-30</date>
				<name xml:id="HFB">Heather F. Ball</name> XML editing.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2016-05-20</date>
				<name xml:id="AM">Anne Martin</name>Final Review.
            
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000562_0001"><!--pb/@n='1r'--></pb>
<lb/><p rend="right"><space extent="3" unit="words"/><placeName><settlement type="village">Mabotsa</settlement></placeName> <date when="1844-09-09">9 June 1844</date></p><!--The deletion that begins here and the text at the top of the page (both apparently in pencil) do not appear to be in Livingstone's hand--><!-- have now attempted to code this with a <delSpan> AM --><delSpan spanTo="#del-1" hand="#U"/>
<lb/><p>Dear Sir</p>
<lb/><p><space extent="3" unit="words"/>The Lord having in tender mercy restored me
<lb/>to my wanted health. I have much cause for gratitude in
<lb/>being able again to communicate with you. The affliction
<lb/>from which I have been raised was both painful and <w>pro-
<lb break="no"/>-tracted</w>. As the wounds discharging profusely prevented
<lb/>the union of the fragments into which the bone was
<lb/>broken and these having seldom been properly secured
<lb/>every motion of the body produced a grating irritation
<lb/>which reacted on the wounds. But through the mercy
<lb/>of our Heavenly Father the whole has healed well beyond
<lb/>my most sanguine expectation, and the bone is perfectly
<lb/>straight and firm. It was a severe trial of patience to
<lb/>be laid aside so long and at a period too when every
<lb/>assistance that can be rendered is required. But though
<lb/>I fear I have not learned all that was intended by the
<lb/>chastisement, I trust I have realized much which though
<lb/>I knew I did not fully feel before. And I hope I am
<lb/>now more anxious than ever that my spared life may
<lb/>be entirely consecrated to the glory of my great Deliverer.<anchor xml:id="del-1"/></p>
<lb/><p>The <term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term> are at present busily engaged in
<lb/>removing from their former location to the spot on which
<lb/>we reside, and it is cheering <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">to</add> observe <add place="below" rend="gray" hand="#U">^</add> <add place="above" rend="gray" hand="#U">that</add> the subordinate
<lb/><term type="occupation">chiefs</term> have with one exception chosen sites for their villages
<lb/>conveniently near to that on which we <del type="strikethrough" hand="#U">purpose</del> <add place="above" hand="#U">propose</add> to erect
<lb/>the permanent premises. We purpose to build a house
<lb/>to serve as school and meeting house as soon as possible
<lb/>and then we hope our efforts to impart a knowledge of
<lb/>saving truth will assume a more regular form than at
<lb/>present. <add place="inline" rend="gray" hand="#U">[</add>Among a people as degraded as <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>, no
<lb/>very decided result can be expected unless there is a continuous
<lb/>application of the truth to their minds, and for this <term type="occupation"><w>mission<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-aries</w></term> in <placeName><bloc>Africa</bloc></placeName> have superior advantages to those in countries
<lb/>more densely populated. There the <orgName>mass of the population</orgName>

	

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000562_0002"><!--pb/@n='1v'--></pb>
<lb/>cannot be addressed very frequently or the address followed by
<lb/>continued and pointed appeals to the same individuals. While
<lb/>here we generally have opportunities of directing the highs on
<lb/>to the same minds continuously. And it appears by the
<lb/>Divine blessing to ensure greater <del type="strikethrough" hand="#U">results</del> <add place="above" hand="#U" rend="gray">efforts</add> than desultory efforts
<lb/>between which considerable periods intervene. Conversion among
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> is in general by no means a quick process.
<lb/>Their depravity being <hi rend="underline">subnatural</hi>, some time elapses ere they
<lb/>are raised to the level of sinners in other countries and then
<lb/>they seem to require time again before they can accomodate their
<lb/>minds to the change of thought and motive. There may be
<lb/>a leaning to the side of holiness for a long period but
<lb/>generally a thorough revolution is wrought out before their
<lb/>convictions become embodied in action. <add place="inline" hand="#U" rend="gray">[</add>I visited the
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term> frequently before the establishment of the <orgName>mission</orgName>
<lb/>But it was not <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> my fifth visit that sufficient
<lb/>confidence was inspired to draw forth a cordial invitation
<lb/>for me to settle among them. And this is the only good I can
<lb/>ascertain effected by my itneraries to them. The reason
<lb/>seems to have been <add place="below" hand="#U" rend="gray">^</add> <add place="above" hand="#U" rend="gray">that</add> too long periods intervened between
<lb/>each journey to produce any lasting impression. And this
<lb/>is not to be wondered at, for nothing can exceed the grovelling
<lb/>earthliness of their minds. They seem to have fallen as low in
<lb/>the scale of humanity as human nature can. At some remote
<lb/>period their ancestors appear to have been addicted to animal
<lb/>worship for each tribe is called by some animal. By it they
<lb/>swear and in general neither kill nor eat it, <choice><sic>alledging</sic><corr>alleging</corr></choice> as a cause
<lb/>that these animals are the friends of their tribe. Thus the <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">word</add> <term type="tribe">Batlapi</term>"
<lb/>literally translated is "<hi rend="underline">They</hi> (of the) <hi rend="underline"><term type="animal">Fish</term></hi> <term type="tribe">Bakwain</term> "<hi rend="underline">They</hi> (of the)
<lb/><hi rend="underline"><term type="animal">Crocodile</term></hi>". <term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term>, "<hi rend="underline">They</hi> (of the) <hi rend="underline"><term type="animal">monkey</term></hi>" &amp;c <add place="inline" hand="#U" rend="gray">[</add>But if the
<lb/>conjecture is not wrong they have degenerated from even that
<lb/>impure form of worship and the wisest among them have now
<lb/>no knowledge of it but suppose some of their ancestors must
<lb/>have been called by these names. They have reached the extreme of
<lb/>degradation. When we compare the <term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term> with the <w>inhabit<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-ants</w> around <placeName><settlement type="town">Lattakoo</settlement></placeName>, the latter appear quite civilized, and
<lb/>their present state of partial enlightenment shows that the
<lb/>introduction of the <bibl>gospel</bibl> into a country has a mighty influence

	

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000562_0003"><!--pb/@n='2r'--></pb>
<lb/>even over those by whom it is either not known or rejected. I am
<lb/>not now to be understood as speaking of the <orgName>converts</orgName> nor of the new
<lb/>phases of character the transforming power of the <bibl>gospel</bibl> has developed
<lb/>among them. But I allude to the unconnected and to those other
<lb/>than saving influences of <term type="faith">Christianity</term> which so materially modify
<lb/>the social system at home. On many these influences have
<lb/>operated for years and they have not operated in vain. Hence
<lb/>the mass of the population in the <placeName><region>Kuruman district</region></placeName> are not now
<lb/>in that state the <bibl>Gospel</bibl> found them, and in which the poor
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term> now are. There the existence of Deity is tacitly admitted
<lb/>by nearly all. <add place="below" hand="#U" rend="gray">^</add> <add place="above" hand="#U" rend="gray">those who form</add> The exceptions <add place="below" hand="#U" rend="gray">^</add> <add place="above" hand="#U" rend="gray">to this rule</add> denying it rather on account of
<lb/>attachment to their lusts, than in sober seriousness. <add place="inline" hand="#U" rend="gray">[</add>And I
<lb/>believe the number is but small who have not the idea floating
<lb/>on their minds, that this life is but the beginning of our
<lb/>existence and death but one event in a life which is
<lb/>everlasting. But the <term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term> have had no thoughts on
<lb/>the subject. Their mind is darkness itself, and no
<lb/>influences have ever operated on it but those which
<lb/>have left it supremely selfish. it is only now that <orgName>Christians</orgName>
<lb/>have begun to endeavour to stop the stream which has swept <add place="below" hand="#U" rend="gray">^</add> <add place="above" hand="#U" rend="gray">them</add>
<lb/>generation after generation <del type="strikethrough">of them</del> into darkness. And I may <gap agent="hole" extent="1" unit="words"/>
<lb/>Holy Spirit aid our <del type="strikethrough" hand="#U">efforts</del> <add place="above" hand="#U" rend="gray">endeavours</add>. For without this mighty power all
<lb/>human efforts will be but labour in vain. That power exerted
<lb/>over <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> - raising them from the extreme of degradation-
<lb/>and transforming them into <term type="occupation">worshippers</term> of the Living God constitutes
<lb/><hi rend="underline">the</hi> wonder and <hi rend="underline">the</hi> cause for gratitude in the <orgName><term type="tribe">Bechuana</term> mission</orgName><add place="inline" hand="#U" rend="gray">]</add></p>
<lb/><p>Our <orgName>native</orgName> <term type="occupation">assistant</term> <persName>Mebaloe</persName> has been of considerable value
<lb/>to the <orgName>mission</orgName>. In endeavouring to save my life he nearly
<lb/>lost his own for he was caught and wounded severely. But
<lb/>both before our being laid aside and since recovery he has
<lb/>shown great willingness to be useful. The cheerful manner
<lb/>in which he engages with us in manual labour on the
<lb/>station. And his affectionate addresses to his <orgName>countrymen</orgName>
<lb/>are truly gratifying. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edwards</persName> took him to several villages
<lb/>near the <placeName><settlement type="town">Kurrechane</settlement></placeName> lately in order to introduce him to his
<lb/>work and I intend to depart tomorrow for the same purpose
<lb/>in several villages of <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">the</add> <term type="tribe">Makone</term>, situated <choice><abbr>N.E.</abbr><expan>North East</expan></choice> of this. In all there
<lb/>may be a dozen considerable villages situated at convenient
<lb/>distances around us and we each purpose to visit them statedly



	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000562_0004"><!--pb/@n='2v'--></pb>
<lb/>it would be of immense advantage to the cause had we many such
<lb/><term type="occupation">agents</term>. But after being assured by <choice><orig>bretheren</orig><reg>brethren</reg></choice> on the spot whom
<lb/>I presumed to be intimately acquainted with the state of the <orgName>mission</orgName>.
<lb/>that many such could be got: but after most earnest pleading
<lb/>for and <choice><sic>recieving</sic><corr>receiving</corr></choice> assurances of support from my friends at
<lb/>home. I am sorry to say I cannot succeed according to my
<lb/>desire. Suitable individuals are generally so wedged and dovetailed
<lb/>among their relatives, I fear some time must yet elapse ere
<lb/>that means of spreading the <bibl>gospel</bibl> can be extensively brought
    
<!-- Text interrupted by postal information; continues after break at bottom of page HB 10/30/12 -->
	<cb/>
<lb/>into operation. Still, believing that it is extremely well
<lb/>adapted to the state of this country. And having seen that
<lb/>it has been extensively blessed for the conversion of souls
<lb/>I shall never lose sight of it. And constantly pray that
<lb/>God may incline the hearts of his <orgName>converts</orgName> to feel more
<lb/>compassion for their <orgName>countrymen</orgName> <space dim="horizontal" extent="5" unit="chars"/>Believe me
<lb/><hi rend="right"/>Dear Sir
<lb/><hi rend="right"/><space extent="2" unit="words"/>Yours Affectionately
<lb/><hi rend="right"/><space extent="2" unit="words"/><persName>David <choice><orig>Livingston</orig><reg>Livingstone</reg></choice></persName></p>

<lb/><cb rend="right"/>
<lb/><ab><add place="inline" hand="#U" rend="black"><placeName><settlement type="village">Mabotsa</settlement></placeName> <date when="1844-06-09">June 9, 1844</date> 
<lb/><space extent="1" unit="words"/><persName>David <choice><orig>Livingston</orig><reg>Livingstone</reg></choice></persName>,</add></ab>

	<cb rend="vertical"/>
<lb/><ab><del type="strikethrough" hand="#U">Care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Phillip</persName> <placeName><settlement type="city">Cape Town</settlement></placeName></del>
<lb/>
<lb/>The <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> Arthur Tidman</persName>
<lb rend="center"/><space extent="1" unit="words"/><placeName>Mission House</placeName>
<lb rend="center"/><space extent="2" unit="words"/><placeName>Blomfield <choice><abbr>St.</abbr><expan>Street</expan></choice></placeName>
<lb rend="right"/><space extent="3" unit="words"/><placeName><settlement type="city"><hi rend="underline">London</hi></settlement></placeName></ab>

	<ab>
<lb/><hi rend="underline">single</hi></ab>

	<ab>
<lb/>Received <date when="1844-10-09"><choice><abbr>Oct</abbr><expan>October</expan></choice> 9, 1844</date></ab>


			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>