<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000800">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Arthur Tidman</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Arthur Tidman, 24 September 1853</title>
				<author>Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
				<publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
				<date>2017</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000800</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">University of London. School of Oriental and African Studies; CWM/LMS/Livingstone Wooden Box, item 77</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0320</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Tidman, Arthur, 1792-1868</persName>; </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1853-09-24">24 September 1853</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Sekeletu's Town</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="und">Undetermined</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2013-06-06</date>
				<name xml:id="MW">Megan Ward</name>Initial transcription and XML encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2013-06-09</date>
				<name xml:id="AW">Adrian S. Wisnicki</name>Proofreading.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2013-09-02</date>
				<name xml:id="HFB">Heather F. Ball</name>Additional encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2016-07-26</date>
				<name xml:id="AM">Anne Martin</name>Final Review.
            
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000800_0001"><!--pb/@n='1r'--></pb>
<lb/><p rend="right"><space extent="2" unit="words"/><placeName><settlement type="town">Town of <persName>Sekeletu</persName></settlement></placeName>, <placeName><region>Linyanti</region></placeName>, <date when="1853-09-24">24<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> September 1853</date></p>
<lb/>
<lb/>
<lb/><p><persName>The Reverend Doctor Tidman</persName></p>
<lb/><p rend="center"><space extent="5" unit="words"/>My Dear Sir</p>
<lb/><p><space extent="8" unit="words"/>When the obstacles which caused our <!-- Question again about how to code first line- right-margin coding, or spacing coding? (lett76 ref) HB 9-2-13 --> <!-- Using rend=right right-aligns the entire paragraph, so I don't think this can be right, but I have not changed this AM -->
<lb/>detention at <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> were removed we passed quickly towards the <placeName><region>country
<lb/>of <persName>Sebituane</persName></region></placeName> <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> within one degree of Latitude from this town. All the people
<lb/>were then suddenly laid prostrate by <term type="ailment">fever</term>, except one lad and myself. This
<lb/>caused a further loss of time but through the goodness of God, all recovered.
<lb/>On reaching this, the Southern capital of the <term type="tribe">Makololo</term> we were <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice>
<lb/>with all the demonstrations of welcome which they are accustomed to
<lb/>bestow on their <term type="occupation">chiefs</term>. The idea seemed universal that with a <term type="occupation">missionary</term>
<lb/>some great indefinite good had arrived. Many expected to be elevated
<lb/>at once to a condition equal to that of the <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> and inhabitants
<lb/>of <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName>, of which they had <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> very exaggerated accounts; 
<lb/>others imagined that they would very soon be transformed into civilized
<lb/>men, possessing the clothing, <term type="animal">horses</term>, arms, <choice><orig>waggons</orig><reg>wagons</reg></choice>, &amp;c. of <orgName>Europeans</orgName>,
<lb/>"<persName>Jesus</persName> had not loved their forefathers, hence their present degradation. He
<lb/>"had loved the white men, and given them all the wonderful things they
<lb/>"now possess. And as I had come to <term type="occupation">teach</term> them to pray to Jesus, and to
<lb/>"pray for them, their means would soon be all supplied." A very
<lb/>great deal was expected too from medicines and my liberality in
<lb/>giving things I have <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">not</add> in my posession. Patient industry, and perseverance
<lb/>in learning were never thought of. The <term type="occupation">chief</term> not yet nineteen years
<lb/>of age, frequently pressed me to name something I wished, so that
<lb/>he might by presenting it <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice> his affection, and I suspected,
<lb/>induce me forthwith to commence the work of metamorphosis
<lb/>by means of enchantments. But when I steadily refused to mention 
<lb/>any object I desired more than to secure their temporal and spiritual
<lb/>welfare by means of the <bibl>gospel</bibl>, he seemed to test my sincerity
<lb/>by presenting 4 small and 8 large <term type="animal">elephant</term>'s tusks. I had not
<lb/>an opportunity of refusing them, as they were brought and laid down
<lb/>by <del type="strikethrough">my</del> <add place="above">the</add> <choice><orig>waggon</orig><reg>wagon</reg></choice> during my absence. And then the <term type="occupation">chief</term> came and
<lb/>begged me so earnestly to accept them I felt at a loss how to act.
<lb/>In other circumstances, I should have felt no hesitation in appropriating
<lb/>them to defray expenses incurred entirely on account of this people.  
<lb/>But as it was, though I had no <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">direct</add> evidence that the <term type="occupation">chief</term>'s object was
<lb/>such as I have described, the mere suspicion led me when departing
<lb/>for the <placeName><region>Barotse country</region></placeName>, to request him to leave orders that if any
<lb/><term type="occupation">traders</term> came my <choice><sic>wory</sic><corr>worry</corr></choice> must be used as well as his own. By
<lb/>this means no offence was given which might have been the case  
<lb/>had I at once sent them back. Some months were spent here.
<lb/>for though I soon proposed to examine the country in order to
<lb/>discover a suitable locality for a mission, <persName>Sekeletu</persName> objected first
<lb/>that he had not yet had a satisfactory look at me. He must
<lb/>see me longer. Then he could not think of allowing me to go <add place="below">alone</add><!-- Alone is obviously a catchword as it is the first line of the next page...how do we code to reflect? HB 9-2-13 -->

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000800_0002"><!--pb/@n='1v'--></pb>
<lb/>alone. He must accompany me and see that no evil <choice><sic>befel</sic><corr>befell</corr></choice> me. This required
<lb/>considerable preparation, during which I offered to <term type="occupation">teach</term> the people to read
<lb/>Long and profound were the deliberations over this. They are never in
<lb/>a hurry in <placeName><bloc>Africa</bloc></placeName>, and <term type="occupation">reading</term> seems so supernatural; it cannot be
<lb/>explained to those who know nothing of letters. At last the <term type="occupation">chief</term> told
<lb/>me that he was "afraid that learning to read might change his heart,
<lb/>and make him content with one wife only, as in the case of <persName>Sechele</persName>" It
<lb/>was in vain to urge that the altered state of mind contemplated would be
<lb/>as voluntary as the present. -- So underhand means would be employed
<lb/>to convert, all the means employed being open <term type="occupation">teaching</term>. -- There is no compulsion
<lb/>The truth is taught respecting God's will and the belief or unbelief of the
<lb/>instructed is left as an affair between their judge and themselves.
<lb/>It was just as I have felt in my early years in contemplating that
<lb/>everlasting <term type="occupation">preaching</term> <term type="occupation">praying</term> &amp; <term type="occupation">singing</term> prolonged into Heaven. Quite
<lb/>failing to realize the altered state of mind which produces a relish for
<lb/>such service it seemed as if celestial joys might be endured, rather
<lb/>than be consigned to the other quarter. As I was then subjected to
<lb/>repeated attacks of the <term type="ailment">Fever</term>, I did not press the subject long. But 
<lb/>when we returned from the <placeName><region>Barotse</region></placeName>, an experiment of which I
<lb/>have reason to be satisfied was set on foot. <persName>Sekeletu</persName>'s Father in law
<lb/>and step-father were appointed to learn to read in order that their
<lb/>experience may serve as a beacon to others. Though the plan exhibits
<lb/>the extreme of <orgName>African</orgName> caution, they applied themselves so rigorously
<lb/>they and several others mastered the Alphabet perfectly in one day.
<lb/>But <term type="occupation">teaching</term> to read being less my object in this journey than
<lb/><term type="occupation">preaching</term> the <bibl>gospel</bibl> of peace while endeavoring to discover
<lb/>a salubrious locality for a mission, I shall proceed to relate
<lb/>our visit to the <placeName><region>Barotse country</region></placeName>.</p>
<lb/><p>Two sketches are enclosed, one long and large or just as I put <!-- At this line begins a large bracket around the paragraph in the left-margin HB 9-2-13 -->
<lb/>it down as we went along. The other small - reduced to the Latitudes
<lb/>&amp; Longitudes according <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">to</add> observations taken as opportunities occurred.
<lb/>The large is sent in order that you may see several remarks,
<lb/>which my pen is not fine enough to insert in the reduced scale.
<lb/>and in order that if necessary a more correct reduction may be made.
<lb/>We embarked on the river called everywhere <geogName type="river">Leeambye</geogName> at the village
<lb/>of <placeName><settlement type="village">Sekhosi</settlement></placeName>. <orgName>our fleet</orgName> consisting of 33 canoes and <orgName>our company</orgName> of
<lb/>about 160 men. From the bend at <placeName>Katrina-molelo</placeName> up to the
<lb/>commencement of the <placeName><geogName type="valley">Barotse valley</geogName></placeName>, the country is covered by
<lb/>forest and <term type="insect">Tsetse</term>. The country otherwise seemed well adapted for
<lb/>a residence. Many villages of <term type="tribe">Banyeti</term>, a poor but industrious
<lb/>people are situated on both banks. They are expert as <term type="occupation">hunters</term>
<lb/>of <term type="animal">hippopotami</term> &amp; other animals. They cultivate <term type="plant_foodstuff">grain</term> too extensively
<lb/>At the bend above named commences the rocky bottom which
<lb/>forms cataracts and rapids all the way up to the <placeName><region>Barotse</region></placeName>. The
<lb/>river is of very great beauty and breadth. In the Southern
<lb/>confines of Latitude 16° the high banks open to leave the 
<lb/>river and stretch away to the <choice><abbr>N.N.E.</abbr><expan>North North East</expan></choice> and <choice><abbr>N.N.W.</abbr><expan>North North West</expan></choice> <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> between <!-- Just wanted to confirm these directions are indeed N and not S (DL has similar ones) HB 9-2-13 --><!-- I think they are definitely Ns AM -->
<lb/>twenty and thirty miles apart. The intervening space is <del type="cancelled">the</del>
<lb/>the <placeName><region>Barotse country</region></placeName> and is annually inundated as lower

 
	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000800_0003"><!--pb/@n='2r'--></pb>
<lb/><placeName><country>Egypt</country></placeName> is by the <placeName><geogName type="river">Nile</geogName></placeName>. The valley is covered with coarse succulent grasses
<lb/>which are the pasturage of large herds of <term type="animal">cattle</term> during a portion of the year.
<lb/>There are many villages of <term type="tribe">Makololo</term> in the valley. I have not put down
<lb/>all that I visited and many were seen in the distance. But there are
<lb/>no large towns. The reasons are the mounds on which alone towns
<lb/>and villages are built are all small. And the people require to be separate
<lb/>on account of being rich in <term type="animal">cattle</term>. <placeName><settlement type="town">Nariele</settlement></placeName> does not contain 1000
<lb/>inhabitants. The ridges are thickly strewed with villages. The people
<lb/><term type="tribe">Banyeti</term> and <term type="tribe">Barotse</term> are not rich in <term type="animal">cattle</term> but they require to
<lb/>live apart on account of cultivating large gardens of <term type="plant_foodstuff">sugar cane</term>
<lb/><term type="plant_foodstuff">sweet potato</term>, <term type="plant_foodstuff">manioc</term>, <term type="plant_foodstuff">yams</term>. <term type="plant_foodstuff">millet</term> <term type="plant_foodstuff">maize</term> &amp;c &amp;c. The exhalations
<lb/>which arise from a valley 20 miles broad and about 100 long produce
<lb/><term type="ailment">Fever</term> which is very fatal even among <orgName>natives</orgName>. It prevails most
<lb/>virulently when the waters of inundation are retiring. We went
<lb/>North till we came to the junction of the <placeName><geogName type="river">Leeba</geogName></placeName> or <placeName><geogName type="river">Londa</geogName></placeName> with the
<lb/>main stream <placeName><geogName type="river">Leeambye</geogName></placeName> in 14° 11' south <choice><abbr>Lat.</abbr><expan>Latitude</expan></choice> and found the country
<lb/>presenting the same characteristics as I have described. On returning
<lb/>towards <placeName><settlement type="town">Nariele</settlement></placeName> I went to the <placeName><geogName type="ridge">Eastern ridge</geogName></placeName> in order to examine
<lb/>that and see the establishment of a <term type="occupation">Merchant</term> from the farthest
<lb/>inland station of the <term type="people">Portuguese</term>, opposite <placeName><settlement type="town">Benguela</settlement></placeName>. A stockade had
<lb/>been erected, and a flagstaff for the <term type="nationality">Portuguese</term> banner planted. The houses
<lb/>of the <term type="occupation">merchant</term> and some bastards were in the <orgName>West African</orgName> style. The
<lb/>owner whom I had previously seen at <placeName><region>Linyanti</region></placeName> was absent but his
<lb/><add place="below">^</add> <add place="above"><term type="occupation">servants</term></add> did their utmost to <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice> me kindness. When my <term type="occupation">boatmen</term> prepared my
<lb/>bed outside, They insisted on my occupying their <term type="occupation">master</term>'s couch, and I
<lb/>never felt so grateful in my life for a warm shelter for I was in the
<lb/>cold stage of one of the <term type="ailment">intermittents</term> which continue to plague me after
<lb/>the <term type="ailment">Fever</term>. I thought of going Westward in company with this <term type="occupation">merchant</term>
<lb/>but the sight of <orgName>gangs of poor wretches</orgName> in chains at the stockade
<lb/>moved me resolve to proceed alone. I have not, I am sorry
<lb/>to confess, discovered a healthy locality. The whole of the <placeName><region>country of
<lb/><persName>Sebituane</persName></region></placeName> is unhealthy. The current of the river is rapid as far as
<lb/>we went, and <choice><orig>shewed</orig><reg>showed</reg></choice> we must have been on an elevated table
<lb/>land. Yet the inundations cause the <term type="ailment">fever</term> to prevail very extensively.
<lb/>I am at a loss what to do, But will not give up the case as
<lb/>hopeless. Shame upon us if we are to be outdone by <orgName><orgName>slave</orgName> <term type="occupation">traders</term></orgName>.
<lb/>I met <orgName>Arabs</orgName> from <placeName><geogName type="island"><choice><orig>Zanquebar</orig><reg>Zanzibar</reg></choice></geogName></placeName>, subjects of the <persName>Imanin of <placeName><region>Muscat</region></placeName></persName>
<lb/>who had been quite <choice><sic>accross</sic><corr>across</corr></choice> the <placeName><region>continent</region></placeName>. They wrote Arabic readily <!-- Should Arabic be tagged because a language? And if yes, how coded? HB 9-2-13 -->
<lb/>in <bibl>my note book</bibl> and boldly avowed that Mahomet was the greatest
<lb/>of all the <term type="occupation">prophets</term>. In pursuance of a nobler object than theirs
<lb/>I have determined to try and <choice><sic>fulfil</sic><corr>fulfill</corr></choice> the second part of my enterprise
<lb/><add place="marginleft"><choice><abbr>viz.</abbr><expan cert="high">videlicet</expan></choice></add> open up a way to the coast. I give the <placeName><region>West</region></placeName> the preference because
<lb/>it is nearer. If my calculations are right, the Longitudes of the
<lb/>map of last year are all wrong. The <choice><orig>waggon</orig><reg>wagon</reg></choice> stand for instance instead
<lb/>of being in 26° is 23° 48' or 50'. I have repeated the calculations
<lb/>of Lunar distances again and again and always with the same result
<lb/>But I do not wish this error published <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> I hear from the 
<lb/><term type="occupation">Astronomer</term> at the <placeName><region>Cape</region></placeName> to whom I have submitted the

 	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000800_0004"><!--pb/@n='2v'--></pb>
<lb/>observations and also some occultations by which to test them. But
<lb/>for the destruction of my celestial map by the <orgName>Boers</orgName> I might have
<lb/>determined the Longitudes by occultations alone, they being much more
<lb/>to be depended on than the commmon method of Lunar distances. If then
<lb/>I am right we are nearer the <placeName><region>west</region></placeName> than the <placeName><region>East coast</region></placeName>. <placeName><settlement type="town">Nariele</settlement></placeName> is on
<lb/>23° East and the confluence of the <placeName><geogName type="river">Leeba</geogName></placeName> or <placeName><geogName type="river">Londa</geogName></placeName> not much more.
<lb/>I have not had time to work out the Longitude of that point but the
<lb/>river <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">(<placeName><geogName type="river">Leeba</geogName></placeName>)</add> comes from the capital of a powerful state whose <term type="occupation">chief</term> is
<lb/>reported to be friendly to foreigners. If I am permitted to return by
<lb/>this <term type="occupation">chieftain</term> it will be water carriage for perhaps <choice><orig>⅔</orig><reg>2/3</reg></choice><hi rend="sup">ds</hi> of the way.
<lb/>And should a mission be established there in time it will be all the
<lb/>better - I intend to try for <placeName><settlement type="city">Loanda</settlement></placeName> because though farther many
<lb/><term type="people">English</term> live there. I go on <term type="animal">horse</term>back. <choice><orig>Waggon</orig><reg>Wagon</reg></choice> travelling being reported
<lb/>impossible on account of forests and numerous rivers. The <term type="people">Portuguese</term>
<lb/>are carried <unclear>up</unclear> in hammocks hung on poles. Two <orgName>slaves</orgName> carry a man
<lb/>It does not look well. The <term type="nationality">Portuguese</term> maps are all constructed from
<lb/><orgName>native</orgName> reports, so no <choice><sic>dependance</sic><corr>dependence</corr></choice> can be placed on them. Many tribes
<lb/>inhabit the country all more or less accustomed to the visits of
<lb/>strangers. The greatest difficulty I apprehend is that of making our
<lb/>objects understood. Their languages bear a close affinity to the <placeName><region>Barotse</region></placeName><!-- Should Barotse be termed as region, language, or tribe here? HB 9-2-13 -->
<lb/>dialect but this I was compelled to give up reducing.</p>
<lb/>
<lb/><milestone unit="section" rend="line"/>
<lb/><p>I never had a touch of the <term type="ailment">Fever</term> till my employment became
<lb/>sedentary here. I have had eight attacks since The last when going
<lb/>North of <placeName><settlement type="town">Nariele</settlement></placeName> was very severe, being accompanied with large
<lb/>loss of florid blood. It thinned me much. But on no occasion
<lb/>did I <subst><del>lay</del><add place="over-text">lie</add></subst> by. Fits of vertigo probably from exhaustion troubled
<lb/>me for some time. Everything seemed to rush to the left and I had
<lb/>to lay hold on something to prevent a fall. These induced me to give
<lb/>up collecting <placeName><region>Barotse</region></placeName> words and other materials for a <bibl>dictionary</bibl>. <!-- Should Barotse be termed as region, language, or tribe here? HB 9-2-13 -->
<lb/>Though still thin the <term type="ailment">intermittents</term> have left, and I am only waiting for
<lb/><seg type="weather">the rain to commence</seg> to start for the <placeName><region>West</region></placeName>. They begin next month
<lb/>It will be seen that <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">rs</hi> <choice><abbr>L.</abbr><expan>Livingstone</expan></choice></persName> had better not come to the <placeName><region>Cape</region></placeName> to
<lb/>meet me at the time appointed. If I reach <placeName><settlement type="city">Loanda</settlement></placeName> in <date when="1854-02">February</date>
<lb/>I must return with the people again and will be here instead of
<lb/>at the <placeName><region>Cape</region></placeName>. The time unavoidably lost by <orgName>Boers</orgName> and <term type="ailment">Fever</term>
<lb/>renders a little extension of my furlough necessary. Then if the
<lb/><orgName>Directors</orgName> sanction a permanent station or any other form of
<lb/>labour for this miserable <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName>, some other mode of travelling
<lb/>in from the <placeName><region>west</region></placeName> must be arranged. A few kind words
<lb/>to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> <choice><abbr>L.</abbr><expan>Livingstone</expan></choice></persName> from you, will I think make her willing to prolong
<lb/>her stay in <placeName><country>Scotland</country></placeName>. Although the prospect seems dark for
<lb/>the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName> it may not be quite so gloomy as I have drawn
<lb/>it The <orgName>natives</orgName> describe the mortality as very great and that
<lb/>attacks of <term type="ailment">fever</term> are excessively frequent &amp; severe. I have given
<lb/>you their ideas. But my own except at times are not so sombre 
<lb/>I tried <orgName>native</orgName> remedies in some of the attacks to which I was
<lb/>subjected in order to discover if they had any valuable means of 
<lb/>cure but After being stewed in vapour baths, and smoked <del type="strikethrough">in</del>
<lb/>over fires of green plants in hot potsherds &amp;c &amp; I find that our 
<lb/>own medicines are much more efficacious and safer. I have not lost

    

	<pb n="0005" facs="liv_000800_0005"><!--pb/@n='3r'--></pb>
<lb/>a single patient by <term type="ailment">fever</term>. And if I had been able <supplied cert="high">to</supplied> regulate my diet I should
<lb/>not have been subjected to so many attacks. As it was we were frequently
<lb/>compelled to eat on the principle of laying in a stock for the next day. <orgName>My
<lb/>own people</orgName> being too weak to go with me and the <term type="tribe">Makololo</term> cook only in the
<lb/>evenings when travelling. Then if I left the canoe in order to visit a village
<lb/>there are <del type="cancelled">soo</del><add place="above">so</add> many branches of the river intersecting the valley everywhere
<lb/>I was always wet up to the middle. I fear to give you either a too <w>encourag<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-ing</w> or discouraging report. I am afraid to incur the responsibility of
<lb/>inducing you to regard the case as hopeless. The <term type="nationality">American</term> <term type="occupation">missionaries</term>
<lb/>report the <placeName><region>Gaboan</region></placeName> station as not warranting the long established belief
<lb/>that <orgName>Europeans</orgName> could not live there. And my firm conviction is
<lb/>that even the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName> of <placeName><bloc>Africa</bloc></placeName> merits a fair trial. Such with the
<lb/>help of God and your sanction I am determined to give it.)</p><!-- There's an end parenthesis here but no opening one earlier. -->
<lb/>
<lb/><milestone unit="section" rend="line"/>
<lb/><p>The <orgName><orgName>slave</orgName> <term type="occupation">trade</term></orgName> was prohibited here, and a large <orgName>party of <term type="tribe">Mambari</term></orgName>
<lb/>who were here endeavoring in vain to renew it, fled precipitately as
<lb/>soon as they heard that I had crossed the <placeName><geogName type="river">Chobe</geogName></placeName>. The <term type="tribe">Makololo</term> <w>remon-
<lb break="no"/>strated</w> with them but they asserted that I would take all their
<lb/>goods from them because they dealt in <orgName>slaves</orgName>. A <term type="person">Portuguese</term>
<lb/>came from the <placeName><region>West</region></placeName> but he finding no market remained only
<lb/>three days and returned. It was different in the <placeName><region>Barotse</region></placeName> or
<lb/><placeName><region>Northern division</region></placeName> of the country. Another <term type="nationality">Portuguese</term> <term type="occupation">merchant</term>
<lb/>came thither and by means of an <term type="occupation">underchief</term> who had some
<lb/>pretensions to the <orgName>chieftainship</orgName> obtained free access to all the 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Banyeti</term>, <term type="tribe">Batoka</term> and <term type="tribe">Bashukulorupo</term> villages East of the
<lb/><geogName type="river">Leeambye</geogName>. <unclear cert="medium">There</unclear> the stockade which gave great offence to the <!-- "There" looks to have been written over Then, but cannot be 100% certain HB 9-2-13 -->
<lb/><term type="tribe">Makololo</term> was erected without the knowledge or permission
<lb/>of the <term type="occupation">chief</term>. They would have commenced hostilities at
<lb/>once in order to drive the whole <orgName><orgName>slave</orgName><term type="occupation">trading</term> party</orgName> out of
<lb/>the country but a variety of considerations induced me to
<lb/>intercede for them and by that intercession they will be allowed
<lb/>to depart in peace. Probably <choice><sic>decieved</sic><corr>deceived</corr></choice> by the assurances
<lb/>of the disaffected <term type="occupation">underchief</term> they seem to have had no idea
<lb/>of the risk they were running. But when the <term type="occupation">conspirator</term>
<lb/>came down with the intention of cutting off <persName>Sekeletu</persName>, He was
<lb/>instantly seized and killed. His fathers and several others <!-- "s" in "fathers" is fading- how code if <gap> doesn't allow for text within brackets? HB 9-2-13 -->
<lb/>were cut off in the most cold blooded manner. And when I <w>remon<supplied>-</supplied>
<lb break="no"/><choice><sic>stated</sic><corr>strated</corr></choice></w> against the shedding of human blood, the <term type="occupation">counsellors</term>
<lb/>quietly remarked, "You see we are still <orgName>Boers</orgName>, we are not
<lb/>yet taught" But for this unfortunate affair no <term type="occupation">trading</term>
<lb/>in <orgName>slaves</orgName> would have been allowed. In this they have the precedent
<lb/>of the former <term type="occupation">chief</term> of the <term type="tribe">Barotse</term> who refused to grant the
<lb/><term type="tribe">Mambari</term> permission to visit his country as <orgName><orgName>slave</orgName> <term type="occupation">traders</term></orgName>

    

	<pb n="0006" facs="liv_000800_0006"><!--pb/@n='3v'--></pb>
<lb/>A cannon of small calibre was found in the possession <term type="occupation">underchief</term>
<lb/>mentioned</p>
<lb/><p>The country in the direction of <foreign xml:lang="und"><placeName><geogName type="waterfall">Mosioatunya</geogName></placeName></foreign> has high mountains
<lb/>and the <placeName><region>Batoka country</region></placeName> is a high table land without trees except along
<lb/>the rivers. Healthy spots might be found in both of these but
<lb/>in neither did I feel it duty to travel because the vicinity of
<lb/><persName>Mosilikatse</persName> renders it impossible for <term type="tribe">Makololo</term> or any other tribe 
<lb/>to reside there. A change may yet be effected among the <term type="tribe"><choice><orig>Matibele</orig><reg>Matebele</reg></choice></term>
<lb/>which would change the present aspect of affairs</p>
<lb/><p rend="right"><space extent="3" unit="words"/>Believe me Dear Sir</p>
<lb/><p rend="right"><space extent="5" unit="words"/>Yours Affectionately</p>
<lb/><p rend="right"><space extent="7" unit="words"/><persName>David <choice><orig>Livingston</orig><reg>Livingstone</reg></choice></persName></p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>