<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_001828">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Thomas S. Livingstone</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Thomas S. Livingstone, 10 October 1862</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2010</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_001828</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">National Library of Scotland; MS. 10701, ff. 138-139</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1862-10-10">10 October 1862</date></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2010-01-20</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>Transcribed by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
			<change when="2017-06-18" who="#MW">Proofing and XML encoding</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_001828_0001"/><!--pb/@n='01'-->
<lb/><p><placeName>Rovuma Bay</placeName> <date when="1862-10-10">10<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> Oct<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi></p>
<lb/><p rend="right">1862.</date> </p>
<lb/><p>My Dear <persName>Tom</persName>, </p>
<lb/><p>We have been up the <placeName>Rovuma</placeName> 114 
<lb/>miles in a straight line from the coast but 
<lb/>156 by adding the Latitude &amp; Longitude together, 
<lb/>and having given <placeName>Oswell</placeName> an account of our 
<lb/>voyage up from <placeName>Zambesi</placeName> to <placeName>Johanna</placeName> I now 
<lb/>give you some information about our trip 
<lb/>up this river. The Orestes is a fine large Man of war 
<lb/>with 21, 68 powder guns came to <placeName>Johanna</placeName> as 
<lb/>we were about to leave for this coast, and 
<lb/><persName>Captain Gardner</persName> very kindly offered to tow 
<lb/>us over, and there by save our coals for our 
<lb/>return. She walked away with the Pioneer as 
<lb/>if she had nothing behind her. Up and down 
<lb/>over huge waves, for it blew very fresh the 
<lb/>Poor little Pioneer had to tumble &amp; tear along 
<lb/>till snap went a cable as thick as your 
<lb/>thigh, and we had to get up stream on our own 
<lb/>hook. And soon came into this bay. <persName>Captain 
<lb/>Gardner</persName> went up with us for two days to 
<lb/>see us fairly started. He turned at a little Lake 
<lb/>called "<placeName><geogName type="lake">Chidia</geogName></placeName>" about 3 miles long &amp; one wide. 
<lb/>It lies among the hills, and before parting 
<lb/>with our good friends we walked up to 
<lb/>see it, and some ebony trees which were 
<lb/>needed. I saw some bits of fossil wood 
<lb/>lying on a sandstone rock. This we know 
<lb/>as a sign that coal lies beneath and having 
<lb/>said so was rather glad when a few days 
<lb/>afterward I found bits of coal in the sand 
<lb/>in the bed of <placeName><geogname type="river">Rovuma</geogName></placeName>. he people knew 
<lb/>that it would burn and said it came 
<lb/>down with the water but they knew not whence</p>

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_001828_0002"/><!--pb/@n='02'-->
<lb/><p>While we were up the hills looking at the Lake a marine 
<lb/>officer said he had been fired at by the <orgName>natives</orgName> 
<lb/>three times - we did not believe it, as they seemed 
<lb/>quite friendly and we were equally so with them, 
<lb/>but set a <choice><sic>gaurd</sic><corr>guard</corr></choice>. On proceeding farther up we 
<lb/>spent Sunday on the North bank and an old man 
<lb/>having come to us &amp; understood that we were 
<lb/>quite friendly lots of people visited us - In the 
<lb/>afternoon I walked up to their villages but found 
<lb/>them very much alarmed. They shewed no 
<lb/>surprise at our warship and we could make 
<lb/>ourselves but little understood as the language 
<lb/>differs much from those on the <placeName><geogName type="river">Zambesi</geogName></placeName>.
<lb/>but seeing women and children all fleeing 
<lb/>I called to a man not to fear as I was only 
<lb/>looking at the country. He asked if I would 
<lb/>drink &amp; bought me a cup of native beer. there 
<lb/>was much cultivation though the country was 
<lb/>covered with thick forest &amp; brush-wood which 
<lb/>has always to be cleared away. Above this we 
<lb/>found people living on sand banks in the River. 
<lb/>They have villages on the land &amp; plenty of corn 
<lb/>stowed away in the woods but are afraid of being 
<lb/>stolen themselves. Stealing <add place="above">&amp; selling</add> each other seems the 
<lb/>only trade they have. In one village there were 
<lb/>two human heads cut off. they tried to induce us 
<lb/>to land among them but when we stopped it was 
<lb/>only to make purchases and go on. At last a 
<lb/>large party followed us evidently bent on mischief 
<lb/>but we were kind to them and paid them well 
<lb/>for dragging one of the boats a short distance. At 
<lb/>a narrow part where the passage comes close to 
<lb/>a high bank they began to <del type="strikethrough">fire</del><add place="above">shoot</add> their arrows on us 
<lb/>we stood and expostulated with them a long time - 
<lb/>and having induced them to come to the boats 
<lb/>gave them over thirty yards of cloth as a token of 
<lb/>friendship. They repaid our kindness by telling 
<lb/>us to go on and at once firing a volley from 
<lb/>muskets and bows at us. Four bullets went through 
<lb/>the sail of my boat. They evidently expected that 
<lb/>we should run away and seeing that we did not 
<lb/>they did. &amp; on our return we only looked at each 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_001828_0003"/><!--pb/@n='03'-->
<lb/>other. They had no cause whatever for wishing our 
<lb/>blood. "We <choice><orig>wont</orig><reg>won't</reg></choice> let white people go up this river." there 
<lb/>are a lot of river pirates, and as soon <add place="above">when</add><del type="strikethrough">as</del> we passed 
<lb/>them, all were friendly, and much trade is carried on 
<lb/>by means of canoes. Seven canoes went with us 
<lb/><unclear cert="low">three deep</unclear>. They come down to buy salt with rice - 
<lb/>I was glad that we used every means in our power 
<lb/>to avoid collision but we see that <orgName>slave slealers<orgName> are blood 
<lb/>thirsty murdererers. The river has a table land on each 
<lb/>side which looks like hills 500 feet high till we get up 
<lb/>about 60 or 70 miles. We then leave the hills &amp; have 
<lb/>what seems a large plain with small granite hills in 
<lb/>front. This continues till we come among rocks 
<lb/>in the stream with numerous passages between, 
<lb/>through these small canoes pass with ease but our 
<lb/>boats would have been smashed had we gone on 
<lb/>as we returned. We were informed that about 
<lb/>30 miles in front the <placeName><geogName type="river">Rovuma</geogName></placeName> is joined by the 
<lb/><placeName><geogName type="river">Lienda</geogName></placeName> which comes from the hills on the East 
<lb/>side of the Lake. The <placeName><geogName type="river">Rovuma</geogName></placeName> comes from the 
<lb/>West but is narrowed by rocks. Our object in 
<lb/>coming was to ascertain if this river will afford 
<lb/>a better outlet from the Lake region than that 
<lb/>to which the Portuguese lay claim. We found the 
<lb/>river unusually and excessively low. Tsetse 
<lb/>abounds but should Englishmen be established 
<lb/>on <placeName><geogName type="lake">Lake Nyassa</geogName></placeName> they will undoubtedtly prefer 
<lb/>carrying their commerce out by this outlet 
<lb/>to paying dues to Portuguese for the <placeName>Shire</placeName> &amp; 
<lb/><placeName><geogName type="river">Zambesi</geogName></placeName> which they now virtually blockade 
<lb/>against free trade. This looks a more 
<lb/>healthy looking river than any we have seen - 
<lb/>the rocky table land I have referred to rises 
<lb/>from the banks though sometimes there is 
<lb/>a mile of fine level alluvial soil between 
<lb/><gap extent="1" unit="lines" agent="damage"/>unwilling to 
<lb/><gap extent="1" unit="lines" agent="damage"/> in the 
<lb/><gap extent="1" unit="lines" agent="damage"/>of the people on 
<lb/>the <placeName>Shire</placeName> who were more alarmed when we 
<lb/>first came than the Makonde of <placeName><geogName type="river">Rovuma</geogName></placeName>.


	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_001828_0004"/><!--pb/@n='04'-->
<lb/>To leave them now would be just leaving them 
<lb/>to be eaten up by the <orgName><placeName>Tette</placeName> slavehunters</orgName>. We propose 
<lb/>therefore to go back and put Lady Nyassa on 
<lb/>her Lake by way of <placeName>Shire</placeName> which is much more 
<lb/>our country than it is Portuguese. In that land 
<lb/>too the remains of dear Mama rest. Her body
<lb/>consecrates that soil and will always be interesting 
<lb/>to us. She died in the cause to which our lives 
<lb/>are consecrated. It took us 15 days to go up and 10 
<lb/>to come down. We know but little more than 
<lb/>the river. The people cultivate oil seeds largely 
<lb/>they put hives on the trees as at <placeName><geogName type="river">Londa</geogName></placeName> &amp; honey is 
<lb/>plentiful. Cotton is cultivated and Ebony abundant 
<lb/>their clothing is very scanty, and calico is in great 
<lb/>demand. At our furthest point and at another 
<lb/>part of the way we come to the <orgName>slave</orgName> route from 
<lb/>the lake to <placeName>Quiloa</placeName><placeName>(Kilwa)</placeName> there an English 
<lb/>merchant might introduce lawful trade with 
<lb/>advantage to the cause of humanity if merchants 
<lb/>would try and direct their trade so as to 
<lb/>produce the greatest amount of good- </p>
<lb/><p>Your friend <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Rae</persName> had to turn back with 
<lb/><persName>Captain Gardner</persName> from a little illness - we had 
<lb/>fever in our party but it did not last long. 
<lb/>The trip gave us a month in the boats - we 
<lb/>never stopped except Sundays &amp; one half day 
<lb/>and came back pretty brown &amp; tired. You 
<lb/>will let <persName>Agnes</persName><persName>Robert</persName> &amp; <persName>Oswell</persName> have a 
<lb/>reading of this but I <choice><orig>dont</orig><reg>don't</reg></choice> like many people 
<lb/>to see my letters. I shall write to <persName>Agnes</persName>
<lb/>next, but it will be a good while before 
<lb/>I can give an account of our operations 
<lb/>at <placeName><geogName type="lake">Nyassa</gegoName></placeName>. We shall go back to <placeName>Johanna</placeName>
<lb/><placeName>Mohilla</placeName> and then to the <placeName><geogName type="river">Zambesi</river></placeName>. <persName>Captain 
<lb/>Gardner</persName> wished me to meet him at 
<lb/><placeName><country>Mozambique</country></placeName> on New years day but I hope 
<lb/>to be in the <placeName>Zambesi</placeName> then. God bless 
<lb/>&amp; guide you<reg>.</reg><gap extent="2" unit="words" agent="damage"/></p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>
