<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000491">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Parents and Sisters</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Parents and Sisters, 29 September 1841</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2007-10-30</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000491</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">National Library of Scotland; MS. 10701, ff. 12-13</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0036</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Parents and Sisters</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1841-09-29">29 September 1841</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kuruman</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2007-10-30</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Intial Transcription by Caroline Overy
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2008-02-05</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>Proof by Chris Lawrence
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000491_0001"/><!--pb/@n='12r'-->
<addSpan spanTo="#p12r-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left margin of p12r'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent"><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he heat is beginning. North winds sweeping over the long <unclear cert="low">tract</unclear> of country in that direction become 
<lb/>so heated when they come here they are like the blast of a furnace, sometimes crumble the grass into 
<lb/>powder</p><anchor xml:id="p12r-01"/>
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Kuruman</placeName> 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> September 1841</p>
<lb/><p>My Dear Parents &amp; Sisters</p>
<lb/><p>In case I have no other opportunity of writing you 
<lb/>previous to setting off towards the north I now begin. I am sorry I 
<lb/>had not one ready yesterday when a Griqua passed this way 
<lb/>I sent several to friends &amp; I hope this wont be long behind 
<lb/>any of which you may hear<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>I am busy learning the language which is not remarkably 
<lb/>difficult the only impediment is a want of proper aids such 
<lb/>as Dict<hi rend="sup">s</hi><reg>,</reg> Grammars &amp;c<reg>.</reg> I hope however soon to conquer 
<lb/>it &amp; then preach Christ &amp; him crucified to the <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="illegible"/><term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term><reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I have a great deal of work in the way of helping the infirm 
<lb/>&amp; many of them seem attached to me on account of little 
<lb/>attentions shewn to themselves or children of whom they are 
<lb/>remarkable fond. Mothers are mothers I see all over 
<lb/>the world if only a little if only a little of poor humanity remains uncorrupted 
<lb/>by the customs of sin. How is my mother<reg>?</reg> I Hope comfortable<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>May God bless her and give her an inheritance with the 
<lb/>blessed in Heaven by sanctifying her to himself<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>I have got no letter as yet from you &amp; have now 
<lb/>written you 5. It is no easy matter to have all the 
<lb/>correspondence to oneself but I hope they are on their way<reg>.</reg> 
<lb/>Well what shall I tell you about, I suppose Janet &amp; Agnes would like a lion story or something of that 
<lb/>sort that I cant however give for I have not dared to 
<lb/>look one in the face. A terrible fellow was shot a short 
<lb/>distance from this &amp; the sight of his dead body so (shall I 
<lb/>say) frightened me I have no wish to have intercourse 
<lb/>with his majesty again. I would rather meet with 
<lb/>some <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">members</add> of the Royal families among men than of beasts 
<lb/>for the former in this country at least are an 
<w>insignific-<lb break="no"/>ant</w> race of beings, distinguished for nothing but 
<lb/>superior impudence in begging &amp; generally worse looking 
<lb/>than any of their attendants. I have been in 
<lb/>company with <persName>Waterboer</persName> the Griqua chief. He is 
<lb/>rather an exception in point of intellect although 
<lb/>in bodily appearance he is a little bushman 
<lb/>of the <term type="tribe">Matebele</term><reg>.</reg><choice><reg>O</reg><orig>o</orig></choice>ur chief was here a few weeks ago for the 
<lb/>purpose of being baptized &amp; admitted into the church, a feeble 
<lb/>decrepit old man tottering into the grave. After he had 
<lb/>carelessly heard the offers of mercy for about 25 years 
<lb/>we trust he has now turned to the Lord. His 
<lb/>baptism has caused great excitement through the whole 
<lb/>country particularly amongst the violent opponents of the 
<lb/>gospel. I hope it will lead others to think of themselves 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000491_0002"/><!--pb/@n='12v'-->
<lb/>&amp; look for mercy before it is too late. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> are 
<lb/>great beggars, indeed they seem to make it a matter of conscience 
<lb/>to neglect no opportunity of asking &amp; a refusal does not by 
<lb/>any means put them out if it is done in a jocular way<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>It is only occasionally they think it worth while to tell you 
<lb/>what their opinion of you is &amp; really it is ludicrous enough 
<lb/>to hear their epithets, instead of getting vexed by them they 
<lb/>always powerfully excite my risible faculties. Only think of an 
old grey headed <del type="strikethrough"><unclear cert="medium">fat</unclear></del> man or woman coming forward &amp; saluting 
<lb/>me with the epithet "Father, king, Gentleman &amp;c &amp;c and then 
<lb/>after a little conversation requesting as a great favour a knife 
<lb/>handkerchief or only a little bit of my shirt to bind their heads &amp; 
<lb/>when I give them the hint that though I much wish to gratify 
<lb/>my children it is quite out of my power. My father or mother 
<lb/>adopts quite a different style &amp; tells me "Verily thou art a dog 
<lb/>tiger" &amp;c "and whoever marries you will marry a wolf"<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hese paternal addresses have one good effect they usually bring 
<lb/>something to my mind which sets them off in good humour<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>When <persName><unclear cert="low">Moteeke</unclear></persName> was with us during the whole fortnight he never 
<lb/>begged any &amp; for this he formerly was notorious, the sisterhood 
<lb/>will be amused to know I was physician to his majesty but 
<lb/>I nearly got into disgrace by shouting out to him as he lay 
<lb/>asleep in the middle of the path at midday with his karross 
<lb/>over his head<reg>.</reg> Hallo my lad this is not night. He awak
<lb/>ed with a start when I beheld who it was I stooped 
<lb/>down &amp; examining his eyes <unclear cert="medium">told</unclear> him I should give him 
<lb/>some ointment for them in the afternoon. He seemed 
<lb/>quite well pleased &amp; thanked me for my care of him<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>When talking to him of his past life he always 
<w>commen-<lb break="no"/>ced</w> crying like a child. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his is remarkable for a 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bechuana</term> &amp; particularly for a king, they never weep 
<lb/><choice><sic>untill</sic><corr>until</corr></choice> the Spirit works upon their hearts &amp; then they 
<lb/>weep like children. Sometimes in the chapel they 
<lb/>hide their heads in their karosses &amp; creep under the 
<lb/>forms to avoid the eyes of the preacher. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his however 
<lb/>wont do they then scream out &amp; occasionally rush 
<lb/>out of chapel fleeing with all their might. It has often 
<lb/>made me wonder for in performing most 
<lb/>severe surgical operations they sit both men &amp; 
<lb/>women as if they had no feeling - In one case of 
<lb/><term type="medical">fungous</term> 4 inches in length &amp; nearly 2 in breadth <add place="above">nearly 1/2<!--half--> in height</add> I employed a 
<lb/>severe but quick mode of getting rid of it. During the operation 
<lb/>I expected him to get up &amp; dance from the pain<reg>.</reg> But no. He 
<lb/>sat <choice><sic>immoveable</sic><corr>immovable</corr></choice> &amp; talked with as composed a countenance as 
<lb/>if he felt nothing, "A man like me never cries" said he 
<lb/>with the greatest composure. "Its only children who cry"<reg>.</reg>

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000491_0003"/><!--pb/@n='13r'-->
<lb/>The spirit of God alone can affect their health. Without this aid all our efforts 
<lb/>must be ineffectual<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>There are many believers scattered up &amp; down the country even far from 
<lb/>this &amp; where all is opposition (apparantly) the missionaries are pleased to 
<lb/>know that there is piety even in the centre of the opposition. Pious 
<lb/>women particularly are often found where none <del type="strikethrough">were</del> <add place="above">are</add> expected 
<lb/>and often it is impossible to hold intercourse with them as it 
<lb/>would subject them to great annoyance from their heathen 
<lb/>husbands. Only a <unclear cert="low">shred</unclear> of this can be said where much 
<lb/>is needed. We hope however the Lord will uphold his 
<lb/>own work in their hearts &amp; enable them to 
<lb/>persevere unto the end. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he women have hard work 
<lb/>to perform amongst the <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> - they cultivate the ground 
<lb/>and build the houses while <del type="strikethrough"><unclear cert="low">the</unclear></del> "Lords of the Creation" sew karosses 
<lb/>milk the cattle &amp; hunt or sleep. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey make very neat 
<lb/>builders indeed. It would puzzle their men to do half as well 
<lb/>and if the latter are spoken to about it they reply "O it is good for 
<lb/>them" "it makes them strong" &amp;c.  It is only a very few of 
<lb/>the younger people who can be <unclear cert="high">inclined</unclear> to do a little of women's 
<lb/>work &amp; I dare say their own opinion that hard work makes 
<lb/>makes their wives look soon old has more influence over them 
<lb/>than any of our arguments. When sitting round a fire 
<lb/>by our waggon I have sometimes tried to let the women have 
<lb/>a share of it by requesting the men to give way, but 
<lb/>that was out of the question. "We are the kings" was <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/>
<lb/>a sufficient reason for the women being compelled to <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/><supplied reason="damage">quite</supplied>
<lb/>behind in the cold. How would <persName>Agnes</persName> like this system of things<reg>?</reg></p>
<lb/><p>The old spectacles <add place="above"><unclear cert="low">ks?</unclear></add> mother put with my bag were a most acceptable 
<lb/>present to an old woman who made great efforts to learn to 
<lb/>read but her nose not being of proper shape for the antique 
<lb/>thing to adhere <del type="strikethrough">by</del> <add place="above">on</add> their own natural way she must hold them 
<lb/>always to with the hand. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he beads are invaluable - money being 
<lb/>of very little use &amp; rather a losing concern as they will take nothing 
<lb/>but silver &amp; they always prefer a few beads or a hankerchief 
<lb/>to it <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/>. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hamilton</persName> has just returned from an <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">itinerating</add> journey 
<lb/>of a month or nearly 200 miles towards E by north. He met 
<lb/>great opposition in some places &amp; encouragement in others<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>He is quite well in health and so I am thankful to say we 
<lb/>all are. <persName>Fergus</persName> &amp; <persName>David</persName> still within reach of 
<lb/>you I should have written them but feared they 
<lb/>might be removed ere my letters arrived. I hope to write 
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Naismith</persName> soon as also <unclear cert="low">S<hi rend="sup">l</hi> &amp; J<hi rend="sup">n</hi></unclear>. Remember me kindly to 
<lb/>them. Could they not write me my letter will cross 
<lb/>theirs on the way if they do. How is <persName>Duncan</persName>? I suppose 
<lb/>gone to America - &amp; <persName>I <unclear cert="medium">Wheeler</unclear></persName>? D<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. The sun shines 
<lb/>down our chimnies here. Yours affect<hi rend="sup">y</hi> D L</p>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000491_0004"/><!--pb/@n='13v'-->
<lb/><p>I can write no more to <persName>Charles</persName><reg>.</reg> He is a shabby fellow for a 
<lb/>correspondent. Tell him I say so. I think frequently of you 
<lb/>all but this language engages mixing thoughts. I am never 
<lb/>pleased with the progress I make, the natives do jumble 
<lb/>their words so together &amp; then they are so stupid at 
<w>underst-<lb break="no"/>anding</w> if there is any blunder in my sentences. But I hope 
<lb/>soon to overcome. I shall after returning live entirely 
<lb/>amongst them &amp; speak not a word of English, I must 
<lb/>conquer. Yesterday a man came to carry medicine for his 
<lb/>wife whom I had just been to see. I gave him instructions 
<lb/>to let her have it immediately. Before I could say stop the 
<lb/>fellow had it whisked into his own stomach. Although not 
<lb/>very agreeable (castor oil) <add place="above"> a large quantity</add> he yielded prompt obedience to what he 
<lb/><anchor xml:id="envelopePosition" type="positionMarker"/>thought I wished, &amp; the reason was I did not use the phrase most 
<lb/>commonly employed. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he people here are much like what the 
<lb/>patriarchs must have been. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey are all nomadic if they 
<lb/>can possibly find a few cattle. Some are mighty hunters, not 
<lb/>your red coated gentry after a fox - I know men here who 
<lb/>have attacked lions &amp; killed them with no other weapons than 
<lb/>an asagai in one hand &amp; the Kaross wound round the other 
<lb/>arm to thrust into his mouth - the mill is more original 
<lb/>still than that of the two women which I have seen in use 
<lb/>in the colony, a flat stone (broad) with a little roundish one to rub 
<lb/><addSpan spanTo="#p13v-01" place="marginright"><!--addSpan/@place='right margin of p13v'--></addSpan>with a sort of shoving motion as women in Scotland do with 
<lb/>their clothes at the bottom of the tub. I can understand 
<lb/>why <persName>Rachel</persName> felt so much at being barren, nothing is so 
<lb/>great a curse to a B. wife as want of children, they are really 
<lb/>miserable if without &amp; children are so valuable. <anchor xml:id="p13v-01"/></p>

<ab type="envelope">
<address>
<addrLine>Care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Phillip</persName>, Church Square
<lb/>
Cape Town</addrLine>
<addrLine><persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Livingston</persName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>Almada St.</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>Hamilton</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine>N B</addrLine>
<addrLine>single sheet</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>