<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P5 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000490">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Joseph J. Freeman</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Joseph J. Freeman, 23 September 1841</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London, UK</pubPlace>
				<publisher>University College London</publisher>
				<date>2012</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000490</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">University of London. School of Oriental and African Studies; CWM/LMS/Livingstone Wooden Box, item 16</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0035</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Freeman, Joseph J., 1794-1851</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1841-09-23">23 September 1841</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kuruman</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2012-03-08</date>
				<name xml:id="JM">Jared McDonald</name> initial transcription and XML encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-04-26</date>
				<name xml:id="KS">Kate Simpson</name> proofreading.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-07-07</date>
				<name xml:id="HFB">Heather F. Ball</name> XML editing.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-09-12</date>
				<name xml:id="AW">Adrian S. Wisnicki</name> XML editing.
            
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000490_0001"><!--pb/@n='1'--></pb>
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> <date when="1841-09-23">23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> September 1841</date></p>
<lb/><p>Dear Sir</p>
<lb/><p>That I might be able in my first communication
<lb/>to inform the Directors respecting my prospects of usefulness
<lb/>in the cause of <persName>Christ</persName> amongst the Heathen I have delayed
<lb/>announcing my arrival at <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> for a period of nearly
<lb/>two months. <space dim="horizontal" extent="3" unit="chars"/>We came hither on the <date when="1841-07-31">31<hi rend="sup">st</hi> July</date> and
<lb/>received a most cordial welcome from the <choice><orig>bretheren</orig><reg>brethren</reg></choice>
<lb/><persName>Hamilton</persName> and <persName>Edwards</persName>, the warmth of it awakened
<lb/>in my bosom feelings of fraternal affection to both
<lb/>and these subsequent intercourse has tended
<lb/>much to increase</p>
<lb/><p>As it is in accordance with my own long cherished 
<lb/>desire and the intentions of the Directors that my
<lb/>chief energies should be directed to the evangelization
<lb/>of the tribes in the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName> the mode in which
<lb/>this can best be effected has become a topic
<lb/>of intense interest in many conversations, we have 
<lb/>had together. <space dim="horizontal" extent="3" unit="chars"/>The decision of the Directors, from 
<lb/><choice><sic>judgements</sic><corr>judgments</corr></choice> matured by long experience is that an
<lb/>extensive native agency is the most efficient mode
<lb/>of spreading the gospel.  In this decision most
<lb/>of the missionaries I have seen fully concur,
<lb/>The question therefore where are these to be got for
<lb/>the extensive field beyond us has become to me
<lb/>one of peculiar interest,  Whilst in <placeName><country>England</country></placeName>
<lb/>I had formed the opinion that great things
<lb/>might be done by means of this mission, -
<lb/>that it might be formed into a sort of
<lb/>focus from which might diverge in every
<lb/>direction the beams of Divine truth but after

	

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000490_0002"><!--pb/@n='2'--></pb>
<lb/>having personally inspected most of the surrounding localities
<lb/>in <choice><orig>connexion</orig><reg>connection</reg></choice> with this station I am compelled partially
<lb/>to relinquish the hope in so far as very extended operation<supplied>s</supplied>
<lb/>are concerned, the great desideratum is a want of
<lb/>population,  There is no want of success considering the
<lb/>smallness of the number who usually attend the preaching of
<lb/>the word, nor can we consider even the attendance small
<lb/>when we remember the paucity of people actually within
<lb/>a reasonable distance of the church.  What in <placeName><country>England</country></placeName>
<lb/>we should call a fair proportion pay respect to the gospel
<lb/>by their presence and a larger proportion still give
<lb/>gratifying evidence of <choice><sic>attatchment</sic><corr>attachment</corr></choice> to its principles by their
<lb/>walk and conversation. But the population being
<lb/>small even although there is a large proportion of
<lb/>believers there must be a small number qualified
<lb/>if with nothing more with only the willing mind to endu<supplied>re</supplied>
<lb/>hardship for the benefit of their fellow men. I should
<lb/>not have called your attention to this which appears
<lb/>the only unfavourable feature in the mission had there
<lb/>been any probability of an increase of population
<lb/>The cause of the steady decrease instead of augmentation
<lb/>of inhabitants has been in operation for a great numbe<supplied>r</supplied>
<lb/>of years, the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName> is quiet, as the gospel extends its
<lb/>influence peace will become more permanent and unless
<lb/>the <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> entirely relinquish their present mode of
<lb/>life, - hold something else in estimation as their chief
<lb/>riches than cattle We cannot expect that <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName>
<lb/>will ever become populous.  Regard for the welfare
<lb/>of their cattle will always lead them to choose more 
<lb/>healthy locations for them than what this district presents</p>
<lb/><p>That the Directors may judge whether my fears are well
<lb/>grounded I may mention that within a circle of 8 or 10 miles
<lb/>around the station there are not a thousand inhabitants. 
<lb/>The total number of native houses, (occupied &amp; unoccupied)
<lb/>on this station is 185, <choice><orig>⅕</orig><reg>1/5</reg></choice> at least should be deducted
<lb/>for the unoccupied or used only as sort of storerooms
<lb/>and sleeping apartments for the unmarried females

	

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000490_0003"><!--pb/@n='3'--></pb>
<lb/>But if we take this number and take as an average the highest
<lb/>from frequent personal inspection I should say we can possibly
<lb/>give, <choice><abbr>avg.</abbr><expan>average</expan></choice> 5 We have only 925 as the total number of men
<lb/>women and children.  The above average exceeds by 2 that 
<lb/>usually taken by the French missionaries in estimating the <w>popu
<lb break="no"/>-lation</w> around them. <space dim="horizontal" extent="3" unit="chars"/>There is however a much
<lb/>larger population about 16 miles off. Probably there are
<lb/>in that location 1500 souls, Amongst whom also the gospel
<lb/>has met with considerable success,  In another direction
<lb/>about 30 or 35 miles distant there are two villages each
<lb/>containing from 150 to 200 inhabitants</p>
<lb/><p>Although the population is small in this district there is
<lb/>no want of inhabitants farther to the North and <w>North-
<lb break="no"/>East</w>. At <placeName><settlement type="village">Taons</settlement></placeName> (pronounced Towns) which lies about
<lb/>East by North of this <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Owen</persName> of the Church Missionary
<lb/>Society estimated the population at 15 or 20,000, the <choice><orig>bretheren</orig><reg>brethren</reg></choice>
<lb/>itinerate thither although it is nearly 100 miles distant
<lb/>and though but little positive success has attended their
<lb/>endeavours the prospect is cheering, the truth is working
<lb/>its way and will soon prevail, even the violent <gap agent="damage" extent="5" unit="chars"/><w><supplied cert="high">oppo-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-ition</w> manifested in encouraging for anything is better <gap agent="damage" extent="4" unit="chars"/><supplied cert="high">than</supplied>
<lb/>stupid indifference</p>
<lb/><p>In view of the limited choice we are reduced to at this
<lb/>station I may be allowed to suggest that we make the most
<lb/>of whatever agents we can find, Although desirable that
<lb/>they have somewhat more than decided piety it is I
<lb/>conceive not absolutely necessary,  Evils may arise from
<lb/>their ignorance and mistakes but good will certainly be
<lb/>done and I should hope it will abide while the effects
<lb/>of their deficiencies will vanish before more efficient
<lb/>agents whom they themselves may now be instrumental 
<lb/>in partially preparing,  Making the most of every man
<lb/>under them seems to have been the reason, by the blessing 
<lb/>of God, of the great success of the <choice><orig>bretheren</orig><reg>brethren</reg></choice> at <placeName><settlement type="village">Griqua Town</settlement></placeName></p>
<lb/><p>I purpose accompanying <choice><abbr>Br.</abbr><expan>Brother</expan></choice><persName>Edwards</persName> in his journey
<lb/>to the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName> as I am informed by the <choice><orig>bretheren</orig><reg>brethren</reg></choice> who are
<lb/>best able to judge it will be advantageous for me in many
<lb/>respects. I shall become better acquainted with the habits
<lb/>of the people, their language and by exclusion from

	

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000490_0004"><!--pb/@n='4'--></pb>
<lb/>from all European society for some time I hope to slip more
<lb/>readily into their mode of thinking which is essentially different
<lb/>from ours. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edwards</persName> seems intimately acquainted with
<lb/>native character and there is little fear but we shall be kindly
<lb/>received more especially by those who have again &amp; again sent
<lb/>messages for missionaries, There is reason to believe that the
<lb/><add place="inline">˄</add><add place="above">names</add> of <persName>Hamilton</persName>, <persName>Edwards</persName> &amp; <persName>Moffat</persName> are well known hundreds of
<lb/>miles beyond us as the nomadic habits of the people very much
<lb/>favours the transmission of news - We take with <add place="below">^</add><add place="above">us</add> two of
<lb/>the best qualified of our members here for the purpose of planting
<lb/>them as native teachers in some promising locality, the expenses
<lb/>of one of whom (if I do not receive in time the concurrence of
<lb/><persName>D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Phillip</persName>), I shall endeavour to defray myself. the work is
<lb/>urgent. souls are perishing: and what more efficient
<lb/>introduction can there be, for the new missionaries which
<lb/>I hope will soon follow us, than the residence for some
<lb/>months previously of one or two native teachers</p>
<lb/><p>I am exceedingly gratified to observe the confidence which 
<lb/>has been inspired into the minds of the <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> of the
<lb/>efficacy of our medicines . by a very successful care of treatment 
<lb/>which happened a day or two after our arrival. The <choice><orig>bretheren</orig><reg>brethren</reg></choice>
<lb/>say it is altogether unprecedented and an <choice><sic>unsuccesfull</sic><corr><choice><orig>unsuccessfull</orig><reg>unsuccessful</reg></choice></corr></choice> case
	<cb/>
<lb/>since has not in least abated their confidence. I feel <choice><orig>thankfull</orig><reg>thankful</reg></choice>
<lb/>and hope it will by the blessing of God, enable <add place="below">^</add><add place="above">me</add> to win
<lb/>their attention to a much more important topic than
<lb/>the preservation of their bodies, even the salvation of
<lb/>their immortal souls.</p>
<lb/><p rend="right">Faithfully &amp; Affectionately 
<lb/>yours
<lb/><persName>David <choice><orig>Livingston</orig><reg>Livingstone</reg></choice></persName></p>
	<ab>
<lb rend="center"/>Care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>Phillip</persName>, <placeName>Church Square</placeName>
<lb rend="right"/><placeName><settlement type="city">Cape Town</settlement></placeName>
<lb/><persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> J. J. Freeman</persName>
<lb/><placeName>Mission House</placeName>
<lb/><placeName>Bloomfield St.</placeName>
<lb/><placeName><settlement type="city">London</settlement></placeName></ab>
<!-- Postal information on letter- not transcribed HB 9/11/12 -->
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>