<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P5 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000459">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to John Arundel</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to John Arundel, 2 July 1839</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London, UK</pubPlace>
				<publisher>University College London</publisher>
				<date>2012</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000459</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">University of London. School of Oriental and African Studies; CWM/LMS/Livingstone Wooden Box, item 11</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0005</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Arundel, John, 1778-1848</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1839-07-02">2 July 1839</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Ongar, Essex</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2012-03-03</date>
				<name xml:id="AJS">AJ Schmitz</name> Initial transcription and XML encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-24-04</date>
				<name xml:id="KS">Kate Simpson</name> Proofreading
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-07-07</date>
				<name xml:id="HFB">Heather F. Ball</name> XML editing.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-09-12</date>
				<name xml:id="AW">Adrian S. Wisnicki</name> XML editing.
            
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000459_0001"><!--pb/@n='1r'--></pb>
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName><settlement type="town">Ongas</settlement> </placeName> <date when="1839-07-02">2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> July /39</date></p>
<lb/><p>Dear Sir</p>
<lb/><p>Having been informed a few days ago 
<lb/>by <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Cecil</persName>, that there had been some intimation of a wish 
<lb/>on the part of the Directors, that I should be employed in the 
<lb/><placeName><bloc>West Indies</bloc></placeName> in preference to <placeName><region>South Africa</region></placeName>, and being 
<lb/>desirous to enter upon that sphere of labour, and, I trust, that 
<lb/>only, in which I may be able most efficiently to advance the 
<lb/>great cause of our Blessed Redeemer;  Permit me to state 
<lb/>the following particulars for their consideration, previous to 
<lb/>coming to a final decision on my case -</p>
<lb/><p>When first I felt the expansive benevolence of the 
<lb/>gospel in my heart, It became an interesting question to 
<lb/>me,  How can I spend the remainder of my days in bringing 
<lb/>my fellowmen to the enjoyment of the same happiness and 
<lb/>peace? <space dim="horizontal" extent="3" unit="chars"/> After much prayer for the Divine direction, it 
<lb/>appeared to be in accordance <supplied cert="high">with</supplied> the will of Providence that I should
<lb/>attempt to obtain a medical education in order to render service 
<lb/>to the cause of missions. by that means;  After much exertion 
<lb/>and overcoming considerable difficulties, in which I was sensibly 
<lb/>assisted by the good hand of providence, I spent two years 
<lb/>in that study, all which time, in the event of my being 
<lb/>sent to the <placeName><bloc>West Indies</bloc></placeName>, might be considered as lost, For I 
<lb/>could not use the knowledge which I have obtained 

       

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000459_0002"><!--pb/@n='1v'--></pb>
<lb/>without in all probability incurring the displeasure of medical 
<lb/>men who have gone thither for the sake of gain, and it is 
<lb/>well known how easily medical men can destroy each <choice><sic>others</sic><corr>other's</corr></choice>
<lb/>influence and usefulness, when an unsuccessful case occurs, 
<lb/>as many hundreds of young men have experienced in this and 
<lb/>other countries; <space dim="horizontal" extent="3" unit="chars"/>In this manner might not only that means 
<lb/>which I had hoped to have exerted to subserve the cause 
<lb/>of religion be rendered inoperative, but likewise my moral 
<lb/>and religious influence be weakened-</p>
<lb/><p>Added to this I may be permitted to mention, that 
<lb/>settling in the <placeName><bloc>West Indies</bloc></placeName> has always appeared so much 
<lb/>like the ministry at home that my thoughts have not at all 
<lb/>been attracted in that direction, but always to other parts of 
<lb/>the world</p>
<lb/><p>I beg leave to state likewise in reference to a 
<lb/>proposal to send me out in the present year, my earnest 
<lb/>desire for more education, This has always been my 
<lb/>wish and the more I contemplate the magnitude of the 
<lb/>work, the greater does the necessity of good preparation 
<lb/>for it appear to be; even when commencing study 
<lb/>in prospect of being a missionary, so fully was I 
<lb/>convinced of its importance, that it formed no 
<lb/>part of my plan, to offer myself to any society, <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice>
<lb/>suitably educated.  Lest I should be sent out 
<lb/>unfurnished for the work, and I at length did</p>

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000459_0003"><!--pb/@n='2r'--></pb>
<lb/><p><persName>Rev.<hi rend="sup">d</hi> J. Arundel</persName></p>
<lb/><p><placeName>Mission House</placeName></p>
<lb/><p><placeName>Bloomfield <choice><abbr>St.</abbr><expan>Street</expan></choice></placeName></p>
<lb/><p><placeName><settlement type="city">London</settlement></placeName></p><!-- There is additional text here that is not in DL's hand. AW 9/12/12 --><!-- Postal information on letter- not transcribed HB 9/11/12 -->
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>