<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000642">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Margaret Sewell</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Margaret Sewell, 20 September 1847</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2007-07-17</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000642</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">National Library of Scotland; MS. 20312, ff. 4-5</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0176</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Sewell, Margaret</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1847-09-20">20 September 1847</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kolobeng, Bakwain Country</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2007-07-17</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Intial Transcription by Caroline Overy
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2007-11-06</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Christopher Lawrence</name>Proof by Chris Lawrence
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000642_0001"/><!--pb/@n='4r'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Kolobeng</placeName>, <placeName>Bakwain Country</placeName> 20 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi></p>
<lb/><p rend="right">1847</p>
<lb/><p>My very Dear Friend</p>
<lb/><p>It is now a considerable time since I heard from you<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>But supposing a letter or a parcel to be on its way I begin to asnwer it by 
<lb/>anticipation. Your last kind favour we <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> &amp; duly acknowledged while 
<lb/>at <placeName>Kuruman</placeName> in March or May last. <hi rend="underline">We</hi> (you see I use the language of 
<lb/>sovereigns &amp; great folks now) were very much reduced in strength during 
<lb/>our first years residence among the <term type="tribe">Bakwain</term>, and took a tour Eastward 
<lb/>by way of recruiting it, having at the same time some important 
<w>mission-<lb break="no"/>ary</w> duties to perform among the tribes in that direction. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he journey 
<lb/>did me good but my better half became as thin as a lath. Having 
<lb/>scarcely any provisions at home &amp; a meeting of Committee being about 
<lb/>to be held at <placeName>Likatlong</placeName> we were glad to pay a visit to <placeName>Kuruman</placeName><reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Our visit proved very beneficial to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L.</persName> We got a daughter there too 
<lb/>and when we returned we were gratified by witnessing that love for 
<lb/>us had not been diminished among the <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> by our absence<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he expressions made use of by them were so extravagant I should 
<lb/>feel if I attempted to commit them to paper that I was writing 
<lb/>what the Irish call "blarney". <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>heir deeds subsequently have 
<lb/>been more pleasing than their words. <placeName>Chonuane</placeName> was a bad spot 
<lb/>for a European to live in. Water very scanty &amp; bad so we could 
<lb/>not procure necessary food by irrigation. Both Chief &amp; people 
<lb/>saw this &amp; had been searching for a better locality for us. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey told 
<lb/>me what they had done and asked what I wished them to do for they 
<lb/>"were determined to cleave to us wherever we went". They had selected 
<lb/>the <placeName>Kolobeng</placeName> a fine stream about 40 miles N.W. of <placeName>Chonuane</placeName> &amp; after 
<lb/>examining it we were glad to remove to the blessed sound of gurgling 
<lb/>waters, you have your nightingales<reg>,</reg> thrushes<reg>,</reg> blackbirds &amp; canaries. Of all 
<lb/>the birds in the world commend me to the merry frogs whistling with 
<lb/>might &amp; main their midnight carols. We thank Him through whom 
<lb/>alone we have obtained influence among the heathen and we pray 
<lb/>it may be a pledge of their future conversion. We have of course 
<lb/>to begin again at the beginning. We have built temporary houses 
<lb/>already. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he country being thickly wooded we did not need to go 
<lb/>far for materials. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he chief without any suggestion from 
<lb/>us told us that the meeting house must be his work entirely<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I wish you to be at no expense whatever said he. It shall be 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000642_0002"/><!--pb/@n='4v'-->
<lb/>my work to build a house for God who is the defence of my town"<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Subsequently he desired me to name the dimensions, form &amp;c believing 
<lb/>that I should only be a looker on, but we or our party said, it is 
<lb/>for the God of all so we shall all work at it. Unfortunately we are 
<lb/>obliged by the advanced state of the season to decide to decide on a tem
<lb/><!--no hyphen-->porary meeting house. We must attend as soon as possible to 
<lb/>the wants of the body. If we do not sow we shall be starving again 
<lb/>by the winter. We get up a temporary building now in order 
<lb/>that our work of systematic instruction may go on in all 
<lb/>weathers, and also during the period in which we must attend to 
<lb/>our bodily wants.</p>
<lb/><p>I believe now the <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> believe that we are their real friends<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his is a great step in advance. We never got so far with the 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term>. After leaving the latter people poor <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edwards</persName> was 
<lb/>obliged to pay a fine for harsh expressions made use of by him to the 
<lb/>chief. Had he not done so <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName> would have had no place among 
<lb/>our stations. I am sorry he lost his temper - loss of temper is loss of 
<lb/>influence but keep in temper &amp; you may say what you like 
<lb/>to this people - the <persName>chief of Mabotsa</persName> became enraged in turn &amp; 
<lb/>he &amp; his people expelled <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Inglis</persName>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey proceeded to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edwards</persName><reg>'</reg>
<lb/>house for the same purpose as they had to <persName>Inglis'</persName> but a fine 
<w>appeas-<lb break="no"/>ed</w> them for the time. My heart is sore for <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName>, I deeply regret 
<lb/>taking <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edwards</persName> there however all may yet turn out well<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I suppose you know <persName>Inglis</persName> domiciled in my house there. If 
<lb/>you wish me to tell how he goes on I must say easy enough<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>He wanted to be a great man among us. The <term type="tribe">Bahurutse</term> wished 
<lb/>a missionary from <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey sent repeated messages to him 
<lb/>to come to them &amp; take them into their own country <add place="below">^</add><add place="above"><unclear cert="low">Mosega</unclear></add> and place 
<lb/>a missionary among them. It was simply the result of 
<w>un-<lb break="no"/>bounded</w> confidence in him as a tried friend of <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term><reg>.</reg>
<lb/>We are Independents but we need not tell the natives so. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> I.</persName> thought 
<lb/>otherwise. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he <term type="tribe">Bahurutse</term> removed half way to their own country 
<lb/>&amp; <persName>Inglis</persName> the whole way. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he former <add place="below">^</add><add place="above">now</add> play falsely with him - they have 
<lb/>not confidence in one who can declare unfriendly feelings to their 
<lb/>old friend. After expulsion from <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName> he sat down at a 
<lb/>fountain to which he expects the <term type="tribe">Bahurutse</term> to come. He who 
<lb/>so often declared his determination to go home if he did not 
<lb/>get a <unclear cert="low">sphere</unclear> embracing a population of some thousand 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000642_0003"/><!--pb/@n='5r'-->
<lb/>lives with a mere handful of people expecting a tribe to come to him<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>In the mean time the precious contributions of the poor Christians in 
<lb/>England are being expended in doing what? -- I have seen so 
<lb/>much evil under the sun since I left your roof I begin to think that 
<lb/>madness &amp; folly &amp; evil are necessary ingredients in our present 
<lb/>sphere. O your question related to <persName>Inglis<reg>'</reg> wife</persName>. She is at <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName>
<lb/>living with the <persName>Edwards</persName>. How she does I do not know. Not a 
<lb/>single Mokhatla child comes to school. What services are conducted 
<lb/>are attended by the dependants of the mission - the <term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term> never 
<lb/>come since <add place="below">^</add><add place="above">the</add> period of the fine mentioned above. <choice><reg>S</reg><orig>s</orig></choice>o how she gets 
<lb/>on is to me a mystery - I suppose <persName> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi><unclear cert="low">Mather</unclear></persName> mentioned some 
<lb/>troubles he has had in India from the follies of others. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey are to be 
<lb/>found everywhere<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>How is my dear friend <persName>Maclehose</persName>? Be sure &amp; tell me. I do not 
<lb/>write him now. I would but can not. He does not even send 
<lb/>my account<reg>.</reg> Present my kind regards to him <add place="above">&amp;</add> his better half &amp; assure 
<lb/>him of my unabated esteem. A friend upbraided me for 
<lb/>writing long letters to one who never answered &amp; yet wrote 
<lb/>short ones to him who always gave double or treble the quantity<reg>,</reg>
<lb/>this paralysed my pen. I must hear from him now. </p>
<lb/><p>We were much gratified by a letter from the former <persName>Miss Leslie</persName><reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Let us know about her as much as you can. Never forget 
<lb/>the immortal  <persName>Howie</persName> if you hear ought of him - also <persName>Dickson</persName>
<lb/>&amp; <persName>Holland</persName>. I hear from <persName>Watt</persName>. Where is <persName><unclear cert="medium">Best</unclear></persName> &amp; <persName>Ayrton</persName>
<lb/>&amp; old <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wildman</persName> - I have heard of <persName>Charles</persName> &amp;c from <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pyne</persName>
<lb/>whom I believe you now know better than formerly -</p>
<lb/><p>Of <persName>Mokoteri</persName> I hear no good. The poor fellow wishes much to 
<lb/>get married but is unable to get a wife of any respectability - He lately 
<lb/>went on oxback to court &amp; the Father of the family applied a rod to 
<lb/>his back forthwith. He is a Griqua &amp; felt insulted by a degraded person presuming to ask one of his daughters - Poor fellow this is 
<lb/>different treatment from writing names in Albums &amp; giving 
<lb/>locks of his curly poll to London exquisites - he was spoiled &amp; 
<lb/>now reaps the fruits of his pride &amp; folly.</p>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000642_0004"/><!--pb/@n='5v'-->
<lb/><p><choice><reg>Y</reg><orig>y</orig></choice>ou do not forget us in your prayers. May you enjoy every 
<lb/>temporal &amp; spiritual blessing &amp; believe me yours ever</p>
<lb/><p rend="right">Very Affectionately</p>
<lb/><p>D Livingston</p><anchor xml:id="envelopePosition" type="positionMarker"/>
<lb/><p><persName><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he Ashtons</persName> are very well at present. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey lost a fine little boy 
<lb/>whilst we were at <placeName>Likatlong</placeName>. We have a little boy running 
<lb/>about &amp; a little girl in her mothers arms. Poor little niggers<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I often look at them here in the heart of Africa &amp; think, what 
<lb/>do I not -? May He who feeds the Ravens Remember them<reg>.</reg></p>
<ab type="envelope">
<address>
<addrLine><del type="strikethrough" hand="#hand01">Care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Philip</persName> Cape Town</del></addrLine>
<addrLine><persName>M<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">rs</hi></hi> Sewell</persName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>57. Aldersgate St.</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><hi rend="underline">London</hi><!--various postmarks--></addrLine>
</address>
</ab>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>