<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_001528">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Joseph B. Braithwaite</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Joseph B. Braithwaite, 26 January, 7 February 1860</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2008</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_001528</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">National Library of Scotland; MS. 20312, ff. 57-63</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0985</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Braithwaite, Joseph B., 1818-1905</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date from="1860-01-26" to="1860-02-07">26 January, 7 February 1860</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">River Zambesi</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2008</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>Intial Transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2008-01-03</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>First proof
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2008-02-28</date>
				<name xml:id="JB">Janet Browne</name>second proof
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_001528_0001"/><!--pb/@n='57r'-->
<lb/><p><placeName>River Zambesi</placeName> 26<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">th</hi></hi> January 1860. </p>
<lb/><p>My Dear Friend </p>
<lb/><p>I <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> your welcome letter 
<lb/>of March last a few days ago, and thank you for the 
<lb/>enclosure of your friend from <placeName>Leeds</placeName>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he defects we 
<lb/>have unfortunately experienced in the <term type="boat">Ma Robert</term> or 
<lb/>rather the "Asthmatic" are so numerous that it 
<lb/>would require a treatise as long as a lawyer's 
<lb/>specification of any simple subject to give you 
<lb/>an idea of them, and they have inflicted so much toil 
<lb/>that a feeling of sickness comes over me when I 
<lb/>advert to them. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he only feasible explanation of the 
<lb/>conduct of the contractors I can see, is that probably 
<lb/>the Zambesi Expedition and the Great Niger Expedition 
<lb/>being alike, <del type="strikethrough">Will</del> all must either perish or be so ill 
<lb/>as to be unable ever to notice any defects. 
<lb/>"<choice><reg>W</reg><orig>w</orig></choice>orks which will last a few months will do all - 
<lb/>they require". "why waste time on works so soon to perish." </p>
<lb/><p><hi rend="underline">Steel Plate is a failure</hi>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his is no fault of the Lairds. 
<lb/>It is excessively hard, does not wear at all by friction, 
<lb/>but decomposition sets in universally on both 
<lb/>surfaces, and <del type="strikethrough">hard</del> black scales, strongly magnetic, 
<lb/>are formed with surprising rapidity. In twelve 
<lb/>months our Funnel, Furnace - Deck &amp; bottom 
<lb/>were made like sieves even though the plates 
<lb/>were well protected by Peacock's Patent paint. 
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his vessel was formed pretty nearly on the 
<lb/>plan proposed by your friend. <figure><!--<graphic url="LETT1074-1.gif"/>--><figDesc/></figure> in 
<lb/>length 75 ft. - coupled below. The 
<lb/>coupling below being a bolt which simply slipped into 
<lb/><choice><sic>into</sic><corr>notext</corr></choice> a hole in another<reg>.</reg><figure><!--<graphic url="LETT1074-2.gif"/>--><figDesc/></figure> The least wear in the 
<lb/>bolt or hole such as actually took place in the 
<lb/>first week, allowed of a pumping action 
<lb/>between the compartments and perpetual 
<lb/>wet in the cabin was the consequence. 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_001528_0002"/><!--pb/@n='57v'--> 
<lb/>One would not blame any one for this either. 
<lb/><choice><reg>B</reg><orig>b</orig></choice>ut the calculation of displacement was according 
<lb/>to <persName>M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">r</hi></hi> Macgregor Laird</persName> that she should draw 13 
<lb/>inches only and if loaded up to two feet she could 
<lb/>carry from "ten to twelve tons" of cargo. We lately 
<lb/>tried her, without water in the boiler or fuel, or crew 
<lb/>or provisions or tools, and in salt water she 
<lb/>drew 23 inches. She drew 19in. at <placeName>Liverpool</placeName> without 
<lb/>the house or hatches on - and with her crew 
<lb/>a small stock of provisions, and one days fuel 
<lb/>on board she draws 31 inches. The water being 
<lb/>then only 5 inches from the paddle shafts. </p>
<lb/><p>The form - an imitation of Niger canoes - is long 
<lb/>narrow &amp; turned up at the ends. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his to make her 
<lb/>turn quickly! It is followed by the negroes because 
<lb/>the trees will not allow greater breadth, and the 
<lb/>bent up end allows the<del type="strikethrough">m</del><add place="above">canoe</add> to slide up a bank instead 
<lb/>of giving a shock. Here canoes are often made 
<lb/>of crooked trees &amp; the craft being bent like the stock 
<lb/>from which it is hollowed - some future contractor 
<lb/>may spend other people's money in Zambesi canoe 
<lb/>shaped vessels as if it were the best adapted for 
<lb/>turning round corners.! We drew more water 
<lb/>from <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Laird</persName> following the "Niger canoe form" 
<lb/>than your friend's model would do, from so 
<lb/>much having been bent up, and have derived no 
<lb/>advantage whatever from the use of the steel plate. 
<lb/>You have no idea of what our wretched vessel 
<lb/>is from the photograph. <hi rend="underline">That</hi> is not a photograph 
<lb/>of a vessel, but the photograph of a picture. 
<lb/>Whoever suspects a photograph of telling lies? No 
<lb/>one. You will be able to look on your photograph 
<lb/>in a new light I discovered before I left <placeName>Liverpool</placeName>. 
<lb/>This form of vessel is most unmanagable for 
<lb/>if she touches at all it is on the middle compartment 
<lb/>she rests and she goes round on a pivot rather 
<lb/>than move off, unless she has way on her 
<lb/>we cannnot turn but by a long circuit<reg>.</reg></p>

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_001528_0003"/><!--pb/@n='58r'-->
<lb/><p>The engine was beyond doubt made for some 
<lb/>other purpose. <persName>M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">r</hi></hi> Laird</persName> denies this, but his own 
<lb/>foreman stated this to be the case. <add place="above">to <persName>M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">r</hi></hi> Rae</persName>, our engineer</add>. The cylinder is a 
<lb/>low pressure one applied to a high pressure 
<lb/>engine <figure><!--<graphic url="LETT1074-3.gif"/>--><figDesc/></figure> This large recess shews what is stated. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he 
<lb/>supply pipe is considerably smaller than the 
<lb/>feed pipe, and the valves of the pump being 
<lb/>of India rubber are perpetually going wrong. 
<lb/>When she was tried at <placeName>Liverpool</placeName> two 
<lb/>men were employed constantly working 
<lb/>the pump. The boiler tubes are much too 
<lb/>few and situated all at one side, and chiefly 
<lb/>below the level of the fire. The draught being 
<lb/>insufficient to clear them, ashes fall <add place="above">back</add> from 
<lb/>the furnace, and choke the half of the tubes 
<lb/>after a few hours steaming - until the 
<lb/>steam is generated from one side the other 
<lb/>remains cool. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he hand may be held in the 
<lb/>water from right hand cock while the other 
<lb/>will scald. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he bridge made of bricks is 
<lb/>a continual nuisance by breaking down 
<lb/>and with the best wood on the river - Lignum 
<lb/>vitae dried, we cannot move up the river so 
<lb/>fast as a man can walk. A ton of this 
<lb/>fuel will not give 7 hours steam. We tried a 
<lb/>ton of ebony this week and it did not give 
<lb/>five hours, our speed being scarcely a mile 
<lb/>an hour against a three knot current. It is 
<lb/>heart breaking work I assure you. We spend 
<lb/>far more time in wood cutting than steaming<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Nor can she tow. We were obliged to leave 
<lb/>our pinnace at <placeName>Senna</placeName> a few days ago because 
<lb/>she held her back so much. Yet we were 
<lb/>promised ten or rather over ten knots. </p>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_001528_0004"/><!--pb/@n='58v'-->
<lb/><p>So long as we had coals we did pretty well but no sooner 
<lb/>did the <term type="boat">Pearl</term> leave than I saw that we had been 
<lb/>victimized. With common wood we could not 
<lb/>carry food for our crew. Any canoe beats us 
<lb/>unless we are going down stream. No one will 
<lb/>ever believe the toil we have been put to in wood 
<lb/>cutting. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he quantity consumed is enormous &amp; 
<lb/>we cannot get sufficient for speed into the furnace<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>It was only a dogged determination not to be beaten 
<lb/>that carried me through. Of late we have been spending 
<lb/>precious time tinkering which might have been 
<lb/>employed in doing good service to the cause of 
<lb/>civilization in <placeName>Africa</placeName>. But all will come 
<lb/>out right at last. We are not alone. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hough 
<lb/>truly we deserve not His Presence he encourages 
<lb/>the trust that it is granted by the word. I am 
<lb/>with you always even unto the end of the world. </p>
<lb/><p>I have thus mentioned some of the defects 
<lb/>of our wretched punt. Unfortuntely a mail 
<lb/>bag was lost on the bar off <placeName>Kongone</placeName> lately &amp; we 
<lb/>don<reg>'</reg>t know whether we are to get a vessel 
<lb/>in lieu of that which <persName>Bedingfeld</persName> for his own 
<lb/>ends got me to reject. But I wrote to my 
<lb/>friend <persName>James Young</persName> of <placeName>Glasgow</placeName> to get me 
<lb/>another out of my own money if £2000 
<lb/>will do it. We want one for the Lake 
<lb/>region. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hat is the slave market and the 
<lb/>prospect seems fair of cutting out a large 
<lb/>portion of the supply from the slave ports 
<lb/>on the East coast by the introduction of 
<lb/>the gospel and lawful commerce on 
<lb/><placeName>Nyassa</placeName>. I think the object a worthy one 
<lb/>to employ the money which Providence lately 
<lb/>put into my power. I do not touch on  
<lb/>that funded for my family. We want one which 
<lb/>will be capable of being unscrewed into pieces of 
<lb/>say 500 lbs each<reg>.</reg>

	<pb n="0005" facs="liv_001528_0005"/><!--pb/@n='59r'--> 
<lb/>Steel plate will not do. We send home <persName>M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">r</hi></hi> Rae</persName> who 
<lb/>well knows all our wants and what would be 
<lb/>suitable. <persName>M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">r</hi></hi> Tod</persName> of <placeName>Glasgow</placeName> has been thought 
<lb/>of for making the vessel proposed. We require 
<lb/>strength - little draught of water &amp; power equal 
<lb/>at least to the heavy lumbering canoes of this 
<lb/>river. A condensing engine of forty horse at least, 
<lb/>with furnaces proper for burning wood. We 
<lb/>think <persName>M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">r</hi></hi> Rae</persName> will be able to see that we get the 
<lb/>proper thing. <choice><reg>I</reg><orig>i</orig></choice>f the Government grants the means 
<lb/>for one boat it will be a help for we require 
<lb/>to establish a communication with the <placeName>Cape</placeName><reg>.</reg>
<lb/>It is impossible for you to <choice><sic>concieve</sic><corr>conceive</corr></choice> how 
<lb/>backward every thing is here. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>nd the Portuguese are 
<lb/>not to be depended on. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>heir establishments 
<lb/>are only small penal settlements, and as no women 
<lb/>are sent out the state of morals is frightful. The 
<lb/>worst disease universal either hereditary or acquired. 
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he only chance of success is away from them. 
<lb/>Nothing would prosper in their vicinity. 
<lb/><persName>Baines</persName> our artist was left at <placeName>Tette</placeName> in order to 
<lb/>spare him exposure to <term type="disease">malaria</term> and he fell before 
<lb/>the moral atmosphere of the place - was dishonest - 
<lb/>- diseased &amp;c and we were obliged to send him 
<lb/>away. Very likely he may turn round &amp; blame me 
<lb/>though he begged to be allowed to remain without 
<lb/>salary before I had spoken a word about his 
<lb/>conduct. <persName>Bedingfeld</persName> tried all he could to incite 
<lb/>the Portuguese against the Expedition as soon 
<lb/>as he returned, and even wrote letters to the Boletim 
<lb/>of Mozambique to damage us - This may appear 
<lb/>odd to our friends at home as they have no idea 
<lb/>how often the same things happen even among 
<lb/>missionaries. <persName>M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">r</hi></hi> Moffat</persName> brought two young men 
<lb/>with him from <placeName>England</placeName>. One did nothing for four 
<lb/>years, and after spending a good deal of money was 
<lb/>sent off to <placeName>Canada</placeName>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he other sat down in a 

	<pb n="0006" facs="liv_001528_0006"/><!--pb/@n='59v'--> 
<lb/>comfortable house &amp; garden and not even the Directors 
<lb/>could dislodge him till lately. After all I have seen I am 
<lb/>convinced that were Christianity not Divine it would 
<lb/>be trampled out by its propagators. Among Portuguese 
<lb/><persName>Baines'</persName> example will do no harm, for they are the 
<lb/>lowest of the low. I tried to give him the benefit of a 
<lb/>doubt as to his sanity but it would not do. All the 
<lb/>rest i.e. <persName>D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Kirk</persName>, <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> C. Livingstone</persName> &amp; <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Rae</persName> with 2 
<lb/>English sailors do well. I do not remember whether 
<lb/>I mentioned that <persName>Thornton</persName> the geologist failed. An entire 
<lb/>want of energy set in after our arrival. I tried him 
<lb/>for eight months - talking seriously to him &amp; warning 
<lb/>him that should his inactivity <del type="strikethrough">prev</del> continue I must 
<lb/>stop his pay. <persName>D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Kirk</persName> &amp; <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> C. L.</persName> did the same. We could 
<lb/>not get him to work. In eight months he did not 
<lb/>accomplish 8 days geology. His salary ran on at 
<lb/>about £1 per day. This money is supposed to be 
<lb/>spent by me, so I had to cut him off. He then 
<lb/>went away with a half caste trader towards <placeName>Zumbo</placeName>, 
<lb/>and if he works now it is more than he would 
<lb/>do while with us. He belongs I believe to <placeName>Bradford</placeName> in <placeName>Yorkshire</placeName>. </p>
<lb/><p>we are now on our way up the river to the 
<lb/><placeName>Makalolo country</placeName>, but must go overland from 
<lb/><placeName>Kebrabasa</placeName> or in a whaler. We should be 
<lb/>better able to plan our course had our letters 
<lb/>not been lost. We have never been idle 
<lb/>and do not mean to be. 
<lb/>We have been trying to get the Portuguese Government 
<lb/>to acknowledge free trade on this river. 
<lb/><choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>nd but for long delay in our letters - the 
<lb/>negotiation might have been far advanced<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I hope <persName>Lord John Russell</persName> will help in this 
<lb/>matter and then we must have a small 
<lb/>colony or missionary &amp; mercantile 
<w>settle-<lb break="no"/>ment</w><reg>.</reg> If this our desire is granted 

	<pb n="0007" facs="liv_001528_0007"/><!--pb/@n='60r'--> 
<lb/>it is probable we shall have no cause to lament our 
<lb/>long toil &amp; detention here. My wife's letters too were 
<lb/>lost so I don<reg>'</reg>t know how or where she is. 
<lb/>Our separation and the work I have been engaged in were 
<lb/>not contemplated but they have led to our opening a 
<lb/>path into the fine cotton field in the North. <choice><reg>Y</reg><orig>y</orig></choice>ou will 
<lb/>see that the discoveries of <persName>Burton</persName> &amp; <persName>Speke</persName> confirm 
<lb/>mine respecting the form of the continent and its 
<lb/>fertility. It is an immense field. I crave the honour 
<lb/>of establishing a focus of christianity in it, but 
<lb/>should it not be granted will submit as most 
<lb/>unworthy. I have written <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Venn</persName> twice 
<lb/>and from yours I see something is 
<w>con-<lb break="no"/>templated</w> in <placeName>Cambridge</placeName>. You did not send 
<lb/>a copy of the lectures there because you thought others 
<lb/>would do it. We always believe that <add place="above">to be a</add> great law of 
<lb/>nature "What everyone is likely to do no <add place="above">one</add> does", and 
<lb/>get a laugh in finding each of our friends saying 
<lb/>some one is sure to send you so &amp; so. I did not 
<lb/>expect a <hi rend="underline">volume</hi> from the lectures but thought 
<lb/>that <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Murray</persName> would issue a cheap edition. 
<lb/>If it does good its all right. If young men come 
<lb/>to this country they must lay their account 
<lb/>with doing every thing for themselves. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey 
<lb/>must not expect to find influence at once 
<lb/>and all the countries near to the Portuguese 
<lb/>have been greatly depopulated. We are now 
<lb/>ascending this river without vegetables 
<lb/>and living on salt beef &amp; pork. Slave trade has 
<lb/>done its work for formerly all kinds of 
<w>pro-<lb break="no"/>visions</w> could be procured at every point &amp; 
<lb/>at the cheapest rate. We cannot get anything 
<lb/>for either love or money in a country the 
<lb/>fertility of which is truly astonishing<reg>.</reg></p>

	<pb n="0008" facs="liv_001528_0008"/><!--pb/@n='60v'-->
<lb/><p>As a finish to the subject of this vessel I give the notes 
<lb/>of the <persName>brothers Laird</persName> "<placeName>Hamilton Square</placeName></p>
			
</div>
			<div>
<lb/><p rend="right">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 16 /58 </p>
<lb/><p><persName>D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Livingstone's</persName> launch will more 
<lb/>probably exceed the ten knots than fall 
<lb/>short of it when kept in <hi rend="underline">proper trim</hi>. 
<lb/>She appears admirably adapted for what 
<lb/>she was proposed for, the <placeName>Upper Zambesi</placeName>
<lb/>above <placeName>"Tete"</placeName> If she is heavily laden 
<lb/>with stores her speed will of course 
<lb/>be diminished as her draught of 
<lb/>water is increased. As they are putting 
<lb/>the engine together it is impossible 
<lb/>to alter the power - even if desirable, 
<lb/>which it is not. </p>
<lb/><p>x<space dim="horizontal" extent="2" unit="chars"/>x<space dim="horizontal" extent="2" unit="chars"/>x<space dim="horizontal" extent="3" unit="chars"/>x x<space dim="horizontal" extent="4" unit="chars"/>x<space dim="horizontal" extent="2" unit="chars"/>x<space dim="horizontal" extent="2" unit="chars"/>x x 
<lb/><!--These are just little glyphs he wrote to divide chunks of text. I BELIEVE that they are acting like an '...' to indicate ommitted paragraphs --></p>
<lb/><p>(on another subject - the <placeName>Niger</placeName>) 
<lb/><persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Livingstone</persName> may calculate 
<lb/>on one ton for every inch Depth 
<lb/>in the Launch, and as in the 
<lb/>River he may safely load her 
<lb/>to 2 ft from ten to twelve tons 
<lb/>will be available for stores and 
<lb/>crew. As to space the plan sent 
<lb/>up shews accurately the Room </p>
<lb/><p>x xx<space dim="horizontal" extent="2" unit="chars"/>x<space dim="horizontal" extent="3" unit="chars"/>x<space dim="horizontal" extent="3" unit="chars"/>x  
<lb/><!--These are just little glyphs he wrote to divide chunks of text. I BELIEVE that they are acting like an '...' to indicate ommitted paragraphs --></p>
<lb/><p><persName>Macgregor Laird</persName></p>
			
</div>
			<div>
<lb/><p rend="right">4 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1859 </p>
<lb/><p>It was with feelings of 
<lb/>surprise &amp; regret that 
<lb/>I read the extract from 
<lb/><persName>D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Livingstone's</persName> letter 
<lb/>published in the Times 
<lb/>last Friday &amp; now 
<lb/>confirmed by yours 
<lb/>of Saturday. </p>
<lb/><p>Some of the remarks 
<lb/>made are calculated to 
<lb/>mislead the public &amp; one 
<lb/>is positively untrue. </p>
<lb/><p>In meeting these 
<lb/>objections it is well 
<lb/>to remember that the 
<lb/>Launch was designed 
<lb/>to perform a particular 
<lb/>service, which was to 
<lb/>act as a dispatch or 
<lb/>expeditionary craft 
<lb/>carrying but few 
<lb/>people and little luggage 
<lb/>that her draught of 
<lb/>water was to be 12  to 14 
<lb/>inches and not to exceed 
<lb/>18 inches<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>After trying to prove that the failure was owing to 
<lb/>her being loaded up to 2 ft 6, he adds, there is 
<lb/>however one statement <del type="strikethrough">which I must deny</del> about the 
<lb/>cylinder being an <hi rend="underline">old one</hi> originally cast for a low pressure 
<lb/>engine, which I must deny. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>nd curious enough I made 
<lb/>a pair of engines from the same pattern for a yacht 
<lb/>I built for the <persName>Duke of Leeds</persName> which have given the 
<lb/>greatest satisfaction during the whole season. <!-- Strictly speaking, this is where the second letter ends but there is no way to code this other than with a comment.-->It is 
<lb/>signed <persName>John Laird</persName>. Ours <hi rend="underline">is</hi> a low pressure 
<lb/>cylinder notwithstanding, and "Ten to Twelve tons" of people 
<lb/>are not "a few" nor is a mile an hour great dispatch<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p><persName>David Livingstone</persName></p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>