<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000766">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to William C. Oswell</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to William C. Oswell, 20 September 1852</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2007-05-29</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000766</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Royal Geographical Society (Great Britain); Archives, DL 1/1/3</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0288</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Oswell, William C., 1818-1893</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1852-09-20">20 September 1852</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kuruman</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>DATE</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>Initial Transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2007-06-06</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>Proof by Chris Lawrence
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2007-08-07</date>
				<name xml:id="JB">Janet Browne</name>Proof by Janet Browne
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000766_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1r'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Kuruman</placeName> 20<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> September</p>
<lb/><p rend="right">1852</p>
<lb/><p>My Dear <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi><choice><sic>Oswel</sic><corr>Oswell</corr></choice></persName></p>
<lb/><p>You will see by the date of this that I am 
<lb/>much slower in my movements than I anticipated when we parted. I 
<lb/>have met many obstacles in my way. One of them for instance the 
<lb/>complete breaking down of one of the wheels of <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Conibrick</persName> caused 
<lb/>a delay of more than a fortnight. All the spokes parted company with 
<lb/><choice><sic>with</sic><corr>no text</corr></choice> the nave at what a poetical person would call "one fell swoop"<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>The different causes of detention vexed me rather But now I find 
<lb/>they were the means in the good Providence of God of preventing 
<lb/>me from falling into the hands of the <term type="tribe">Boers</term> and being stripped of 
<lb/>everything. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he proclamation of their independence by the Gov<hi rend="sup underline">t</hi> -
<lb/>according to the recommendation of <persName>Major Hogg</persName> (who by the way is 
<lb/>lately dead) and public dinners given to Pretorius at <placeName>Bloemfontein</placeName> &amp; 
<lb/><placeName>Natal</placeName>, seem to have been given a fresh impulse to their policy &amp; spirit 
<lb/>for on the 28<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> ult. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey appeared in the Bakwain country. They were 
<lb/>600 strong and had about 700 of the Eastern tribes with them. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey 
<lb/>detached a party with four waggons to my house before the 
<lb/>main body went out to <placeName>Sechele's</placeName> town at <placeName>Limane</placeName>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hese broke open 
<lb/>the house - tore all my books and scattered all the boxes in the hollow 
<lb/>below. <choice><reg>t</reg><orig>T</orig></choice>hey took out the medicines and smashed the bottles against 
<lb/>the rocks. Broke the wooden chairs, carried away sofa, bedstead 
<lb/>table, dishes &amp;c &amp;c. and a good quantity of coffee &amp; tea &amp; sugar &amp;c &amp;c 
<lb/>belonging to Webb Coddrington, Green, Macabe &amp;c. Also the smith<reg>'</reg>s 
<lb/>forge anvil - <add place="above">3 corn mills</add> and all our tools both smith' &amp; carpenter's. On 29 <hi rend="sup underline">th</hi>
<lb/>they went in a body to near <placeName>Limane</placeName> drew up their waggons in 
<lb/>order - filling up the spaces with bushes. <add place="above">A party in the meantime</add> went to Church in the <placeName>Khotla</placeName>
<lb/>or public place of meeting. <persName>Mebalwe</persName> conducting the service - and after 
<lb/>the afternoon service they informed <persName>Sechele</persName> that they had come to fight 
<lb/>because he had refused to prevent Englishmen going North, that the 
<lb/>whole country had been given to them by the Gov<hi rend="sup underline">t</hi> and they had resolved 
<lb/>to put down chieftainship. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>nd he must send away his wives and 
<lb/>children. He replied that he was a man of peace - that he would 
<lb/>not molest Englishmen seeing they always treated him well &amp;c<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>On Monday they began their attack on the town by firing with swivels<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>They communicated fire to the houses. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his made many of the 
<lb/>women flee and the heat became so great the men huddled 
<lb/>together on the little hill in the middle of the town - the smoke 
<lb/>prevented them from seeing the <term type="tribe">Boers</term> though the latter saw 
<lb/>them huddled in groups. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey killed 60 <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> and 35 <term type="tribe">boers</term>
<lb/>fell - and a great number of horses. <persName>Sechele</persName> shot 4 <term type="tribe">boers</term> with

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000766_0002"/><!--pb/@n='1v'-->
<lb/><choice><sic>with</sic><corr>notext</corr></choice> his two double barrelled guns. <choice><reg>W</reg><orig>w</orig></choice>hen they made a dash at the 
<lb/>hill, one bullet passing through two men, and a bullet went through 
<lb/>the sleeve of his coat. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hese 60 are those whom they counted near 
<lb/>the town <persName>Sechele</persName> thinks others may have fallen among the women 
<lb/>who ran away - these are not yet counted. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey maintained their 
<lb/>position one whole day on the hill, cutting off the <term type="tribe">boers</term> every time 
<lb/>they came near. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he <term type="tribe">Boers</term> continued their firing with swivels 
<lb/>till the evening and then retired. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> having no 
<lb/>water fled from <placeName><choice><sic>Limase</sic><corr>Limane</corr></choice></placeName> during the night, and the <term type="tribe">Boers</term> did 
<lb/>not feel inclined to follow them - <add place="above">Some of</add> the women and children 
<lb/>who were captured ran away &amp; reported that two of the <term type="tribe">boers</term> who 
<lb/>were wounded died after leaving. The town being burned of course 
<lb/>all the corn it contained was consumed. Parties on horseback 
<lb/>went out either during the battle or afterwards and took all the 
<lb/>cattle of the <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> to be found near. The chief cattle posts are in 
<lb/>the <placeName>Kalihari.</placeName> All <persName>Paul's</persName><persName>Mebaloe's</persName> and my cattle are taken. I had but 
<lb/>few however. The whole of <persName>Sentuhe's</persName> cattle were taken too. His 
<lb/>people did not fire a shot.  <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he <term type="tribe">Boers</term> killed three <unclear cert="low">Wanketse</unclear> - burned the town and all their corn of course. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey met as if by accident 
<lb/><persName>Mosielele's</persName> cattle &amp; swept them off. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey were fleeing Kahihari wards 
<lb/>they did not fire a shot either. Mosielele had fled from <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName>
<lb/>and <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edwards</persName> fled to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Inglis<reg>'</reg></persName> place. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> E</persName> attempted to expostulate 
<lb/>with them and they took out an achter or sambok to him. 
<lb/>They seem very anxious to get a hold of me. Frequently expressed 
<lb/>a wish to that effect. I am not conscious of ever having done 
<lb/>anything offensive. Nor can I see anything in <persName>Sechele's</persName> conduct 
<lb/>to them which I can call bad. The oxen of the English, <persName>Webb</persName> &amp;c 
<lb/>and those of Motsahona and Api are gone too. <persName>Webb</persName><persName>Codrington</persName> &amp;c 
<lb/>are gone to <persName>Sebituane's.</persName> I shall write you again as soon as 
<lb/>I hear from them how matters stand in that country. Api 
<lb/>came to an outpost of <persName>Mosilikatse</persName> and the people gave him 
<lb/>ten tusks and pressed him strongly to go to the old gentlemen 
<lb/>but Api was afraid and got off by promising to go next 
<lb/>year. <persName>Viljoen</persName> &amp; <persName>Pert</persName><add place="above">5 or 6 in all</add><persName>Jacobs</persName> went in again to the <placeName>Lake</placeName>
<lb/>and a party is sent off by <persName>Sechele</persName> to cut them off. <persName>Viljoen's 
<lb/>wife</persName> entreated the Commando of <term type="tribe">Boers</term> not to go till her husband 
<lb/>should return - but in vain. And it will be a miracle if 
<lb/>he escapes. Another party of <term type="tribe">Boers</term> about thirty in number 
<lb/>also went in and they are to be cut off too. Then a sort of 
<lb/>guerilla warfare is to be commenced. They would have listened 
<lb/>to <persName>Viljeon's wife</persName> but expected their cannon would make <persName>Sechele</persName>
<lb/>flee instantly to the desert. Considering that it is the first 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000766_0003"/><!--pb/@n='2r'-->
<lb/>battle the <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> have fought with guns they did well. I feel 
<lb/>sorry for them. All improvement is at an end in the country around<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he <term type="tribe">boers</term> may find Magahesberg soon as insecure as the frontier is. 
<lb/>Stealing cattle is more agreeable to their natures than labour. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>nd the 
<lb/><term type="tribe">boers</term> are to blame for beginning the war. All the corn being 
<lb/>burned or carried off. The people must either steal or starve. This 
<lb/>you will say is far from orthodoxy. <choice><reg>B</reg><orig>b</orig></choice>ut I am not saying 
<lb/>what ought to be but what is likely to be - I have lost a 
<lb/>good deal but will now move so much more lightly than 
<lb/>I would have done had they let me alone. I cannot <choice><sic>concieve</sic><corr>conceive</corr></choice>
<lb/>what pleasure it could give them to tear my books and waste 
<lb/>the medicines. I had a very fine selection of medical books, and 
<lb/>the medicines I kept with great care because very pure and sent 
<lb/>out from <placeName>England</placeName> by a friend of mine in consumption. Being 
<lb/>a medical man he selected them with great care and knowing 
<lb/>that his lungs were gone he told me to be sure and write 
<lb/>soon &amp; let him know of their arrival for if I did not 
<lb/>he would not be there to <choice><sic>recieve</sic><corr>receive</corr></choice> it. <persName>Webb's</persName> party has been 
<lb/>warned to keep apart from <persName>Viljoens's</persName> party so I think 
<lb/>they are quite safe. <persName>Sechele</persName> lost his waggon too. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>lso a 
<lb/>waggon belonging to <persName>Macabe.</persName></p>
<lb/><p><persName>George</persName> is with me on a trading speculation. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Rutherford</persName>
<lb/>advanced £100 to enable him to make a trial and I lent <supplied cert="high" reason="damage">him</supplied>
<lb/>my second waggon in order to enable him to spend most 
<lb/>of his money in goods. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>nd in consideration for the use of 
<lb/>the waggon he is to assist me in building. I am not sure 
<lb/>whether I mentioned to you in my last that finding <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
<lb/>Montagu</persName> had not left the copy of your map in the colonial 
<lb/>office I gave a copy to be kept in the colonial office and 
<lb/>a note taken of the discovery as an authority as to it having 
<lb/>been effected by Englishmen viz you &amp; myself. I found out 
<lb/>the above when I had to go to <persName>Lieut. Gov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Darling</persName> for powder<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>He knew nothing about <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Montagu's</persName> copy. Indeed had never 
<lb/>seen any till he saw my copy. - I also gave a rough 
<lb/>copy of my letter to the Geog. Society to the Advertizer. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his was 
<lb/>some time after you left and I may have told you already. 
<lb/>I made some enquiries after the map which you lost and all 
<lb/>I could learn about it was that <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Arnot</persName> sent it to <placeName>Algoa 
<lb/>Bay</placeName>. He did not send it by post. I shall settle with the 
<lb/>man at <placeName>Motito</placeName> who kept your oxen and also with <persName>Sechele</persName><reg>.</reg>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000766_0004"/><!--pb/@n='2v'-->
<lb/><persName>Sechele</persName> sent the property he took from <persName>Moyle</persName> out to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName> my 
<lb/>10 guns and 21 oxen. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey are now at <placeName>Kuruman<reg>.</reg></placeName><persName>Moyle</persName> tried to 
<lb/>go to <placeName>Lehututung</placeName> I do not know whether he has suceeded. <persName>Shelley</persName> and <persName>Richard Orpeu</persName> went trying to go through the desert too. <choice><reg>L</reg><orig>l</orig></choice>ost 
<lb/>his oxen and his servant <persName>Adam</persName> came here a short time 
<lb/>ago for fresh oxen. <persName>Shelley</persName> is lying somewhere West of <placeName>Sequagua</placeName><persName>Pomores</persName><unclear cert="low">&amp;</unclear><unclear cert="low"><persName>Skete</persName></unclear> &amp; others reached <placeName>Lehututuñ</placeName> - found no elephants 
<lb/>and are waiting for rain to get back again. <persName>Sechele's</persName>
<lb/>children are here for instruction. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey live with M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Moffat<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I would go away now but am suspicious of the second 
<lb/>party of <term type="tribe">Boers</term>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey are thirty in number and would probably 
<lb/>plunder our waggons. And supposing I should meet some of 
<lb/>them fleeing they might look on me as the instigator of the 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bakwains.</term> I expect to be blamed now more than ever<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><anchor xml:id="envelopePosition" type="positionMarker"/>It is not improbable I shall be represented as fighting among the 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bakwains.</term> I feel very anxious to get away. As soon as the hunters 
<lb/>come out I shall know how to stir. At present I don<reg>'</reg>t know 
<lb/>whether the <term type="tribe">Boers</term> have retired for good. Upwards of 300 <term type="tribe">boers</term> were cut off by the fever. Old <persName><unclear cert="low">Austin</unclear></persName> and all his family fell 
<lb/>victims. All the friends here are as usual. <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup underline">rs</hi> Moffat</persName>
<lb/>present their kind regards. I heard of your arrival at <placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName>
<lb/>have not yet heard of <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">rs</hi> L.</persName> in <placeName>England.</placeName><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hat God may bless 
<lb/>and reward you for all your kindness to me and mine is the 
<lb/>constant prayer of yours affectionately <persName>D Livingston</persName></p>
<ab type="envelope">
<address corresp="#envelopePosition">
<addrLine>Care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> W Thompson</persName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName><hi rend="underline">Cape Town</hi></placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><hi rend="underline">prepaid</hi></addrLine>
<addrLine><persName>W C <choice><sic>Oswel</sic><corr>Oswell</corr></choice> Es<hi rend="sup underline">q</hi></persName></addrLine>
<addrLine>8 Gloucester Terrace</addrLine>
<addrLine>Regent's Park</addrLine>
<addrLine>London</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>