<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000776">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Margaret Sewell</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Margaret Sewell, 22 November 1852</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2007</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000776</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">National Library of Scotland; MS. 20312, ff. 20-21</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0297</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Sewell, Margaret</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1852-11-22">22 November 1852</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kuruman</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2007-07-30</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Intial Transcription by Caroline Overy
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2008-01-04</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>First proof
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2008-02-23</date>
				<name xml:id="JB">Janet Browne</name>second proof
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000776_0001"/><!--pb/@n='20r'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Kuruman</placeName> 22 November</p>
<lb/><p rend="right">1852</p>
<lb/><p>My Very Dear Friend</p>
<lb/><p>I have not written you for some time 
<lb/>because I believed you would have a living epistle by you 
<lb/>who would answer the purpose better than pen and paper<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I expected that my better half would have found her way 
<lb/>straight to 57<choice><reg>,</reg><orig>.</orig></choice> but I suppose she must have forgot your 
<lb/>address.  I am sure I would not forget it. Well you have 
<lb/>seen my little niggers, noisy enough I fear they made your 
<lb/>quiet domicile. I was sometimes bothered by their roaring 
<lb/>and ranting and noise but now I wish I could hear 
<lb/>it again. It is much easier to live a batchelor's life than 
<lb/>one of widowhood. The "stillness is shocking to me." Of the 
<lb/>poor batchelor it may be said as <persName>Cowper</persName> said of his 
<lb/>bird "that delight he never knew." I am getting quite 
<lb/>poetical I declare. I must stop or instead of a letter you 
<lb/>will <choice><sic>recieve</sic><corr>receive</corr></choice> a sonnet to the Moon or some other bit of wise 
<lb/>nonsense.</p>
<lb/><p>I have met with many obstacles to my progress 
<lb/>Northwards since I left the Cape. <choice><reg>B</reg><orig>b</orig></choice>ut I found when 
<lb/>I arrived here that the delay had been wisely ordered 
<lb/>for had I got on as well as I wished I should have 
<lb/>been at <placeName>Kolobeng</placeName> exactly at the time the commando 
<lb/>of Boers came. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey vow vengeance against me 
<lb/>and the reason of their hatred is the following. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey 
<lb/>have attacked and plundered eight tribes since I have 
<lb/>come into the country and on each occasion, have 
<lb/>carried off large numbers of captive children and 
<lb/>killed great numbers of the parents. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey have 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000776_0002"/><!--pb/@n='20v'-->
<lb/>no compunction for they believe the blacks have no souls<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>In these massacres they never lost a single man for having 
<lb/>guns and horses the natives cannot approach them with 
<lb/>their spears. The <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> however fought bravely, and 
<lb/>killed about 30 of them. A son of <persName>Pretorius</persName> the rebel 
<lb/>chief was among the number. <persName>Sechele</persName> had two bullets 
<lb/>through his hat and one through the sleeve of his coat<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Now the difference in this attack is all ascribed to me<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>"It<reg>'</reg>s all owing to thst horrid doctor" they say - and we shall 
<lb/>have his head yet for it. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey believe that I must have 
<lb/>taught them to fight. Only fancy your reverend friend 
<lb/>"teaching the young idea how to shoot" boers. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey 
<lb/>gutted our house - tore <add place="below">^</add><add place="above">the</add> books &amp; smashed all the bottles 
<w>contain-<lb break="no"/>ing</w> medicines. I have not got the length of taking joyfully 
<lb/>the spoiling of my goods. We had just bought an iron 
<lb/>sofa. I may have sat twice on it but not oftener. It was 
<lb/>intended to be a spare bed for any stranger as well as a resting 
<lb/>affair for ourselves. Now only think of a big fat Boeress 
<lb/>enjoying it and drinking coffee out of my wife's kettle &amp;c. 
<lb/>They are worse savages than the natives. Yet the ministers of 
<lb/>the Dutch Reformed church go among them administering 
<lb/>the sacrament - baptism without the least discrimination<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>The people have been severely punished and viewing 
<lb/>their punishment apart from the iniquities of the 
<lb/>Boers. It seems a judgement on them for rejecting the 
<lb/>gospel. They have rejected it. And I hope they may be 
<lb/>led to repent of their unbelief. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>heir kindness to us 
<lb/>personally was very great and I feel much for them 
<lb/>but it is not to be forgotten that they have by unbelief 
<lb/>done despite to the spirit of grace. All the fault the 
<lb/>Boers could charge on <persName>Sechele</persName> was his refusal 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000776_0003"/><!--pb/@n='21r'-->
<lb/>to throw obstacles in the way of Englishmen going to the 
<lb/>countries beyond. Our Government can do nothing for 
<lb/>the natives <add place="above">in the Interior</add>. It has foolishly been led into a war with the 
<lb/>Caffres and though wishing to exterminate them cannot effect 
<lb/>it. <persName>Sir George Cathcart</persName> brutally hangs or shoots all prisoners 
<lb/>even women are not spared. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he Hottentot leader wrote 
<lb/>to him lately requesting him to fight with men and not 
<lb/>with women. And now that he finds his brutality avails 
<lb/>nothing - the "Caffres being just as they were and where 
<lb/>they were 20 months ago"* <addSpan spanTo="#p21r-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left margin of fol. 21r'--></addSpan>* statement of a leading colonial Newspaper<anchor xml:id="p21r-01"/> He tells the friendly chiefs 
<lb/>to <choice><sic>recieve</sic><corr>receive</corr></choice> the enemy among them - which means "for 
<lb/>any sake take them away from fighting with me. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey 
<lb/>may beat me out after all". <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his after about 
<lb/>two millions of English gold have been squandered 
<lb/>in the war. The Hottentots have fought bravely 
<lb/>they <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="blotting"/><supplied reason="blot">advance </supplied> and retire in strict military order by 
<lb/>the sound of the bugle and though our troops are 
<lb/>furnished with all sorts of guns &amp; rifles they never 
<lb/>come out of an engagement unscathed. If no 
<lb/>other good comes out of this struggle than this we 
<lb/>feel sure that nobody will henceforth laugh at 
<lb/>missionaries for believeing that Hottentots have souls 
<lb/>and no future Caffre war will be undertaken 
<lb/>with as little cause as the former wars have had. 
<lb/><persName>Calderwood</persName> has £600 per annum as a magistrate 
<lb/>he preaches on Sunday and beats the Caffre seats of 
<lb/>honour on Monday. The Caffres say he holds the 
<lb/>bible in one hand and the Sambok <add place="above">(whip<reg>)</reg></add> in the other. They <add place="above">(converts)</add>
<lb/>have been forced in some cases to fight against their 
<lb/>own chiefs &amp; have asked to be shewn in the bible 
<lb/>the text which authorized such conduct. My opinion 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000776_0004"/><!--pb/@n='21v'-->
<lb/>from all I have heard of your friend is that though he 
<lb/>should do good for fifty years to come he will not counteract 
<lb/>the evil of his missionary magisterial course. He was the 
<lb/>main instrument in the condemnation of <persName>Botha</persName> a Hottentot 
<lb/>officer of forty years service and it came out that he <unclear cert="medium">(Cald)</unclear>
<lb/>had been in the habit of acting as a Government informer<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><persName>Calderwood</persName> himself admitted it in the Newspapers. At the same 
<lb/>time confessing he had not an interpreter when he took the 
<lb/>accusation &amp; sent it to the Government<reg>.</reg></p><anchor xml:id="envelopePosition" type="positionMarker"/>
<lb/><p>I was quite taken aback with this for I have always understood 
<lb/>him to be a man who would not rest with the <unclear cert="medium">stilt</unclear> of an 
<w>interpr-<lb break="no"/>eter.</w> In our part of the country the missionaries are decidedly the best 
<lb/>scholars in the native language. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>here is not a man of us except 
<lb/>perhaps <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ross</persName> who needs an interpreter. From all I can learn 
<lb/>the less you hear of <persName>Calderwood</persName> the better. I am sorry he has 
<lb/>turned out so. I had a high opinion of him formerly. Please 
<lb/>present my love to <persName>Charles</persName>. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L.</persName> was highly pleased with 
<lb/>you all.  I leave this in a few days. Ever Affectionately 
<lb/>D Livingston<reg>.</reg></p><addSpan spanTo="#p20r-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left margin of fol.20r'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p>I have got your parcels up to  - Reviews for Jan Feb. &amp; March 1851 - inclusive 
<lb/>and your very welcome letters, last one being N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 25<reg>.</reg></p><anchor xml:id="p20r-01"/><addSpan spanTo="#p20v-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left margin of fol.20v'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p><!-- written up side of 20v-->Thank <persName>Charles</persName> for his kind promises of welcome<reg>.</reg> Fain would I see you all again<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>But I have such a world of work before me I shall never have time to visit England<reg>.</reg></p><anchor xml:id="p20v-01"/><addSpan spanTo="#addEnd-21v" place="end"><!--addSpan/@place='Sheet folded to make envelope. Envelope text on the middle of fol. 21v'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p>Care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> W. Thompson</persName></p>
<lb/><p><del type="strikethrough"><hi rend="underline">Cape Town</hi></del></p>
<lb/><p><hi rend="underline">Prepaid</hi></p>
<lb/><p><persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">rs</hi> Sewell</persName></p>
<lb/><p><placeName>57 Aldersgate St.</placeName></p>
<lb/><p>London</p><anchor xml:id="addEnd-21v"/>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>