<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000738">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Hamilton M. Dyke</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Hamilton M. Dyke, 1 December 1851</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2007-06-26</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000738</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">National Library of Scotland; MS. 10707, ff. 31-32</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0262</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Dyke, Hamilton M., 1817-1880</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1851-12-01">1 December 1851</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kolobeng</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2007-06-26</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Initial Transcription by Caroline Overy
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>Unknown</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>Proofed by Chris
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000738_0001"/><!--pb/@n='31r'-->
<lb/><p><placeName>Kolobeng</placeName> 1<hi rend="sup underline">st</hi> December 1851</p>
<lb/><p>My Dear Friend</p>
<lb/><p>I was pleased a few days ago to <choice><sic>recieve</sic><corr>recieve</corr></choice> an epistle 
<lb/>from you containing some statistics with which I have 
<lb/>troubled you. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey seem to have driven your own domestic 
<lb/>affairs out of your head for you do not mention your 
<lb/>better half - so I conclude she is dead and I am now 
<lb/>addressing my widowed brother Dyke. Have you no 
<lb/>children either? You must try and remember that every 
<lb/>body is not so transcendental as yourself. I for one 
<lb/>like to hear how the families of my friends get on. I don<reg>'</reg>t 
<lb/>want scandal but I give you an example by telling 
<lb/>you that I have four children - three boys and a girl 
<lb/>and the fifth a little girl is in Heaven. I must soon 
<lb/>part with them for the region to which we go to settle 
<lb/>in is a feverish one and though one may dispose 
<lb/>of his own life in the way he thinks best for His 
<lb/>Redeemer's glory - he can scarcely be said to have the 
<lb/>lives of his children at his disposal. How do you 
<w>em-<lb break="no"/>ploy</w> your time? Do you think the young are likely to 
<lb/>become a set of model Christians? Are they better 
<lb/>upon the whole than those who have believed after they 
<lb/>have grown up? We have a theory that though the 
<lb/>old have not become great things yet your hopes ought 
<lb/>to be sustained by the expectation of great things to be 
<lb/>effected among the young. We seem to think we shall 
<lb/>make a <unclear cert="medium">set</unclear> of model Christians from among 
<lb/>the young. And I begin to doubt whether the notion 
<lb/>is sound? Are we models ourselves? Providence 
<lb/>took Tahiti out of our hands and we are deprived 
<lb/>of the Hottentots. Are we not taught that <unclear cert="high">our</unclear> ideas 
<lb/>of doing wonders with the young are erroneous. Our 
<lb/>duty seems to be to preach the gospel to every creature 
<lb/>and those who believe will be saved those who believe not 
<lb/>be condemned. A great number of both become manifest 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000738_0002"/><!--pb/@n='31v'-->
<lb/>of both young &amp; old. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hough I have plagued you for 
<lb/>statistics, excuse me while I beg a few more. If convenient 
<lb/>will you let me know - How many years the Basuto Mission 
<lb/>has been established. What the average missionary force in each 
<lb/>seven years of the time. <add place="above">with</add> What <add place="above">expense or a rough guess at it</add> the average number of 
<lb/>converts in each seven years<!--this doesn't make sense - not sure where added bits go-->. Can you furnish any 
<lb/>statistics of the Wesleyans. Don't turn up your nose 
<lb/>at the work I would fair extract out of you. You seem 
<lb/>of rather a desponding turn of mind. Some such work 
<lb/>in your leizure moments will do you good. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his is 
<lb/>a <hi rend="underline">medical</hi> opinion so you must bear with me.</p>
<lb/><p>I sympathize with you sincerely in your afflictions<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I know it must be extremely trying to you to see defections 
<lb/>in the church. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he world may deride &amp; scorn but you 
<lb/>have the sympathy of your bretheren in Christ and far 
<lb/>better of Our great High Priest in the Heavens. Here we 
<lb/>have nothing to encourage. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he people have had no corn 
<lb/>for four successive years, and have now removed about 
<lb/>8 miles up the <placeName>Kolobeng</placeName>. I would remove with them 
<lb/>but they are so badgered by Boers<reg>.</reg><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey have in addition 
<lb/>to the hunger no heart to learn. God has by his good 
<lb/>guidance opened up for us a large field on the North 
<lb/>and we may either enter in there &amp; work for Him or 
<lb/>begin &amp; build again in order carry forward his work among 
<lb/>the <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he former seems to me to be the best 
<lb/>for the Divine glory and I am now going Southwards 
<lb/>in order to deposit my family some where and then 
<lb/>return for the Interior work. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he existence of <term type="medical">African 
<lb/>fever</term> renders this step necessary. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he whole country 
<lb/>of <persName>Sebitoane</persName> so far as we saw it is an immense marsh<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>It is intersected in every direction by numerous rivers 
<lb/>and these overflow annually &amp; cover many miles 
<lb/>of <gap extent="0.5" unit="words" agent="damage"/><supplied reason="damage" resp="#CL">sur</supplied>face. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he higher parts are only a few feet above 
<lb/>the surrounding lowlands. Tsetse abounds, we lost about 
<lb/>40 oxen - a wonderful insect. It only affects domesticated 
<lb/>animals. We lived two months in the midst of it 
<lb/>our children were bitten and <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> no harm. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>nd 
<lb/>you may see Pallahs<reg>,</reg> waterbucks, buffaloe<reg>,</reg> Zebras &amp;c &amp;c 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000738_0003"/><!--pb/@n='32r'-->
<lb/>living undisturbed in the very midst of the venemous insect<reg>.</reg> Calves 
<lb/>are not killed by it so long as they suck their dams but dogs fed on 
<lb/>milk die. Its poison is fatal to domestic animas only but is a 
<lb/>henpecked husband not as much as domestic animal as 
<lb/>a calf. Let such beware.</p>
<lb/><p><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he <placeName>Sesheke</placeName> we believe to be the main branch of the <placeName>Zambesi</placeName><reg>.</reg>
<lb/>It is from 300 to 500 yards wide - and when it overflows 
<lb/>it extends fifteen miles out. Date trees abound and so do 
<lb/>Palmyra and other trees which were new to us. Sugar cane 
<lb/>and sweet potatoes are planted by the <term type="tribe">Barotse</term><reg>.</reg> And slave 
<lb/>dealing has begun among them. A party of <term type="tribe">Nambari</term>
<lb/>another tribe from the Nor West came last year and carried 
<lb/>off about 800 slaves. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey brought lots of English 
<lb/>manufactures to purchase slaves with. Blue <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/> &amp; 
<lb/>striped cottons. Blue<reg>,</reg> red &amp; green baize. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey would 
<lb/>not take ivory or cattle in exchange. The people 
<lb/>of <persName>Sebitoane</persName> are a mixture of <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term>, <term type="tribe">Bamangwato</term>
<lb/>&amp; 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Masuto</term>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he River tribes a black race <unclear reason="damage" cert="high">speaking another</unclear>
<lb/>language are subject to them. I tried <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi><gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/></persName>
<lb/>translation but <unclear reason="damage" cert="medium">they</unclear> seem to have adopted more 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bakwain</term> words than <term type="tribe">Suto</term>. And could <unclear reason="damage" cert="medium">understand</unclear> me 
<lb/>better when I read <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat<reg>'</reg>s</persName> testament. He <add place="above">(<persName>Sebitoane</persName>)</add><unclear reason="damage" cert="high">has</unclear> done 
<lb/>good service to us in introducing the Sitchuana in that 
<lb/>region<reg>.</reg> We found people every where who understood us 
<lb/>though the river languages differ as much from Sitchuana 
<lb/>as Latin does from English. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>here is an immense 
<lb/>population on the rivers - very black &amp; strong but not 
<lb/>warlike. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey excell all in basket making &amp; as smiths 
<lb/>potters &amp; workers in wood. Iron &amp; honey abound in 
<lb/>their country and they seem to have abundance of food<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>It was to our inexpressible sorrow that <persName>Sebitoane</persName> fell 
<lb/>sick &amp; died while we were there. We hope God will establish 
<lb/>his kingdom in that dark region.</p>
<lb/><p>Present our kind regards to <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi><unclear cert="medium">Cassilis</unclear></persName> and to 
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Dyke</persName>. And believe me affectionately yours </p>
<lb/><p rend="center">D Livingston</p>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000738_0004"/><!--pb/@n='32v'-->
 <addSpan spanTo="#addEnd-32v" place="end"><!--addSpan/@place='Sheet folded to make envelope. Envelope text on the middle of fol. 32v'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p><persName>Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> <unclear cert="low">T. H.</unclear> Dyke<!--not sure of ititials--></persName></p>
<lb/><p>Missionary</p>
<lb/><p><placeName>Basuto Country</placeName></p>
<lb/><p>Via Colesberg</p><anchor xml:id="addEnd-32v"/>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>