<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_001848">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Joseph B. Braithwaite</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Joseph B. Braithwaite, 21 November 1862</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2007-06-16</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_001848</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">National Library of Scotland; MS. 20312, ff. 111-112</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 1292</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Braithwaite, Joseph B., 1818-1905</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1862-11-21">21 November 1862</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Quillimane River</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2007-06-15</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>Intial Transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2008-03-01</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>Proofed by Chris Lawrence
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_001848_0001"/><!--pb/@n='111r'-->
<addSpan spanTo="#p111r-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left hand margin of fols. 111r, 111v, 112r'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">A <placeName>London</placeName> city missionary came out with six Scotchmen to join me. His name is <persName>Jehan</persName> they are 
<lb/>2 carpenters, 2 masons and 1 smith. All work at their trades &amp; the wages go to a common fund<reg>.</reg></p><anchor xml:id="p111r-01"/>
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Quillimane River</placeName> 21<hi rend="sup underline">st</hi> Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
<lb/>1862 </p>
<lb/><p rend="left"><persName>Bevan Braithwaite Esq.</persName></p>
<lb/><p>My Dear Friend</p>
<lb/><p>I <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> your welcome letter 
<lb/>from <placeName>Ilfracombe</placeName> of the 8<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> Sept<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> the day before yesterday 
<lb/>from <term type="boat">H.M.S.Rapid</term> which called here and found 
<lb/>us cutting wood to prosecute the rest of our voyage 
<lb/>from <placeName>Johanna</placeName> to <placeName>Zambesi</placeName>: our coals ran down 
<lb/>when we were 20 or 30 miles from our port of entrance 
<lb/>and the wind being contrary we bore away back to this 
<lb/>river for fuel. I have also to reply to a letter I 
<lb/><choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> about 3 months ago which I cannot lay 
<lb/>my hands upon but must say for it and all 
<lb/>others you find time to write I am sincerely thankful<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>We found that during our long detention down in the 
<lb/>lowlands the river had fallen so low that we should 
<lb/>be able to do but little work up <placeName>the Shire</placeName> but 
<lb/>hauling the <term type="boat">Pioneer</term> through shoal water till the next 
<lb/>flood came. <choice><reg>S</reg><orig>s</orig></choice>o resolved to spend the time between - 
<lb/><choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>ugust &amp; this in trying to get an outlet from the 
<lb/>Lake region to the sea by <placeName>Rovuma</placeName>. We went up in  
<lb/>boats 156 miles or 114 in a straight line &amp; touched 
<lb/>twice on the slave route from <placeName>Nyassa</placeName> to <placeName>Quiloa</placeName>
<lb/>(Keelwa) along which about 20 000 slaves pass 
<lb/>annually for the <placeName>Red Sea</placeName> &amp; <placeName>Persian gulph</placeName>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he 
<lb/><placeName>Rovuma</placeName> will be an outlet for us if the Portuguese 
<lb/>continue to refuse free trade on the <placeName>Zambesi</placeName>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he 
<lb/>people far up were very friendly. Near the coast 
<lb/>they were hostile and fired upon us though we 
<lb/>stood exposed to their arrows &amp; muskets over an 
<lb/>hour and having induced some to come to my 
<lb/>boat made friends, and gave in token of friendship 
<lb/>about 30 yards of cloth. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>s we then moved on 
<lb/>they gave us a volley &amp; bolted back among the long 
<lb/>grass &amp; bushes with which the river's bank was 
<lb/>covered. In returning they shewed no wish to 
<lb/>assault us. In the <placeName>Shire</placeName> we have influence now &amp; 
<lb/>return thither rather than commence at the bottom 
<lb/>of the ladder there. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he people on the <placeName>Shire</placeName> were very 
<lb/>hostile at first but never did more than bend 
<lb/>the bow. We shall now go at our work at the <placeName>cataracts</placeName>
<lb/>with a will<reg>.</reg></p>

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_001848_0002"/><!--pb/@n='111v'-->
<addSpan spanTo="#p111v-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left hand margin of fols. 111r, 111v, 112r'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">They had bought 2 waggons to go overland but the magistrate wrote to the Governor about them and 
<lb/>he has sent the letter &amp; says the magistrate is a man of</p><anchor xml:id="p111v-01"/> 
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">We are much refreshed by our sea voyage. I could 
<lb/>write but little at <placeName>Johanna</placeName> but sent one private 
<lb/>letter to <persName>Sir Roderick</persName>. I would not press publication 
<lb/>all the influence and attention excited when at home 
<lb/>was done by a higher hand. It came without effort 
<lb/>on my part further than doing my duty here and 
<lb/>if the same Power sees fit they won't be able to 
<lb/>avoid publication. <choice><reg>C</reg><orig>c</orig></choice>ommit th<del type="strikethrough">e</del>y way unto &amp;c and in 
<lb/>all thy way acknowledge Him and he shall direct 
<lb/>thy steps are good words and true. Possibly it may 
<lb/>be best for me to be taken away but the work being 
<lb/>as in my heart I believe it to be - not of man - others 
<lb/>will carry it on, and it will be completed. Don<reg>'</reg>t 
<lb/>you think that there is something in "He that believeth 
<lb/>shalt make not haste" - not make a fuss or get into 
<lb/>a flurry as if all were going to the dogs when the 
<lb/>things concerning the kingdom don<reg>'</reg>t run in the 
<lb/>groove we have chalked out for them. Perhaps 
<lb/>I am a little influenced by the last despatch I <choice><sic>received</sic><corr>recieved</corr></choice>
<lb/>from <persName>Earl Russell</persName>. <del type="strikethrough">He says</del> (between ourselves only) 
<lb/>He says that he had <choice><sic>received</sic><corr>recieved</corr></choice> and laid the information 
<lb/>before the <persName>Queen</persName> "(which has been declined publication 
<lb/>and adds that "the reports of the proceedings of your 
<lb/>expedition have been read with great interest, 
<lb/>and the discretion, courage, and perseverance 
<lb/>that you have shewn in the face of great trials 
<lb/>difficulties merit the highest approbation". </p>
<lb/><p>He "read with deep regret your account of the 
<lb/>encouragement given by the Portuguese to the 
<lb/>traffic in slaves. I have desired her Majesty<reg>'</reg>s 
<lb/>representative at <placeName>Lisbon</placeName> to make a strong protest to the 
<lb/>Portuguese Government against the acts of their 
<lb/>authorities, and I trust that measures will be taken 
<lb/>to put a stop to these practices." We found a <add place="above">Portuguese</add> barque 
<lb/>up at the village (I am cutting wood near the mouth 
<lb/>of the river as I write.) She had taken a large quantity 
<lb/>of rice on board. I sent an officer on board to buy 
<lb/>some sail needles<choice><reg/><orig>?</orig></choice> and the hatches were covered over 
<lb/>with tarpaulins as soon as he came near. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he 
<lb/>Governor too was very anxious to explain all about 
<lb/>her as a perfectly legal trader &amp;c. but our black man 
<lb/>found out that the slaves to be shipped are at present 
<lb/>in the village. I gave information to the Rapid </p>

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_001848_0003"/><!--pb/@n='112r'-->
<addSpan spanTo="#p112r-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left hand margin of fols. 111r, 111v, 112r'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">sound judgement. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey behave well he says which is more than our man of war 
<lb/>crew does. I propose to employ them. Do you know anything about <persName>Jehan</persName>?</p><anchor xml:id="p112r-01"/>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">and hope she will capture her as I wish to shew 
<lb/>our Government that there is little likelihood of 
<lb/>the Portuguese giving up slaving so long as they are 
<lb/>allowed to pursue an exclusive policy on this coast<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey have made this country a slave preserve &amp; 
<lb/>will continue so to keep it if allowed<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>As to the steamer <term type="boat">Lady Nyassa</term> I have thought 
<lb/>that we could apply to the Government with 
<lb/>more force for about half the expense after we 
<lb/>have got her into sucessful working on the Lake<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>If they decline doing that they may pay it in 
<lb/>another way by increasing my salary. <persName>Lord 
<lb/>Malmesbury</persName> said when in office that I had gone 
<lb/>out with too small a salary, and put that opinion 
<lb/>on record in the Foreign Office. <choice><reg>S</reg><orig>s</orig></choice>o I have a plea 
<lb/>there. We have slave trade commissioners with 
<lb/>a thousand <add place="above">at <placeName>Cape Town</placeName></add> and in <placeName>Loanda</placeName> £1500 per annum<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I am doing as much work as any five of them 
<lb/>but doing it <hi rend="underline">con amore</hi> and I would rather if possible 
<lb/>pay all the expense if I can than come in ferma 
<lb/>pauperis before them. 
<lb/>I shall give all I can out 
<lb/>of my salary to educate the children and after education 
<lb/>it will do them no harm to work their way in the 
<lb/>world. I have £800 at the <placeName>Cape</placeName> and don<reg>'</reg>t want to die 
<lb/>rich. Pity that some of these old stupids such as he 
<lb/>who has left a large fortune to the <persName>Emperor of Russia</persName>
<lb/>can<reg>'</reg>t be better advised. I would spend for them 
<lb/>a too easy thing to do you will say. Well there is 
<lb/>some truth in  <persName>Sir Roderick's</persName> nonsense. One of the 
<lb/>Missionaries <add place="above"><persName>Rowley</persName></add> sent a letter to the <placeName>Cape</placeName> accusing me 
<lb/>of being the author of all the Bishop's fighting. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he 
<lb/>Editor in publishing it pointed out in the 
<lb/>Bishops's own journal furnished proof that 
<lb/><persName>Rowley</persName> was in error. He says in his journal 
<lb/>written Aug. 25 I asked him <persName>(Livingstone)</persName> whether 
<lb/>he thought that circumstances could arise which 
<lb/>would make us go again and fight. He said "No" 
<lb/>you will be oppressed with requests but don't go." 
<lb/>He mentions our being attacked by the <term type="tribe">Ajawa</term>
<lb/>exactly as I did." In attempting to come to a 
<w>con-<lb break="no"/>versation</w> with the <term type="tribe">Ajawa</term> chiefs we were involved 
<lb/>as we had expected in an encounter with them." I 
<lb/>tried to retire but we were surrounded. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>nd this 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_001848_0004"/><!--pb/@n='112v'-->
<lb/>had no connection with the bishop deliberately &amp; 
<lb/>with the full consent of <persName>Rowley</persName> taking the offensive 
<lb/>on three occasions when I was away at <placeName>Lake 
<lb/>Nyassa</placeName> and the bishop like a man says in his 
<lb/>journal that he did it all on his own responsibity<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he clergyman who gave the letter of <persName>Rowley</persName> for 
<lb/>publication wrote an apology to me for doing it 
<lb/>and said he "had been blamed by all his friends 
<lb/>both lay and clerical". I wonder that the church should 
<lb/>send out such a man as <persName>Rowley</persName> so lately one of 
<lb/>the pro intoning rioters in St. George's in the East as a 
<lb/>missionary. A man who out of pure spite could say 
<lb/>"there is no cotton on the highlands" such a story. His 
<lb/>bishop bought a cotton gin from me to clean or shew 
<lb/>the natives to clean it. <choice><reg>S</reg><orig>s</orig></choice>pinning &amp; weaving cotton meets 
<lb/>the eye in every direction. I suppose <persName>Sir R</persName> meant that 
<lb/>they were in the way by their folly in bringing a bad report 
<lb/>on the country. <placeName>Magomero</placeName> was a cesspool because 
<lb/>200 people deposited without one sanitary regulation 
<lb/>No wonder they had <term type="ailment">dysentry</term> and <term type="ailment">ulcers</term>. But I shall 
<lb/>not abate one jot in doing all I can to aid them 
<lb/>notwithstanding. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>heir work is not of individuals 
<lb/>but of the great church of England. I have just 
<lb/>spent four days in wood cutting &amp; towing their 
<lb/>supplies over the <placeName>bar of Quillimaine</placeName>. In answer 
<lb/>to the prayers of many good people success 
<lb/>will one day come and He who <add place="above">sees &amp;</add> hears in secret 
<lb/>will not overlook what is done for his sake. </p>
<lb/><p>Is there any truth in a rumour I see in an 
<lb/>American paper that the <persName>Prince of Wales</persName> intends 
<lb/>to take an active part in emigration? I am 
<lb/>ashamed to say I have not written to your brother 
<lb/>Charles and his wife for a long time though 
<lb/>I have their very kind letters by me. Will you 
<lb/>shew them this and beg their patience. It has 
<lb/>not been for want or will. Did a paper in the 
<lb/>Quarterly on "<placeName>Dorset</placeName>" draw you down to that 
<lb/>county. Come here and I shall shew a country 
<lb/>worth looking at. With kindest salutations 
<lb/>to your wife &amp; family &amp; to all our friends </p>
<lb/><p>I am very affectionately yours<reg>.</reg><persName>David Livingstone</persName></p> 
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>