<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_002508">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to H. Bartle E. Frere</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to H. Bartle E. Frere, 1 February 1867</title><!-- RGS scribal copy of letter C&C 1909 original in private hands-->
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2008-07-04</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_002508</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Royal Geographical Society (Great Britain); Archives, DL 4/4/3</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 1909</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Frere, H. Bartle E., 1815-1884</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1867-02-01">1 February 1867</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Bemba</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: unknown</handNote>
				<handNote xml:id="hand02">Scribe: unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2008-07-04</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>Initial Transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2009-01-23</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Christopher Lawrence</name>Proof by Chris Lawrence
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div><!--<p rend="center"><handShift new="hand01"/><pb n="0"/>Copy of letter from <lb/><persName>D<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> David Livingstone</persName> - dated 1 <hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">st</hi></hi> February. 1867. <lb/></p>-->

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_002508_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Bemba</placeName>. 1<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">st</hi></hi> February 1867. </p>
<lb/><p rend="left"><hi rend="underline">Copy</hi></p>
<lb/><p><del type="strikethrough" hand="#hand02">My dear <persName>Sir Bartle</persName>,</del></p>
<lb/><p><del type="strikethrough" hand="#hand02">By the first opportunity I have met with since 
<lb/>we left the coast I send a Despatch for <persName>Lord Clarendon</persName>, &amp; 
<lb/>a request to <persName>D<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Seward</persName> to copy it for your private 
<lb/>information. It does not coincide with the views of <persName>Col: 
<lb/>Pelly</persName>, and I assure you it was not without long and 
<lb/>anxious thought that I ventured to differ <del type="strikethrough">with him</del><add place="above">from</add>
<lb/>him. I do not refer to him by name but feeling convinced 
<lb/>that his reasoning as to the continuance of the <placeName>Zanzibar</placeName> Slave trade is untenable I beg that you will do me the 
<lb/>favour to read a portion at least of what I have 
<lb/>written. My sorrowful convictions have been deepened 
<lb/>by all I have seen of the working of the system, &amp; 
<lb/>the dire ruin which for the sake of this paltry island 
<lb/>annually overtakes much larger &amp; more beautiful 
<lb/>portions of Country. I have been quite unable to copy 
<lb/>it myself. </del>I had no prospect of sending coast wise, but 
<lb/>here I met a party of black Arab slave traders from 
<lb/><placeName>Bagamois</placeName>, near <placeName>Zanzibar</placeName>, and while they agree to take a 
<lb/>packet they will not wait more than half a day for me 
<lb/>to write; they have come here for the first time - About 
<lb/>10° 10′ south Lat. &amp; 31° 50′ East Long. </p>
<lb/><p>We have been a long time in making our way here, but 
<lb/>some of the delay was pleasant for I had intercourse with 
<lb/>people who had not engaged in the slave trade. We came 
<lb/><fw type="catch" place="marginbottom" rend="right">round</fw>

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_002508_0002"/><!--pb/@n='2'-->
<lb/>round the south end of the Lake. I was apprehensive if I took 
<lb/>my Johanna men round the Northern Extremity they would 
<lb/>bolt at the first sight of danger. They actually did run away 
<lb/>on mere report of the doings of the terrible <term type="tribe">Mazitu</term> or Zulus &amp; 
<lb/>I was left with a following of nine Africans, six of whom 
<lb/>are Nassick boys. The Johanna men had proved themselves 
<lb/>such thieves it was a relief to get rid of them. The most 
<lb/>influential chief on the watershed between coast &amp; Lake, 
<lb/>called <persName>Mataka</persName> wished very much that some of the boys 
<lb/>would remain with him &amp; shew the use that could be 
<lb/>made of his cattle in Agriculture. <persName>Abraham</persName> met two 
<lb/>uncles there, but no entreaty would induce him to 
<lb/>remain though <persName>Mataka</persName> was extremely liberal &amp; seemed to 
<lb/>please<del type="strikethrough">d</del> them all. "How can I stop where I have no mother &amp; 
<lb/><choice><reg/><orig>"</orig></choice>no sister?" was the invariable reply. I promised to try 
<lb/>&amp; get some boys acquainted with Indian Agriculture 
<lb/>from the same school; but the system for teaching for 
<lb/><placeName>India</placeName> &amp; not for <placeName>Africa</placeName> had better be <del type="strikethrough">recalled</del> altered. 
<lb/><persName>Abraham</persName> has done good service to me since so I have no 
<lb/>reason to be dissatisfied with him.//I was obliged to go very 
<lb/><del type="strikethrough">carefully</del> cautiously, and seven or eight miles was all 
<lb/>we could accomplish in a day. We went Westwards 
<lb/>from the heel of the Lake - ascended <persName>Kirk's</persName> range which 
<lb/>is only the edge of a plateau densely <del type="strikethrough">populated</del> peopled 
<lb/>with various tribes of <term type="tribe">Manganja</term> who have not yet 
<lb/>engaged in slaving. After going Westwards till we were 
<lb/>past the Longitude of the Mazitu, we turned to the North, 
<lb/>&amp; taking up the point we left off at in 1863 we continued 
<lb/>our Northerly course, at times making a little westing. 
<lb/>We crossed the wide valley in which the <placeName>Loangua</placeName> flows - 
<lb/>the bed of an ancient Lake - <choice><sic>the</sic><corr>we</corr></choice> ascended the heights of 
<lb/><placeName>Lobisa</placeName> in the Southern borders of Lat. 11° South. Here we came 
<lb/>to 
<lb/><fw type="catch" place="marginbottom" rend="right">to</fw>

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_002508_0003"/><!--pb/@n='3'-->
<lb/>to a depopulated country - an immense forest. The <term type="tribe">Babisa</term>
<lb/>were eager slavetraders &amp; the ruin that has followed that 
<lb/>traffic is now apparent in only a few hamlets occurring 
<lb/>at wide intervals - &amp; small patches of a species of 
<lb/>Millett at various parts in the jungle. The people had 
<lb/>little or no grain to sell. They were living on Mushrooms 
<lb/>chiefly, good only for producing dreams of roast 
<lb/>beef of bygone days. While in the valley of the <placeName>Loangua</placeName>
<lb/>we had plenty of game &amp; easily kept the pots boiling, 
<lb/>but here not a beast was to be seen, &amp; daily trudging 
<lb/>through dripping sloppy forests with the feet almost 
<lb/>constantly wet, and gnawing hunger in the inner man 
<lb/>took the flesh off our bones. We crossed the <placeName>Chambeze</placeName>, 
<lb/>as <placeName>Zambeze</placeName> is here called, in Lat. 10° 34′ S. only 40 
<lb/>yards wide. <choice><reg>B</reg><orig>b</orig></choice>ut it had plenty of animals on its banks &amp; 
<lb/>we soon got a supply of meat. This, the chief town of 
<lb/>this side of <placeName>Bemba</placeName> has a treble stockade round it - the 
<lb/>inner line having a deep ditch besides. If not mistaken 
<lb/>we are on the water shed between <placeName>Chambeza</placeName> and <placeName>Luapula</placeName>
<lb/>which is said to flow into <placeName>Lake Tanganiyka</placeName>. It is said 
<lb/>to be very large but I hope to let you know better from the 
<lb/>Lake itself where I hope to find letters &amp; our second 
<lb/>supply of goods. We are 4,500 feet above the sea, the 
<lb/>temperature cool &amp; the rains more abundant than I ever 
<lb/>saw them in Africa - very few days pass without a 
<lb/>shower. The Interior is chiefly forest &amp; excessively 
<lb/>leafy - one can see but a little way of <space dim="horizontal" extent="1" unit="words"/> on an elevation. 
<lb/>The Gum copal tree, another, a Cres <unclear cert="medium">Alpinca</unclear>, abound, 
<lb/>with Rhododendrons &amp; various evergreen tress - the 
<lb/>two first furnish the bark cloth with is the principal 
<lb/>clothing of the people. We have had no difficulties with 
<lb/>the natives. Hunger &amp; wet have been our greatest hindrances<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>We could not for some time find out where the Portuguese 
<lb/>route 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_002508_0004"/><!--pb/@n='4'-->
<lb/>to <placeName>Cazemba</placeName>lay but it has been placed by the map makers 
<lb/>too far East. Hence they had no mountain chains such 
<lb/>as we have met with. The watershed between <placeName>Loangua</placeName>
<lb/>&amp; <placeName>Chambeze</placeName> is 6,600 feet above the sea - They went in 
<lb/>search of ivory and slaves. </p>
<lb/><p>In case the sepoys destroyed my letter which I sent 
<lb/>back with them I may say that their scheme was to 
<lb/>force me to return as soon as they had killed all the 
<lb/>beasts of burden. The Havildar actually payed in 
<lb/>behalf of the rest eight Rupees to our Arab guide to 
<lb/>feed &amp; lead them back to the coast. When found out 
<lb/>there was a good deal of blubbering &amp; they eagerly 
<lb/>accepted a sentence to carry light loads. They obeyed 
<lb/>none of the Havildar's orders he evidently conniving 
<lb/>with them. They were an intolerable drag &amp; frustrated 
<lb/>the best means I could devise for securing provisions 
<lb/>namely by my going forward and sending in all directions for food. They would not march if I were 
<lb/>not present &amp; even then when I was out of sight 
<lb/>they lay down &amp; slept. On finding that one <unclear cert="low">Bunado</unclear>
<lb/>threatened to shoot a Nassick boy when he got him out 
<lb/>of English power I sent them back with ample cloth 
<lb/>in the hands of a merchant to pay all expenses. The 
<lb/>Havildar came on but could be made of no use in any 
<lb/>way - &amp; when we heard at the Lake that the seven 
<lb/>Mahometans of the party had remained at Matakas 
<lb/>where food was abundant in order probably to let 
<lb/>their pay accumulate while they played the mendicant 
<lb/>the Havildar became sulky and shammed unaccountable 
<lb/>pains in his feet &amp; returned to join the others. </p>
<lb/><p>Mataka's town &amp; country are the most likely for a 
<lb/>permanent settlement to be made. It is elevated &amp; 
<lb/>cool. English peas were in full bearing &amp; bloom in 
<lb/><fw type="catch" place="marginbottom" rend="right">July</fw>

	<pb n="0005" facs="liv_002508_0005"/><!--pb/@n='5'-->
<lb/>July. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he altitude is over 3000 feet &amp; his country is 
<lb/>mountainous &amp; abounds in running streams the 
<lb/>sources of the <placeName>Rovuma</placeName>. <persName>D<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Norman Macleod</persName> promised 
<lb/>me to try &amp; get some German missionaries from 
<lb/><placeName>Harmsburg</placeName> in <placeName>Hanover</placeName> &amp; salaries for them if I could 
<lb/>indicate a locality. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hese same men go without salaries 
<lb/>&amp; are artificers of different kinds but this is a mistake 
<lb/>they ought to have a little for some of them have in sheer 
<lb/>wont taken to selling brandy even - but at Makata's 
<lb/>they could easily raise wheat by sowing it at the 
<lb/>proper time, &amp; native produce by planting when 
<lb/>the rains come - but it would require a leader of 
<lb/>some energy - &amp; not a fellow who would wring his 
<lb/>hands if he had no sugar &amp; his tea. I have 
<lb/>almost forgotten the taste of sugar, &amp; tea is made 
<lb/>by roasting a little Joare &amp; calling the decoction 
<lb/>either tea or coffee. I have written to the <persName>D<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">r</hi></hi></persName> &amp; given 
<lb/>some account of the difficulties to be overcome. 300 
<lb/>miles is a long way to go but I feel more &amp; more 
<lb/>convinced that <placeName>Africa</placeName> must be christianized from 
<lb/>within. </p>
<lb/><p rend="center">Believe me affectionately yours </p>
<lb/><p rend="center">(signed) <persName>David Livingstone</persName></p>
<lb/><p>His Highness the Sultan did all he could for us &amp; 
<lb/>was extremely kind but his people to whom I bore 
<lb/>an epistle all skedaddled as soon as they heard 
<lb/>that the "English were coming. " The Dhowes (2) on 
<lb/>the Lake were kept out of my way lest I should 
<lb/>burn them as slavers! &amp; I could not get across the 
<lb/>middle of the Lake. </p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>