<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000827"><!-- LP122 -->
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Charles Livingstone</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Charles Livingstone, 8 November 1854</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2006-10-09</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000827</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0347</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Livingstone, Charles, 1821-1873</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1854-11-08">8 November 1854</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Golungo Alto</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">David Livingstone Centre; 779</bibl><!--1854-11-08--><!--Original:1854-11-08-->
				<bibl xml:id="extent">12 pages</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2006-09-05</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Initial Transcription
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000827_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1r'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Golungo Alto</placeName></p>
<lb/><p rend="right">8<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> Nov<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi></p>
<lb/><p rend="right">1854</p>
<lb/><p>My Dear <persName>Charles</persName></p>
<lb/><p>Its a weary time since I heard 
<lb/>from any of my former correspondents. And I have 
<lb/>but slender hopes of seeing any epistle from you 
<lb/>while I am in <placeName>Western Africa</placeName>. the ship of the 
<lb/><persName>Commodore</persName> called the "<term type="boat">Scourge</term>" has gone up to 
<lb/><placeName>Fernando Po</placeName> for the mails. She is much beyond 
<lb/>her time and we cannot guess the cause of her 
<lb/>detention But when she comes my last hopes 
<lb/>of hearing from friends will have to expire. I 
<lb/>go away into the region where there are no mails, 
<lb/>to cheer the weary wanderer.</p>
<lb/><p>I would have been father away before this 
<lb/>but bad health &amp; good hope kept me about a 
<lb/>month longer than was absolutely necessary 
<lb/>at <placeName>Loanda</placeName>. Then when I came up into the 
<lb/>coffee country as I had written some <term type="reference">papers 
<lb/>in a Newspaper</term> recommending agriculture 
<lb/>instead of slave trading. It was expected that 
<lb/>I would shew some interest in the efforts 
<lb/>of a few who are making laudable efforts to 
<lb/>establish themselves as coffee growers. the trees 
<lb/>are ready planted for them, and all that the 
<lb/>best coffee in the world requires is to have 
<lb/>the ground partially cleared and the fruit 
<lb/>dried and sorted. they shewed extraordinary 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000827_0002"/><!--pb/@n='1v'-->
<lb/>kindness and I had to refuse their gifts of coffee 
<lb/>rice &amp;c. I encouraged them to persevere and 
<lb/>among other things I learned that the views 
<lb/>of your <persName>Professor of Political Economy</persName> are 
<lb/>nonsense. I shall return to this subject again 
<lb/>In the mean time - I may relate that after spending 
<lb/>some 8 or 10 days as above I came back to 
<lb/>this the residence of the <persName>chief of the District</persName> called 
<lb/><placeName>Golungo Alto</placeName>, And when on the point of starting 
<lb/>he was seized with one of the deadly <term type="ailment">fevers</term> of 
<lb/>this land. I of course could not leave one 
<lb/>who had shewed me a great deal of kindness 
<lb/>when bending under disease I entered his dwelling 
<lb/>in my way down to <placeName>Loanda</placeName>. I have been 
<lb/>treating him for 8 days past. His head became 
<lb/>affected and as he has none but slaves 
<lb/>about him, I have to see everything done 
<lb/>both by night and by day. Pity the poor 
<lb/>mortal who falls sick among his slaves. this 
<lb/>is a most kind and considerate master yet 
<lb/>he says to me - "If you had not been here I think 
<lb/>they would have knocked me on the head." they 
<lb/>run riot among the eatables - As I do not 
<lb/>venture to scold in Portuguese I can only be 
<lb/>amused in silence at the affection developed 
<lb/>by the domestic institution. they kill the goats 
<lb/>&amp; fowls - then tell me with faces of the most 
<lb/>innocent wonderment - "<hi rend="underline">the thing is dead</hi>" When 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000827_0003"/><!--pb/@n='2r'-->
<lb/>I tell them to throw them away there follows only 
<lb/>a comfortable roasting. When the <choice><sic>sweatmeats</sic><corr>sweetmeats</corr></choice> are devoured 
<lb/>then one comes and tells me with a countenance 
<lb/>of horror - "these slaves are robbing <add place="above">master of</add> everthing" and 
<lb/>this very one I have come accidentally upon 
<lb/>in the act of eating Pine Apples rolled in a large 
<lb/>plate of sugar. I can scarcely get the washerwoman 
<lb/>to put my clothes in order though I pay her for 
<lb/>it. Let who will go for slavery I vote for the 
<lb/>freeman. I have seen a good deal of it now 
<lb/>and from the unstudied words and actions of 
<lb/>respectable masters I very much doubt if 
<lb/>there is the least truth in the averment that 
<lb/>many masters treat their slaves with kindness 
<lb/>Living in the practice of habitual injustice 
<lb/>to them, it is extremely questionable whether the 
<lb/>better sort even can claim by a few driblets 
<lb/>of civility, the appellation of Kind Masters. It 
<lb/>is fortunate that this country contains but few 
<lb/>slaves in comparison with free men. In 
<lb/>some districts of the Province the statistics drawn 
<lb/>up by those who have no apparent motive 
<lb/>for misstating the facts, <add place="above">shew</add> the proportion of 
<lb/>slaves in the entire population is 6.79 per cent.</p>
<lb/><p>But let us look at the subject of an armed 
<lb/>force putting down the slave trade. the views 
<lb/>entertained by <persName>your Professor</persName> - that such means 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000827_0004"/><!--pb/@n='2v'-->
<lb/>would only have the effect of increasing the 
<lb/>horrors of the treatment of those who would be 
<lb/>sent notwithstanding, to supply the demand. 
<lb/>That no means would be effective for the 
<lb/>suppression of this species of commerce so 
<lb/>long as the profits were so large - And then if I 
<lb/>recollect rightly in true Yankee style he jerked 
<lb/>himself a little beyond the full length of his 
<lb/>tether by the windy climax, that Great Britain 
<lb/>would have consulted the interests of the slaves 
<lb/>more had she instead of <unclear cert="medium">cruizers</unclear> fitted out 
<lb/>convenient well ventilated - well found Emigrant 
<lb/>ships to convey the negroes to the Brazils, 
<lb/><unclear cert="medium">Bating</unclear> the wind bag tacked on to the tail of them 
<lb/>I considered his sentiments just. And would 
<lb/>have been pleased had our squadron been 
<lb/>withdrawn. But since I came into this 
<lb/>country I found that the oft repeated tales 
<lb/>of the increased horrors and increased numbers 
<lb/>are nothing else than concoctions of the 
<lb/>slave traders feeling the pressure from without 
<lb/><placeName>Angola</placeName> sent some thousands of slaves 
<lb/>annually down the coast for exportation 
<lb/>the trade was carried on thus. A trader went 
<lb/>to the Interior to purchase wax, ivory &amp;c. and 
<lb/>slaves. And he always purchased as many as 
<lb/>would carry his merchandise down to the 

	<pb n="0005" facs="liv_000827_0005"/><!--pb/@n='3r'-->
<lb/><add place="above"><unclear cert="low">2d</unclear></add> coast. He was sure of a market. Indeed in 1837 
<lb/>or just before the treaty for slave trade suppression 
<lb/>with Portugal came into operation <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Gabriel</persName>
<lb/>counted 39 ships in <placeName>Loanda Harbour</placeName> all waiting 
<lb/>for cargoes of slaves. At present no ship dare 
<lb/>appear on the coast with slave <unclear cert="medium">fettings</unclear> except to 
<lb/>make a dash into some one or two harbours 
<lb/>load hastily by night &amp; put to sea next morning 
<lb/>but to return to the slaves of the time when 
<lb/>when there were no British cruizers on the coast. All 
<lb/>that came down were sold &amp; exported. And as they 
<lb/>cannot now export them neither can they 
<lb/>buy them and therefore a new system of 
<lb/>carrying merchandise <add place="above">became</add> necessary. the new 
<lb/>system is called, of "Carregadores" or carriers and 
<lb/>the native chiefs living under the Portuguese are 
<lb/>obliged to furnish these carriers to do the work 
<lb/>formerly done only by slaves going to be exported. 
<lb/>this district supplies 400 monthly, and other 
<lb/>districts in proportion - I have met a thousand 
<lb/>of them in one day either going or returning 
<lb/>and every man of them was a proof of the 
<lb/>effectiveness of the English cruizers in repressing 
<lb/>the slave trade - for, up to the time when the 
<lb/>ships were placed on the coast all this work 
<lb/>of carrying was performed by those who had no hope of return</p>
<lb/><p>Again, Before the English squadron began 
<lb/>its operations the prices of good young slaves 

	<pb n="0006" facs="liv_000827_0006"/><!--pb/@n='3v'-->
<lb/>throughout the country near the coast or say within 
<lb/>200 miles of the coast line varied from 70 to 80 
<lb/>dollars per head (as they say) Now the very best 
<lb/>may be had for from 10 to 20. If the reason is 
<lb/>asked it invariably is "Because we can not now 
<lb/>export them." But say some slave trade abettors 
<lb/>if they can only get one cargo in four safe into 
<lb/>the transatlantic ports they realize handsome profits 
<lb/>I shall give you my reasons for doubting this. 
<lb/>At present the thing seems to cut two ways. Slaves 
<lb/>are very cheap now in <placeName>Angola</placeName> and that is 
<lb/>clearly the effect of the intervention of an armed 
<lb/>force. they are said to <add place="above">be</add> dear in proportion in 
<lb/><placeName>Cuba</placeName> &amp; <placeName>Brazil</placeName>. As soon as a trader gets his 
<lb/>ten dollar per head cargo clear off the African coast 
<lb/>Does he value them at that or at <add place="above">the</add> 150 or 200 dollars 
<lb/>he expects to get in <placeName>Cuba</placeName>. Clearly to my mind, 
<lb/>his livestock has become very precious in 
<lb/>the beast's own estimation, and unless some 
<lb/>exception, of operative self interest, <hi rend="underline">failing</hi> to 
<lb/>influence him, can be proved as existing in his 
<lb/>case. the most powerful motive he knows comes 
<lb/>into play to make him lessen the horrors of 
<lb/>the middle passage. though he regards them as 
<lb/>beasts, it is well known all over the world that 
<lb/>the most brutal being alive will be more likely 
<lb/>to treat <add place="above">well</add> a horse worth £200 than if it were worth 
<lb/>£10. only.</p>

	<pb n="0007" facs="liv_000827_0007"/><!--pb/@n='4r'-->
<lb/><p>My reasons for doubting the plea of handsome profits 
<lb/>being realized by the few slave traders who manage 
<lb/>to get clear off with an occasional cargo. are 
<lb/>the following. I have made many enquiries and 
<lb/>have not been able to discover more than two 
<lb/>or three who have hold of riches got in the slave trade 
<lb/>But again and again have individuals been 
<lb/>pointed out to me as having been once very 
<lb/>rich and having lost their all in it. But setting 
<lb/>aside particular cases let us look at the 
<lb/>capital of <placeName>Angola</placeName> - the city of <placeName>Loanda</placeName>. It may 
<lb/>be said to be in ruins and if the cause of 
<lb/>the decay be enquired into - It is the inability to 
<lb/>carry on the slave trade as in what they term 
<lb/>the <unclear cert="medium">Palmy</unclear> days of the city. they have an expressive 
<lb/>way of indicating the pressure from without. We 
<lb/>refrain say they "pela forca da necessidade" ("by the 
<lb/>power of necessity") the public gardens on the 
<lb/>walls of which stood the inscription written with 
<lb/>all the successful slaveholder's pride "Let this serve 
<lb/>as an example to Posterity" are now in ruins 
<lb/>and so unrecognisable a gentleman of the Navy 
<lb/>asked me when near it "Where are the gardens 
<lb/>spoken of in the accounts of Loanda?" Many 
<lb/>now turn their attention to Agriculture who 
<lb/>if the tales of antisquadronites were true would 
<lb/>much prefer the handsome profits of every 
<lb/>fourth voyage. Indeed the tale seems to have 

	<pb n="0008" facs="liv_000827_0008"/><!--pb/@n='4v'-->
<lb/>been got up by those who are friendly to the trade 
<lb/>and others including <persName>your professor</persName> and your 
<lb/>obd<hi rend="sup underline">t</hi> servant followed in the trail. thinking our 
<lb/>selves knowing fellows <add place="above">too</add> and so far ahead of the ancients 
<lb/>who thought that hard knocks would serve best 
<lb/>the villains who trample remorselessly on God's image 
<lb/>in ebony. the reason why some opinions 
<lb/>get afloat is, occasionally in England people may 
<lb/>give utterance to very strong views and their 
<lb/>auditors are in profound ignorance that the 
<lb/>spokesman is deriving a good income from 
<lb/>an indirect connection with the slave trade 
<lb/>I saw bales of goods for the traffic marked "<placeName>Glasgow</placeName>" 
<lb/>If the American flag were not so often employed 
<lb/>to cloak it there would be fewer profits still.</p>
<lb/><p>I have been examining some of the old Jesuit 
<lb/>Mission stations in the country and the fruits 
<lb/>of their labours. From all accounts the 
<lb/>Jesuits were very exemplary in their lives and 
<lb/>devoted themselves to the instruction of the 
<lb/>people conscientiously. the effect of their efforts 
<lb/>is seen in the numbers who can read &amp; write 
<lb/>in the country. They teach each other now 
<lb/>and in the <placeName>district of Ambaca</placeName> it is considered 
<lb/>a disgrace for any one to be unable to read 
<lb/>When the Jesuits were expelled from Portuguese 
<lb/>Territory by the <persName>Marquis of Pombal</persName>, the 

	<pb n="0009" facs="liv_000827_0009"/><!--pb/@n='5r'-->
<lb/><choice><sic>the</sic><corr>notext</corr></choice> place of the Jesuits was supplied by a batch of the 
<lb/>regular priesthood, with five long beards. these were 
<lb/>graceless <unclear cert="low">bardies</unclear>, who loved to tuck up their <unclear cert="low">nalects</unclear>
<lb/>around their waists and join in the dances of the natives 
<lb/>I visited one of the stations called <placeName>Bango</placeName> a few days 
<lb/>ago. It consists of a good church and row of 
<lb/>buildings at right angles to the farther end. these 
<lb/>contain the dormitories of the missionaries and 
<lb/>some large chests for holding their grub. there 
<lb/>are no books, all, with the silver &amp; gold having 
<lb/>been removed by the present <persName>bishop to Loanda</persName>
<lb/>there are no inscriptions on their graves. they 
<lb/>were just allowed to die out. &amp; the poor fellows 
<lb/>sleep in silence waiting for the sound of <add place="above">the</add> terrible 
<lb/>trumpet. the people could tell nothing about these 
<lb/>last batch except their fine beards. But one 
<lb/>ventured on being questioned to tell that an inhabitant 
<lb/>of the lovely valley of <placeName>Bango</placeName> was honoured by 
<lb/>the arrival in his domicile of a little <hi rend="underline">white</hi> stranger 
<lb/>Being afraid to speak out on the occasion He 
<lb/>remarked. "A wonderful thing has happened in 
<lb/><placeName>Bango</placeName>. Both my wife and I am black yet 
<lb/>we have got a white child! this must be another 
<lb/>of the miracles of St. Hilarion" - (the patron saint 
<lb/>of the establishment) the man told it with a 
<lb/>twitching of the muscles about the mouth which 
<lb/>shewed he had often enjoyed a hearty guffaw 
<lb/>on the subject before</p>
<lb/><p>You will <choice><sic>percieve</sic><corr>perceive</corr></choice> that the country possesses 

	<pb n="0010" facs="liv_000827_0010"/><!--pb/@n='5v'-->
<lb/>features of great interest. the people are ready for 
<lb/>reading the word of God. What a difference between 
<lb/>them and those with whom I have to deal in the 
<lb/>regions beyond. Long years of our short lives 
<lb/>must be spent in the monotonous labour of 
<lb/>teaching to read those who have an inveterate 
<lb/>propensity to believe that they are conferring a 
<lb/>great favour by condescending to learn. And 
<lb/>after they have acquired a knowledge of reading 
<lb/>the majority of the young turn their backs as 
<lb/>obstinately against the gospel as before. they 
<lb/>think we have some interested motive in drawing 
<lb/>them to Christ. they will lose some of their 
<w>self-<lb break="no"/>esteem</w> if they yield. &amp;c &amp;c So that more rigorous 
<lb/>measures by God's providence seem absolutely 
<lb/>necessary to humble or punish them. Yet when 
<lb/>As in the case of <placeName>Tahiti</placeName> the rod falls upon them 
<lb/>what a hulleboloo we make about it in 
<lb/>England. Here the people have been suffering 
<lb/>the rod of the oppressor for centuries, and as they 
<lb/>can read they are in a proper state for <choice><sic>recieving</sic><corr>receiving</corr></choice>
<lb/>divine knowledge I have a strong desire to 
<lb/>scatter some bibles among them. And perhaps 
<lb/>do more. But will the Portuguese allow me? 
<lb/>I came out behind them. they would not have 
<lb/>allowed me to go in from <placeName>Loanda</placeName>. No English 
<lb/>man ever saw their fine fruitful country before 
<lb/>Being known now somewhat in the world they 

	<pb n="0011" facs="liv_000827_0011"/><!--pb/@n='6r'-->
<lb/>could not for shame refuse me passage back. But 
<lb/>it is ten to one if they would allow me to land 
<lb/>a box of bibles at <placeName>Loanda</placeName>. To do them justice 
<lb/>however I must say they have all treated me 
<lb/>with extraordinary kindness - * the above are my 
<lb/>suspicions more than actual knowledge of what 
<lb/>they would have done. <persName>the bishop</persName> did everything 
<lb/>he could for me. giving presents to all my 
<w>com-<lb break="no"/>pany</w> - a horse saddle &amp; bridle <del type="strikethrough">for the chief</del> and 
<lb/>the dress of a Colonel with Epaulettes cocked hat &amp;c 
<lb/>for the chief. Sending an order to all the 
<lb/>commandants to furnish me with every th<gap extent="3" unit="chars"/>
<lb/>I needed till beyond Portuguese territory 
<lb/>He embraced me when parting, bless His 
<lb/>Reverendissimus, I would have preferred 
<lb/>a kiss from my wife to a hug from this 
<lb/>benevolent &amp; kind hearted celibate in crimson 
<lb/>silk gown &amp; golden cross hung to his neck 
<lb/>It will be better not to publish anything 
<lb/>about the state of the Angolese perhaps for 
<lb/>Rome is vigilant and would not hesitate 
<lb/>to act immediately if it were only to shut 
<lb/>the door. I earnestly pray I may be permitted 
<lb/>to do something for the spread of Knowledge 
<lb/>of Christ here. Physically it is one of the finest 
<lb/>countries in the world but one would not 
<lb/>think so at the coast. In here the luxuriance 
<lb/>of vegetation is wonderful and beautiful. The </p>
<lb/><note n="*" place="marginleft" anchored="true">* this although they looked upon my coming as another wedge 
<lb/>in against their slave trading - When they saw me in the interior calculating 
<lb/>longitudes they wondered why a "<unclear cert="medium">Doctor</unclear> Mathematico" should pretend to be a missionary</note>

	<pb n="0012" facs="liv_000827_0012"/><!--pb/@n='6v'-->
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">missionaries introduced many fine fruit trees from 
<lb/>South America. One called fruta da Conde is like cream 
<lb/>in taste. A wild one called Masubiri has a large 
<lb/>fruit and resembles in appearance the breadfruit 
<lb/>I wish I could send you seeds. Edens fruits 
<lb/>have all been allowed to degenerate except the 
<lb/><anchor xml:id="envelopePosition" type="positionMarker"/> vine. In the Millennium I suppose they will be 
<lb/>recultivated and as much improved as the apple is 
<lb/>above the crab. My love to your spouse, and 
<lb/><unclear cert="medium">Sma'</unclear>family. I shall leave this as soon as my 
<lb/>patient is better. I have found an invaluable 
<lb/>friend <add place="above">in <placeName>Loanda</placeName> - West Coast (of Africa)</add> in Her Majestys Commissioner <persName>Edmund 
<lb/>Gabriel</persName> Esq<hi rend="sup underline">re</hi> Any letter sent to him will be 
<w>for-<lb break="no"/>warded</w> to England by him if I am there. <persName>D. Livingston</persName></p><!--written across back of envelope once folded--> 

<addSpan spanTo="#addEnd-6v-1" place="marginright"><!--addSpan/@place='right margin of p. 6v'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p>I have written <persName>John</persName> by same mail 
<lb/>a yankee vessel will take both to the States 
<lb/>(<placeName>Boston</placeName>?)</p><anchor xml:id="addEnd-6v-1"/> 

<addSpan spanTo="#addEnd-6v-2" place="end"><!--addSpan/@place='Sheet folded to make envelope. Envelope text on the middle of p. 6v'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p><!--enevelope--><persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> Charles Livingston</persName></p>
<lb/><p><hi rend="underline"><placeName>Plympton</placeName></hi></p>
<lb/><p>Near <placeName>Boston, Massachusetts</placeName></p>
<lb/><p><hi rend="underline"><!--double underline-->United States</hi></p><!--hand 01 bottom left of enevlope once folded - Paid--><!--several postmarks--><anchor xml:id="addEnd-6v-2"/>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>