<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_001428">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to John Washington</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to John Washington, 25 May 1859</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2009-10-06</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_001428</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">National Museum of the Royal Navy (Great Britain); MSS. 120</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0892</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Washington, John, 1800-1863</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1859-05-25">25 May 1859</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kongone Harbour</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2009-10-06</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Initial Transcription by Caroline Overy
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2009-10-17</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>First Proof by Chris Lawrence
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_001428_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1'--> 
<!-- Foliation is off on this potentially -->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Kongone Harbour</placeName></p>
<lb/><p rend="right">25 May 1859</p>
<lb/><p><hi rend="underline">Private</hi></p>
<lb/><p>My Dear Captain Washington</p>
<lb/><p>We came down here for 
<lb/>the 24<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> in expectation of meeting a 
<lb/>cruizer with salt provisions for our 
<lb/>crew but our letters to the Admiral must 
<lb/>have suffered detention somewhere or 
<lb/>the service may have required the 
<lb/>presence of the ships elsewhere. We have 
<lb/>lately been up the <placeName>Shire</placeName> and discovered 
<lb/>a magnificent inland Lake called 
<lb/><placeName>Shirwa</placeName>. We visited the river in 
<lb/>the beginning of this year and created 
<lb/>considerable alarm the people never 
<lb/>having been visited by white men 
<lb/>before. Remaining at <placeName>Tette</placeName> during 
<lb/>a portion of the unhealthy season 
<lb/>we returned to the <placeName>Shire</placeName> and found 
<lb/>the people all so friendly that we 
<lb/>left the vessel in charge of the 
<w>Quarter-<lb break="no"/>master</w> and Stoker - <persName>Walker</persName> &amp; <persName>Rowe</persName>
<lb/>and with <persName>D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Kirk</persName> &amp; 15 <term type="tribe">Makololo</term>
<lb/>prodeeded Northwards on foot. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he 
<lb/>chief with whom they remained is 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_001428_0002"/><!--pb/@n='2'--> 
<lb/><persName>Chibisa</persName> - an influential man as we found 
<lb/>by a servant he sent with us. We went 
<lb/>Northwards along the banks of the river 
<lb/>and in ten days had risen 1500 feet above 
<lb/>the ship - the river rushing over cataracts 
<lb/>is confined in a narrow channel and 
<lb/>with very little trouble would afford water 
<lb/>power equal to that of all the mills in 
<lb/>England. We then got information that 
<lb/>a large lake existed on our east and 
<lb/>believing that the <placeName>Shire</placeName> came out of it we tried 
<lb/>to go along it to fix the point of departure but 
<lb/>a marsh prevented our going to the North West 
<lb/>end of a Lofty mountain <placeName>Dzomba</placeName> or as 
<lb/>the people nearest pronounce it <placeName>Zomba</placeName> to 
<lb/>which the course of the <placeName>Shire</placeName> seemed to lead us 
<lb/>coming round the southern talus of <placeName>Zomba</placeName>
<lb/>we got a distant view of <placeName>Lake Shirwa</placeName>
<lb/>and were informed that the <placeName>Shire</placeName> had no 
<lb/>connection with it. The spur of <placeName>Zomba</placeName> which 
<lb/>we crossed was 3400 ft. above the ship 
<lb/>and the mass of the mountain on our left seemed 
<lb/>higher than <placeName>Morambala</placeName> which we ascertained 
<lb/>to be 4000 so we say <placeName>Zomba</placeName> is over 6000 ft. 
<lb/>Four days afterwards we reached the shores of 
<lb/><placeName>Shirwa</placeName> and a grand sight it is for it is surrounded 
<lb/>on all sides by lofty mountains equal if not 
<lb/>of greater altitude than <placeName>Zomba</placeName>. We went up 
<lb/>some distance the <placeName>mount <unclear cert="low">Pirimiti</unclear></placeName> and could 
<lb/>not see anything except a watery horizon 
<lb/>and two mountain tops like little islands 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_001428_0003"/><!--pb/@n='3'--> 
<lb/>in the blue distance fifty or sixty miles away<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>There is an uninhabited mountain island near 
<lb/>where we stood called <placeName>Shirwa</placeName> too. It is of a 
<lb/>spear or were it not so inelegant a tadpole 
<lb/>shape. We were in Lat. 15º 23′. Long. 35 35′ E 
<lb/>the Long. wants a correction for I observed 
<lb/>Antares for the East side of the Moon &amp; found 
<lb/>out afterwards that it was not in distance<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>We cannot be far wrong in saying between 
<lb/>35º &amp; 36º E. Long. This point is at the 
<lb/>beginning of the broad part and 30 miles 
<lb/>or so of tail stretch away southward<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he natives say and I see no reason to 
<lb/>doubt them that <placeName>Shirwa</placeName> is separated 
<lb/>by only five or six miles of comparatively 
<lb/>level land from <placeName>Nyinyesi</placeName> (= stars) the 
<lb/><placeName>Nyanja</placeName><placeName>'Nyassa</placeName> or <placeName>Uniamesi</placeName> for it 
<lb/>is called the "great Nyanja" but this 
<lb/>word, meaning only a collection of water 
<lb/>or a river, as the <placeName>Shire</placeName>, caused us much 
<lb/>confusion. When we enquired for <placeName>Nyanja</placeName>
<lb/>we were supposed to speak of either 
<lb/>the <placeName>Shire</placeName>, the <placeName>Shirwa</placeName> - a marsh - 
<lb/>or the <placeName>Lake 'Nyassa</placeName> - but <placeName>Nyinyesi</placeName>
<lb/>is distinctive. We subsequently found 
<lb/>out that the lower small end of <placeName>Shirwa</placeName>
<lb/>is separated by about 30 miles only 
<lb/>of Latitude from the branch of the <placeName>Shire</placeName>
<lb/>the <placeName>Ruo</placeName> up which we went seven or eight miles 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_001428_0004"/><!--pb/@n='4'--> 
<lb/>and not much over 2000 f<hi rend="sup underline">t</hi> of altitude. 
<lb/>While waiting to see if we are to get another 
<lb/>ship capable of stemming the rapids, we mean 
<lb/>to examine <placeName>Shirwa</placeName> perhaps <placeName>Nyinyesi</placeName> more 
<lb/>carefully. A first visit creates alarm 
<lb/>so we have to manage slowly to avoid collision<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>There is no outlet known to <placeName>Shirwa</placeName> - the 
<lb/>water is bitter but drinkable. It resembled 
<lb/>a very weak solution of Epsom salts. Many 
<lb/>streams flow into it for it is a very well 
<lb/>watered region. Vegetation &amp; streams with 
<lb/>bogs nearly identical with those of <placeName>Londa</placeName>. 
<lb/>People numerous and well armed with 
<lb/>large bows and poisoned arrows - they cultivate 
<lb/>an immense quantity of cotton. The farther 
<lb/>we went the more important did the 
<lb/>crop appear. All spin &amp; weave it. They 
<lb/>have no ivory, but plenty of provisions 
<lb/>at a cheap rate. We slept 20 nights on the 
<lb/>ground out of doors and got our clothes wet 
<lb/>with dew off the tall grass (7 or 8 ft) which 
<lb/>overhangs the paths every morning yet came 
<lb/>back in good health to the vessel. We saw 
<lb/>many old people and it seems from its 
<lb/>altitude to be a healthy region. The mountains 
<lb/>are very beautiful - generally clothed with vegetation 
<lb/>and often inhabited. <placeName>Zomba</placeName> is so and 
<lb/>we could see the cultivated patches from 
<lb/>below by their 
<lb/>brighter green. By the way 
<lb/>this mountain is not in the Lake 
<lb/>but it lies between the <placeName>Shirwa</placeName>  &amp; <placeName>Shire</placeName> valleys 

	<pb n="0005" facs="liv_001428_0005"/><!--pb/@n='5'--> 
<lb/>and to a spectator on <placeName>Nyinyesi</placeName> probably 
<lb/>appears standing in the Lake. The Longitudinal 
<lb/>crack speculation is a "cracked" one and must 
<lb/>go alongside of the <placeName>Zambesi</placeName> flowing down 
<lb/>to Quilimane and getting lost in the 
<lb/><placeName>Kalahari Desert</placeName>. The information collected 
<lb/>by the church missionaries (<unclear cert="low">bating</unclear> size) is 
<lb/>as far as we can learn the most reliable<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>We hope to be able to be able to tell you more about 
<lb/>it and we hope that our divergence 
<lb/>for a time only, from the <term type="tribe">Makalolo</term>
<lb/>country may be looked on favourably by the Foreign Office. The <term type="tribe">Makololo</term> performed their service very well. <placeName>Tette</placeName>
<lb/>suffers from a drought so it is a 
<lb/>benefit to take them where provisions 
<lb/>are cheap. I have given them while at 
<lb/><placeName>Tette</placeName> about 8 shillings worth of goods 
<lb/>weekly, but gave those who went 
<lb/>with us small wages. The whole trip 
<lb/>to <placeName>Shirwa</placeName> cost under £10. The Kroomen 
<lb/>say they cannot travel - but they are 
<lb/>bad specimens - the picked ones you 
<lb/>sent for all deserted on seeing that 
<lb/><persName>Bedingfeld</persName> was with us - so we got 
<lb/>a sorry lot off the streets of Sierra Leone 
<lb/>a crew of four English sailors and 

	<pb n="0006" facs="liv_001428_0006"/><!--pb/@n='6'--> 
<lb/>trusting to country people for wooding 
<lb/>would be preferable to Kroomen for 
<lb/>country people eat country produce<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Our fellows must have man of war's 
<lb/>allowance <add place="above">of cocoa, tea sugar flour biscuits &amp; beef &amp;c.</add> and we have to expend our 
<lb/>expedition stores on them though when 
<lb/>we leave the ship to go anywhere they are 
<lb/>useless. They got fever before we did. 
<lb/>We have an excellent <term type="tribe">Makololo</term> stoker 
<lb/>and the Quarter master says that they 
<lb/>beat the Kroomen in splitting wood. If 
<lb/>the <term type="tribe">Makololo</term> perform good service at 
<lb/><placeName>Nyinyesi</placeName> and they seem eager for it 
<lb/>having imbibed a little of the spirit of 
<lb/>discovery I hope you may get me 
<lb/>authorized to pay them say £1 or £1.10 
<lb/>each.</p>
<lb/><p>We have had fever among us 
<lb/>in spite of quinine but of so mild a 
<lb/>form that I failed to recognize it. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he 
<lb/>difference may be in our being well 
<lb/>provided for. I had it severely when 
<lb/>destitute of every comfort. <persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Kirk</persName>
<lb/>and I set down the attacks as common 
<lb/>colds - their repeated appearance with 
<lb/>the same symptoms in the same person 
<lb/>at last led us to conclude it was 
<lb/>fever. <persName>Baines</persName> gets heady &amp; incoherent 

	<pb n="0007" facs="liv_001428_0007"/><!--pb/@n='7'--> 
<lb/>having it is said once had brain fever. <persName>Rae</persName>
<lb/>exactly a severe cold. In <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> C. Livingstone</persName> as 
<lb/>if bilious. In <persName>Thornton</persName> it is like indigestion - 
<lb/><persName>D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Kirk</persName> and I have escaped - though we 
<lb/>have had enough of exposure to Malaria<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>We don<reg>'</reg>t believe in quinine as a preventative 
<lb/><persName>Rae</persName> took it without intermission - 
<lb/>but got it &amp; so did <persName>C. Livingstone</persName><reg>.</reg>
<lb/>We take it now though we have neither 
<lb/>sherry nor spirits to mix it by way 
<lb/>of keeping you folks from blaming 
<lb/>us after we are gone!</p>
<lb/><p>We left <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> C. Livingstone</persName> orders 
<lb/>to proceed to the gold region South West 
<lb/>of <placeName>Tette</placeName> in April but an irruption 
<lb/>of the Landeens prevented him. We 
<lb/>have a collection of plants to send 
<lb/>by the man of war - a box of Buaze 
<lb/>to be manufactured into cloth. We intend 
<lb/>sending seeds <add place="above">of it</add> &amp; live plants to India. 
<lb/>We send also sketches of the rapids 
<lb/>by <persName>Baines</persName> in oil. They are the only 
<lb/>things he does well. His natives are 
<lb/>a compound of Low West African 
<lb/>negro - South Australian and Patagonian 
<lb/>quite unlike the people here and useless 
<lb/>for the purposes of Ethnology. The 

	<pb n="0008" facs="liv_001428_0008"/><!--pb/@n='8'--> 
<lb/>only peculiarities <persName>D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Kirk</persName> and I can 
<lb/>detect is a widening of the alae nasi and 
<lb/>prolongation of the head upwards &amp; 
<w>back-<lb break="no"/>wards</w> - this <persName>Baines</persName> cannot catch. 
<lb/><persName>Rae</persName> is an excellent engineer - very 
<lb/>obliging, willing &amp; well behaved. But 
<lb/>he leaves at the end of two years I suppose 
<lb/>for the sake of rising in his profession 
<lb/>as he is much esteemed by Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi><persName>Tod</persName>
<lb/>and <persName>Macgregor</persName> of Glasgow. It would be 
<lb/>no loss though <persName>Baines</persName> and <persName>Thornton</persName>
<lb/>retired too <add place="above">(<persName>Baines</persName> becomes a little heady sometimes)</add> - The latter is too young for 
<lb/>roughing it. The expedition would be quite 
<lb/>as efficient without them. I have had 
<lb/><persName>Thornton</persName> mining coal at <placeName>Tette</placeName> but he does 
<lb/>very little, and - he lays all the blame on 
<lb/>the people employed under him. He cannot 
<lb/>be trusted out of sight and is frequently 
<lb/>ill - a small expedition is the most 
<lb/>manageable in <add place="above">exploration.</add> This is of course between 
<lb/>ourselves. The luggage becomes a nuisance.</p>
<lb/><p><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he Portuguese have got a new Governor 
<lb/>General and his brother supersedes our 
<lb/>best friend <persName>Major Secard</persName> at <placeName>Tette</placeName>. We have 
<lb/>to vacate the commandant<reg>'</reg>s residence and 
<lb/>will use our iron house. They try to make 
<lb/>all we discover appear theirs &amp; will soon set 
<lb/>up a settlement at the mouth of the <placeName>Shire</placeName>, and 
<lb/>a custom house here for this purpose. Please 
<lb/>present my kind salutations to <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">rs</hi> W.</persName> David Livingstone</p>

	<pb n="0009" facs="liv_001428_0009"/><!--pb/@n='9'--> 
<addSpan spanTo="#p1-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left margins of pp. 1-3'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p><persName>D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Kirk</persName> and <persName>C. Livingstone</persName> with the Quarter master &amp; stoker are all than can be wished. They 
<lb/>take kindly to the natives. We make another spirit level and will try Magnetical observations at 
<lb/><placeName>Shirwa</placeName> for <persName>Gen. Sabine</persName>. We shall probably try &amp; carry a whaler with us on the axle &amp; wheels 
<lb/>designed for the Launch but say nothing lest we fail<reg>.</reg></p>

	<pb n="0010" facs="liv_001428_0010"/><!--pb/@n='1v'-->
<lb/><p>Meteorology was in <persName>Bedingfeld's</persName> department and a sorry set of instruments he 
<lb/>selected. Mountain barometer without index error - another 

	<pb n="0011" facs="liv_001428_0011"/><!--pb/@n='2r'--> 
<lb/>broken - Maximum thermometer broken another useless &amp; other things awanting 
<lb/>altogether - a sextant I would not pick off the <unclear cert="medium">streets</unclear>. Fortunately I brought my own 
<lb/>I have sent my observations to <persName>Maclear</persName><reg>.</reg></p><anchor xml:id="p1-01"/><addSpan spanTo="#p9-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left margin'--></addSpan><!-- is this addspan in the right place - presume it was written before pages 5r and 5v; Chris thinks not--><!-- Yes, this is the envelope sheet. Livie likely originally decided to put a little note written up the envelope - then several months later, he added a longer note - which can almost be considered another letter (in a sense)-->
<lb/><p>I shall ask the Admiral to <choice><sic>recieve</sic><corr>receive</corr></choice> the 
<lb/>Kroomen - the lighter we are the better<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Two English sailors are better than 10 Kroomen<reg>.</reg></p><anchor xml:id="p9-01"/>
<lb/><p>P.S. It would lessen our expenses and not 
<lb/>impair our efficiency if we could ship the Kroomen 
<lb/>on board a man of war without breaking their 
<lb/>engagement for two years. The <term type="tribe">Makololo</term> would 
<lb/>not be half the expense - they are quite as much 
<lb/>sailors as four fifths of the Kroomen we have got. 
<lb/>The Portuguese and we are good friends, but when they are 
<lb/>drunk we hear that they dislike the Expedition in their 
<lb/>hearts, and when we recollect what they did to <persName>Macleod</persName>
<lb/>if another ship is sent out a Pennon <add place="above">with guns</add> or authority to wear 
<lb/>one would be an advantage, but of this you are the 
<lb/>best judge. D. L.</p>

	<pb n="0012" facs="liv_001428_0012"/><!--pb/@n='10'-->
<ab type="envelope">
<address>
<addrLine><persName>Captain Washington R. N.</persName></addrLine>
<addrLine>Admiralty</addrLine>
<addrLine>D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Livingstone</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>