<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P5 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_003018">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to John McRobert and Catherine McRobert</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to John McRobert and Catherine McRobert, 5 June 1844</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London, UK</pubPlace>
				<publisher>University College London</publisher>
				<date>2012</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_003018</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">National Library of Scotland; Acc. 13274</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0102</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>McRobert, John, 1793/4-1876</persName>; <persName>McRobert, Catherine</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1844-06-05">5 June 1844</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Mabotsa</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2011-12-10</date>
				<name xml:id="AJS">A.J. Schmitz</name> initial transcription and XML encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-03-04</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Jared McDonald</name> proofreading.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-07-01</date>
				<name xml:id="HFB">Heather F. Ball</name> XML editing.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-09-09</date>
				<name xml:id="AW">Adrian S. Wisnicki</name> XML editing.
            
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_003018_0001"><!--pb/@n='1'--></pb>
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName><settlement type="village">Mabotsa</settlement></placeName> <date when="1844-06-05">5 June 1844</date></p>
<lb/><p>My Dear <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">rs</hi> M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>Robert</persName></p>
<lb/><p>I expected to have heard from you long before this 
<lb/>as it is now the fourth time I have written you and considerable intervals have
<lb/>always elapsed between each.  But though hope deferred maketh the 
<lb/>heart sick I cannot say mine is in that state yet, and perhaps the 
<lb/>reason is we in this outlandish region are so constantly obliged to defer 
<lb/>our hopes we at last become used to the employment.- I shall now 
<lb/>give you some account of what is doing here <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">in order</add> that you may understand  
<lb/>we are not unmindful of our obligations to your exertions. And first 
<lb/>of all I may mention that your agent <persName>Mebaloe</persName> (alias <persName>David Molehane</persName>) 
<lb/>has since we came to this sphere of labour given us entire satisfaction 
<lb/>in all the operations requiring manual labour he has worked with us 
<lb/>in a manner which <choice><orig>shews</orig><reg>shows</reg></choice> he is in earnest and his addresses to 
<lb/>his countrymen are characterized by good sense, affection and 
<lb/>faithfulness. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edwards</persName> took him lately to a number of 
<lb/>villages situated near the <placeName><settlement type="village">Kureechane</settlement></placeName> in order to introduce him 
<lb/>to the people and I intend in a day or two to do the same in a 
<lb/>number of villages of the <term type="tribe">Makone</term> situated North East of 
<lb/>us. There are about a dozen villages around us, some of them 
<lb/>of considerable size and situated conveniently for itinerary 
<lb/>to which we intend paying stated visits. <persName>Mébaloe</persName> will take a part 
<lb/>in this labour and we hope the Lord will incline the hearts of his <w>country- 
<lb break="no"/>-men</w> to listen to the words of life from his mouth. A long continued 
<lb/>application of the truth to their minds seems the only mode by 
<lb/>which <del type="cancelled">at</del> by the Divine blessing it can find its way to their hearts 
<lb/>their minds are so thoroughly absorbed by what is seen they never once 
<lb/>bestow a thought on what is invisible.  Every motion of their souls 
<lb/>has a reference to earth &amp; to that only.  and as this has been the case 
<lb/>from generation to generation they seem to have sunk as far as 
<lb/>human nature can go. At one period they seem to have worshipped 

     

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_003018_0002"><!--pb/@n='2'--></pb>
<lb/>animals But if I am not wrong in my conjecture that idolatry <w>degener<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-ated</w> so far that only the mere vestiges of it now remain, these <w>rem<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-nants</w> of animal worship are the facts that each tribe is called by the 
<lb/>name of an animal, By it they swear, In general neither kill nor eat 
<lb/>it, Sometimes they <choice><sic>wont</sic><corr>won't</corr></choice> look at it &amp; say it is the friend of their tribe 
<lb/>thus the name <term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term> is literally <hi rend="underline">they</hi> (of the) <hi rend="underline">monkey</hi>, <term type="tribe">Battapi</term>, <hi rend="underline">they</hi>
<lb/>(of the) <hi rend="underline">Fish</hi>, the <term type="tribe">Bakwain</term>, they of the <choice><orig>crokodile</orig><reg>crocodile</reg></choice><term type="tribe">Bachuéne</term> they of 
<lb/>the Baboon. The <term type="tribe">Barolong</term> if asked by what they swear invariably 
<lb/>answer "we dance to iron", and in hunting they kill a khoodoo, a 
<lb/>magnificent animal of the antelope kind invariably make loud 
<lb/>lamentations before commencing to flay it. As yo yo yo we have 
<lb/>killed our father,  yo yo yo &amp;c. believing if they do not make a sort 
<lb/>of weeping some of them will die in consequence of the neglect 
<lb/>But whether animal worship was formerly prevalent among them 
<lb/>or not they now give that place in their affections so entirely 
<lb/>to the creature which belongs to the Creator they know of nothing 
<lb/>superior to the possession of oxen &amp; plenty of milk from their cows 
<lb/>their depravity seems subnatural and a considerable time appears to 
<lb/>be required before they are raised to the level of sinners in other countries 
<lb/>this view may be the effect of my unbelief but we find that 
<lb/>conversion is always a slow process among <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>
<lb/>In the <placeName><settlement type="village">Lattakoo</settlement></placeName> district the gospel has effected wonders on the 
<lb/>whole population so much so indeed they are not to be compared 
<lb/>to the <term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term>. You will of course understand when I speak of 
<lb/>a change effected on the whole population I do not refer to the 
<lb/>new phases of character which the gospel has developed in 
<lb/>believers But to the unconverted and to those other than saving 
<lb/>influences of Christianity which so materially modify the 
<lb/>social system at home. There the general conviction has 
<lb/>been produced that there is a God, that man has some 
<lb/>relationship to Him - that this life is but the beginning of our 
<lb/>existence and death but one event in a life which is <w>ever- 
<lb break="no"/>-lasting</w> - there are still a great want in the moral feeling and 

     

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_003018_0003"><!--pb/@n='3'--></pb>
<lb/>strange stupor &amp; somnolence of conscience But compared to what 
<lb/>they were and what the <term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term> now are the former are enlightened 
<lb/>&amp; civilized. Yet even at <placeName><settlement type="village">Lattakoo</settlement></placeName> the process of conversion 
<lb/>is slow. A not much quicker rate obtains than there was in the churches 
<lb/>of <persName>D<hi rend="sup underline">rs</hi> Haugh</persName> &amp; <persName>Wardlaw</persName> when I was in <placeName><settlement type="city">Glasgow</settlement></placeName>. (O these good 
<lb/>men, my heart warms to them everytime I look up at their portraits 
<lb/>I seem to hear their voices yet even in the still still quietness of the 
<lb/>desert. words from some ministers enter right into the soul and 
<lb/>glow there for ever. O that I had the tongue of the learned &amp; wisdom 
<lb/>to win souls) It is the greatness of the change - Christianity transforming 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> (I have not a word expressive of the extreme of degradation) into 
<lb/>men, that constitutes the wonderful cause for gratitude. I believe 
<lb/>it is a greater miracle than instantaneous cure of the blind would 
<lb/>be to them. It arrests more attention than any physical change 
<lb/>I have occasionally been called to cases of imminent danger 
<lb/>and the disease simulating another had I not had the benefit of the 
<lb/><del type="cancelled">the</del> <add place="above">familiar instructions of</add> most eminent medical men in <placeName><settlement type="city">London</settlement></placeName> I should probably have 
<lb/>mistaken complaint &amp; treatment &amp; the case ended fatally. But 
<lb/>proper treatment here administered restoration to health quickly 
<lb/>followed But notwithstanding that and my having travelled 40 miles 
<lb/>sometimes sixty under a burning sun &amp; spending nearly the whole 
<lb/>of several nights watching in their huts, <add place="above">besides providing medicine</add> the cure instead of arresting  
<lb/>attention scarcely secured thanks from the individual But let a 
<lb/>man turn from his evil ways to serve the Lord <del type="cancelled">and</del> the whole 
<lb/>country hears of it. The good are glad &amp; the wicked <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice><w>under- 
<lb break="no"/>-stand</w> the folly of the man who has ceased to follow the customs 
<lb/>of his ancestors. they are not all insensible to the benefits they 
<lb/>have <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> by medicine But while that does much to secure their 
<lb/>attention &amp; sometimes affection the Holy Spirit gives more <w>power<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>-ful</w> testimony to the truth of the gospel by the conversion of souls 
<lb/>than we could give by the possession of the power of working 
<lb/>miracles. Pray we beseech you that He may work mightily among 
<lb/>the <term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term> &amp; surrounding tribes --- My life was mercifully spared 
<lb/>when in danger by the jaws of a lion, <persName>Mebaloe</persName> nearly lost his in 
<lb/>his faithful endeavours to save me, both of <add place="above">us</add> <add place="below">^</add> were much hurt, he 

     

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_003018_0004"><!--pb/@n='4'--></pb>
<lb/>in the thigh &amp; I in the shoulder &amp; arm, the bone of the latter being smashed 
<lb/>to <choice><sic>peices</sic><corr>pieces</corr></choice> and twelve gashes besides. But through the tender mercy of 
<lb/>our God we are both now quite well May the spared lives be entirely 
<lb/>devoted to the glory of our Great Deliverer. It was he who saved and 
<lb/>he who healed my wounds Blessed be his glorious name for ever &amp; ever
<lb/>I think I mentioned several objections against sending clothes to the 
<lb/>people of this country for gratuitous distribution, these do not apply 
<lb/>to those lately brought by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName>, they will be given as rewards 
<lb/>for labour on the station &amp; will besides giving a taste of civilization 
<lb/>save the funds of the society &amp; wont destroy their feeling of independence 
<lb/>so as to make them any greater beggars than they naturally are
	<cb/>
<lb/>And now my dear Friend I must bid you again farewell. May you 
<lb/>both be favoured with every needed blessing Yours affectionately</p>
<lb/><p rend="right"><persName>David <choice><orig>Livingston</orig><reg>Livingstone</reg></choice></persName></p>
	<ab>
<lb/>Home of <persName>Rev D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi>Phillip</persName><placeName><settlement type="city"><hi rend="underline">Cape Town</hi></settlement></placeName>
<lb/><persName>Rev.<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> I. M<hi rend="sup underline">c</hi>Robert</persName>
<lb/><placeName><settlement type="town">Cambuslang</settlement></placeName> near 
<lb/><hi rend="underline">2 Sheets</hi><space dim="horizontal" extent="12" unit="chars"/><placeName><settlement type="city"><hi rend="underline">Glasgow</hi></settlement></placeName></ab>

			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>