<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_002673">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Paper Prepared for the Royal Geographical Society by Dr Livingstone</title>
                <title type="alternative">Paper Prepared for the Royal Geographical Society by Dr Livingstone, January 1862</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>DATE</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_002673</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Royal Geographical Society (Great Britain); Archives, DL 3/13/3</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Papers and Reports, 20</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1862">January 1862</date></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2008-06-11</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>Initial Transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2009-03-18</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Christopher Lawrence</name>Proof by Chris Lawrence
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_002673_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1r'-->
<lb/><p rend="center"><hi rend="underline"><placeName><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he Royal Geographical Society</placeName></hi></p>
<lb/><p>Under the impression that the Fellows of the Royal 
<lb/>Geographical Society appreciate attempts made by 
<lb/>our countrymen for the benefit of their fellow men, 
<lb/>I may mention before proceeding to detail the operations 
<lb/>of our own mission on <placeName>Lake Nyassa</placeName>, that we 
<lb/>had the pleasure of shewing the <placeName>Oxford</placeName> &amp; <placeName>Cambridge</placeName>
<lb/>missionaries, the way from <placeName>Dakanamoio Island</placeName>
<lb/>a few miles below <placeName>Murchison's cataracts</placeName> to the 
<lb/>highlands of the <placeName>Manganja</placeName> South of <placeName>Mount 
<lb/>Zomba</placeName>. We left the ship in their company on 
<lb/>the 15<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> July and in two marches reached the edge 
<lb/>of the plateau of some 3000 feet on which 
<w>geo-<lb break="no"/>graphers</w> will agree that, with common sense, 
<lb/>the missionaries are more likely to enjoy good 
<lb/>health while pursuing their benevolent enterprise 
<lb/>than they would be on any of the adjacent 
<w>low-<lb break="no"/>lands.</w> Here we were mortified to find that 
<w>ad-<lb break="no"/>vantage</w> had been taken of the route followed by <persName>D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi>
<lb/>Kirk</persName> from the <placeName>Shire</placeName> to <placeName>Tette</placeName> to institute an extensive 
<lb/>system of slave hunting in the very country to which 
<lb/>the bishop and his associates had come. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he 
<lb/>first party met had eighty four captives. As it 
<lb/>was possible that they might have been bought, 
<lb/>they were asked how they came to be bound and led 
<lb/>in that way towards <placeName>Tette</placeName>. It turned out that 
<lb/>a marauding party of a tribe named Ajawa 
<lb/>or Ajauwa had been incited by the <placeName>Tette</placeName> people 
<lb/>to attack village after village of Manganja, kill 
<lb/>the men and sell the women and children to them. 
<lb/>During the course of the enquiry the adventurers 
<lb/>escaped into the forest, and the best thing that 
<lb/>could be done was to present these and the captives 
<lb/>of three other Portuguese parties to the bishop to try 
<lb/>what he could make of them. Altogether they 
<lb/>numbered about one hundred and forty souls - 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_002673_0002"/><!--pb/@n='1v'-->
<lb/>chiefly women and children. After all who choose 
<lb/>to have the Mission have departed, a little flock probably 
<lb/>of a hundred will remain free from parental 
<lb/>control and from contamination with heathenism. 
<lb/>No modern mission has been more auspiciously 
<lb/>commenced. Not even the <placeName>London</placeName> Mission in 
<lb/><placeName>Madagascar</placeName> when <persName>King Radama</persName> presented a 
<lb/>large body of youths for instruction, for the 
<lb/>instruction was to subserve his own political 
<lb/>ends. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he new mission may therefore well be 
<lb/>upon its metal to shew fruits at least equal to 
<lb/>those of which the Independents can tell, and which 
<lb/>long after all the departure of all the missionaries 
<lb/>from <placeName>Madagascar</placeName>, have stood the test of bloody 
<lb/>persecutions. Placed as they are in the Centre of the 
<lb/>slave market with all our hearts we wish them 
<lb/>success. * see narrative of <persName>Johns</persName> &amp; <persName>Freeman</persName>; <persName>Ellis</persName> insists. </p>
<lb/><p>The spot selected for a temporary residence is, 
<lb/>to the eye, about 15 miles south <add place="above">the middle of</add><placeName>Mount Zomba</placeName>. It 
<lb/>is on the banks of a stream about 10 yards wide called 
<lb/><placeName>Magomero</placeName> - and will serve <del type="strikethrough">better</del> <add place="above">more extended</add> acquaintance 
<lb/>with the country enables them to choose a better. The 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Manganja</term> - (pronounced <term type="tribe">Mañ-nja</term> never 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Manggganja)</term> have so little organization that 
<lb/>the destruction of one village after another produced 
<lb/>no union for mutual defense. Their paramount 
<lb/>chief, who lives on the <placeName>Shire</placeName>, did nothing but 
<lb/>help those who were carrying off his people across 
<lb/>that river. The nation seemed in no ways 
<w>sur-<lb break="no"/>prised</w> at his supineness. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he only effort made 
<lb/>was to send for a chief who is believed to ensure 
<lb/>victory by his sorceries - and the bravery of the 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Manganja</term> of which we <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice>such 
<lb/>highly coloured accounts from the Portuguese, 
<lb/>shewed itself in universal flight before the <term type="tribe">Ajawa</term><reg>.</reg>
<lb/>It was plain that if these marauders were not 
<lb/>induced to desist the fine fertile country would 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_002673_0003"/><!--pb/@n='2r'-->
<lb/>soon be inhabited by the missionaries alone. With 
<lb/>a view to stop the effusion of more blood we set off 
<lb/>to hold a parley with the <term type="tribe">Ajawa</term>, and found them at the 
<lb/>base of <placeName>Mount Zomba</placeName>. Unfortunately we came 
<lb/>upon them in the very moment of victory for they 
<lb/>were burning three villages, and a long line of 
<lb/>captives laden with plunder were moving along to 
<lb/>the temporary residence of the plunderers. Here the 
<lb/>bishop offered up a solemn &amp; fervent prayer &amp; 
<lb/>with the accents of his prayer we could hear the 
<lb/>sad wail for the dead, and the shrill screams of joy 
<lb/>over the victory - a panic seized the captives <add place="above">or carriers</add> as 
<lb/>we first appeared in sight - all dashed down their 
<lb/>loads and fled. <choice><reg>B</reg><orig>b</orig></choice>ut the <term type="tribe">Ajawa</term> soon demanded 
<lb/>if we came peaceably. Our assurances in the 
<lb/>affirmative were neutralized by some <term type="tribe">Manganja</term>
<lb/>followers calling out, "Our Chibisa (the great sorcerer) 
<lb/>has come". And most unfortunately the effect 
<lb/>of this foolish call in depriving us of the protection 
<lb/>of our English name was not realized until 
<w>after-<lb break="no"/>wards.</w> Elated too with continued success they 
<lb/>probably thought that a small party of about twenty 
<lb/>would prove such an easy prey, that they began 
<lb/>to shoot us with their poisoned arrows. Even 
<lb/>slowly retiring from their village was considered 
<lb/>only evidence of fear, and they crowded round 
<lb/>to within fifty yards, and but for recourse to 
<lb/>our firearms in self defence would soon have 
<lb/>cut us all off. <del type="strikethrough">We</del> So little did we anticipate this, 
<lb/>the English name having hitherto served to 
<lb/>ensure respect, that we had barely ammunition 
<lb/>to serve our purpose. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he <term type="tribe">Manganja</term> followers 
<lb/>alone suffered from the arrows and guns of the 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Ajawa</term>. After this small band of sixty or eighty 
<lb/>robbers were driven off other bodies of <term type="tribe">Ajawa</term>
<lb/>have been employed by the people of <placeName>Tette</placeName> and 
<lb/><del type="strikethrough">to me</del> it seems evident that it is intended to 
<lb/>root out the mission without the authorities 
<lb/>being in any way compromised. We have 
<lb/>some reason to believe that the guns were handled by Portuguese 
<lb/><add place="inline">slaves</add><reg>.</reg></p>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_002673_0004"/><!--pb/@n='2v'-->
<lb/><p>Returning to the ship at <placeName>Dakanamoio Island</placeName>
<lb/>we began the carriage of a boat past <placeName>Murchison's 
<lb/>Cataracts
</placeName>on the 6<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> of August. And in three 
<lb/>weeks placed her on the <placeName>Upper Shire</placeName> in Lat. 15°15 20′ 
<lb/>S. The cataracts begin in 15° 55′ S. So we have 35′ 
<lb/>or 40′ of land carriage. The Western bank was 
<lb/>followed that being smoother than the Eastern 
<lb/>In the worst parts a few small trees cut down 
<lb/>opened a path for our shouting assistants who 
<lb/>kindly considered the boat as a certificate of 
<lb/>peaceful intentions to them at least. Launched 
<lb/>on the <placeName>Upper Shire</placeName> we were virtually on the Lake, 
<lb/>for there is but little difference of level. It has 
<lb/>little current, and is all of good depth. Before 
<lb/>entering the Lake proper in <del type="strikethrough">£15</del> <add place="above">14°</add> 25′ we pass 
<lb/>through the <placeName>Lakelet Pamalombe</placeName> - ten or twelve 
<lb/>miles long and five or six broad. It is nearly 
<lb/>surrounded by a broad belt of Papayrus 
<lb/>so densely planted we could scarcely find an 
<lb/>opening to the shore. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he plant is eight or ten 
<lb/>feet high <del type="strikethrough">and</del> air is excluded where it grows 
<lb/>and so much sulphuretted hydrogen gas 
<lb/>evolved the white paint o<del type="strikethrough">f</del> <add place="above">n</add> the bottom of the 
<lb/>boat was blackened. Myriads of Mosquitoes 
<lb/>shewed, as I think they always do, the presence 
<lb/>of malaria, and warned us off to the more 
<lb/>healthy shores of the <placeName>Lake Nyassa</placeName>. We sailed into 
<lb/>it on the 2<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> September and felt refreshed 
<lb/>by the greater coolness of the air in contact 
<lb/>with this large body of water. </p>
<lb/><p><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he depth was the first point of interest and 
<lb/>while skirting the Western shore about a 
<lb/>mile out, we found, as the <placeName>Upper Shire</placeName> was 
<lb/>from 9 to 15 feet, the Lake deepened from 9 to 
<lb/>fifteen fathoms. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hen as we rounded the 
<lb/>grand mountainous promontery, <placeName>Cape 

	<pb n="0005" facs="liv_002673_0005"/><!--pb/@n='3r'-->
<lb/>Maclear</placeName>, we could feel no bottom with our leadline 
<lb/>of 35 fathoms or 210 feet. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>s we subsequently wended 
<lb/>our way along the Western shore which is just a sucess <add place="above">ion</add>
<lb/>of bays, we found that where the bottom was sandy 
<lb/>at a mile from the land the depth varied from 
<lb/>six to fourteen fathoms. In a rocky bay about Lat. 
<lb/>11° 40′ S. we had bottom at 100 fathoms, but a 
<lb/>mile out of it we found none with a fishing line 
<lb/>of 116 fathoms or 696 feet, but this was 
<w>un-<lb break="no"/>satisfactory</w> as the line broke in coming up - according 
<lb/>to our present knowledge a ship could find 
<lb/>anchorage only near the shore. </p>
<lb/><p>Reverting to the Southern end we found the tongue 
<lb/>of the Lake from which the <placeName>Shire</placeName> flows to be about 
<lb/>30 miles long and ten or twelve broad. Rounding 
<lb/><placeName>Cape Maclear</placeName> Westwards we enter another arm 
<lb/>which stretches Southwards some 18 miles, and is 
<lb/>from 6 to 12 miles broad. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hese arms of the Lake 
<lb/>give the Southern <add place="above">end</add> a forked appearance, and 
<lb/>with the help of a little imagination it may be 
<lb/>likened to the boot shape of <placeName>Italy</placeName>. It is 
<lb/>narrowest about the ankle - 18 or 20 miles<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>From this it widens to the North, and in the 
<lb/>upper third or fourth it is fifty or sixty miles 
<lb/>broad. It's length is over 200 <add place="above">(or) (225)</add> miles. But we 
<lb/>were there at a very unfavourable period of 
<lb/>the year. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he "smokes" filled the air with an 
<lb/>impenetrable haze, and the Equinoctial gales 
<lb/>rendered it impossible for us to cross to the 
<lb/>Eastern side. As the sun rose behind mountains 
<lb/>sketches and bearings of these at different Latitudes 
<lb/>enabled us to secure approximate measurements 
<lb/>of its width - there are several crossing places 
<lb/>as at <placeName>Tsenga</placeName> and <placeName>Molamba</placeName> and about the 
<lb/>beginning of the upper third they get over by 
<lb/>taking advantage of the island <placeName>Chizumora</placeName>, but 
<lb/>further north they go round the end instead, though 
<lb/>that takes several days. Like all narrow seas 
<lb/>surrounded as this is by mountains, tremendous 
<lb/>swells get up very suddenly. On one of these occasions 

	<pb n="0006" facs="liv_002673_0006"/><!--pb/@n='3v'-->
<lb/>we were caught a mile from the shore and could 
<lb/>neither advance nor recede - <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he men all became 
<lb/>so sea sick &amp; they could scarcely be made to keep the 
<lb/>boat's head to the sea. Terrific rollers with 
<w>per-<lb break="no"/>pendicular</w> sides, and hairy heads came across the 
<lb/>Lake, but fortuntely broke either before they reached 
<lb/>or had passed us. We were riding at anchor in 
<lb/>seven fathoms. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he boat behaved admirably during 
<lb/>the six weary hours we were detained there, but 
<lb/>one roller breaking on her would have ended our 
<lb/>exploration. After this we trusted implicitly to the 
<lb/>opinions of our seaman <persName>John Neil</persName>, and often sat 
<lb/>cowering for days together waiting for the surf to go 
<lb/>down. We had to beach the boat every night to 
<lb/>save her from being swamped at anchor - and did 
<lb/>we not believe that the frequent storms were peculiar 
<lb/>to that period of the year would call <placeName>Nyassa</placeName> "the Lake 
<lb/>of storms". No current could be detected. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he sounding 
<lb/>line shewed no deflection from the perpendicular. 
<lb/>The boat swing at her anchor whenever the slightest 
<lb/>breath of wind blew her - and patches of water loving 
<lb/>grass which the natives anchor over fishing creels 
<lb/>to attract the fish by the shade, invariably shewed 
<lb/>the direction of the wind alone - the natives are 
<lb/>aware however that a long continued gale raises 
<lb/>the water a few inches on the shore to which it blows, 
<lb/>and then of course it must return to its level. We 
<lb/>tried hard <del type="strikethrough">for</del> <add place="above">to</add> find a current, for we hope to - 
<lb/>navigate the Lake ourselves, and "an unknown 
<lb/>current" is the plank by which many lubbers 
<lb/>who lose their ships are saved. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he height of the 
<lb/>water varies between the wet and dry seasons 
<lb/>about three feet. Five rivers flow into it from 
<lb/>the West. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey are from 15 to 30 yards wide and 
<lb/>some require canoes in crossing. <choice><reg>B</reg><orig>b</orig></choice>ut unitedly 
<lb/>they do not account for <add place="above">evaporation and</add> the <placeName>Shire's</placeName> perennial 
<lb/>flow. A large river may come in further north, 
<lb/>but great was my disappointment in not 
<lb/>finding a river that would lessen the longitude 
<lb/>towards the country of the Makololo. Many 
<lb/>torrents - stagnant when we passed - discharge 
<lb/>much water in the rainy season. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he water 

	<pb n="0007" facs="liv_002673_0007"/><!--pb/@n='4r'-->
<lb/>is fresh, but somewhat earthy tasted and hard - this 
<lb/>may not be the case when the Lake is full - the water 
<lb/>never becomes hot as in the <placeName>Shire</placeName> &amp; <placeName>Zambesi</placeName>. We 
<lb/>were there during the hottest period of the year - and 
<lb/>we could bathe in its delightful water whenever 
<lb/>we chose, for the alligators though enormous fellows, 
<lb/>are well fed on fish and seldom kill men. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey 
<lb/>capture people in the <placeName>Zambesi</placeName> chiefly when the water 
<lb/>is disco<del type="strikethrough">u</del>loured and they cannot see their natural 
<lb/>prey. Fish abound in <placeName>Nyassa</placeName> and the vast 
<lb/>population on its shores all engage in catching them 
<lb/>with trawling nets - creels, hooks, torches or 
<lb/>poison. As the sun declines groups of natives 
<lb/>in hundreds sit and gossip under the shady trees 
<lb/>near the water's edge waiting till the surf goes down. 
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hen launching their canoes they commence 
<w>traw-<lb break="no"/>ling,</w> and often continue their labours most of the 
<lb/>night. Toiling in a state of nudity they too suffer 
<lb/>from fever, but their skins are much more 
<lb/>torpid in function than ours - our beards grow 
<lb/>as much in a week as their wool does in a month. 
<lb/>Hence "conformity to the customs of the natives" 
<lb/>which people sometimes enjoin, would require 
<lb/>a modification of our highly excitable skins - the 
<lb/>son of the celebrated traveller <persName>Mungo Park</persName> is said 
<lb/>to have gone about <placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName> in a sheet like the 
<lb/>Fulahs and conformity to native customs soon 
<lb/>terminated fatally. </p>
<lb/><p><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he numbers of people we saw on the Lake 
<lb/>exceeded all I have observed elsewhere. Probably 
<lb/>the rains will draw off many to their agriculture. 
<lb/>In the South West we have the <term type="tribe">Maravi</term>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hen as we 
<lb/>go North we come among the <term type="tribe">Marimba</term> - then 
<lb/>the <term type="tribe">Matumboka</term> or <term type="tribe">Atimboka</term> - <term type="tribe">Makusa</term>
<lb/>and <term>Mañkambira</term> - they are essentially one 
<lb/>people - with one language, and much the same 
<lb/>appearance. All like the <term type="tribe">Manganja</term> are marked 
<lb/>with circatrices in straight lines which crossing 
<lb/>each other form lozenge <add place="above">or triangular</add> shaped devices - but 
<lb/>the <term type="tribe">Matumboka</term> raise the skin <add place="above">into</add> heart like lumps, 
<lb/>and file their teeth to points - there is a slight 
<lb/>difference in the dialects spoken, but all understand 

	<pb n="0008" facs="liv_002673_0008"/><!--pb/@n='4v'-->
<lb/>each other: and the <term type="tribe">Manganja</term> language serves every 
<lb/>where. The name <term type="tribe">Marimba</term> might be applied to them 
<lb/>all. We never heard the name <term type="tribe">Wanyassa</term> except among 
<lb/>Arabs. The prefix Wa belongs to the North - the <term type="tribe">Abisa</term>
<lb/>or <term type="tribe">Awisa</term> <add place="above">or <term type="tribe">Babisa</term></add> never call themselves <term type="tribe">Wabisa</term>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>here 
<lb/>are <term type="tribe">Marimba</term> on the East coat and <term type="tribe">Auguru</term>. 
<lb/>We heard <term type="tribe">Ajawa</term> firing cannon on that side 
<lb/>near the Southern end. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey are probably marauders 
<lb/>engaged in slave hunting. </p>
<lb/><p><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he people are all clothed with the inner 
<lb/>bark of a species of acacia, steeped, &amp; beaten till 
<lb/>it is soft. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he fair sex are to use the very mildest 
<lb/>term, really very plain. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he lips, large enough if let 
<lb/>alone are pierced and distended with quartz stones 
<lb/>till they are hideous - <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he men are better looking 
<lb/>than the women. We were quite as great curiosities 
<lb/>to them, as the hippopotamus was to the highly 
<lb/>civilized who live on the banks of the <placeName>Thames</placeName>. 
<lb/>They were upon the whole civil. At one village 
<lb/>only were they impudent, and they were a little 
<lb/>"elevated" by beer. Twice they went the length of 
<lb/>lifting up the edge of our sail which we used 
<lb/>as a tent as boys do the curtains of travelling 
<lb/>menageries at home. <choice><reg>B</reg><orig>b</orig></choice>ut they did not cross 
<lb/>the line I made on the sand when we were at 
<lb/>meals. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey spoke of us indeed as "<hi rend="underline">Chirombo</hi>" 
<lb/>- wild beasts, but they had no idea that they 
<lb/>were understood. <choice><reg>N</reg><orig>n</orig></choice>o fines were levied nor 
<lb/>dues demanded. </p>
<lb/><p>When about half way up the Lake an Arab dhow 
<lb/>lately built to carry slaves across fled from us to the 
<lb/>Eastern shore. In the sphere to which this vessel's 
<lb/>operations extended the people were worse - expert 
<lb/>thieves possibly from the East coast crept up to 
<lb/>our sleeping places about 4 oclock in the morning 
<lb/>and made off with what clothing they could lay 
<lb/>their hands on - no food was to be had except 
<lb/>what we could shoot. Fortunately elephants and 
<lb/>hippopotami were tame. At 11° 40′ we entered the borders 
<lb/>of a a tribe of <term type="tribe">Zulus</term> called <term type="tribe">Mazitu</term> or <term type="tribe">Mazite</term> who 
<lb/>came originally from 

	<pb n="0009" facs="liv_002673_0009"/><!--pb/@n='5r'-->
<lb/>the South opposite <placeName>Sofala</placeName> or <placeName>Inhambane</placeName>. 
<lb/>Here the shores of the Lake were strewed with skeletons 
<lb/>and putrid bodies of the slain. Our land party 
<lb/>dreaded meeting the inflictors of the terrible vengeance 
<lb/>of which the evidences everywhere met the eye, 
<lb/>without a European in their company. So 
<lb/>I left the boat, and a mistake separated us 
<lb/>from it three days - the country is mountainous 
<lb/>and the spurs of the mountains come sheer down 
<lb/>to the Lake. While toiling along up and down steep 
<lb/>ravines, our most strenuous efforts could 
<lb/>not make five miles a day <add place="above">in a straight line</add> - the boat had 
<lb/>gone on twenty miles and a storm prevented 
<lb/>its return. We met seven <term type="tribe">Mazite</term> who 
<lb/>seemed as much afraid of me as the men 
<lb/>were of them. I went to them unarmed - they 
<lb/>wished me to sit in the sun while they sat in 
<lb/>the shade, and rattled their shields, (a proceeding 
<lb/>that inspires terror among the natives) when 
<lb/>I refused, and came &amp; sat down beside them, 
<lb/>they refused to take me to the boat or to their chief - 
<lb/>thought that my note book was a pistol, and 
<lb/>on parting sped away up the hills like frightened 
<lb/>deer. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he country had been well peopled, 
<lb/>but new skeletons lay in every hut among 
<lb/>broken pots - and other utensils - no food could 
<lb/>be found and, but for four goats we had with 
<lb/>us, we should have starved. On the second 
<lb/>day the land party gave in, but taking two 
<lb/>of the best, I pushed on after the boat, and 
<lb/>on the morning of the fourth day met it 
<lb/>coming back. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he last Latitude taken was 
<lb/>Lat. 11° 44′ S. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he boat had gone about 24′ North 
<lb/>of that. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he Northing made on shore was less 
<lb/>than that, but from elevations of over a 
<lb/>thousand feet, and from the boat at least 
<lb/>20 miles more were seen. So we may venture 

	<pb n="0010" facs="liv_002673_0010"/><!--pb/@n='5v'-->
<lb/>to assert that the Lake extends into the southern 
<lb/>borders of the tenth degree of South Latitude - our 
<lb/>provisions were expended - the land desolate 
<lb/>except a few pirates on detached rocks off the 
<lb/>coast. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he people inhospitable - our land party 
<lb/>had turned, and without <del type="strikethrough">them</del> <add place="above">it</add> an accident to 
<lb/>the boat would have proved fatal to us all. 
<lb/>This was the first time I <add place="above">had</add> turned without 
<w>accom-<lb break="no"/>plishing</w> what I <add place="above">had</add> set out to do - but turn we 
<lb/>must though in sight of the large mountain 
<lb/>masses looming in the distance in which 
<lb/>the Lake probably ends. We pulled back in the 
<lb/>boat in one day what <add place="above">on land</add> with the most 
<w>heart-<lb break="no"/>breaking</w> toil, I had accomplished in three - 
<lb/>and a good fellow called <persName>Marango</persName> laded us 
<lb/>with all the different kinds of food he had, 
<lb/>and regretted that we could not spend a whole 
<lb/>day with him drinking beer.  </p>
<lb/><p>The information collected about the Rovuma 
<lb/>affords a good illustration of the instability of the 
<lb/>foundation on which <add place="above">much</add> speculative geography 
<lb/>stands - one intelligent native, with apparently no 
<lb/>motive for misleading us, asserted most positively 
<lb/>that our boat could sail out of the Lake into the 
<lb/>river. Another - that it must be carried a few 
<lb/>yards. While a third would maintain that the land carried 
<lb/>was at least fifty miles. It would at that season 
<lb/>of the year <add place="above">have</add> been foolhardiness to cross the Lake, 
<lb/><del type="strikethrough">and</del> to gain certainty for ourselves. In three out of 
<lb/>four storms our little boat could not have lived. 
<lb/>We met two Arabs who had come down from 
<lb/><placeName>Katanga</placeName> in the far interior to buy calico with 
<lb/>ivory at the Lake. One had lived in the interior 
<lb/>14 and the other 16 years. They drew <placeName>Nyassa</placeName> discharging 
<lb/>towards the South and <placeName>Tanganyika</placeName> towards 
<lb/>the North - which last we know from <persName>Major 

	<pb n="0011" facs="liv_002673_0011"/><!--pb/@n='6r'-->
<lb/>Burton</persName> to be nonsense. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey reported another Lake 
<lb/>called <placeName>Moelo</placeName>, and say that the <placeName>Loapola</placeName> <add place="above">or <placeName>Luapula</placeName></add> flows 
<lb/>into it. I wonder who will be set down as the 
<lb/>discoverer of that after the English have been there. </p>
<lb/><p><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he fish in the Lake are very abundant. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his 
<lb/>may be the reason why the alligators are so tame. 
<lb/>They are <add place="above">as already remarked</add> always most destructive to human life 
<lb/>when the <placeName>Zambesi</placeName> is discoloured, and they 
<lb/>cannot procure their usual diet of fish - 
<lb/>One fish shaped like trout ascends the rivers 
<lb/>to spawn. It is very good, having somewhat 
<lb/>the flavour of herring - clouds exactly like 
<lb/>columns of smoke floated over the Lake 
<lb/>and led us to conjecture that they arose 
<lb/>from the burning of grass on the opposite 
<lb/>shore - but passing through one of these 
<lb/>clouds we found that it consisted of insects 
<lb/>no larger than our smallest gnats - they 
<lb/>are called <hi rend="underline">Kungo</hi> and are collected and boiled 
<lb/>into cakes which reminded me by their flavour 
<lb/>of roasted locusts, but the taste is fishy. 
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his is probably the smallest winged insect 
<lb/>used as food by man. Locusts are here 
<lb/>unknown. </p>
<lb/><p><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he only trade there on the Lake is in slaves. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he 
<lb/>people do not attempt to kill elephants or 
<w>hippo-<lb break="no"/>potami</w> with their bows and arrows, and 
<lb/>both animals are remarkably tame - slaves 
<lb/>were often offered to us for sale. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he cotton 
<lb/>grown on the upper part of the Lake is of a 
<lb/>remarkably fine quality. We could only <del type="strikethrough">reply</del> <add place="above">state</add>
<lb/>that we should soon come in a larger vessel 
<lb/>and purchase their cotton. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>nd judging 
<lb/>from the quantity we have purchased 
<lb/>from a small portion of the <placeName>Shire</placeName> and that 

	<pb n="0012" facs="liv_002673_0012"/><!--pb/@n='6v'-->
<lb/>not in crop time the produce from <placeName>Nyassa</placeName>
<lb/>with its remarkably extended coast line will in 
<lb/>the course of a year or two be very considerable. 
<lb/>The actions however of the Portuguese slave 
<lb/>hunters on our footsteps have a more depressing 
<lb/>effect on our spirits than all the physical 
<lb/>obstacles we have to encounter or than the 
<lb/>Fever itself. </p>
<lb/><p rend="right"><persName>David Livingstone</persName></p>
<lb/><p> P.S. On returning to the <placeName>Upper Shire</placeName> we had 
<lb/>a good view of the country East of it and I 
<lb/>suspect that we have been misled as to the 
<lb/>length of the <placeName>Lake Shirwa</placeName> or <placeName>Tamanda</placeName> for 
<lb/>the country near the <placeName>Lake Nyassa</placeName> is all mountainous 
<lb/>a level patch however exists from about 14° 40′ 
<lb/>to 40° 50′ S. and it is probable that here the 
<w>hippo-<lb break="no"/>potami</w> cross from the river to the Lake - 
<lb/>the native information was correct enough 
<lb/>I believe only they looked on the <placeName>Upper Shire</placeName>
<lb/>as part of <placeName>Lake Nyinyesi</placeName> or <placeName>Nyassa</placeName>
<lb/>while we took the Lake proper as its real 
<lb/>beginning. We never have had time to 
<lb/>examine the <placeName>Lake Shirwa</placeName>, but think that 20 
<lb/>or 30 miles may have to be cut off its length 
<lb/>in the maps. </p>
<lb/><p>When we reached the upper most cataract 
<lb/>we slung our boat to a branch of a fine 
<lb/>shady tree about ten feet from the ground - 
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he elephants which abound there may disturb 
<lb/>it but nothing else will. We then walked past 
<lb/>the cataracts having completed our trip of 
<lb/>600 miles going &amp; coming in three months. 
<lb/>Our next work is carrying a steamer which 
<lb/>we expect in pieces by a road made by ourselves 
<lb/>past the cataracts. 
<lb/><persName>D.L.</persName></p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>