<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_001731">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Heinrich Barth</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Heinrich Barth, 18 February 1862</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2009-01-21</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_001731</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Royal Geographical Society (Great Britain); Barth Correspondence</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 1181</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Barth, Heinrich, 1821-1865</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1862-02-18">18 February 1862</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">HM Exploring Ship "Pioneer"</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2009-01-21</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Initial Transcription by Caroline Overy
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2009-01-31</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Christopher Lawrence</name>Proof by Chris Lawrence
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_001731_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1'--><!--
<p>D. Livingstone an <persName>H. Barth</persName></p>
<p rend="right">StA</p>
-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><term type="boat">H.M. Exploring Ship Pioneer</term></p>
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>R. Zambesi</placeName> 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feby 1862</p>
<lb/><p>My Dear <persName>Dr. Barth</persName></p>
<lb/><p>your very welcome letter of July 1861 reached me at the same 
<lb/>time that a steamer for <placeName>Lake Nyassa</placeName> did, and as we are carrying it 
<lb/>up towards its destination I snatch a few moments to acknowledge 
<lb/>your kind remembrance of a fellow explorer. We shall be engaged at 
<lb/>least twelve months in carrying the piece of the steamer past the 
<w>ca-<lb break="no"/>taracts</w> - they extend over 35 miles of latitude, and the descent of 
<lb/>the river in that space amounts to 1200 feet. But we must disembark 
<lb/>before we reach them and on land carriage will not be less than 70 
<lb/>or 80 miles - the <placeName>Shire</placeName> above the cataracts is all smooth and deep -. 
<lb/>We carried a boat up in August last and when we launched her above 
<lb/>the uppermost cataract were <choice><sic>virtuelly</sic><corr>virtually</corr></choice> upon the Lake for we sailed 
<lb/>easily into <placeName>Nyassa</placeName> on the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> september. It is a very deep Lake and 
<lb/>very surrounded on all sides by mountains &amp; highlands it is subject 
<lb/>to sudden and dangerous storms - our sounding line was only 35 
<lb/>fathoms on 210 feet. That seldom reached the bottom 2 miles from the 
<lb/>shore, and in the North we could feel no bottom with a fishing line 
<lb/>of 690 feet. We coasted along the western shore and found the length 
<lb/>to be over 200 miles long. It begins in Lat. 14° 25′ S. and <choice><sic>retends</sic><corr>extends</corr></choice> to 
<lb/>the southern borders of the tenth degree of south Lat. The shape is 
<lb/>somewhat like the boot shape of Italy but the toe <add place="above">from</add> which <placeName><choice><reg>S</reg><orig>s</orig></choice>hire</placeName> flows 
<lb/>turned the other way: The ankle is the narrowest part = 18 or 20 
<lb/>miles but in the North it is 50 or 60. We did not succeed in the 
<w>ob-<lb break="no"/>ject</w> we set out to accomplish namely, to ascertain about the river 
<lb/><placeName>Rovuma</placeName> - if it can be a pathway out. It was mortifying but we returned 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_001731_0002"/><!--pb/@n='2'-->
<lb/>about as wise as we went. One man would declare that we might sail 
<lb/>out of the Lake into the river another that we must carry the boat 
<lb/>a few yards - another, fifty miles or a month; and we dared not cross 
<lb/>over to ascertain for ourselves, for three <add place="above">out</add> of the four storms we 
<w>wit-<lb break="no"/>nessed</w> would have swamped our little boat. We might have gone round 
<lb/>the Northern end as the people told us that they did, but war had 
<w>de-<lb break="no"/>populated</w> the country North of Lat. 11° 40′ and no food could be 
<w>ob-<lb break="no"/>tained.</w> We were forced back by hunger, and slinging our boat to a 
<lb/>branch of a lofty and shady tree above the uppermost cataract reached 
<lb/>the ship after three months absence.</p>
<lb/><p>The Lake has several small round rocky islands in it. All are 
<lb/>destitute of inhabitants except one - It rises and falls with the 
<lb/>wet and dry seasons about 3 feet. The water is fresh &amp; cool - it 
<lb/>abounds in fish and a <del type="strikethrough">layer</del><add place="above">larger</add> population, than I have seen anywhere 
<lb/>else, lives on its shores. Slaving is the only trade known, and an 
<lb/>Arab dhow(?) has lately been built on its shores to carry slaves 
<lb/>across. It fled from us twice. About 19,000 slaves pass annually 
<lb/>through the custom house of <placeName>Zanzibar</placeName>, and the greater part of these 
<lb/>come from the <placeName>Nyassa</placeName> and the valley of the <placeName>Shire</placeName>. I earnestly hope 
<lb/>that I may live to do something to stop this gigantic evil. When on 
<lb/>the lake with our steamer "<term type="boat">Lady Nyassa</term>" or as i like to call her, 
<lb/>the "Lady of the Lake", we shall have easy access to over 300 miles 
<lb/>of cotton producing country. A minister of the Free church of 
<w>Scot-<lb break="no"/>land</w> is now with us with a view to obtaining information for the 
<lb/>establishment of a christian Mission on the lake or adjacent highlands<reg>.</reg>

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_001731_0003"/><!--pb/@n='3'-->
<lb/>I have recommended him to go up with us and see for himself. The <choice><sic>peo</sic><corr>notext</corr></choice>
<lb/>people seemed to us to be civil, no fines were levied nor dues 
<w>de-<lb break="no"/>manded</w> and I have no doubt but in the course of a number of years 
<lb/>patient and labourious missionaries will see fruits of their labours.</p>
<lb/><p>You will have heard that we have a church of England Mission on 
<lb/>the <placeName>Manganja highlands</placeName> East <placeName>Murchisons cataracts</placeName>. I went up with the 
<lb/>bishop to introduce him to the people and shew him a healthy locality<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>We found that the Portuguese had set up an extensive system of slave 
<lb/>hunting. The first party we met had (84) eightyfour women <reg>&amp;</reg> children 
<lb/>bound together. While making enquiries among these poor people the 
<lb/>adventurers fled into the forest, and left the whole on my hands - so 
<lb/>I thought the best thing I could do with them was to hand over that 
<lb/>party and some others to the bishop to begin school with. The slave 
<lb/>hunters had employed another tribe called <term type="tribe"><choice><sic>Ajwa</sic><corr>Ajawa</corr></choice></term> to attack the <placeName><w>Man-<lb break="no"/>ganja</w> villages</placeName>, kill the men <reg>&amp;</reg> sell the women and children to them. 
<lb/>After seeing the spot selected for the mission we went to try to 
<w>in-<lb break="no"/>duce</w> the <term type="tribe">Ajawa</term> to cease the shedding of blood - came to them when 
<lb/>in the act of burning three villages and were attacked with muskets &amp; 
<lb/><choice><sic>poisened</sic><corr>poisoned </corr></choice> arrows. This was my first hostile encounter in Africa. 
<lb/>Though often on the point of it - I am sorry that it took place - 
<lb/>we drove them off but had I in the least anticipated aught of the 
<lb/>sort I would have made <add place="above">use of</add> presents and fair words before going near 
<lb/>them. We acted in self-<del type="overwritten">defensive</del><add place="over-text">defence</add> alone but while we were in <placeName>Nyassa</placeName>
<lb/>the bishop and missionaries took the offensive and drove away a tribe 
<lb/>of <add place="above">these</add><term type="tribe">Ajawa</term>. I am extremely sorry that they did this for though defen-
               

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_001731_0004"/><!--pb/@n='4'-->
<lb break="no"/>sive war may be lawful, offensive war cannot be right on the party 
<lb/>of a bishop. It is the first time that this party has engaged in 
<lb/>mission work. You may know that they are called "High Church" I 
<lb/>approved heartily of their coming out here and still I think that 
<lb/>that they will be useful <choice><sic>and still I think they will be useful</sic><corr>notext</corr></choice>, for 
<lb/>High Churchism can only flourish in seclusion, and when good people 
<lb/>engage in active benevolence 
<lb/>the bigotry of the closet and cloister 
<lb/>must <choice><sic>vanih</sic><corr>vanish</corr></choice>. The bishop is a very good man and so are most of his 
<lb/>associators. We may therefore hope that despite this false step 
<lb/>success may attend their efforts.</p>
<lb/><p>What a hard hearted man you are - I publish another book - No, No 
<lb/>- one book in a man's life is quite enough. How you got through 
<lb/>five volumes is more than I can tell. <persName>Sir Roderick Murchison</persName> set me 
<lb/>to write once, and I did not like to be beaten, but he may as well 
<lb/>tell me to stand on my head as write another. You will excuse the 
<lb/>foregoing few notes as all I can give at present. My wife is here so 
<lb/>not a word to any one till the steamer is on the Lake.</p>
<lb/><p rend="center">Yours most truly</p>
<lb/><p rend="center"> David Livingstone</p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>