<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P5 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000549">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to [Elizabeth?] Pyne</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to [Elizabeth?] Pyne, 5 October 1843</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London, UK</pubPlace>
				<publisher>University College London</publisher>
				<date>2012</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000549</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Bodleian Library. Weston Library; MSS. Afr. s. 141, ff. 11-12</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0091</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Pyne, Elizabeth, 1799/1800-1853</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1843-10-05">5 October 1843</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kuruman</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2011-11-19</date>
				<name xml:id="AJS">A.J. Schmitz</name> initial transcription and XML encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-10-04</date>
				<name xml:id="HFB">Heather F. Ball</name> proofreading and XML editing.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-10-30</date>
				<name xml:id="AW">Adrian S. Wisnicki</name> proofreading and XML editing.
            
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000549_0001"><!--pb/@n='11r'--></pb>
	<ab><!-- This <ab> has no clear relation to the other <abs> in this letter. AW -->
<lb/>I wrote <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi><choice><abbr>P.</abbr><expan>Pyne</expan></choice></persName> some time ago and 
<lb/>will send him no more than kind regards until see his
<lb rend="center"/>own handwriting. My love to his children
</ab>
	<ab><!-- This <ab> continues from the bottom of page 12v and then onto the <abs> on, successively, 11v, 12r, 12v. So I have numbered the lines in these <ab>s continuously. AW -->
<lb/>about these great ones for it was quite a treat to meet them in this
<lb/>wilderness b<gap agent="blotting" extent="2" unit="chars"/><unclear cert="high">ut</unclear> they felt it to be the same. For they sitting with us on stones 
<lb/>and handing round the sugarless coffee threw off all reserve. They had their
</ab>
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> <date when="1843-10-05">5 <choice><abbr>Oct<hi rend="sup">r</hi></abbr><expan>October</expan></choice> 1843</date></p>
<lb/><p>My Dear friend</p>
<lb/><p>On returning about three days from the 
<lb/><placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName> I saw with joy your welcome handwriting But O
<lb/>what heavy tidings it brought. Three of my friends gone
<lb/>and all of them much younger than I. How solemnly 
<lb/>this voice speaks O that my heart were not so <w>familiar<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>ized</w> with death. As it is however I feel these events 
<lb/>in providence more than I have done others for a long 
<lb/>time past. May I have grace to improve by them. Teach me 
<lb/>to remember my own days. That I may apply my heart unto 
<lb/>wisdom. <persName>Miss Marshall</persName> is gone before and we are 
<lb/><choice><sic>we</sic><corr/></choice> really following in the path which leads to the <unclear cert="medium">mansion</unclear>
<lb/>she <del type="cancelled">has</del> has found prepared her with regions of the 
<lb/>blessed. She is arrived at home. How she wonders she 
<lb/>ever looked at this earth as her home. May we die the 
<lb/>death of the righteous and may our last end be like hers. It 
<lb/>seems as if the portion of our existence is the 
<lb/>most important we shall ever spend. On it hangs an 
<lb/>eternity.  It is then of more importance how we live and 
<lb/>act here than it can be at any future period of our being 
<lb/>I wish this truth for truth it seems to me were ever 
<lb/>before my eyes. You must have felt a strange want 
<lb/>in your house after she left you, a gap which will 
<lb/>never be filled up till you are all transplanted into the 
<lb/>celestial paradise. Think of the dear children, will they 
<lb/>all be taken up there? O with what earnestness should 
<lb/>we not pray for their conversion for they possessing 
<lb/>the same natures as others need to be converted and if 
<lb/>not must -- but I <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice> endure the idea I was about 
<lb/>to express.  How does <persName>Mary</persName> feel now? And but I forget 
<lb/>his name is it <persName>Moreland</persName> and - My head is filled with 
<lb/>names of <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term> I am sorry I have forgot <choice><sic>their</sic><corr>them</corr></choice>

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000549_0002"><!--pb/@n='11v'--></pb>
<lb/>their images are however still on my heart. May
<lb/>the Lord lift up on them the light of his countenance
<lb/>and bless them &amp; turn them to himself. Poor <persName>Radford</persName>
<lb/>my brother and <persName>Salome</persName> whose turn will it be next? 
<lb/>He sends I now learn a box of medicines to me and ere 
<lb/>They arrive the hands that prepared them and the heart 
<lb/>that beat warmly in sealing up that box lie cold 
<lb/>in the Tomb But he is where sorrow is forever 
<lb/>ceased What can be compared to obtaining an inheritance 
<lb/>there. The way is open blessed be God. Let us strive 
<lb/>to enter in. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi><choice><abbr>Tho<hi rend="sup">s</hi></abbr><expan>Thomas</expan></choice> Cecil</persName> must under the <w>circumst-
<lb break="no"/>ances</w> in which it <choice><sic>occured</sic><corr>occurred</corr></choice> felt the loss of their <persName>Salome</persName>
<lb/>severely. Young &amp; full of life But it is in vain to write 
<lb/>You can understand it all. How comforting she is 
<lb/>enjoying happiness greater than she ever felt 
<lb/>here. Poor little <persName>Emily</persName> I shall never forget her 
<lb/>though I had forgot her name until your letters 
<lb/>reminded me of what I <choice><sic>herd</sic><corr>heard</corr></choice> often in vain tried 
<lb/>to recall. The Lord bless you all. I hope your little boy 
<lb/>is better. You mentioned <persName>Miss <choice><abbr>M.</abbr><expan>Marshall</expan></choice></persName>'s illness indeed but 
<lb/>this time had elapsed ere I <choice><sic>recieved</sic><expan>received</expan></choice> your former 
<lb/>letter induced me to believe she must have long 
<lb/>before its arrival quite recovered.  It is the Lord<supplied>'</supplied>s 
<lb/>doing and he does all things well.</p>
<lb/><p>I have just returned from the country of the 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term> after haveing in conjunction with <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi><w>Ed<supplied>-</supplied><lb break="no"/>wards</w></persName> of this station erected a hut for shelter 
<lb/>during the warm season now just setting in</p>
	<ab>
<lb/>Indian servants with them but we being better acquainted with the country 
<lb/>got on better than they. I am not yet quite sure whether <persName><unclear cert="high">Mahotsa</unclear></persName>
<lb/>will be my station.  I like <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Edwards</persName> very much <!-- I cannot make out word AJS 11/20 --></ab>


	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000549_0003"><!--pb/@n='12r'--></pb>
	<ab>
<lb/>we are to be formed into a committee and that committee is to decide where 
<lb/>each is to be situated some other may go there and should that be the case 
<lb/>one of the younger missionaries, perhaps <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Nighs</persName> will be my companion 
</ab>
<lb/><p>We may be said fairly to have commenced missionary 
<lb/>operations in the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName>. The <term type="tribe">Bakhatta</term> professed to be 
<lb/>very glad at our arrival to live amongst them. We 
<lb/>bought a piece of ground perhaps as large as <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi><choice><abbr>T</abbr><expan>Thomas</expan></choice></persName><choice><sic>s</sic><corr>'s</corr></choice>
<lb/>for a gun beads and some ammunition. You 
<lb/>may think this cheap but it is far beyond to value 
<lb/>they attach to it. Indeed land may be said in this 
<lb/>country to be of no value. Every one sows as he 
<lb/>likes and no one asks another as to where he can 
<lb/>fix his garden. Had we given nothing &amp; begun to 
<lb/>plant in the best portion fo the country we should 
<lb/>not <add place="below">^</add><add place="above">have</add>been esteemed intruders. This is the land of liberty 
<lb/>in another sense than the Yankees apply the words 
<lb/>to their country. We however thought it best 
<lb/>to make a regular bargain stipulating that 
<lb/>no one <add place="below">^</add><add place="above">should</add> have authority over us or the land 
<lb/>specified. I wrote an agreement before them 
<lb/>read it in Si<del type="strikethrough">c</del><add place="below">^</add><add place="above">tch</add>uana and then had the chief &amp; his 
<lb/>principal men to sign it by affixing their 
<lb/>marks. I believe it is the first thing of the sort 
<lb/>that has been done in the <term type="tribe">Bechuana</term> country
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName> bought <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> for beads but I 
<lb/>dont know he had any deed. I take a copy 
<lb/>of this and <add place="below">^</add><add place="above">will</add> send you <add place="above">in the box</add> the original that you may 
<lb/>see I am no lawyer when sitting under a tree 
<lb/>surrounded by a crowd of chattering <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>
<lb/>I remember <persName>Mary</persName> was drawing the last time I was 
<lb/>in your house. If she could see our fine valley 
<lb/>it would inspire her so. She would instantly take 
<lb/>a drawing of it &amp; perhaps myself <unclear cert="medium">aping</unclear> the lawyer in the 

    

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000549_0004"><!--pb/@n='12v'--></pb>
<lb/>midst of it. We are surrounded with mountains - 
<lb/>woods to the summits.  Many ever greens &amp; others gr<gap agent="illegible" extent="4" unit="chars"/>
<lb/>all trees.  There is a stream on each side of the spot 
<lb/>with many little waterfalls in the course of one of them 
<lb/>At one part of the valley the trees are exactly as in 
<lb/>gentleman's park at home. Some of them are 
<lb/>four feet in diameter. A party of Indian gentlemen 
<lb/>who had come for the purpose of hunting &amp; 
<lb/>getting health restored made this same remark 
<lb/>on beholding it. One would have taken a drawing 
<lb/>of it for us had time permitted. They were very 
<lb/>agreeable and kindly supplied us with meat during 
<lb/>the time we were hunting. One is a Scotchman 
<lb/>and though not in a lucrative <del type="cancelled">pas</del> situation compared 
<lb/>to others in <placeName><country>India</country></placeName> has £800 per annum. He is 
<lb/>first cousin to <persName>Lord Breadalbane</persName>. Another is 
<lb/><persName>Captain Steele</persName> of the Cold Stream Guards A. D. to the Guns 
<lb/>of Madras. He and I became so friendly he promises 
<lb/>to do many things for me but I fear he will 
<lb/>forget. He has often hunted at <placeName><settlement type="village">Dugar</settlement></placeName> &amp; will return 
<lb/>to <placeName><country>England</country></placeName> after he has served 4 years longer in 
<lb/><placeName><country>India</country></placeName>. He obliged me much in several respects 
<lb/>particularly in taking a little money to <placeName><settlement type="town">Cape Town</settlement></placeName>
<lb/>where he says being well acquainted with the 
<lb/>Governor he will open a channel whereby 
<lb/>I shall be able to transit a little occasionally 
<lb/>to my brother in <placeName><settlement type="town">Oberlin</settlement></placeName>. He promises to write 
<lb/>me soon and gives me his address. But alas 
<lb/>he is not pious. I could tell you much more</p>
	<ab>
<lb/>I have however been permitted <add place="above">to</add> be instrumental in commencing the first 
<lb/>station in the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName> and though I love it much I must hold myself in readiness 
<lb/>to do what is best for the cause  May the Lord direct us    
<lb/>Ever Affectionately Yours
<lb/><persName><abbr>D.L.</abbr><expan>David Livingstone</expan></persName></ab>

			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>