<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000527">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to James Maclehose</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to James Maclehose, 20 June 1843</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2008</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000527</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">National Library of Scotland; MS. 656, ff. 85-90</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0072</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Maclehose, James, 1811-1885</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1843-06-20">20 June 1843</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kuruman</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2007-11-15</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>Intial Transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2008-02-29</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>Proofed by Chris
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000527_0001"/><!--pb/@n='85r'-->
<lb/><p><placeName>Kuruman</placeName> 20<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">th</hi></hi> June 1843 </p>
<lb/><p>My very Dear Friend </p>
<lb/><p>I am sorry I cannot begin by thanking you 
<lb/>for your last. Your first I have not yet <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice>, But I have 
<lb/>&amp; abundant cause for thankfulness, and I would now 
<lb/>proceed to express it were I not conscious words are inadequate 
<lb/>for the purpose. You have got me a good friend in <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> M<hi rend="sup">c</hi> Robert</persName>. I pray the Great Head of the church may through 
<lb/>grace bestow on you the <choice><sic>recompence</sic><corr>recompense</corr></choice> I wish you in the 
<lb/>resurrection of the just. But I am in distress respecting 
<lb/>her you must if you please help me out of it. She kindly 
<lb/>spoke of sending some things to the <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>, I thought 
<lb/>it might be dresses she meant &amp; I could not help telling her 
<lb/>I had an aversion to such things. You know how 
<lb/>difficult it is to say anything calculated to pain a lady. I 
<lb/>felt it sorely. But a conviction that the tendency of these 
<lb/>presents of clothes is to hinder the cause compelled me to speak 
<lb/>out. You must if you please be so kind as apologise 
<lb/>for my rudeness. </p>
<lb/><p>Some of the presents consist of good strong apparel &amp; 
<lb/>although the distribution of them induces endless heartburnings 
<lb/>I should not object to them because they are very useful 
<lb/>to the poor of the flock<reg>.</reg> But the freight &amp; land carriage cost 
<lb/>as much to the Directors as would suffice to purchase the 
<lb/>same in the colony. I remember <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Arundel</persName> once said 
<lb/>to me with a sigh, "I don<reg>'</reg>t know what people put into these 
<lb/>boxes but if they gave us the money they think them worth 
<lb/>that with the saving of expense would soon make up 
<lb/>the hundred thousand." I could tell him now and only think 
<lb/>how he would stare when I assured him there are in some 
<lb/>old dirty ball dresses, old socks dirty as when thrown aside 
<lb/>by the wearer. Old dirty shirt collars for people who have 
<lb/>no shirts. Old coverings of parasols &amp; silk buttons I remember 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000527_0002"/><!--pb/@n='85v'-->
<lb/>to have seen on old maid's dresses when a little boy. What on 
<lb/>earth makes people send such trash, would they themselves like 
<lb/>to go with thin ball dresses if they had nothing under &amp; their skins 
<lb/>black? You see acknowledgements from the directors to a 
<lb/>whole string of people sometimes, I fancy if the Directors knew all 
<lb/>they would return much more grateful acknowledgements 
<lb/>if the donors would come, pay the expenses &amp; take them away. 
<lb/>But they are in a dilmemma &amp; like ourselves don<reg>'</reg>t like to speak 
<lb/>out when harm may be done by it. No one would like 
<lb/>to refuse a present from a poor old disciple who longing 
<lb/>for the advancement of the redeemer's kingdom, should 
<lb/>bring a thing of no value, grateful he or she had been permitted 
<lb/>to give to that dearest of causes. Who could refuse the old 
<lb/>disciple the delight he or she must feel in contributing. Other 
<lb/>considerations besides this would prevent us making a public 
<lb/>exposure of the abuses which <del type="strikethrough">have</del> are connected with these 
<lb/>presents<reg>.</reg> But could we separate the ball dress contribution 
<lb/>from the rest for them I should have no bowels of 
<w>comp-<lb break="no"/>assion,</w> married they are not, old maids they I think they must 
<lb/>be who sent these accompaniments of nonsense, <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
<lb/>Moffat</persName> used to say "any thing will be useful to us"<reg>.</reg> But 
<lb/>he had no idea people would have such India rubber consciences<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>I don<reg>'</reg>t suppose <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M<hi rend="sup">c</hi> R</persName> would have sent any useless 
<lb/>articles But I have such a dislike to those which have come 
<lb/>I felt constrained to decline <choice><sic>recieving</sic><corr>receiving</corr></choice> any more. I think from 
<lb/>the way she writes she has good sense enough not to be offended 
<lb/>with me for it. Almost anything would be of <add place="above">more</add> value to 
<lb/>the cause than the things some send.</p>
<lb/><p>I shall now give you some account of the state of 
<lb/>the country &amp; the manner in which I have been employed 
<lb/>since I last wrote you. I told you of <persName>Sebeque</persName> and 
<lb/>his <unclear cert="low">overseers</unclear> who were sent to me last year with the 
<lb/>present of an ox. On that occasion I advised him 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000527_0003"/><!--pb/@n='86r'-->
<lb/>not to to have the country of the <term type="tribe">Bakalihari</term> to which he had 
<lb/>been driven by <persName>Mosilikatze</persName> as there was a probability if he 
<lb/>did so <persName>Mahura</persName><del type="strikethrough">the</del> chief of the <term type="tribe">Batlapi</term> would attack him<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>He acted contrary to my advice &amp; having no guns many of 
<lb/>his people were massacred by <persName>Mahura</persName> - a party of the 
<lb/>believers of <placeName>Kuruman</placeName> were with him at the very time of 
<lb/>attack &amp; as M. is their chief both <persName>Sebeque</persName> &amp; all the heathen 
<lb/>in the interior believed they had acted the part of accomplices 
<lb/>to <persName>Mahura</persName><reg>.</reg> Some incidents which occured during the period of 
<lb/>their visit served very much to deepen the unfavourable 
<lb/>impression. The accidental firing of a musket on the 
<lb/>evening preceding the attack by one of the visiting party 
<lb/>was afterwards interpreted as having been the signal by which 
<lb/><persName>Mahura</persName> was apprised of the situation of <persName>Sebeque</persName>. - The 
<lb/>singing at family worship was construed as the incantations 
<lb/>for success - and the collecting of <persName>Sebeque's</persName> people in the 
<lb/>morning of attack (it being Sabbath) for public worship as 
<lb/>only a pretext by which <del type="strikethrough">they</del> to aid the work of slaughter<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he reception of these news made me most anxious 
<lb/>again to visit the interior, that by my presence &amp; explanation 
<lb/>I might endeavour to disabuse their heathen minds of the 
<lb/>prejudices they had inbibed. I felt if no effort were 
<lb/>made for that purpose, the prejudices against our 
<lb/>people might be transferred to our gospel &amp; thus much 
<lb/>harm be done to the cause<reg>.</reg> But the natives here were 
<lb/>so certain that <persName>Sebeque</persName> would revenge himself on the 
<lb/>first party from <placeName>Kuruman</placeName> that fell into his hands 
<lb/>they thought it madness to think of going<reg>.</reg> I was therefore 
<lb/>obliged to wait some months <choice><sic>untill</sic><corr>until</corr></choice> their fears subsided 
<lb/>before I could get a few to drive my waggon<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>On the 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Feb last I left this &amp; shaped my course 
<lb/>for <persName>Sebeque's</persName> village &amp; after about 10 days travelling 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000527_0004"/><!--pb/@n='86v'-->
<lb/>reached in safety (Poor Bint lost his wife by the overturning of 
<lb/>his waggon in <placeName>Caffreland</placeName>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hat accident I met twice and yet 
<lb/>not a hair of my head harmed. How thankful I ought to be 
<lb/>for <del type="strikethrough">my</del><add place="above">the</add> merciful preservation. Once I was reading, my legs 
<lb/><choice><sic>accross</sic><corr>across</corr></choice> the waggon &amp; I did not know of my danger <choice><sic>untill</sic><corr>until</corr></choice> I 
<lb/>was suddenly <del type="strikethrough">returned</del><add place="above">transferred</add> from the sitting to the standing posture 
<lb/>my boxes<reg>,</reg> books <reg>,</reg> bed <reg>,</reg> meal bags &amp; watercask simultaneously <unclear cert="low">crashing</unclear>
<lb/>their level behind me - ) My driver had been one of the party 
<lb/>which visited <persName>Sebeque</persName> at the time of attack and a most 
<lb/>precarious recognition of him followed when we arrived at 
<lb/>the place where he &amp; the remainder of his warriors were 
<lb/>seated. I squatted down beside him &amp; observed my poor servant was looking "unutterable things" <persName>Sebeque</persName> then 
<lb/>demanded of me why I had attacked and destroyed his 
<lb/>people &amp; stolen all his cattle. I replied by demanding why 
<lb/>he had neglected to follow my advice &amp; thus destroy himself &amp;c. 
<lb/>Some of the messengers I had seen last year being still alive 
<lb/>then recognised me and we soon became very good 
<lb/>friends. He told me the reasons he left the country of the 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bakalihari</term> were his people were yearly diminished by 
<lb/>a fever which prevails there<reg>.</reg> His heart longed again 
<lb/>to eat corn and being ignorant of the power of guns 
<lb/>he had dispised the powers of the <term type="tribe">Batlapi</term>. I partook 
<lb/>of his hospitaility for several days &amp; was pleased with 
<lb/>all I saw of him. He is the bravest of the all the <term type="tribe">Bechuana</term><reg>.</reg> This after he had cut off detachment after detachment of 
<lb/>the people of <persName>Mosilikatze</persName> the tyrant was obliged to 
<lb/><unclear cert="low">Amen</unclear>. "There is only one man in this country said  M. 
<lb/>&amp; that is <persName>Sebeque</persName>" - it being Saturday when I arrived 
<lb/>I explained to him how we spend the day following. Next 
<lb/>morning before daybreak I was pleased to hear his herald 

	<pb n="0005" facs="liv_000527_0005"/><!--pb/@n='87r'-->
<lb/>the kings orders that "nothing was to be done on that day but 
<lb/>praying to God hearing the words of the foreigner"<reg>.</reg> During the 
<lb/>different services he was a most attentive listener and he 
<lb/>put many sensible questions concerning the strange things I had 
<lb/>brought to his ears. He mentioned that he had seen <persName>Mr 
<lb/>Moffat</persName> once but as <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.</persName> was then young &amp; did not 
<lb/>understand the language it is not remarkable <persName>Sebeque</persName> remembered 
<lb/>nothing of what had been said. May the Lord enlighten his 
<lb/>dark <unclear cert="low">mind</unclear> &amp; lead him to the Lamb of God which taketh away 
<lb/>the sins of the world.</p>
<lb/><p>Leaving <persName>Sebeque</persName> I proceeded to the <term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term> a people 
<lb/>with whom the Directors have approved of our proposal 
<lb/>to form a new mission. I told you something of them 
<lb/>before but as I hope to be building a house there long 
<lb/>before you <choice><sic>recieve</sic><corr>receive</corr></choice> this I shall give you a little more 
<lb/>information concerning our intended station<reg>.</reg><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey are 
<lb/>very near to the spot where <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Campbell</persName> in his progress of 
<lb/>discovery northwards thought proper to turn about &amp; 
<lb/>go home. The iron foundaries he heard of but was 
<lb/>not permitted to see, belong to them. Very likely he thought 
<lb/>the same reasons were in operation there as are in 
<lb/>our chemical works at home, nothing of the sort 
<lb/>however enters into their heads, they are only afraid 
<lb/>lest their iron should be bewitched by the presence of 
<lb/>strangers. Iron bewitched is when it is burned to a 
<lb/>cinder by the <del type="strikethrough">the</del> brisk application of their bellows - 
<lb/>and lest this disaster should happen they actually put 
<lb/>in medicines with the ore &amp; sleep at a distance from 
<lb/>their own houses during the whole season of smelting<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>The connection between the bellows &amp; burnt iron they 
<lb/>never dream of. It is all the effect of witchcraft 

	<pb n="0006" facs="liv_000527_0006"/><!--pb/@n='87v'-->
<lb/>the ore is found in abundance at the junction of the igneous 
<lb/>&amp; aqueous formations &amp; nowhere is covered by any 
<lb/>depth of soil, <choice><reg>o</reg><orig>O</orig></choice>ne side of the valley being the line of 
<lb/>demarcation between the trappean &amp; sandstone rocks 
<lb/>the latter stretching northwards gives a different 
<lb/>kind of pasturage. These peculiarities will <del type="strikethrough">give</del>
<lb/>be of advantage to our station, the iron works will 
<lb/>present a temporal consideration and attach the people to 
<lb/>the spot <choice><sic>untill</sic><corr>until</corr></choice> by the grace of God we have imparted a sense 
<lb/>of its spiritual advantages. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he different vegetation 
<lb/>which exists will probably be favourable for the cattle 
<lb/>of the natives. The want of which advantage has always 
<lb/>been a great drawback to the prosperity of <placeName>Kuruman</placeName><reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>This town is also near to what was formerly the site 
<lb/>of that of <persName>Mosilikatze</persName>. I walked over it and the place 
<lb/>where he suffered his last defeat by a handful of 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Boers</term> &amp; a very few human bones were the only vestige 
<lb/>I could discover of all that belonged to him. He 
<lb/>is now living more than 350 miles north East of his 
<lb/>former location &amp; still carries on his old practices<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>When I was at the <term type="tribe">Bakwain</term> villages I saw several 
<lb/>women who had <del type="strikethrough">escaped</del> been taken captive by his 
<lb/>people last year &amp; escaped again from their tyranny 
<lb/>their tale of sorrow had no effect on their callous 
<lb/>fellow countrymen but it had a powerful effect 
<lb/>on the people of my waggon. A step nearer to 
<lb/><persName>Mosilikatze</persName> they would not go, entreaty <unclear cert="low">while</unclear> &amp; 
<lb/>threatening were all in vain, the fellows turned 
<lb/>their noses in the sand as if the Arabian Simoom 

	<pb n="0007" facs="liv_000527_0007"/><!--pb/@n='88r'-->
<lb/>had been passing, &amp; their very hearts seemed like to die with 
<lb/>them<reg>.</reg> I was thus brought to the necessity of either 
<lb/>relinquishing my design of going still farther north, or 
<lb/>quitting the waggon &amp; proceed on a pack ox, I chose 
<lb/>the latter &amp; leaving the waggon in charge of my own people 
<lb/>with three wild <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> of <placeName>Bubi</placeName> proceeded on my 
<lb/>journey. This mode of travelling has some inconveniences 
<lb/>but to me it was by far the pleasantest part of my 
<lb/>tour. I visited no fewer than four villages of the 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bakalihari</term> where on account of the sand of the 
<lb/>desert a waggon could not have come, they are 
<lb/>a poor degraded people, the slaves of the other tribes 
<lb/>of <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>. They live far from water and 
<lb/>every thing we consider essential to comfort<reg>.</reg> But 
<lb/>though in one sense destitute in another they are kindly 
<lb/>supplied by a bountiful providence. They have 
<lb/>shewn me more than 40 different kinds of roots 
<lb/>&amp; about 30 different fruits the desert spontaneously 
<lb/>yields them<reg>.</reg> Some of these it is true are absolutely 
<lb/>indigestible &amp; others produce <add place="above">such</add> dreadful pains in the 
<lb/>inner men of those who are unaccustomed to 
<lb/>them I have been obliged to have recourse to an 
<lb/>emetic. Yet there are others by no means unsavoury 
<lb/>esculents. I suppose custom makes them all 
<lb/>savoury to them. Locusts &amp; wild honey were as 
<lb/>good as any thing I got. You remember this 
<lb/>was the food of the Baptist. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he locusts are 
<lb/>better than the shrimps our good friend <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs </hi> Sewell</persName>
<lb/>used to munch. Only they have just too much 

	<pb n="0008" facs="liv_000527_0008"/><!--pb/@n='88v'-->
<lb/>of a grassy taste, some swarms would <unclear cert="low">were not</unclear> make 
<lb/>one believe in eating them that he had become a twin 
<lb/>brother of old <unclear cert="low">Nebuchadnezzar</unclear>. I may mention that the 
<lb/><choice><sic>the</sic><corr>no text</corr></choice> one ingredient of the Baptist food is dreadfully 
<w>const-<lb break="no"/>ipating</w> &amp; the other just the opposite. And had he lived 
<lb/>in the desert of the <term type="tribe">Bakalihari</term> he would have had no 
<lb/>difficulty in finding a constant supply of both<reg>.</reg> Of the 
<lb/>one I saw no fewer than 19 swarms in one year 
<lb/>&amp; yet no particular damage was done to the 
<lb/>crops of the natives, &amp; had I followed all the calls 
<lb/>of the honey birds which invited me to hives I 
<lb/>should never have been without a sufficiency 
<lb/>of the other - The <term type="tribe">Bakalihari</term> were very kind to me<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>But during most of that part of the journey I &amp; my 
<lb/>three companions were dependent on my gun. Sometimes 
<lb/>we had a pleasure you never knew, "We rejoiced <add place="above">as</add> in the 
<lb/>day of slaughter"<reg>.</reg> At other times we had to feast on 
<lb/>what we saw in our dreams only. The pleasure 
<lb/>I enjoyed in sitting <add place="above">with the natives of the desert</add> round the fire in the evenings &amp; when 
<lb/>listening to their wild tales introducing the story of the 
<lb/>Great Salvation was greater than I ever before felt 
<lb/>in this work. Occasionally our conversation on 
<lb/>subjects connected with Eternity were prolonged till 
<lb/>past midnight. I thus became better acquainted 
<lb/>with their modes of thinking than I could otherwise 
<lb/>have done<reg>.</reg> May the Lord generously own my 
<lb/>poor endeavours to make known his name to 
<lb/>these poor wanderers in the wilderness. </p>

	<pb n="0009" facs="liv_000527_0009"/><!--pb/@n='89r'-->
<lb/><p>You may have heard that the <term type="tribe">Bechuana</term> have no idea of a 
<lb/>future state. I know this was the opinion of most missionaries 
<lb/><choice><sic>untill</sic><corr>until</corr></choice> lately. But we have discovered a parallel a form in 
<lb/>which all their traditions are embodied and this shews clearly 
<lb/>they have always had the idea of future existence. The knowledge 
<lb/>of this parallel is universal, even among the poor <term type="tribe">Bakalihari</term> it served as an excellent introduction to a conversation<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Perhaps you may like to hear it. It is as follows. The 
<lb/>cameleon walks very slowly. The black lizard very quickly 
<lb/>God sent the former with a message to men, saying, Go tell 
<lb/>mankind that when they die they do not entirely perish 
<lb/>their shade flys upward, they will again return, the 
<lb/>lizard was sent afterwards with a message from the Devil 
<lb/>(Barino or evil spirits) &amp; being swift of foot outran the 
<lb/>cameleon &amp; came first to men. His message was 
<lb/>When you die you die like the game, there is an end of 
<lb/>you. You will never return. A messenger is coming 
<lb/>after me to say when men die they will again return<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Don<reg>'</reg>t believe him he tells lies only. </p>
<lb/><p>I had experienced some merciful preservations during 
<lb/>my late tour. Seeing an animal on a tree one day I drew 
<lb/>near for the purpose of securing it for our pot. But 
<lb/>when within a few feet of some brushwood near the 
<lb/><unclear cert="low">base</unclear> of the tree, a tiger lurking there seized the little dog 
<lb/>which preceded me &amp; shook him as if it had been a mouse 
<lb/>in his jaws. He at the same time growled horribly, which 
<lb/>made me think it was a lion. I retreated a few steps in 
<lb/>order to to take aim for flying is of no use in the case 
<lb/>of a lion. He then came out from his covert &amp; I got 
<lb/>a good view of him. But as he did not seem to 
<lb/>wish an encounter I was quite willing to be of the 
<lb/>same mind &amp; allowed him to move off into the forest<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Had I been first instead of the dog, it is probable I should 

	<pb n="0010" facs="liv_000527_0010"/><!--pb/@n='89v'-->
<lb/>have been seized instead of him. Thanks to the Lord for 
<lb/>his care over me. </p>
<lb/><p>You remember the lofty black volcanic rocks of the <placeName>Bakaa</placeName><reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Well I was nearly starved there, a native who went with 
<lb/>me last year was affected with fever while there. After 
<lb/>our departure a report was spread that he had been poisoned<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>The <term type="tribe">Bakaa</term> were determined to give no cause for such an 
<lb/>imputation in future &amp; gave neither poisoned nor wholesome 
<lb/>food, except a few watermelons &amp; sweet reed for three 
<lb/>mortal days. But I had reason to be thankful for the low 
<lb/>diet they put me on, for when descending on the morning 
<lb/>of the second day from their airy abodes to our sleeping place 
<lb/>below, I unfortunately broke one of my finger bones<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>The testatment in my hand served as a point of resistance 
<lb/>between which &amp; the sharp angle of rock my finger was 
<lb/>crushed, a piece of their sweet reed served as a splint 
<lb/>&amp; the low diet saved me from an attack of irritative 
<lb/>fever. The chief &amp; people were quite amicably disposed 
<lb/>towards me<reg>.</reg> But my patience could hold out no longer 
<lb/>than the morning of the third day. When they saw us 
<lb/>preparing to depart the chief &amp; all his wives came down 
<lb/>&amp; entreated us not to depart. They did not wish to give 
<lb/>food lest people should say they had posioned us, they 
<lb/>did not like us to go away without eating anything lest 
<lb/>people should say they were niggardly &amp; refused food to a 
<lb/>stranger. For my part I was glad to get away from both 
<lb/>them &amp; their dilemma in order to get something to eat<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>That same evening I got to the <placeName>Makalaka</placeName> &amp; there got 
<lb/>abundance. Their boiled beans were so good we 
<lb/>awakened during the night again &amp; again to eat them &amp; I 
<lb/>cut the very buttons off my trousers to give them as 
<lb/>tokens of my gratitude. <del type="strikethrough">they</del> we had tried a piece 

	<pb n="0011" facs="liv_000527_0011"/><!--pb/@n='90r'-->
<lb/>of rhinocerous skin roasted the day before but though my teeth 
<lb/>are good it fairly beat me<reg>.</reg> My jaws were quite tired ere I 
<lb/>conquered two mouthfuls. I don<reg>'</reg>t tell these things to make 
<lb/>you pity me, I don<reg>'</reg>t pity myself the pleasure of this work 
<lb/>far outweighs the disagreables of it. We sit here &amp; tell tales 
<lb/>such as these &amp; laugh over them, I mention them to you 
<lb/>that you may be entertained by the recital of the different 
<lb/>things which happen to servants of the same master in 
<lb/>different countries. You must not publish this, I 
<lb/>wrote to a friend of mine quite a confidential letter &amp; I 
<lb/>was ashamed to see it afterwards flourishing in all the 
<lb/>colonial papers &amp; even in the English Record without a 
<lb/>single emendation, the circumstances I state freely here 
<lb/>I should not were it designed for the eye of the public<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I could tell you a long story about hunger &amp;c. How I 
<lb/>was almost dead in the wilderness &amp; unable to trust my 
<lb/>hankerchief which I was using as a hunger belt<reg>.</reg> But 
<lb/>what about it<choice><reg>?</reg><orig>.</orig></choice><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he men of the world suffer as 
<lb/>much &amp; more than ever  I did for the sake of the 
<lb/>gospel of Him who has done so much for me<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>But I must <unclear cert="low">rush</unclear> the story of the finger lest you 
<lb/>think it hindered me greatly, I can bear a little pain 
<lb/>pretty well so it did not require any attention. But 
<lb/>one night a lion approached very near to the bush 
<lb/>under which we were all fast asleep and then 
<lb/>commenced his hideous roaring. My ox leaped in 
<lb/>among us. My poor <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> shrieked for fear 
<lb/>&amp; I half asleep &amp; stupid seized a pistol with the disabled 
<lb/>hand but the rebound hurt me much more than 
<lb/>the bullet did the lion, it rebroke my bone. The 
<lb/>noise however made him move off. My poor 

	<pb n="0012" facs="liv_000527_0012"/><!--pb/@n='90v'-->
<lb/>fellows on seeing the blood again running said by 
<lb/>way of comforting me "You have hurt yourself but you 
<lb/>have redeemed us. Henceforth we will swear by you" 
<lb/>I wished they had felt the value of the blood which was shed for 
<lb/>the redemption of their souls. I had three such escapes 
<lb/>from lions. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his last was the heaviest fellow I have 
<lb/>heard, I can resemble it to nothing better than the noise 
<lb/>made by the letting off the steam in a steam boat. If 
<lb/>there were some breaks in it, the likeness would be complete 
<lb/>as - --- - ---<reg>.</reg><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>his journey on ox back was 
<lb/>more than 400 miles in length. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he pleasures far
<lb/>surpass the pains. Will you join me in thanksgiving 
<lb/>for the marvellous loving kindness of the Lord to one of the 
<lb/>least of all his servants<reg>.</reg> No one had ever such 
<lb/>proof of his care &amp; had such a cold heart afterwards<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>May he forgive me. And may he help me to devote my 
<lb/>whole being to His glorious service. O that my time may 
<lb/>not run to waste that I may do something for Him 
<lb/>who has done so much for me<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>Many many thanks for the Magazines<reg>.</reg> Especially for 
<lb/>our own congregational. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>here's life in it now, 
<lb/>It's a living moving active thing. But formerly it was 
<lb/>as grave as a quaker &amp; readable by people with spectacles 
<lb/>only<reg>.</reg> I enclose a note respecting payment &amp;c. 
<lb/><choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>lso one for <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Sewell</persName> who will inform you 
<lb/>of my reasons for doing so. Now as you get 
<lb/>up the mag. so well I give you the privilege of 
<lb/>being corrector of this parvum in multo letter<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Put in all the words that are left out &amp; put out all those 
<lb/>which ought never to have been in<reg>.</reg> Affectionately yours 
<lb/><persName>D Livingston</persName></p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>