<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000632">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Hamilton M. Dyke</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Hamilton M. Dyke, 20 May 1847</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2007-07-09</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000632</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">National Library of Scotland; MS. 10707, ff. 23r-24v</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0167</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Dyke, Hamilton M., 1817-1880</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1847-05-20">20 May 1847</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Kuruman</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2007-07-09</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Intial Transcription by Caroline Overy
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2008-02-29</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>Proofed by Caroline Overy
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000632_0001"/><!--pb/@n='23r'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Kuruman</placeName> 20 May 1847</p>
<lb/><p>My Dear Brother</p>
<lb/><p>Having come out here for the purpose of attending 
<lb/>a meeting of Committee held at <placeName>Likatlong</placeName>, we have found it necessary 
<lb/>to wait for an expected addition <add place="below">^</add><add place="above">to </add> our family. The delay although pretty 
<lb/>well employed in preparations for another campaign is rather 
<lb/>trying to a head pretty full of plans &amp;c. which we hope to see in 
<lb/>operation for the benefit of our people. But it gives a little 
<lb/><choice><sic>leasure</sic><corr>leisure</corr></choice> for correspondence and I am happy to avail myself of it 
<lb/>for the purpose of acknowledging your most welcome letter<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Unfortunately I have not brought it with me. I shall therefore be 
<lb/>obliged to do the needful from memory, and first of all the books 
<lb/>you mention I have not in my possession. I need not add if 
<lb/>I had you should be most welcome to a perusal. I wish you 
<lb/>much happiness in your intended union. It is a state 
<lb/>notwithstanding the jokes we can pass upon it which can impart 
<lb/>a large amount of true happiness, and a good deal of that 
<lb/>depends on not expecting too much from each other<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Whoever expects his partner to be anything like perfect will as <persName>Goldsmith</persName>
<lb/>has it <term type="reference">"find his godess made of clay"</term> and will be about as little pitied 
<lb/>except an occasional ejac. of "poor fellow" as a person affected 
<lb/>with sea sickness. We have not heard whether you had proceeding 
<lb/>Capewards. Indeed there has been a dearth of news from your 
<lb/>side for some time past. I felt amused when informed that 
<lb/>you must go to the Consistory or what ever else they call it 
<lb/>for Ordination and your old friend <persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Philip</persName> to be left out<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I had imagined that this climate helped to make us forget some of 
<lb/><choice><sic>of</sic><corr>notext</corr></choice> our clerical foibles<reg>.</reg> But perhaps the Atmosphere you live in 
<lb/>contains more of the Antique than ours. </p>
<lb/><p>A short time previous to coming to this place we paid a long 
<lb/>visit to a number of the tribes lying Eastwards of <placeName>Chonuane</placeName><reg>.</reg>
<lb/>We have felt anxious to place a native teacher with one of 
<lb/>them but the fact of Boers living in that region and 
<lb/>claiming authority over all its inhabitants presented obstacles 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000632_0002"/><!--pb/@n='23v'-->
<lb/>to the accomplishment of our wishes. I endeavoured to remove 
<lb/>the disinclination of those worthy landholders <add place="above">to our plan</add> and found that <add place="below">^</add><add place="above">in</add> my presence 
<lb/>it was <choice><sic>easyly</sic><corr>easily</corr></choice> effected while <add place="above">in</add> my <choice><sic><add place="above">absence</add></sic><corr>notext</corr></choice> absence their aversion was just the 
<lb/><choice><sic>the</sic><corr>notext</corr></choice> same as ever. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey hate us cordially. Indeed one old "Christian" 
<lb/>instructed the chief we wished have a settlement with<reg>,</reg> to assassinate 
<lb/>your humble servant. Our visit will have one good result 
<lb/>the natives now know that there are some white men 
<lb/>who are not Boers. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey shewed considerable confidence 
<lb/>in us and especially those who when in subjection to 
<lb/><persName>Mosilikatse</persName> had been visited by missionaries - <persName>Mogale</persName>
<lb/>after <choice><sic>whome</sic><corr>whom</corr></choice> a whole range of Hills is called <placeName>Mogalesberg</placeName> is completely 
<lb/>under the thumb of the <persName>Commandant Kruger</persName>. I could not get 
<lb/>a man to bring me a bit of Tin ore from a hill a mile or two 
<lb/>distant unless I should ask leave first of his excellency the boer 
<lb/>Mogale said it is not now my land. I can do nothing in it except 
<lb/>through <persName><unclear cert="medium">Gen<hi rend="sup">l</hi></unclear> K.</persName>. We had good meetings there and I believe 
<lb/>at that time we were about due North of you. Still farther 
<lb/>to the East and about the latitude of <placeName>Chonuane</placeName> 24° 30′ S. 
<lb/>lie the <term type="tribe">Bagalaka</term><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Arboussie</persName> if I remember rightly spea<del type="strikethrough">c</del>ks 
<lb/>about them in his work. <persName>Mokhopane</persName> or <persName>Secoamari</persName> is 
<lb/>chief of one section, a little fat talkative fellow. We 
<lb/>visited other two sections of the <term type="tribe">Bagalaka</term> - and saw the 
<lb/>residences of others in the distance. <persName>Mañk<add place="above">h</add>opane</persName> chief of 
<lb/>the <term type="tribe">Bamapela</term> is a young man not more than 20 and yet 
<lb/>horribile dictu has 48 wives and 20 children - the latter all 
<lb/>very much resembling himself in feature - these people 
<lb/>and their numbers exceed anything I have seen in this 
<lb/>country, had never seen a missionary before - I was 
<lb/>quite ashamed to be called a Sekoa for the only Makoa 
<lb/>they know are men who treat them as the beasts of 
<lb/>the field. It would make you melancholy were I to 
<lb/>recite all the tales of sorrow &amp; oppression I heard. I gave 
<lb/>most credence to those I heard from the Boers themselves<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Others do so &amp; so said they I don<reg>'</reg>t. On the side of the oppressor 
<lb/>there is power - The people are rich in cattle but have 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000632_0003"/><!--pb/@n='24r'-->
<lb/>no fire arms - so the emigrants carry it all their own way. I shall 
<lb/>give you a specimen of what that <unclear cert="low">really</unclear> is<reg>.</reg> On the month previous 
<lb/>to my visit three or four boers moved up to <persName>Mankopane's</persName> herds 
<lb/>at noon day &amp; singled out 30 of the finest cattle &amp; 50 sheep - and 
<lb/>went off. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey did the same in another tribe about 8 miles off<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>When we came the people ran up the rocks in fear and the chief 
<lb/>told me the reason was the Boers came into their towns drunk their 
<lb/>beer and abused their women &amp;c. and what can we do? "We hold our 
<lb/>hands on our mouths because we have no <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/>" Are these fellows 
<lb/>not sowing the seeds of a future Caffre war? When I told the 
<lb/>Commandant of this deed he pretended to know nothing at all about 
<lb/>it<reg>.</reg> He promised to look after the thieves &amp; said that they belonged 
<lb/>to a party which would obey no Gov<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he Boers believed that 
<lb/>our object was to obtain information from natives respecting 
<lb/>a commando they made on a defenceless <add place="below">^</add><add place="above">but rich</add> man called <persName><unclear cert="low">Melechoe</unclear></persName>
<lb/>and that I wished to introduce guns among the tribes. By the 
<lb/>way if one <persName>Hartley</persName> an English trader comes into your house 
<lb/>you may remember that he formed one of that Commando<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he people I daresay wondered at our curious ways - preaching 
<lb/>praying &amp;c. they could understand but little by one visit and it 
<lb/>is so distant we can<reg>'</reg>t go often. We were 19 days travelling 
<lb/>before we reached our farthest point. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he <placeName>Limpopo</placeName> or 
<lb/><placeName>Ourie</placeName> makes an enormous bend down there coming from 
<lb/>the North thus <figure><!--<graphic url="LETT178-1.gif"/>--></figure> &amp; <choice><sic>recieving</sic><corr>receiving</corr></choice> two large rivers itself becomes 
<lb/><placeName><unclear cert="low">Malinoka</unclear></placeName><unclear cert="low">with</unclear> a truly magnificent stream. A rich country 
<lb/>copper iron &amp; tin are all worked. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he ores rich. We bought 
<lb/>a few spindles &amp; distaffs with cotton yarn<reg>.</reg> But what a scene 
<lb/>that land will present in the great day. What multitudes 
<lb/>who never heard the glad sound. But my space is done 
<lb/>go <unclear cert="low">tipa tseta</unclear> is to spin there<reg>.</reg> Is it so with you. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey have 
<lb/>a great deal of the <unclear cert="low">ole</unclear> sound in their dialect<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>What funny chaps you are over there in Committee. You 
<lb/>take away <unclear cert="low"><persName>Lenine</persName></unclear> &amp; <persName>Langa</persName> from a station which required all 
<lb/>their energy to keep afloat. And then place a young man instead 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000632_0004"/><!--pb/@n='24v'-->
<lb/>of these two hard working veterans. Is this your way of allowing a 
<lb/>station to die a natural death? If it does the blame won<reg>'</reg>t fall on the 
<lb/>proper shoulders. I feel compassion for <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi><choice><sic>Frideaux</sic><corr>Frédoux</corr></choice></persName> left at this 
<lb/>stage of his experience among such a people<reg>.</reg> But this is between 
<lb/>ourselves.</p><anchor xml:id="envelopePosition" type="positionMarker"/>
<lb/><p>Please present very kind regards from <persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L</persName> &amp; self to your esteemed 
<lb/>brother &amp; sister <persName>Cassilis</persName>, and to your better half if indeed you 
<lb/>have secured the Rib additional. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi><persName>Moffat</persName> do the same 
<lb/>the latter wrote from <placeName>Likatlong</placeName>. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>here are no news 
<lb/>here. All goes on as it was in beginning, is now &amp;c </p>
<lb/><p rend="right">Yours ever more D Livingston</p><!--<addSpan to="addEnd-24v" place="Sheet folded to make envelope. Envelope text on the middle of fol. 24v" type="envelope"/>-->
<ab type="envelope">
<address corresp="#envelopePosition">
<addrLine><persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> <unclear cert="low">H. T.</unclear><!--according to C & C is H M Dyke --> Dyke</persName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>Basuto Country</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><del type="strikethrough">care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> T. <unclear cert="medium">Atkinson</unclear></persName>, <placeName>Colesberg</placeName></del></addrLine>
</address>
</ab>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>