<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl"?>
<!--Converted from a TEI P5 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000498">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to John Arundel</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to John Arundel, 22 December 1841</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London, UK</pubPlace>
				<publisher>University College London</publisher>
				<date>2012</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000498</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			 <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>England</country><!-- Change as needed -->
                        <settlement>London</settlement><!-- Change as needed -->
                        <repository>University of London. School of Oriental and African Studies</repository><!-- Change as needed -->
                        <idno type="shelfmark">CWM/LMS/Livingstone Wooden Box, item 18</idno><!-- Change as needed -->
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno type="ccnumber">Letters, 0043</idno><!-- This the CC number; change, as appropriate -->
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote xml:id="U"><label>Unknown Hand</label> This hand is unknown
                                but thought not David Livingstone's.</handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
                <bibl type="sourceMetadata">
                    <title>Letter to John Arundel, 22 December 1841</title><!-- Change -->
                    <author>Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
                    <date type="composition" when="1841-12-22">22 December 1841</date><!-- Change -->
                    <placeName type="compositionPlace">Kuruman</placeName><!-- Change -->
                    <persName type="addressee">Arundel, John, 1778-1848</persName><!-- Change -->
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2012-06-01</date>
				<name xml:id="DC">Danielle Cyphert</name>Initial transcription and XML encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-10-04</date>
				<name xml:id="JM">Jared McDonald</name>Proofreading
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-10-04</date>
				<name xml:id="AW"/>Additional encoding.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2012-10-30</date>
				<name xml:id="HFB">Heather F. Ball</name> XML editing.
            
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2016-03-19</date>
				<name xml:id="EM">E. Alexander Munson</name>Proofreading and Coding Revision.
            
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000498_0001"><!--pb/@n='1'--></pb>
	<ab>
<lb/>I should feel greatly obliged by a communication however short. Please let me know how you are in health, my sheet
<lb/>is filled &amp; I have not said half of what I would but I shall write you again I hope a more connected <bibl>letter</bibl>, Yours affectionately
<lb/><persName><choice><abbr>D</abbr><expan>David</expan></choice> <choice><orig>Livingston</orig><reg>Livingstone</reg></choice></persName>
	</ab>
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> <date when="1841-12-22">22 <choice><abbr>Dec</abbr><expan>December</expan></choice> 1841</date></p>
<lb/><p>My Dear Sir</p>
<lb/><p>You kindly permitted me to address you occasionally
<lb/>a private communication and though I have now been away
<lb/>from <placeName><country>England</country></placeName> more than twelve months I have no yet availed
<lb/>myself of that <choice><sic>privelege</sic><corr>privilege</corr></choice> but I have not delayed long. I have
<lb/>indeed been long from <placeName><country>England</country></placeName> but I have only been but
<lb/>a very short time here. <space dim="horizontal" extent="1" unit="words"/>My time has been spent in the
<lb/>long long journey to this place and recently I have returned
<lb/>from another pretty long journey beyond it-- I undertook
<lb/>this latter journey by the advice and with the approbation of
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hamilton</persName> &amp; <persName>Edwards</persName> to whose counsels I was commended
<lb/>by the <orgName>Directors</orgName> before leaving home. The object of it was to
<lb/>ascertain the state &amp; disposition of certain tribes lying north &amp;
<lb/>North East of this. They had frequently sent messages to
<lb/>the brethren requesting <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> and as frequently the
<lb/>brethren were anxious to visit them but <persName>Mr <choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> could not
<lb/>leave <persName>Mr Hamilton</persName> alone for so long a period as was necessary
<lb/>and it was only when we arrived that the way seemed open
<lb/>As the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName> is to be my field of labours I confess I was glad
<lb/>of an opportunity of entering it at this time－－</p>
<lb/><p>Our journey was in going &amp; returning at least 700 miles
<lb/>in length, but though so long we were not at any time
<lb/>more than 250 directly North. This however is farther
<lb/>in that direction than any <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> have yet been. In
<lb/>one case the people had not before seen a white face and
<lb/>in some others only one, <choice><abbr>viz.</abbr><expan cert="high">videlicet</expan></choice> that of an enterprising trader
<lb/>who has frequently penetrated far beyond anyone else
<lb/>We were however everywhere received with respect and
<lb/>by those tribes situated farthest off even with kindness
<lb/>I was astonished at the difference observable near to
<lb/><orgName>mission stations</orgName>. Within a distance of 100 miles, the
<lb/>people who do not live actually on the stations are violent
<lb/>opponents of the gospel. They partially know the
<lb/>requirements of the gospel. They know they must put
<lb/>away their superfluous wives &amp;c &amp;c, and on their
<lb/>account they hate it cordially. They <choice><sic>wont</sic><corr>won't</corr></choice> listen. the
<lb/><term type="occupation">chiefs</term> to please the teachers call the people together but the
<lb/>latter know the minds of the <term type="occupation">chiefs</term> &amp; they refuse to come
<lb/>They flocked round the <choice><orig>waggon</orig><reg>wagon</reg></choice>s for medicine &amp; would talk
<lb/>on any subject except that which of all others is the
<lb/>most important to be known, And I was pained to
<lb/>hear the scorn thrown on the name of <persName>Jesus</persName> when
<lb/>they thought I did not hear them. One <term type="occupation">chief</term> got
<lb/>up a dance round <persName>Mr Hamilton</persName> lately to drown his
<lb/>voice while preaching. This was an outrage that

	

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000498_0002"><!--pb/@n='2'--></pb>
<lb/>would not be committed by any other <term type="occupation">chief</term> but himself but though
<lb/>not openly opponents to that extent they are no less certainly
<lb/>unfavourable to preaching. When I say this I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> refer
<lb/>to those situated far beyond us. These know nothing of the
<lb/>gospel nor of <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> except that we are good people
<lb/>&amp; friendly with all. But they equally with those nearer &amp;
<lb/>perhaps to a greater degree possess an impression that
<lb/><orgName>Europeans</orgName> are a decidely superior race of people &amp; it
<lb/>would be dangerous to provoke our enmity, the respect
<lb/>to their opinion of us, it must have undergone a complete
<lb/>revolution in the space of the last 20 years. And to what
<lb/>are all to attribute this favourable change by which any white
<lb/>man may travel through the length &amp; breadth of the land
<lb/>without fear of molestation: It would be pleasant
<lb/>could we attribute it to the influence of the gospel which has
<lb/>so long, so affectionately &amp; faithfully been preached to them
<lb/>I expected this was the case but when I have seen one
<lb/>impression over all the tribes and this stronger in porportion
<lb/>as we recede from the regions where the gospel is known
<lb/>I am compelled to give the credit of the change to a less
<lb/>lovely influence - <choice><abbr>viz.</abbr><expan cert="high">videlicet</expan></choice> the successive defeat of two large
<lb/>bands of marauders who had overcome &amp; treated with great cruelty
<lb/>nearly all the <term type="tribe">Bechuanas</term>, by a mere handful of <choice><orig><sic>boors</sic></orig><corr>Boors</corr><reg>Boers</reg></choice> &amp; <term type="tribe">Griquas</term>
<lb/>But this impression which rests in full force in all the
<lb/>tribes beyond 100 miles of this will not love remain so
<lb/>They are now purchasing guns themselves rapidly. They are
<lb/>visited by traders every year, and also by <term type="tribe">Griquas</term> for the same
<lb/>purpose with the traders. And these latter are giving them
<lb/>the diseases of <orgName>Europeans</orgName> without any of their civilization. (The
<lb/><term type="ailment">venereal disease</term> was unknown amongst them until this same
<lb/>year it was taken into the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName> by a <term type="tribe">Griqua</term> whom I know)
<lb/>Persons also from the tribes adjoining us are passing on for
<lb/>the sake of getting game; and if a rigorous effort is not
<lb/>instantly made by us I see no prospect left but that soon
<lb/>the tribes situated 200 &amp; 250 miles distant will become as
<lb/>much opponents of the gospel as those within 100 miles of us
<lb/>Now you must not think me visionary when I say
<lb/>the effort could be made immediately. We don't need
<lb/><orgName>European <term type="occupation">missionaries</term></orgName> to do it. They are good but much
<lb/>can be done with far less expensive machinery. The whole
<lb/>of the tribes we visited could now be placed under effective
<lb/>instructions had we only the means to employ them. The
<lb/>distant tribes would all receive them, not however from
<lb/>a desire to be instructed for I could not ascertain that motive
<lb/>was present in the mind of a simple individual we visited.
<lb/>It is not by any means like the <placeName><region>South Sea Islands</region></placeName>. One wishes

	

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000498_0003"><!--pb/@n='3'--></pb>
<lb/>a teacher because it will make him of more importance in the eyes
<lb/>of his neighbours. Another expects a lot of guns with him &amp;c <del type="cancelled">and</del>
<lb/><add place="marginleft">But</add> it is well they are willing at all to allow teachers to come amongst them
<lb/>some of the tribes nearer would not allow so much. They say if a
<lb/>white teacher comes we will listen to him but we <choice><sic>wont</sic><corr>won't</corr></choice> have a
<lb/>black one. This however is just an excuse for they <choice><sic>wont</sic><corr>won't</corr></choice> listen
<lb/>to a white teacher neither. <space dim="horizontal" extent="5" unit="chars"/> The <orgName>native</orgName> teachers are really
<lb/>most efficient agents in the dissemination of religious truth and
<lb/>if we had two with each of the <placeName><region>Interior</region></placeName> tribes I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> hesitate
<lb/>to affirm that as much would by the Divine blessing be affected
<lb/>by them in the way of removing prejudice &amp; enlightening &amp;
<lb/>saving the people as would be <choice><sic>effected</sic><corr>affected</corr></choice> by any two <orgName>Europeans</orgName>
<lb/>for the first half dozen years at least. <space dim="horizontal" extent="5" unit="chars"/>That you may
<lb/>judge whether I am right or not I shall mention some facts
<lb/>which I wish I could mention to the <term type="occupation">Director</term> without appearing
<lb/>to make an invidious comparison. The facts stare me
<lb/>every day in the face and were I was anxious to stand entirely <!-- Is "were" supposed to be "where"? seems so but cannot be sure HB 10/30/12 -->
<lb/>aloof from party feeling and anything like impeaching that wisdom
<lb/>of those who have preceded me in the work &amp; who are all
<lb/>greatly my superiors in prudence &amp; piety. I should certainly
<lb/>make them publicly known to the <term type="occupation">Directors</term>. But knowing
<lb/>that they are fully aware of the value of <orgName>native</orgName> agents &amp;
<lb/>that they need nothing from me to strengthen their convictio<gap agent="hole" extent="1" unit="chars"/><supplied cert="high">n</supplied>
<lb/>on the subject. I do no more than mention them to yo<gap agent="hole" extent="5" unit="chars"/><supplied cert="high">u</supplied>
<lb/>privately for your own information－－ </p>
<lb/><p>It has been the policy of the <orgName><placeName><settlement type="town">Griqua Town</settlement></placeName> <term type="occupation">mission<gap agent="hole" extent="4" unit="chars"/><supplied cert="high">aries</supplied></term></orgName>
<lb/>all along to employ <orgName>native</orgName> agents. The consequence has been
<lb/>the believers have increased in a compound ratio. They
<lb/>have many imperfections but God has blessed them
<lb/>wonderfully. On our way here we unexpectedly came upon
<lb/>a village on a Sunday morning. The want of water having
<lb/>compelled us to travel at that time. They knew nothing of us
<lb/>&amp; we were entirely ignorant of them yet we found that 
<lb/>public worship &amp; school for the children were regularly kept
<lb/>up although from the illness of <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hughes</persName> &amp; the distance being
<lb/>60 or so miles from <placeName><settlement type="town">Griqua Town</settlement></placeName>, they had been visited
<lb/>by no <term type="occupation">missionary</term> for 10 months previously. This fact
<lb/>greatly strengthened my predilections in favour of employing
<lb/>as soon as possible all who are capable of making known
<lb/>the way of life. We had the best possible opportunity of
<lb/>observing them conduct, and who after seeing it would
<lb/>not wish to have a band of such assistants to aid on the
<lb/>course of truth &amp; holiness. They have imperfections but
<lb/>I see nothing else in the operations of the <orgName><placeName><settlement type="town"><abbr>G.</abbr><expan>Griqua</expan> Town</settlement></placeName> mission</orgName>
<lb/>to account for its success but these very imperfect
<lb/>instruments. The <term type="occupation">missionaries</term> now can do little else
<lb/>than itinerate &amp; superintend them, and they occupy not only
<lb/>what may be called their own field but great part of ours</p>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000498_0004"><!--pb/@n='4'--></pb>
<lb/><p>Am I sorry to see them stretching out on all sides &amp; passing us as they are
<lb/>now doing <choice><abbr>W.</abbr><expan>West</expan></choice> by <choice><abbr>N.</abbr><expan>North</expan></choice>? No I rejoice at it &amp; <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> care though they hug
<lb/>us by &amp; by in their arms &amp; squeeze us out towards the North. If no other
<lb/>motive will send us North then prayers will. It is all the same <del type="strikethrough">of</del>
<lb/>whoever brings in sinners to <persName>Christ</persName>. It is common cause &amp; I am really
<lb/>glad <gap agent="deletion" extent="1" unit="words"/><del type="strikethrough">at see</del> to see the work going on. But unfortunately a little rivalry
<lb/>other than prov <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">o</add>king to love &amp; good works has got in amongst us &amp; those
<lb/>who have been longer in the work have local associations which
<lb/>prevent them seeing something in the same light we do. They look at
<lb/>the subject from a different point of view &amp; consequently it appears in
<lb/>another form to them－－ <space dim="horizontal" extent="1" unit="words"/>But <orgName>native</orgName> agency has been tried here
<lb/>too as well as at <placeName><settlement type="village">Griqua Town</settlement></placeName>. After <persName>M<hi rend="sup"/>r Moffat</persName> went to <placeName><country>England</country></placeName> he
<lb/>seems to have changed a little his opinions on that subject for he
<lb/>wrote back advising the <choice><orig>bretheren</orig><reg>brethren</reg></choice> here to make a trial of two; These
    
<!-- Text interrupted by postal information; continues after break at bottom of page HB 10/30/12 -->
<lb/>were appointed and the consequence has been a large accession
<lb/>to the church. Each at his location has more members under
<lb/>him than are at the station. That is they have more than <choice><orig>⅔</orig><reg>2/3</reg></choice> of
<lb/>the church &amp; the <term type="occupation">chief</term> accessions to it are always from their
<lb/>ministry. Add to this they are much more consistent in their
<lb/>deportment than those here &amp; so affectionate to us &amp; to each
<lb/>other it is quite a treat to visit them - And this notwithstand<supplied>ing</supplied>
<lb/><persName>Mr Edwards</persName> is an excellent <unclear cert="medium">sicuana</unclear> scholar &amp; an excellent preacher
<lb/>in it too. Since I understand him I am quite delighted to hear him
<lb/>I believe this is the case too with the <orgName><placeName><settlement type="town"><abbr>G.</abbr><expan>Griqua</expan></settlement> mission</placeName></orgName> for the truth
<lb/>seems so much more effective &amp; comes home to the heart better
<lb/>in proportion as it is divested of all the strangers which attaches
<lb/><add place="marginleft">to</add> foreigners in every country.</p>
	<cb/>
<lb/><p>I am most anxious that more <orgName>native</orgName> teachers be employed &amp;
<lb/>in this anxiety the <choice><orig>bretheren</orig><reg>brethren</reg></choice><persName><choice><abbr>E</abbr><expan>Edwards</expan></choice></persName> &amp; <persName>Hamilton</persName> now <unclear cert="medium">cordially</unclear> join
<lb/>along with this I make an application to the <orgName>Directors</orgName> and I
<lb/>wait with much anxiety an answer.</p>
	<ab>
<lb/><del type="strikethrough">Care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Phillip</persName>. Church Square</del>
<lb/><placeName><settlement type="town"><hi rend="underline">Cape Town</hi></settlement></placeName>
<lb/><persName>Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> John Arundel</persName>
<lb/><orgName>Mission House</orgName>
<lb/>Bloomfield <choice><abbr>St.</abbr><expan>Street</expan></choice>
<lb/><placeName><settlement type="city">London</settlement></placeName>
<lb/><hi rend="underline">single sheet</hi></ab>

			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>