<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_002634">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Henry Rawlinson</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Henry Rawlinson, [January?] 1873</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2008-09-11</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_002634</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Royal Geographical Society (Great Britain); Archives, DL 4/18/1</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 2028</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Rawlinson, Henry, 1810-1895</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1873-01">[January?] 1873</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">South Central Africa</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Typescript</handNote>
				<handNote xml:id="hand02">Scribe: Pencil</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2008-09-11</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Initial Transcription by Caroline Overy
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2009-05-11</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>Initial Proof by Chris Lawrence
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_002634_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1r'-->
<lb/><p rend="center">South Central Africa</p>
<lb/><p rend="right">1873</p>
<lb/><p>My Dear Sir Henry</p>
<lb/><p>I have felt ever since I left 
<lb/><placeName>Unyanyembe</placeName> on this my concluding trip that I 
<lb/>expressed very inadequately the gratitude that 
<lb/>welled up in my heart to you and all the promoters 
<lb/>of the search &amp; Relief expedition, but I was so 
<lb/>overjoyed by finding that <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Stanley</persName> had promptly 
<lb/>procured fifty five men and what additional goods 
<lb/>I needed to finish all I proposed to do, that I was 
<lb/>more like a boy going home from school than the 
<lb/>staid toothless old fogie I find myself to be. Whatever 
<lb/>you may have thought was lacking you are too 
<lb/>much of a traveller yourself to pass a very heavy 
<lb/>judgement on me, for verily I did feel, and do feel 
<lb/>extremely grateful to you all. I was a little sorry 
<lb/>that a strong dose of the cheap nostrum called 
<lb/>"good advice" the gallant <unclear cert="low">athletes</unclear> chose to wait for 
<lb/>the cessation of the rains, for remaining on a most 
<lb/>unhealthy and awfully stinking island all their 
<lb/>good intentions oozed out at their finger ends, and I 
<lb/>had no opportunity of <unclear cert="low">bringing</unclear> to their notice 
<lb/>the very important service of exploring the Lake system 
<lb/>of the <placeName>Victoria Nyanza</placeName>. I certainly did not need them 
<lb/>for my work - they would have "resigned"  a naval 
<lb/>phrase for "going on strike" before they waded through 
<lb/>half the water I have been obliged to ford around <placeName>Lake 
<lb/>Bangweolo</placeName> and unanimously voted me to be a beast 
<lb/>deserving death or as articles of War say some 
<lb/>worse punishment. I don<reg>'</reg>t know who gave the good 
<lb/>advice, but <persName>Stanley</persName> went off at the beginning of the heavy 
<lb/>rains, and after knowing their worst <choice><sic>cooly</sic><corr>coolly</corr></choice> elected to 
<lb/>go through all the Masika again in order to hasten 
<lb/>up the men and goods I so much needed. I left in the 
<lb/>middle of the Masika too for the reason that I had my 
<lb/>English stock of robust health with which to battle against 
<lb/>the pelting rains. I have had another spell of Masika 
<lb/>on the watershed - the worst I ever endured for the cold 
<lb/>Nor-West stratum again thick with clouds lay like a  wet 
<lb/>blanket on all that upland forest land. For three 
<lb/>months I could not get an astronomical observation 
<lb/>except a <supplied reason="damage" source="published version">few</supplied> snap latitudes. Was led down to the back 
<lb/><unclear cert="low">or</unclear> northern side of <placeName>Bangweolo</placeName> and near its Western 
<lb/>end. Had to plod away to the south-east through 
<lb/>riverine meshes each thread from half a mile to 
<lb/><choice><sic>to</sic><corr>notext</corr></choice> three miles broad - deep and encumbered with 
<lb/>great masses of aquatic vegetation. Branches come out 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_002634_0002"/><!--pb/@n='1v'-->
<lb/>of the larger streams and flow over endless slightly 
<lb/>depressed valleys, among four or five species of 
<lb/>rushes - among three species of Lotus or sacred 
<lb/><choice><sic>lilly</sic><corr>lily</corr></choice> plants - Papyrus plants and many other 
<lb/>plants that grow only in water - very much as other 
<lb/>rivers near the coast flow in branches among 
<lb/>mud and mangroves - some of these deltas of 
<lb/>aquatic vegetation are from forty to fifty miles long 
<lb/>and too broad to be seen over, but only grassy 
<lb/>seas with anthill islands having trees at great 
<lb/>distances from each other - no one but an eye 
<lb/>witness could imagine the vast amount of water 
<lb/>in the country. Six rivers of <placeName>Cam</placeName> or <placeName>Isis</placeName> size flow 
<lb/>from the south - they rise in the ridge of the 
<lb/>watershed, or not so far off, that overlooks the deep 
<lb/>valley of the <placeName>Loangwa</placeName> of <placeName><supplied reason="illegible" source="published version">Zumbo</supplied></placeName>. The shores of the 
<lb/>Lake and for days out are remarkable only for 
<lb/>extreme flatness. When I visited it in the dry season 
<lb/>there was generally no more slope to it than there is 
<lb/>from the <placeName>Isle of Dogs</placeName> down to the <placeName>Thames</placeName>. Now it is 
<lb/>nearly impossible to tell where land ends and lake 
<lb/>begins. <choice><reg>S</reg><orig>s</orig></choice>ome one, overcome by the fascination of 
<lb/>describing unknown <del type="strikethrough">described</del><add place="above">said that</add> it <choice><sic>as</sic><corr>was</corr></choice> like <placeName>Nyassa</placeName>
<lb/><placeName>Tanganyika</placeName> &amp; the <placeName>Albert Nyanza</placeName> overhung by high 
<lb/>mountain slopes that open out into bays &amp; valleys. 
<lb/>The only slopes I saw were those of anthills which 
<lb/>may be called high if thought of as perched on the 
<lb/>general altitude of about 4000 feet. This seems to be 
<lb/>the head of one main line of drainage of the <placeName>Nile</placeName> - but 
<lb/>I am not positive till I meet with <persName>Baker</persName> and for 
<lb/>that meeting I do most intensely long. I was not 
<lb/>aware till <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Stanley</persName> came that a letter that succeeded 
<lb/>one of 1868 from near <placeName>Bangweolo</placeName>, had been destroyed - 
<lb/>the three head men of the caravan that carried the 
<lb/><placeName>Bangewolo</placeName> letter were slain by a tribe in the way but 
<lb/>the survivors carried it on safely to <placeName>Zanzibar</placeName>. Following 
<lb/><placeName>Luapula</placeName> down through <placeName>Moero</placeName> I saw the vast rent in 
<lb/>the lofty black mountains of <placeName>Rua</placeName> through which 
<lb/>the <placeName>Lualaba</placeName> finds its birth, and I went three days 
<lb/>round the end of these <placeName>Rua mountains</placeName> and saw 
<lb/><placeName>Lualaba</placeName> coming out of the same fizzure and 
<lb/>flowing away to the Nor-West. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he drainage clearly 
<lb/>did not go into <placeName>Tanganyika</placeName>, and <supplied reason="damage" source="published version">that</supplied> lake 
<lb/>though it probably has an outlet lost all its interest 
<lb/>to me as a source of the river of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>. I wrote 
<lb/>to this effect in Dec<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> 1868 but it never went 
<lb/>beyond the <persName>Governor of Unyanyembe</persName>. I 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_002634_0003"/><!--pb/@n='2r'-->
<lb/>was amused to find that geographers had been 
<w>bam-<lb break="no"/>boozled</w> most unmercifully by the Arab palaver 
<lb/>that Nile flowed out of <add place="above">Tanganyika's</add> Northern end - that it was 
<lb/>distinctly brackish in shut <add place="above">in</add> bays, and perfectly sweet out 
<lb/>in the main stream, though rivers from whose 
<lb/>banks, as the <placeName>Malagarasi</placeName>, enormous quantities 
<lb/>of salt are daily taken, have been flowing in for 
<lb/>ages - that like all great rivers in this country 
<lb/>having North and South reaches it was fast wearing 
<lb/>away its eastern bank - the village of <placeName>Ujiji</placeName> for 
<lb/>instance stands a full mile east of where it 
<lb/>stood in the <add place="above">now deep</add> water in the memory of persons still 
<lb/>living - that several palm oil palms now stand 
<lb/>out fifty yards from the <placeName>Ujiji</placeName> village <add place="above">shore</add> where 
<lb/>they could not have grown had water been 
<lb/>there when they were young - and many other 
<lb/>land trees now stand in the water in the same 
<lb/>circumstances - these reasons made me form
<lb/>an opinion that it had an outlet and I unwisely 
<lb/>mentioned that opinion in a private letter. We 
<lb/>did not find an outlet in the North, though an 
<lb/>Arab asserted within one day<reg>'</reg>s sail of the <placeName>Lusize</placeName>
<lb/>that positively <placeName>Tanganyika</placeName> water ran out by 
<lb/>it and not in it. He was not ashamed when told to look at it. </p>
<lb/><p>Knowing where the main drainage went 
<lb/>I worked at it though without men and means 
<lb/>and then got Banian slaves, the worst of all 
<lb/>slaves, and about £4 out of £500 or £600 worth 
<lb/>of goods. It was gratifying to see incidentally in 
<lb/>some paper that <persName>Keith Johnstone</persName> who ought 
<lb/>to be called "<hi rend="underline">Secundus</hi>" for he has the genuine 
<lb/>geographical acumen of <persName>Keith Johnstone 
<lb/>"<hi rend="underline">Primus</hi>"</persName> had without knowing the rent 
<lb/>in the <placeName>Rua (not Ruwa or Uruwa) Mountains</placeName>
<lb/>reasoned out the drainage from <placeName>Bangweolo</placeName>
<lb/>as going NW - as I found it and as I 
<lb/>often feared went thence to the <placeName>Congo</placeName>. My 
<lb/>reckoning made it flowing 24º to 25º East - 
<lb/>and no wonder the dense dark forests of <placeName>Manyema</placeName>
<lb/>would puzzle anything except a <choice><sic>gorillah</sic><corr>gorilla</corr></choice>
<lb/>or soko. By a patent process, I succeeded 
<lb/>in squeezing a longitude out of a dead 
<w>chrono-<lb break="no"/>meter</w> and that made it flow in 27º nearly. 
<lb/>The same process made the North end of <placeName>Tanganyika</placeName> nearly the <supplied reason="damage" source="published version">same</supplied> as <persName>Speke's</persName>. </p>
<lb/><p>It is interesting to find <supplied reason="damage" source="published version">an offer</supplied> made to the 
<lb/>Government to supersede <supplied reason="damage" source="published version">me</supplied> by running up to the end of <placeName>Tanganyika</placeName> &amp; to call me out of <placeName>Manyema</placeName>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_002634_0004"/><!--pb/@n='2v'-->
<lb/>where Arab palaver said I was "living like an Arab"<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>My discovery shews that I alone knew what I was 
<lb/>about,  and the other <add place="above">plan</add> than a search &amp; relief expedition 
<lb/>about which you did not enquire would have 
<lb/>shewn the unwisdom of believing Arabs who are 
<lb/>the least reliable of all informants. I wish it to be 
<lb/>especially understood that I twice sent copies of all 
<lb/>my astronomical observations - with sketch maps - 
<lb/>and as opportunities presented themselves pretty 
<lb/>full consecutive accounts of all my work for the 
<lb/>Foreign Office and you. <choice><reg>B</reg><orig>b</orig></choice>ut not a letter was suffered 
<lb/>to pass the members of a slaving coterie or Ring of 
<lb/>which <persName>Ludha Dsmji</persName> was the head &amp; chief money 
<lb/>lender at <placeName>Zanzibar</placeName>, and <persName>Syde bin Salem</persName>, the governor 
<lb/>of <placeName>Unanyembe</placeName> was the chief inland. One letter 
<lb/>alone escaped. It went off in company with a 
<lb/>large packet of observations, Despatches &amp; letters 
<lb/>but in the hands of a buffalo driver who wisely 
<lb/>secreted it on his person in the belief that on its 
<w>product-<lb break="no"/>ion</w> his wages depended. All else were destroyed 
<lb/>though I explained to governor that the packet contained 
<lb/>despatches which his Sultan desired to be sent 
<lb/>on with great care. Evidence that <persName>Syde bin Salem</persName>
<lb/>had by his slave <persName><unclear cert="low">Salum</unclear></persName><!--doesn't look like Salim as in printed version--> plundered my caravan was 
<lb/>not to be allowed to go to the coast - and so of the 
<lb/>plundering by <persName>Thani bin Abdullah</persName> and <persName>Shereef</persName>, and 
<lb/>they were successful - and because these wretches 
<lb/>destroyed my correspondence <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Murray</persName> of the 
<lb/>Foreign Office stopped my salary - a very unEnglish 
<lb/>deed to be laid at the door of the English Government. 
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he slaves did their utmost to prevent <persName>Stanley</persName> going to 
<lb/>aid me and when he went with their army to try &amp; 
<lb/>get past the rebel <persName>Mirambo</persName>, governor cut and ran. 
<lb/>This was promptly enough reported as "<persName>Stanley</persName> in 
<lb/>a difficulty" in hopes of getting him recalled and it 
<lb/>led to the S &amp; R Expedition - no prompt report was 
<lb/>made of my presence at <placeName>Ujiji</placeName> though  Governor 
<lb/>acknowledged that he had <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> two despatches 
<lb/>from me there written immediately after my arrival. 
<lb/><persName>Stanley</persName> learned of my presence only at the <placeName>Malagarassi</placeName>
<lb/>close to <placeName>Ujiji</placeName>. <choice><reg>N</reg><orig>n</orig></choice>ot only was information burked 
<lb/>on its way to you - by notes put into Arab packets being 
<lb/>abstracted, but they gave only what was convenient to 
<lb/>H M Vice Consul. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>nd when the two heads of the Ring 
<lb/>were entrusted with stores and men for me the result 
<lb/>might have been anticipated. I think that the plunderers 
<lb/>or their <supplied reason="damage" source="published version">estates</supplied> ought to refund as was done in the case 
<lb/>of <persName>Baron <supplied reason="damage" source="published version">von der</supplied> Decken</persName> but this may not be agreeable 
<lb/>to their friends - meanwhile we shall see<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>Yours &amp;c. David Livingstone.</p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>