<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_002543">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to H. Bartle E. Frere</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to H. Bartle E. Frere, October 1869, May 1870</title><!-- This is a scribal copy-->
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2008-09-04</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_002543</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Royal Geographical Society (Great Britain); Archives, DL 4/9/1 (all but sheets 16-20)</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 1943</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Frere, H. Bartle E., 1815-1884</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date from="1869-10-01" to="1870-05">October 1869, May 1870</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Manyuema Country</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: unknown</handNote>
				<handNote xml:id="hand02">Scribe: unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2008-09-04</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>Initial Transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2009-03-31</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Christopher Lawrence</name>Proof by Chris Lawrence
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_002543_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><handShift new="#hand01"/><placeName>Manyuema Country -</placeName> October 1869 </p>
<lb/><p rend="left">My dear <persName>Sir Bartle</persName>, 
<lb/>I have not the faintest prospect of 
<lb/>sending a letter for many months to come but 
<lb/>I make a little preparation for the time when the 
<lb/>bustle of sending off a packet may arrive. 
<lb/>It is refreshing also when brought occasionally 
<lb/>to a standstill to hold a little converse on 
<lb/>paper with one's friends, and make believe 
<lb/>that progress is reported. I am in the Country 
<lb/>of the <placeName>Manyuema</placeName> the <term type="tribe">Suaheli</term> say <placeName>Manyema</placeName>- 
<lb/>the reputed cannibals, and about 150 miles 
<lb/>West of <placeName>Ujiji</placeName>. As soon as I was recovered from 
<lb/>pneumonia I went up <placeName>Tanganiyika</placeName> fifty 
<lb/>miles to an islet called <placeName>Kasange</placeName> and then 
<lb/>struck Nor West. This was to avoid a great 
<lb/>mass of high mountains opposite <placeName>Ujiji</placeName>- 
<lb/>I had seen the central <add place="above">line</add> of drainage of the 
<lb/>great <placeName>Nile</placeName> Valley pass through <placeName>Lake Moero</placeName>
<lb/>and thence go away N.W. as the <placeName>Lualaba</placeName><fw type="catch" place="marginbottom" rend="right">It</fw> 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_002543_0002"/><!--pb/@n='2'-->
<lb/>It was reported to enter another Lake 
<lb/>there, and was joined by the river 
<lb/><placeName>Lufira</placeName> therein. <add place="above">On</add> coming out it was said to 
<lb/>flow West but no one knew whither. I 
<lb/>imagined that it might be the <placeName>Congo</placeName>, but 
<lb/>I have since found in coming West that 
<lb/>I am in the great bend this river, which 
<lb/>still retains the name <placeName>Lualaba</placeName>, makes 
<lb/>before turning round, and going N and 
<lb/>N.E. into, I suppose, the <placeName>Nile</placeName>. It is 
<lb/>a very large river, sometimes from eight 
<lb/>to ten miles broad. I have to go down 
<lb/>and see where it joins the eastern arm 
<lb/><placeName>Tanganyika</placeName> - <placeName>Lualaba</placeName> - and <placeName>Tanganyika</placeName> are 
<lb/>evidently the two great head branches into 
<lb/>which <persName>Ptolemy</persName> makes the head waters 
<lb/>collect. Were it not so very Burtonesque I 
<lb/>would call them Lacustrine rivers - 
<lb/>extant specimens of the Lake rivers which 
<lb/><fw type="catch" place="marginbottom" rend="right">abounded</fw> 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_002543_0003"/><!--pb/@n='3'-->
<lb/>abounded in <placeName>Africa</placeName> in prehistoric times. 
<lb/>Slowly and surely has the 
<lb/>light dawned on my mind that 
<lb/>the predecessors of <persName>Ptolemy</persName> the 
<lb/>geographer, who flourished in the second century 
<lb/>of our era must have visited this very 
<lb/>region - and all they have left for us 
<lb/>moderns is the <hi rend="underline">rediscovery</hi> of what has sunk 
<lb/>into oblivion, like the circumnavigation 
<lb/>of <placeName>Africa</placeName> by the Phoenician admiral of 
<lb/>one of the Pharaohs about B.C. 600? </p>
<lb/><p>He was not believed because he said that in 
<lb/>passing round <del type="strikethrough">Labya</del> <add place="above"><placeName>Libya</placeName></add> he had the sun 
<lb/>on his right hand. This stamps his 
<lb/>tale to us as genuine. <persName>Ptolemy</persName>, by 
<lb/>placing the springs between ten &amp; twelve 
<lb/>south latitude, and exhibiting the water 
<lb/>collected into <add place="above">two</add> great arms shewed that his <fw type="catch" place="marginbottom" rend="right">informants</fw> 

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_002543_0004"/><!--pb/@n='4'-->
<lb/>informants had visited the sources - 
<lb/>They were probably traders in ivory, 
<lb/>tamed elephants, slaves, copper &amp; 
<lb/>gold. A map of the Ethiopian gold mines 
<lb/>at the time of <persName>Sethos the II</persName> is the oldest in 
<lb/>the world. The copper mines of the <placeName>Katanga</placeName>
<lb/>on my S.W. have been marked for ages &amp; 
<lb/>the malachite is said to be inexhaustible<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>Bible commentators have been strangely 
<lb/>afraid to place <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> further up than 
<lb/><placeName>Nubia</placeName> - some have ventured to put a 
<lb/>patch of it adjacent to the <placeName>Red Sea</placeName> - 
<lb/>if I remember rightly <persName>"Timbaka the 
<lb/>Ethiopian"</persName> had his seat of empire on the 
<lb/><placeName>Euphrates</placeName> - he must have had a large 
<lb/>slice of <placeName>Africa</placeName> to merit his name - <persName>Sir 
<lb/>H. Rawlinson</persName> thought it was like the 
<lb/><persName>Imaum of Muscat</persName> with his African 
<lb/>possessions. I am not without hopes that 
<lb/>the lost city of <placeName>Meröc</placeName> may have existed 
<lb/>at the confluences of <placeName>Lualaba</placeName> &amp; <placeName>Tanganyika</placeName>
<lb/>the extensive underground houses <fw type="catch" place="marginbottom" rend="right">reported</fw> 

	<pb n="0005" facs="liv_002543_0005"/><!--pb/@n='5'-->
<lb/>reported may have been places of sepulture 
<lb/>of a Race which has left no descendants - 
<lb/>the excavations are ascribed to the Deity &amp; 
<lb/>the modern inhabitants build their rude 
<lb/>huts inside. These are my waking dreams 
<lb/>but they will not divert my mind from 
<lb/>following the line of discovery - to whatever 
<lb/>it may lead. <persName>Sir Roderick</persName> by desiring 
<lb/>me to examine the watershed of <placeName>South Central 
<lb/>Africa</placeName> pointed to the true scientific way of 
<lb/>settling the question of the sources. I understood 
<lb/>it to be the wish of the Council too but have 
<lb/>since <del type="strikethrough">my</del> doubts. He said to me 
<lb/>"You will be the real discoverer of the Sources 
<lb/>of the Nile" - <handShift new="#hand02"/> You will not readily conceive the 
<lb/>difficulty - I had to feel every step of the way - 
<lb/>I was generally groping in the dark for who cared 
<lb/>where the rivers ran - the great upland Valley 
<lb/>revealed itself to the Barometers and then the 
<lb/>courses of the rivers proved it - I am a little 
<lb/>anxious that my friends should understand my 

	<pb n="0006" facs="liv_002543_0006"/><!--pb/@n='6'-->
<lb/>reasons for striving to make a complete work of the 
<lb/>exploration - I have had no letters but very old ones 
<lb/>and don't know the state of my affairs or of my family 
<lb/>the only thing I am sure of is that all my friends 
<lb/>will wish me to complete my task before I retire - 
<lb/>In this wish I join and think it better to do so now 
<lb/>than afterwards in vain - It seems indispensable that 
<lb/>I should go down and see where the two great head 
<lb/>branches join. Then go round outside and South 
<lb/>about all the spring so as to be sure no one else 
<lb/>will come and "cut me out" by finding sources South 
<lb/>of mine - This may enable me to visit the rock 
<lb/>excavations and the Copper mines of <placeName>Katanga</placeName> - If 
<lb/>we could go straight where we wish the work 
<lb/>would soon be done, but we have to go where it 
<lb/>is safe and where cowardly attendants will not be 
<lb/>frightened out of their small wits and smaller sense 
<lb/>of duty - We have to make friends with one tribe in 
<lb/>order to venture to another. In this region of dense 
<lb/>forests scarcely three Villages own the same headman 

	<pb n="0007" facs="liv_002543_0007"/><!--pb/@n='7'-->
<lb/><!--6x-->or know each other - I have a seriously long work 
<lb/>before me but hope that the kind providence which 
<lb/>has helped thus far may aid me through. </p>
<lb/><p>In contemplating my work it is impossible not to 
<lb/>think of poor <persName>Speke</persName> - He affords the best example known 
<lb/>of the eager pursuit of a foregone conclusion - When he 
<lb/>discovered the <placeName>Victoria Nyanza</placeName> he at once concluded that 
<lb/>therein lay the sources of the River of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>. He would 
<lb/>suffer no one to doubt this - nor would he allow his own 
<lb/>mind to admit a flaw. When he saw that the 
<lb/>small River which comes out of it would not account for 
<lb/>the <placeName>Nile</placeName> he conjectured a "backwater" whatever that may 
<lb/>mean as an augmentation of his little "White <placeName> Nile</placeName>" - His 
<lb/>conclusion admitted of no question, and oddly enough <persName>Baker</persName>
<lb/>upheld <persName>Speke's</persName> conclusion - though no large river begins in 
<lb/>a lake.  <persName>Ptolemy's</persName> small lake "Coloe" is a more correct view 
<lb/>of <placeName>Okara</placeName> than that given by <persName>Speke</persName> and <persName>Grant</persName> - Three 
<lb/>Lakes were run by <persName>Speke</persName> into one huge <placeName>Victoria Nyanza</placeName>. 
<lb/>Unless the most intelligent <space dim="horizontal" extent="1" unit="words"/> who spent many years 
<lb/>on the east of this Lake are grievously mistaken it 
<lb/>contains but little water and the River that comes out is 

	<pb n="0008" facs="liv_002543_0008"/><!--pb/@n='8'-->
<lb/>less than half the size of the <space dim="horizontal" extent="1" unit="words"/> out of <placeName>Nyassa</placeName>
<lb/>and at any rate through it could be called a source, the 
<lb/>springs and fountains of the <placeName>Nile</placeName> are unquestionably from 
<lb/>500 to 700 miles further up the Great Valley than <persName>Speke</persName>
<lb/>and <persName>Baker</persName> believed them to be. I feel sorry for <persName>Speke's</persName> friends<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>If I should say little about him some will be offended. 
<lb/>If I say what I think others will take offence - I feel 
<lb/>in a difficulty and would fain not hurt the feelings of 
<lb/>any one - <persName>Grant</persName> needs no pity - the sources led to his getting 
<lb/>a good wife - £2,000 a year and a London house with her, 
<lb/>though he never saw them.  I have lost nearly all my 
<lb/>teeth and am fast drifting into second Childhood - this is 
<lb/>what the sources have done for me. A Dutch lady of 
<lb/>whom I know nothing but from scraps in the newspapers 
<lb/>moves my sympathy more than any other - By wise foresight 
<lb/>in providing a Steamer, and nobly pushing on up the river 
<lb/>in spite of the severest domestic affliction - the loss of her 
<lb/>two Aunts by fever - until after she was assured by <persName>Speke</persName>
<lb/>&amp; <persName>Grant</persName> that they had already discovered in <placeName>Victoria Nyanza</placeName>
<lb/>the sources she sought, she must inevitably by boats or on 
<lb/>land have reached the head waters had they not given, 

	<pb n="0009" facs="liv_002543_0009"/><!--pb/@n='9'-->
<lb/>honestly enough of course, their own mistaken views, 
<lb/>I cannot conceive of her turning before she saw <placeName>Moero</placeName> or 
<lb/><placeName>Bangweolo</placeName> for south of all they had seen. When they had 
<lb/>cut off her hope she still lived to go South west and 
<lb/>shewed as much pluck as if she had been a descendent of 
<lb/><persName>Von Tromp</persName> - We great he donkeys say "Exploration did not 
<lb/>become her sex" - Well, considering that more than 1600 years 
<lb/>have elapsed since the <placeName>Nile</placeName> fountains were formally visited, 
<lb/>and Emperors, Kings - all the great men of antiquity, longed 
<lb/>to know where the great River, rose, exploration does not 
<lb/>seem to have become the other sex either. She came further 
<lb/>up than the two Centurians sent by <persName>Nero Caesar</persName><reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>The <placeName>Manyuema Country</placeName> is in many parts densely 
<lb/>peopled by a rather degraded race - The <term type="tribe">Suaheli</term> firmly believe 
<lb/>them to be Cannibals and tell tales of their purchasing 
<lb/>dead slaves. The different Villages have no political cohesion 
<lb/>and vengeance has been taken sometimes by Suaheli Arabs 
<lb/>for supposed acts of murder and cannibalism committed on 
<lb/>their attendants. If asked the Manyuema laugh and should 
<lb/>they take the enquirer to be credulous, say, Yes we eat people 
<lb/>and laughingly go into details. But intelligent men among 

	<pb n="0010" facs="liv_002543_0010"/><!--pb/@n='10'-->
<lb/>them speak seriously and point away about North 
<lb/>west to the Country of the real men eaters, which may be 
<lb/>that of Du Chaillu's <unclear cert="low">Faus</unclear> - a black stuff smeared on the 
<lb/>cheeks is a sign of mourning - one of my attendants who 
<lb/>believes everything was told that it was animal charcoal 
<lb/>made of the bones of relatives they had eaten - and when 
<lb/>he appeared shocked proceeded in their usual peculiar way 
<lb/>to shew him the skull of a recent victim - he pointed it 
<lb/>out to me in triumph - it was the skull of a Gorillah 
<lb/>here called Soko, and this with Serpents they do eat - the 
<lb/>Soko or Gorillah is abundant. His cry or mew may be 
<lb/>heard any night in the gigantic forests here. It is not 
<lb/>very terrible. It is near what I remember of the call 
<lb/>of a peacock - or Tom cats on the top of a <placeName>London</placeName> house 
<lb/>but not so vicious in tones as he sometimes <unclear cert="low">puts</unclear> - Food 
<lb/>is very abundant - Holcus Serghum - Maize - Sweet Potatoes, 
<lb/>&amp; Cassava yield farinaceous diet. Ground nuts - palm oil palms 
<lb/>and another oil yielding tree supply fatty constituents - Sugar 
<lb/>cane, bananas and plantains <unclear cert="low">damilies</unclear> Goats Sheep &amp; Fowls 
<lb/>in the Villages, and Elephants, Buffaloes Antelopes swarming 
<lb/>in the forests afford plenty of nitrogenous matter - Nets are 

	<pb n="0011" facs="liv_002543_0011"/><!--pb/@n='11'-->
<lb/>made strong enough to hold lions, and Sokos are deceived 
<lb/>by bunches of bananas placed in their way and speared. 
<lb/>If the Manyuema are cannibals they are so without reasonable 
<lb/>cause. For the present I place them alongside the people 
<lb/>who have no knowledge of fire - of a supreme Being - or 
<lb/>a language, but have tails - I shall look for evidence before 
<lb/>I believe them to be very horrible. They build square houses. 
<lb/>The walls entirely of clay, and the Ladies plait their 
<lb/>abundant hair into straw bonnet shape. The brim comes out 
<lb/>about four inches and protects their eyes by its shade - They 
<lb/>will file their teeth to points - the Hussies! </p>
<lb/><p>May 1870 - I offered a handsome present to any one 
<lb/>who would shew me human flesh cooked or eaten but in 
<lb/>vain - The native Arabs or Suaheli pretended to have seen so 
<lb/>much Cannibalism I expected to witness a little - At last a 
<lb/>human finger wrapped in a leaf was brought, probably a 
<lb/>charm taken from a man who was killed in revenge - One 
<lb/>who had lived long among them told me that similar 
<lb/>small portions were all he ever saw, and the Medical profession 
<lb/>use them - the Doctors seem to have caused the Manyuema 
<lb/>or as Suaheli say Manyema to be called Cannibals. If I had 

	<pb n="0012" facs="liv_002543_0012"/><!--pb/@n='12'-->
<lb/>believed one tenth part of the horrible tales the traders 
<lb/>and adjacent tribes told me I might not have ventured 
<lb/>to come among them. Fortunately my mother never frightened 
<lb/>me in infancy with "Bogie" so I am not subject to Bogiephobia 
<lb/>in which the Patient believes in everything horrible if only it 
<lb/>is imputed to be the possessor of a black skin. A worse obstacle 
<lb/>than Manyema Cannibalism - the rainy season - has detained 
<lb/>me some months - the vegetation is exceedingly rank, through the 
<lb/>grass of the Valleys, if grass it can be called which is more 
<lb/>than half an inch in diameter in the stalk &amp; ten or twelve 
<lb/>feet high nothing but Elephants can walk. Broad belts of forest 
<lb/>stand between each district. Into these the vertical sun sends 
<lb/>but a few rays - the rain water stands in holes made by 
<lb/>Elephants' feet, and the dead leaves decay on the damp soil 
<lb/>and make the water of the numerous rills and rivulets of the 
<lb/>colour of a strong infusion of tea.  The mud of mire (scothice 
<lb/>glaur) is awful - bad water - perpetual wettings - brought on 
<lb/>choleraic symptoms and great emaciation. I came to a stand 
<lb/>till the rains cease with the heads of a Suaheli horde which 
<lb/>the needs of cheap ivory brought to <placeName>Ujiji</placeName> - They are as kind as 
<lb/>I could wish - Rest - boiling all the water I use and a new 

	<pb n="0013" facs="liv_002543_0013"/><!--pb/@n='13'-->
<lb/>Potatoe have restored me - but I see that as soon as I 
<lb/>find out when the <placeName>Lualaba</placeName> goes into the lower <placeName>Tanganyika</placeName> 
<lb/>I must retire - I must leave the excavations to some one 
<lb/>else. Up the back or southern slope of the watershed no 
<lb/>River can run - so no one can find sources of the <placeName>Nile</placeName>
<lb/>south of mine, but I would put it modestly - I may be 
<lb/>mistaken as others have been, though at present I cannot 
<lb/>conceive in what.</p>
<lb/><p>I did not understand what <persName>Arrowsmith</persName> meant by 
<lb/>my making the Continent broader than it is but I remember 
<lb/>now that I took an observation on the Coast - The occultation 
<lb/>of the fixed Star by the moon, this is virtually a lunar distance 
<lb/>from the edge to the centre of the moon measured with an 
<lb/>accuracy which no instrument can attain. The observation was 
<lb/>calculated at the <placeName>Cape Observatory</placeName> and differed by only 9″ from 
<lb/>what <persName>Commodore Owen</persName> would have made it but for an error 
<lb/>into which he fell. The Admiralty in order to correct this 
<lb/>error pasted a note on the back of all their Charts requesting 
<lb/>the user of it to add 5′ 9″ to every position along the Coast. 
<lb/>My observation added the 5′ and it is rather to my credit 

	<pb n="0014" facs="liv_002543_0014"/><!--pb/@n='14'-->
<lb/>that I came so near what the Commodore would have 
<lb/>put in with his 13 Chronometers on board - <persName>Arrowsmith</persName> <add place="above">evidently</add> never 
<lb/>saw the note referred to and he has transferred the erroneous 
<lb/>survey to his Maps. Taking his erroneous Maps as the breadth 
<lb/>of the Continent mine is 5′ or say 6 English miles too broad. 
<lb/>A ship sailing by <persName>Arrowsmith's</persName> Map would have to go six 
<lb/>miles overland ere it reached the <placeName>Africa</placeName> he has depicted - 
<lb/>He has made enormous havoc of my positions of 1853-7. 
<lb/>My subsequent observations at some of the same spots prove 
<lb/>indubitably that the first were generally correct but <persName>John</persName>
<lb/>wrote to <placeName>Germany</placeName> and elsewhere glorifying himself for finding 
<lb/>out my errors. I have no doubt as to making mistakes 
<lb/>but considering how I was harassed by fever and fatigue 
<lb/>and unpaid it is not very dignified for him to raise a 
<lb/>hurrah instead of being sorry that I did not do better. 
<lb/>An imperfect sketch of <placeName>Nyassamas shire</placeName> &amp;c was sent to <persName>Sir 
<lb/>Roderick</persName> just to give him a general idea of the Country - 
<lb/>I gave <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Arrowsmith</persName> nothing till I come home and 
<lb/>then gave him observations calculated at the <placeName>Cape</placeName> - In 
<lb/>these the Assistant Astronomer Royal declared that my 

	<pb n="0015" facs="liv_002543_0015"/><!--pb/@n='15'-->
<lb/>position of the Lake could not possibly be four minutes 
<lb/>wrong. Our friend had however got hold of our imperfect 
<lb/>sketch, and a sketch from this sketch by <persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Kirk</persName> and 
<lb/>worked away at them though not employed <add place="above">by</add> me, had to 
<lb/>alter all his work when I gave him the Cape calculations 
<lb/>and charged <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Murray</persName> &amp; me £300 chiefly on account of 
<lb/>these alterations. <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Murray</persName> says that <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> A.</persName> is a Man 
<lb/>of the strictest honour - I don't like such a slice to be 
<lb/>whisked off my property however honourably - He declared 
<lb/>that either my imperfect sketch itself or <persName>Kirk's</persName> Copy was forty 
<lb/>miles wrong. As he got a hold of them long ere I came 
<lb/>home and found by the note appended by the Assistant 
<lb/>Astronomer Royal that from my repeated series of Chronometric 
<lb/>observations I could not possibly be 4′ out my worthy old 
<lb/>friend might this time have given me a share of German 
<lb/>glorification, or at least correct his own maps by the Admiralty 
<lb/>note referred to if not the <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/> Maps also at the Rooms in 
<lb/><placeName>Whitehall Gardens</placeName><reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>My experience with the pupils from Nassick Schools makes 
<lb/>me venture the hint that teaching them to work on board a 

	<pb n="0016" facs="liv_002543_0016"/><!--pb/@n='16'-->
<lb/>Man of War anchored in a healthy spot as is done 
<lb/>by <persName>Lord Shaftesbury's</persName> suggestion with the outcasts of <placeName>London</placeName>
<lb/>would be a great improvement on <persName> <add place="above">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi></add> Price's</persName> plan. I discovered 
<lb/>though all asserted at <placeName>Nassick</placeName>, that they had been taken in 
<lb/>war that all had been Slaves and of the Criminal Class and 
<lb/>they dreaded letting me know whence they had come lest they 
<lb/>should be taken back and made to work again. Work is what 
<lb/>all hate - and in all cases they do as little as they can - they 
<lb/>hope to get back to the school to live in idleness - There they had 
<lb/>tools, but if their statements which I have overheard scores of times 
<lb/>are untrue, they might either work play or do nothing - If 
<lb/>made Sailors of and forced to work they would be a benefit to 
<lb/>the Country - taught to wash, cook and mend and make their 
<lb/>own clothes, and the numerous jobs sailors can do - they would be 
<lb/>respected - while coming as Smiths, Carpenters Masons they only give 
<lb/>occasion for jeering, for not one I have seen or heard of can 
<lb/>handle a tool. If the Sons of my English Gentleman were 
<lb/>treated as these poor unfortunates are they would inevitably 
<lb/>be spoiled for life - we have all to be taught that work 
<lb/>is our lot - a blessing and not a curse - To them work is an 

	<pb n="0017" facs="liv_002543_0017"/><!--pb/@n='17'-->
<lb/>unmitigated evil - I look with great anxiety to the 
<lb/>Freedmen in <placeName>America</placeName> but indulge half a hope that 
<lb/>they have more manhood than mine. The way in which 
<lb/>the US Christian Commission carried on their gigantic work 
<lb/>for the Army may be repeated for the recent Slaves. To 
<lb/>elevate 4,000,000 is a superhuman task but the Lord of all seems 
<lb/>to be putting forth his power to gather all into his kingdom. </p>
<lb/><p>I got a small box from <placeName>Zanzibar</placeName> probably from <persName>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Kirk</persName>
<lb/>with some wine and preserves a few Saturday Reviews &amp; Punches 
<lb/>but not a scrap of a letter - I gleaned all I could from 
<lb/>Advertisements &amp;c - I fear that my letters are kept by an influential 
<lb/>man at <placeName>Unyembe</placeName> or <placeName>Garaganza</placeName> called the "Governor" <persName>Syde bin 
<lb/>Salem Buxaschid</persName> by name for a certain long box was left with 
<lb/>him having medicines two English guns letters and despatches 
<lb/>therein. I sent for it twice &amp; received no answer and I am 
<lb/>uncharitable enough to think that he wants to fall heir to 
<lb/>my guns. I have no letters later than 1866 and none from 
<lb/>you but they may be at <placeName>Nyembe</placeName> - My attendants are too 
<lb/>cowardly to go anywhere without me to shelter them and if 
<lb/>I had gone I should have been thrown into the rainy season 
<lb/>at <placeName>Ujiji</placeName> instead of in Manyema. I was much pleased to 

	<pb n="0018" facs="liv_002543_0018"/><!--pb/@n='18'-->
<lb/>see by a Saturday Review that <persName>Miss Frere</persName> had turned 
<lb/>Author and had wisely chosen a path in literature but 
<lb/>little trodden - Her sister doing the tropical scenery shows that 
<lb/>she had been in <del type="strikethrough"><placeName>India</placeName></del><add place="inline">Africa</add> for my drawing is like what 
<lb/>little boys do on walls &amp; I have no inducement to try 
<lb/>and do better for even photographs shewing good foreheads 
<lb/>were by the wood Engravers made into the low conventional 
<lb/>negro shape. It seemed that they could not draw anything 
<lb/>but the West Coast type, while here very many have finely 
<lb/>shaped heads straight or aquiline thin noses &amp; thin lips 
<lb/>magnificent forms with small feet and hands graceful limbs 
<lb/>and barn door mouths prognathous jaws and dark heels are 
<lb/>never seen. Your name the List of Stewards at the Literary 
<lb/>Fund Dinner told me you were in England but this 
<lb/>was addressed before I saw it - My kindest salutations to 
<lb/><persName>Lady Frere</persName> &amp; her family. Although this is grievously prolix 
<lb/>and the Climate has told on the ink I shall add a little 
<lb/>with the latest information. </p>
<lb/><p rend="center">Affectionately </p>
<lb/><p rend="center">(signed) <persName>David Livingstone</persName></p>

	<pb n="0019" facs="liv_002543_0019"/><!--pb/@n='19'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Lake Bangweolo, South Central Africa</placeName></p>
<lb/><p>My dear <persName>Sir Bartle</persName>, 
<lb/>The route I chose to take up the thread of my 
<lb/>exploration where it was broken by the Banian slaves has proved more 
<lb/>difficult and time consuming than I anticipated. An Arab war at 
<lb/><placeName>Unyanyembe</placeName> led me to go due south so as to avoid bands of marauders 
<lb/>who were incited to lawlessness by the disturbed state of the country. 
<lb/>Four parties of traders had been broken up by them before we started, 
<lb/>but we got away safely, and turning West soon came to <placeName>Tanganyika</placeName>. 
<lb/>The eastern shore is very mountainous and the rocks of the Southern 
<lb/>half chiefly mica schist and gneiss are lifted up on edge as the leaves of 
<lb/>a book when turned up on its back and slightly opened. It seems as 
<lb/>if a wedge the breadth of the Lake had been thrust up from below where 
<lb/>the water now stands, and crushed the strata up and away as they 
<lb/>now appear - the marching was excessively severe and it produced 
<lb/>many cases of subcutaneous inflammation limbs - 'black' nose, or 
<lb/>erysipelas and when I mildly proposed surgically to relieve the tension 
<lb/>the idea was too horrible, but they willingly carried the helpless - not a 
<lb/>shower had fallen, and the grass mostly burned off left a surface covered 
<lb/>with blade ashes from which the heat radiated as out of a furnace or 

	<pb n="0020" facs="liv_002543_0020"/><!--pb/@n='20'-->
<lb/>say an oven. Yet out of this hard hot surface the flowers generally 
<lb/>without leaves persisted in coming. A species of ginger with its large 
<lb/>purple and yellow blossoms was the most conspicuous in obeying some 
<lb/>law like that of the Medes and Persians - when we came to the south end 
<lb/>of <placeName>Tanganyika</placeName> we suddenly mounted 4000 feet up to the highland region - 
<lb/><placeName>Unrungu</placeName> and into the strength of the rainy season there with everything 
<lb/>green, and every place sloppy and slippery - I passed through this region 
<lb/>before and besides almost proving fatal at first, when the rains ceased 
<lb/>and circumstances compelled my remaining for 3 1/2 months at an 
<lb/>altitude of 4,700 feet above the sea it proved eminently restorative - some 
<lb/>folks require a good deal of killing, and then again a mere flea bite 
<lb/>gives the quietus. Three of the <term type="tribe">Baurunga</term> chiefs had died during my 
<lb/>absence - one - <persName>Kasonso</persName> - a great friend of mine for he lent me his son to 
<lb/>guide to <placeName>Liemba</placeName> as the lower portion of <placeName>Tanganyika</placeName> is called, and 
<lb/>sent a large quantity of food after us with no hope of reward - one meets 
<lb/>with good fellows everywhere, and some atrociously bad ones, but I 
<lb/>think that we African travellers have of late years got too much into 
<lb/>the travelwriters habit of turning up the whites of our eyes and holding 
<lb/>up our pains as pious people are all thought to do, whenever we meet with 
<lb/>any trait not exactly "Europe Fashion". The elections had turned the 

	<pb n="0021" facs="liv_002543_0021"/><!--pb/@n='21'-->
<lb/>population all topsy turvey - they elect a sister's son or a brother, because 
<lb/>say the sly dogs the heir apparent may not be heir real - What 
<lb/>blasphemy!! - The old stockades had all been abandoned and new ones 
<lb/>built. Forest and virgin land had to be cultivated, and the reclaimed 
<lb/>acreage was necessarily small. Food was very scarce, and hunger 
<lb/>helped to strengthen our old orthodox faith that chief magistrates ought on 
<lb/>no account to be elected - never saw such cloudy weather - no astronomical 
<lb/>observations except a few snap latitudes could be made for over three 
<lb/>months, and it rained night and day as if it would never tire. 
<lb/>Former positions carefully observed were now now of no use, and the people 
<lb/>shewed a perverse ingenuity in leading us West - when I insisted on 
<lb/>following the compass they had me completely in their power "No 
<lb/>food in that line for ten days" and then I had to think of the 
<lb/>empty stomachs of my poor fellows who were collecting mushrooms 
<lb/>very good no doubt as mushroom ketchup with a joint but no more 
<lb/>fattening alone than the east wind which wild asses snuff up - they 
<lb/>brought us down to the back or North side of <placeName>Bangweolo</placeName> and however 
<lb/>much I longed and watched for a lunar distance none could be 
<lb/>obtained - then the rivulets spread out in the flat country as they came 
<lb/>near the Lake so as to be impossible. Many long return marches for 

	<pb n="0022" facs="liv_002543_0022"/><!--pb/@n='22'-->
<lb/>days together had to be made to extricate ourselves from the marshes 
<lb/>whose threads were from two to three miles broad - the poor 
<lb/>fellows carried me through the waters though it would have been 
<lb/>more agreeable to me to wade, as I did when I had unwillingly 
<lb/><choice><sic>libertoes</sic><corr>liberties</corr></choice>. My thighs became sore from resting all my weight by 
<lb/>the hour on their shoulders. They have hitherto done remarkably well 
<lb/>the highest praise I could bestow would be that they equal the 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Makakolo</term> but they are cowards, and the system of their education 
<lb/>has left out truthfulness as one of the virtues. I always remember 
<lb/>the services of the brave, kind hearted, sensible, truthful and albeit 
<lb/>rather wicked <term type="tribe">Makalolo</term> with a warm glow in my heart - The 
<lb/>rivulets flowing into this Lake often spread out into estuaries 
<lb/>and make <placeName>Bangweolo</placeName> look as if she had a string of oblong 
<lb/>pearls round her neck. At other seasons this may be different 
<lb/>the country adjacent is all flat forest, an hours march in this 
<lb/>brings you to a rivulet flowing in a meadow with one or two 
<lb/>hundred yards of weeping earthenn sponge on each side, a stream 
<lb/>runs along the centre or winds from side to side of the slightly 
<lb/>depressed valley - crossing this and ascending a few feet by a gentle 
<lb/>slope you enter forest again, or plod through great patches of 

	<pb n="0023" facs="liv_002543_0023"/><!--pb/@n='23'-->
<lb/>Brackens and other Ferns into forest again, the rivulets are legion - 
<lb/>none but an eyewitness could believe the prodigious amount of water in 
<lb/>the country all flowing into <placeName>Bangweolo</placeName> - When its discovery was announced 
<lb/>at the coast some one wrote an official description of it to the <placeName>Bombay</placeName>
<lb/>Government and stated that it is like <placeName>Nyassa Tanganyika</placeName> and the 
<lb/><placeName>Albert Nyzanza</placeName>, overhung by high mountain slopes which open out into 
<lb/>bays and valleys or leave great plains &amp;c &amp;c - The Salse and country 
<lb/>adjacent are about 4000 feet above the sea but the only slopes are 
<lb/>those of anthills which can scarcely be called high unless thought of 
<lb/>as perched on the top of the 4000 feet altitude - the country as far as 
<lb/>the eye can reach is remarkable only for extreme flatness - the slope 
<lb/>being generally not more than from the <placeName>Isle of Dogs</placeName> down to the 
<lb/>level of the <placeName>Thames</placeName> - the description was possibly penned from Arab 
<lb/>palavers and the fascination of describing the unknown had better 
<lb/>be resisted or left to the Poets. </p>
<lb/><p>The <placeName>Chambeze</placeName> and other rivers flow into its North Eastern horn 
<lb/>through great spongy Bugas or Prairies - the Portuguese crossed the 
<lb/><placeName>Chambeze</placeName> as I did high up where it is small - they were real 
<lb/>Portuguese and not black men with Portuguese names so they are 
<lb/>the first European discoverers of this river in modern times - the 

	<pb n="0024" facs="liv_002543_0024"/><!--pb/@n='24'-->
<lb/>similarity of name to the <placeName>Zambesi</placeName> led them to consider it a branch 
<lb/>of that river and misled by a map saying "<placeName>Zambesi</placeName> (Eastern branch<reg>)</reg>" 
<lb/>I stupidly made my first crossing as fruitless as theirs - It cost me 
<lb/>full twenty two months to eliminate this error and I was less 
<lb/>excusable than they for I ought to have known and remembered 
<lb/>that while <placeName>Chambezi</placeName> is the true native name of the Northern river 
<lb/><placeName>Zambesi</placeName> is not the native name of the Southern river at all. We 
<lb/>followed the Portuguese corruption of the name rather than introduce 
<lb/>confusion as to a name possessing a rather melancholy interest from 
<lb/>the survey and deaths of the officers of <persName>Commodore Owen</persName> on the river 
<lb/>that flows past <placeName>Zette lama Lupanza</placeName> and into the sea by <placeName>Luabo</placeName> &amp; 
<lb/><placeName>Kongone</placeName>. The name by which the natives all know it and speak 
<lb/>of it to each other is <placeName>Dombazi</placeName> - when the speak to Portuguese or 
<lb/>English they call it <placeName>Zambesi</placeName> or <placeName>Zambeze</placeName>. Above the <placeName>Victoria Falls</placeName>
<lb/>its name is <placeName>Liambai</placeName> - We followed the same course with the 
<lb/>Lake whose rather pretty name is <placeName>Nyanza</placeName> or <placeName>Nyinyesi</placeName> or Lake of 
<lb/>Stars - because the Portuguese corruption <placeName>Nyassa</placeName> was known in 
<lb/>geography, and it was rather dumbfounding to find it printed as 
<lb/>a profoundly learned thing "<placeName>Nyassi</placeName> or the Sea" - <placeName>Nyassi</placeName> meaning 
<lb/>a species of very long grass and nothing else. I gained the first rays 

	<pb n="0025" facs="liv_002543_0025"/><!--pb/@n='25'-->
<lb/>of light about <placeName>Chambeze</placeName> not from my own acuteness but from the 
<lb/>rather bantering remarks of the Cazembe who was lately routed and 
<lb/>slain by a party of Bampamwezi whose countryman Funga Funga 
<lb/>he murdered. Certain Arab traders made great preparations for his 
<lb/>downfall and after going several miles up the boundary on the 
<lb/>Kalungwesi thought better of it, told their slaves that the river was 
<lb/>too deep and went away to trade in Rua - the Banyamwezi brought 
<lb/>the head of Cazembe to the Arabs who are immensely elated in 
<lb/>consequence and after their manner give circumstantial details of 
<lb/>their powers in the fight which would be quite interesting did we 
<lb/>not know that they contained not a word of truth. On telling 
<lb/>this Cazembe that I wished to visit <placeName>Bangweolo</placeName>, he said "one piece of 
<lb/>water is just like another - you have seen water in <placeName>Moero</placeName> and 
<lb/><placeName>Lupuala</placeName>, the very water that was in <placeName>Chambeze</placeName> and <placeName>Bangweolo</placeName> but 
<lb/>as your chief ordered you to see it all by all means go after I have 
<lb/>procured good guides and food for you" &amp;c &amp;c I was not sure that 
<lb/>this was not royal chaff till I stood in the <space dim="horizontal" extent="1" unit="words"/> and 
<lb/>had an intelligent islander slowly moving his hand around 183° of 
<lb/>sea horizon and saying that is <placeName>Chambeze</placeName> forming <placeName>Bangweolo</placeName> and 
<lb/>passing round that Western headland to change its name into <space dim="horizontal" extent="1" unit="words"/>

	<pb n="0026" facs="liv_002543_0026"/><!--pb/@n='26'-->
<lb/>It was then that the discovery of this line of drainage was made, but 
<lb/>some may feel that our allies the Portuguese being the first to cross 
<lb/>of the river deserve all the credit. If so I shall not quarrel over the 
<lb/>matter - but pepper and astrology preceded <persName>Herschel</persName> &amp; <persName>Lockyer</persName> men whose 
<lb/>names I am not worthy to mention - it suits me better to laugh 
<lb/>over the great discover of Inner Africa who after the undoubted 
<lb/>discovery of the <placeName>Chambeze</placeName> made it run East instead of West and 
<lb/>toddle away some 4000 feet uphill; and then challenged me in a 
<lb/>learned periodical to argue the point whether <placeName>Chambeze</placeName> was or 
<lb/>was not the "<placeName>New Zambesi</placeName>". </p>
<lb/><p>The Lake people are of the Bisa stock and have long been eager 
<lb/>slave traders. Large caravans of Babisa Bazao &amp; Banyamwezi - 
<lb/>frequently went to the coast and the effect of the enterprise has in 
<lb/>the first two tribes been depopulation of their own countries. Where 
<lb/>no foreign slave trade has existed the people live in peace, and 
<lb/>follow peaceful cultivation of the soil - the frequent visits of Arab 
<lb/>slavers are followed by chronic warfare and mental soreness 
<lb/>against all strangers, this seems to be the invariable effect of 
<lb/>their system - but in <placeName>Central Africa</placeName> generally war is rare and 
<lb/>women have great influence. When men speak of the tribes being 

	<pb n="0027" facs="liv_002543_0027"/><!--pb/@n='27'-->
<lb/>always in a state of chronic warfare they refer perhaps unwittingly 
<lb/>to people within easy reach of the coast who have had many visits 
<lb/>from slavetraders. In this region a man called <persName>Motoka</persName> took to 
<lb/>marauding on his own account. He inspired terror, and many 
<lb/>yielded to him without resistance. He built a line of huts completely 
<lb/>round a stockade I saw &amp; battled two months in vain - The 
<lb/>blood relations of the besieged chief then assembled and coming 
<lb/>suddenly on <persName>Motoka</persName> caused an utter panic and rout, and 
<lb/>finished his marauding though he himself escaped - the news of 
<lb/>what guns can do and the fate of Cazembe inspired as much fear 
<lb/>of us as the most ardent anthropologist could desire.In many places 
<lb/>the entire people fled from us, and we got nothing in the villages but 
<lb/><unclear cert="low">damnless</unclear> chickens - then when we did get a guide he was sure 
<lb/>to run away - this with the impossibility of making astronomical 
<lb/>observations and cold wet forest gloom made our marches 
<lb/>unpleasant. These I suppose are the Elephantophagi, the Lotophagi 
<lb/>the Ichthyophagi into which the ancient anthropologists divided the 
<lb/>people - Instead of naming our tribes after their eating an ostrich 
<lb/>elephant, fish or lotus eaters we modern anthropoi would divide the 
<lb/>nations according to their drinks, as the Scotch = the whiskey fishoid 

	<pb n="0028" facs="liv_002543_0028"/><!--pb/@n='28'-->
<lb/>fiddlers - the gin and stout guzzlers - the roaring Portheeuers - 
<lb/>the vin ordinaire bibbers - the Lager Bier swillers - and a far off 
<lb/>outlying tribe of the "Sherry Cobbler" and "Brandy Cock tail" 
<lb/>persuasion. - Fish are abundant - Elephants and buffaloes 
<lb/>very numerous and two species of lotus or sacred Lilly grow 
<lb/>even on the plains which are flooded only annually - the only 
<lb/>drink in use is the everlasting Pombe which instead of 
<lb/>strengthening the stomach requires a very strong stomach to 
<lb/>master it, and the taste is anything but delicious. It 
<lb/>will not drive champagne out of the market in our day. - </p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>