<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000537"><!-- LETT83 -->
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Alexander Brownlee</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Alexander Brownlee, 17 July 1843</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2007-03-02</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000537</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Royal College of Physicians and Surgeons of Glasgow; 1/20/11/28/1</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0081</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Brownlee, Alexander, Jr.</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1843-07-17">17 July 1843</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Lattakoo</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2007-03-02</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>First transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000537_0001"/><!--pb/@n='01'-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Lattakoo</placeName> 17<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> July 1843  </p>
<lb/><p rend="left">My Dear Friend </p>
<lb/><p>Your kind &amp; excellent letter reached me some months 
<lb/>ago, and I felt it merited prompt acknowledgement<reg>.</reg> But to answer 
<lb/>it has until now been beyond my power. Our Directors 
<lb/>expecting at the time we left <placeName>England</placeName> that <persName> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>Moffat</persName> would 
<lb/>soon follow - instructed us to remain at this station, learn the 
<lb/>language &amp;c, until,we should <choice><sic>recieve</sic><corr>receive</corr></choice> the benefit of the local 
<lb/>knowledge in choosing a location for a new mission 
<lb/>But finding the language by no means as difficult as they 
<lb/>imagined I have been during several long periods away from 
<lb/>the region of postages acquiring a local knowledge for myself<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>The different journies I have undertaken into the interior of the 
<lb/>country have been long &amp; tedious this is not the region of 
<lb/>railways. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he heavy lumbering Dutch waggon drawn by 
<lb/>oxen or slow paced riding oxen are the only means of 
<lb/>locomotion unless we choose our own lower extremeties 
<lb/>which are slower still. But with these imperfect 
<lb/>conveyances I have gone very far into the interior. I have visited 
<lb/>tribes never before seen by Europeans &amp; preached the 
<lb/>Gospel beyond every other man's line of things. You perhaps 
<lb/>might be interested in something of these savage 
<lb/>tribes, everything about them is so degraded &amp; impure the 
<lb/>mind cannot dwell on the more prominent features of their 
<lb/>character I shall however give you a little &amp; by that 
<lb/>you may perhaps be enabled to form some opinion on 
<lb/>that on which I shall be silent. The whole of the 
<lb/><term type="tribe">Bechuana</term> nation is sunk into a state of the lowest 
<lb/>degradation. It would be difficult to point to their 
<w>infer-<lb break="no"/>iors</w> in the world. Human nature can go no lower 
<lb/>than in their case it has done. They are in point of 
<lb/>courage the veriest cowards and yet if they can kill 
<lb/>without danger of being killed they will murder without 
<lb/>compunction and then make long incisions in their 
<lb/>skins the scars of which are to be standing memorials 
<lb/>of their prowess. I have seen men with from 30  
<lb/>to forty of these "scars of honour" (?) They pointed to them 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000537_0002"/><!--pb/@n='02'-->
<lb/>in triumph and were not ashamed to own that many of 
<lb/>them betokened the murder of helpless women &amp; children 
<lb/><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>heir sense of native duties will be understood when I tell 
<lb/>you the wives are the tillers of the ground, the builders of the houses 
<lb/>and the bearers of all heavy burdens. A man is not 
<lb/>ashamed to say he is not able to carry a weight &amp; his wife 
<lb/>is &amp; he will go &amp; call her for that purpose. I speak of 
<lb/>shame but shame they have none. It is a matter of wonder 
<lb/>to me that have the word in their language they know so very 
<lb/>little of the thing. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>heir knowledge of everything except what 
<lb/>relates to their eating and drinking, oxen sheep and goats is most 
<lb/>limited. A few fables contain all the knowledge they derive 
<lb/>from their forefathers and all the future is darkness. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>heir 
<lb/>lives are embittered with fears of being bewitched, nothing 
<lb/>bad comes but by that agency &amp; evils cannot be averted but 
<lb/>by that means. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey seem to think that no one would 
<lb/>ever die were he not killed by some witch, their notions 
<lb/>of medicine are all based on these suppositions, their 
<lb/>doctors pretend to suck out of the bodies of the sick 
<lb/>pieces of bones, skins of animals, ashes, goats dung &amp;c &amp;c<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>These being the articles supposed to be used by witches to 
<lb/>effect their evil purposes. I was lately with the chief 
<lb/>of the <term type="tribe">Battens,</term> his wife had been ill of an affection 
<lb/>of the heart for more than a month, her medical 
<lb/>man had extracted many wonderful substances from 
<lb/>her system by his skill. I proposed giving him an 
<lb/>emetic previous to his next operation lest he should 
<lb/>have been decieving himself the things of witchcraft 
<lb/>coming out of his own body instead of that of the 
<lb/>patient, but my professional brother did not like 
<lb/>the proposition. He slipped away unpercieved by me 
<lb/>&amp; having cupped her artfully separated the fibrine from 
<lb/>the blood. The white clots of that he now exhibited 
<lb/>in triumph. I don't know how he managed to wash 
<lb/>of the red particles from that contistiuent of the blood 
<lb/>but I instantly took a little blood from the arm of 
<lb/>a bystander, washed the clots with warm water and exhibited 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000537_0003"/><!--pb/@n='03'-->
<lb/>the same substance as he had done. During the day he 
<lb/>found an opportunity of having the village &amp; he availed himself 
<lb/>of it. He had been deceiving them for more than a month 
<lb/>perhaps they knew he must have put the things into his 
<lb/>mouth before before he pretended to suck them out of his patient 
<lb/>but they are so afraid of being bewitched by these doctors 
<lb/>no one had dared to mention his suspicions, sometimes 
<lb/>when I give a child medicine, if he makes any objections 
<lb/>to drink it the friends pour it on his head or drink 
<lb/>it themselves. If a man is found guilty of stealing 
<lb/>they give him an emetic in order to make him vomit 
<lb/>his <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="illegible"/> propensity. The chief of the <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term>
<lb/>shewed me a root which he sprinkled on his legs 
<lb/>to make him run fast. And the friends of another 
<lb/>chief were very angry with me because they thought 
<lb/>I had given him medicine to change his heart instead 
<lb/>of that to cure his disease. </p>
<lb/><p>In all other points they are equally degraded, their 
<lb/>foolish hearts are darkened. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he mind &amp; conscience 
<lb/>are defiled. O how we need the prayers of the church 
<lb/>for the outpouring of the Holy Spirit. Never did I 
<lb/>feel the necessity for this enlightening power as 
<lb/>now. Nothing nothing that the most exalled intellect 
<lb/>can do will be of any avail without it. Nothing 
<lb/>will penetrate the thick crust of ignorance which 
<lb/>envelopes their souls but the beams of the Sun 
<lb/>of Righteousness, the Redeemer mighty your almighty 
<lb/>to save. I ask you to remember us at the Throne 
<lb/>of Grace. We need the prayers of the Lord's people 
<lb/>But cannot face how much unless you were present 
<lb/>in the dark places of the earth. I might have told you 
<lb/>of the success of the gospel but I prefer giving you 
<lb/>these simple details in order to stir you up to more 
<lb/>ardent prayer on our behalf and that thus <del type="strikethrough">tho</del>we 
<lb/>may have greater cause to speak of sucesses than we have </p>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000537_0004"/><!--pb/@n='04'-->
<lb/><p>You will be pleased to hear the Directors have fully approved of our 
<lb/>commencing a new station in the interior. The spot is near 
<lb/>to the place <persName>Mr Campbell</persName> the traveller faced about to go home. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he 
<lb/>iron foundaries he heard of but was not permitted to see belong 
<lb/>to our intended sphere of labour. The reason they refused 
<lb/>him a sight of them was not that which influences the 
<w>prop-<lb break="no"/>rietors</w> of our secret works at home. It must have been 
<lb/>the same fear which is now in operation a fear lest by  
<lb/>his presence the iron should be betwitched. Bewitched iron 
<lb/>you will say what is that? It is simply the effect of a too 
<lb/>energetic application of the bellows it becomes burned to a 
<lb/>cinder they then take these out exclaiming behold the effects 
<lb/>of witchcraft. The fact is so as the evidence being before 
<lb/>their clear eyes no one ever disputes it. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey then apply a 
<lb/>double portion of their prophylactic medicines to the ore 
<lb/>&amp; commence the process anew. To prevent the iron 
<lb/>being thus spoiled they use a great many precautions 
<lb/>They won't allow anyone who has had intercourse with 
<lb/>the other sex since the commencement of the period for 
<lb/>working it to approach the furnaces &amp; the men 
<lb/>employed at it always sleep in the enclosures for the 
<lb/>cattle during the whole of the smelting season. Their tools 
<lb/>are as rude as those of old Tubal Cain but my my space 
<lb/>won't allow me to particularize. I can only mention their 
<lb/>tongs are a piece of the bark of a tree folded on itself, the 
<lb/>hammer a stone &amp; the anvil another &amp; yet they manage to make 
<lb/>very neat work with their anteldiluvian implements 
<lb/>Among these people <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Edwards</persName> who is older than you &amp; I 
<lb/>intend soon to make a beginning. May the Lord smile on 
<lb/>our endeavour to carry his name into that dark region 
<lb/>It is also about 30 miles beyond the spot where the 
<lb/>tyrant <persName>Mosilikatze</persName> was visited by <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Moffat</persName> I lately walked 
<lb/>over the site of his town &amp; the place where he suffered a 
<lb/>dreadful defeat by the Boers but a very few human bones 
<lb/>were the only remains of all that belonged to the tyrant<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>Please present my very kind regards to <persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">rs</hi> Brownlee</persName> &amp; 
<lb/>all the family. Also to <persName>D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Rankin</persName> &amp;c I never hear anything 
<lb/>of the young <persName>James</persName> I always forget to remember in my letters some 
<lb/><addSpan spanTo="#addEnd04-01" place="marginleft"><!--addSpan/@place='left margin of p. 4, continuing on left margin of p. 1'--></addSpan> information which may be interesting to you. I shall enclose it on a slip of paper<reg>.</reg></p>

	<pb n="0005" facs="liv_000537_0005"/><!--pb/@n='01'-->
<lb/><p>I need not say I shall be glad to hear from you as often as you can find it 
<lb/>convenient to write. Every thing is interesting that come from home  
<lb/>so you can be at no loss as what to say<reg>.</reg></p>
<lb/><p>Yours Affectionately </p>
<lb/><p><persName>D. Livingstone</persName></p><anchor xml:id="addEnd04-01"/>

	<pb n="0006" facs="liv_000537_0006"/><!--pb/@n='05'-->
<lb/><p>The information to which I refer is a new way of 
<lb/>treating Prurigo. I shall be glad if you do not need it 
<lb/>but lest you do I send it. It has the 
<w>recomm-<lb break="no"/>endation</w> of both British &amp; Foreign medical journals 
<lb/>so I think it must be of value. It is as follows<reg>:</reg>
<lb/>Begin by dipping a bit of rag in aromatic vinegar 
<lb/>undiluted, or acetic acid undiluted and touch 
<lb/>the pimples with it <choice><sic>untill</sic><corr>until</corr></choice> it causes smarting 
<lb/>as much as the patient can bear. Next 
<lb/>day apply a solution of the nitrate of silver 
<lb/>&amp; proceed to apply it for two or three days running 
<lb/>then the acetic acid again <choice><sic>untill</sic><corr>until</corr></choice> the affliction is 
<lb/>cured. If you purchase a sixpence worth of 
<lb/>nitrate of silver commonly called lunar caustic 
<lb/>&amp; dissolve it in a wine glass of rain water 
<lb/>it will do without the acid. The latter is however 
<lb/>cheap. Touching the pimples freely with 
<lb/>the lunar caustic is very good. This you 
<lb/>could do by putting a piece of the caustic in the end 
<lb/>of a quill. Mixing the part with a little water &amp; 
<lb/>then touching them with the solid medicine<reg>.</reg>
<lb/><choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice> drop or two of nitric acid added to the solution 
<lb/>will prevent it being decomposed. 
<lb/>I hope however you have no need of this advice 
<lb/>if so I shall be glad to hear that you have need 
<lb/>only to know this is in the fire </p>

	<pb n="0007" facs="liv_000537_0007"/><!--pb/@n='06'-->
<lb/><p>Care of <persName>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> Phillip</persName><placeName>Cape Town</placeName></p>
<lb/><p><persName>M<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> M<hi rend="sup underline">rs</hi> Brownlee</persName></p>
<lb/><p><placeName>23 Orr St. Mile End.</placeName></p>
<lb/><p><placeName>Glasgow</placeName></p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>