<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_001969">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Roderick I. Murchison</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Roderick I. Murchison, 4 December 1863, 10 [February 1864]</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2007-06-02</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_001969</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Royal Geographical Society (Great Britain); Archives, DL 3/16/1</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 1399</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Murchison, Roderick I., 1792-1871</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date from="1863-12-04" to="1864-02-10">4 December 1863, 10 [February 1864]</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Murchison's Cat.-Shupanga</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes>
				<handNote xml:id="hand01">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
				<handNote xml:id="hand02">Scribe: Unknown</handNote>
			</handNotes>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2009</date>
				<name xml:id="SM">Sharon Messenger</name>Initial Transcription by Sharon Messenger
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>2009-04-09</date>
				<name xml:id="CL">Chris Lawrence</name>Proofed by Chris Lawrence
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_001969_0001"/><!--pb/@n='1'-->
<lb/><p><placeName>Murchison's Cataracts</placeName> 4 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi></p>
<lb/><p>1863</p>
<lb/><p>My dear <persName>Sir Roderick</persName></p>
<lb/><p>The Despatch containing 
<lb/>instructions for our withdrawal though dated 
<lb/>2<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi> Feby did not reach me till 2 July when the water 
<lb/>had fallen so much the <term type="boat">Pioneer</term> could not be taken 
<lb/>down to the sea. To improve the time therefore 
<lb/>between July &amp; the flood of Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi> I thought that I might 
<lb/>see whether a large river enters the Lake at the North 
<lb/>end and also verify the impression that most of the 
<lb/>slaves drawn to <placeName>Zanzibar</placeName><placeName>Iboe</placeName> &amp; <placeName>Mozambique</placeName>
<lb/>come from the <placeName>Lake District.</placeName> Our plan was to 
<lb/>sail round the East shore &amp; North end of <placeName>Nyassa,</placeName> but 
<lb/>we very unfortunately lost our boat by five of 
<lb/>our natives trying to shew how much more clever 
<lb/>they were than five Makololo who had the management 
<lb/>of it. It broke away from them in a <unclear cert="low">compacting</unclear>
<lb/>still reach of the river and <add place="above" hand="#hand02">rushed</add> away like a shot 
<lb/>over the cataracts. We then went forward on foot 
<lb/>and now struck nor west so as to come to the 
<lb/>Latitude of the north end of the Lake without coming 
<lb/>in contact with Mazite or Zulus who have 
<w>de-<lb break="no"/>populated</w> its shores there. <choice><reg>B</reg><orig>b</orig></choice>ut we soon came to 
<lb/>a range of mountains running N. &amp; S. The 
<lb/>valley on its Eastern base was 2000 feet above 
<lb/>the sea - of remarkable beauty and well supplied 
<lb/>with streams of delicious cold water. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he range 
<lb/>at least 4000 feet above it forms the edge of the 
<lb/>high table land on which the <term type="tribe">Maravi</term> dwell. <del type="strikethrough" hand="#hand02"><choice><reg>B</reg><orig>b</orig></choice>ut</del>
<lb/>we were <add place="above" hand="#hand02">however</add> falsely informed, that no people lived 
<lb/>on the other side and went along the valley till we 
<lb/>came out at the neck of the Lake. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he bold mountainous 
<lb/>promontory of <placeName>Cape Maclear</placeName> on our right and 
<lb/>the <placeName>hills of Tsenga</placeName>in front. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>gain going N. W. we 
<lb/>came to a stockade which the Marzite attacked 
<lb/>the day before and we saw the <choice><sic>loathesome</sic><corr>loathsome</corr></choice> evidence 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_001969_0002"/><!--pb/@n='2'-->
<lb/>of the fight, and wishing to avoid them turned 
<lb/>North East till we came to the Lake &amp; marched 
<lb/>along its shores. On coming to <placeName>Kotakota Bay</placeName>
<lb/>Lat 12° 55′ S. we found two Arabs busily engaged 
<lb/>in transporting slaves across by means of three boats, 
<lb/>and building a dhow to supply the place of one 
<lb/>said to have been wrecked. <hi rend="underline"><choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>hey pay one fathom of  
<lb/>calico, value one shilling for a boy and two for a 
<lb/>good looking girl.</hi> yet they would not pay 
<lb/>but for the ivory which they carry. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice> trader with 
<lb/>twenty slaves must pay at least the price of one 
<lb/>Twenty slaves must pay at least the price of one 
<lb/>slave per day for their sustenance. It is the 
<lb/>joint ivory and slave trade which allow traders the 
<lb/>speculation profitable. This is the crossing place 
<lb/>for nearly all the slaves that go to <placeName>Quilloa</placeName>,
<lb/>(or <persName>Kilwa</persName>) <placeName>Iboe,</placeName> and <placeName>Mozambique.</placeName> A few go 
<lb/>down to the end of the Lake and for <unclear cert="low">Leapue</unclear>go 
<lb/>cross the shire. But here lies the great trades route 
<lb/>to <placeName>Katanga-</placeName><placeName>Cazembe</placeName> &amp;c. The <term type="tribe">Babisa</term> are the 
<lb/>principal traders - the <term type="tribe">Manganja</term> are the cultivators 
<lb/>of the soil. The <term type="tribe">Arabs,</term> the same we met before 
<lb/>were very civil<add place="inline" hand="#hand02">.</add><add place="above" hand="#hand02">They</add> came forth to meet us and presented 
<lb/>Rice, meal, sugar-cane, and a piece of Malachite. 
<lb/>Leaving them we went due West, and in three days 
<lb/>ascended to the edge of the plateau which from below 
<lb/>looks like a range of mountains. The long ascent, 
<lb/>adorned with hill and dale, and the <del type="strikethrough">the</del>running 
<lb/>streams fringed with evergreen trees, <del type="strikethrough" hand="#hand02">was</del><add place="above" hand="#hand02">was</add> very 
<lb/>beautiful to the eye, but sore upon the legs, often 
<lb/>causing <add place="above" hand="#hand02">us</add> all to puff and blow as if broken winded. 
<lb/>The heights have a delicious but peculiarly piercing 
<lb/>air. It seemed to go through us - Five <term type="tribe">Shupanga</term>men 
<lb/>who had been accustomed all their lives to the <term type="disease">malaria</term>
<lb/>of the <placeName>Zambesi Delta</placeName> were quite prostrated by that 
<lb/>which to me was <choice><sic>exhilerating</sic><corr>exhilarating</corr></choice> and bracing. </p>
<lb/><p>We <del type="strikethrough" hand="#hand02">went</del><add place="above" hand="#hand02">travelled</add> about ninety miles West then turned 
<lb/>up to the North West. The country is level but 
<lb/>the boiling point shewed a slope in the direction 
<lb/>we were going. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he edge of the plateau is 3440 
<lb/>feet above the sea 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_001969_0003"/><!--pb/@n='3'-->
<lb/>at the Loangua of the Lake the height shewn is 
<lb/>3270 feet <add place="inline" hand="#hand02">//</add> The direction of the streams verifies these 
<lb/>approximate heights and your famous hypothesis 
<lb/>too - <add place="inline" hand="#hand02">;</add> for the Loangua of the Lake finds its way 
<lb/>backwards to the <placeName>Nyassa</placeName> while another called 
<lb/>the Loangua of the <placeName>Maravi,</placeName> flows to the westward 
<lb/>and at enters the <placeName>Zambesi</placeName> at <placeName>Zumbo.</placeName> The feeders 
<lb/>of these rivers are boggy valleys with pools in their 
<lb/>course. We were said to have crossed one branch of 
<lb/>the <unclear cert="low"><placeName>Moetala</placeName></unclear> or <placeName>Moitawa</placeName> which flows N.N.W. into a 
<lb/>small lake called <placeName>Bemba.</placeName> The valleys in which the 
<lb/>rivers rise closely resemble those in <placeName>Loanda</placeName> or <placeName>Lunda</placeName>
<lb/>but here each bank is dotted over with villages and 
<lb/>a great deal of land is cultivated. The vegetation is 
<lb/>more stunted and the trees covered with <add place="above">flat</add><!--this is DL's addition--> lichens like 
<lb/><add place="above">those</add><!--this is DL's addition--> on old Apple tress in <placeName>Scotland,</placeName> and a long thready sort 
<lb/>like orchilla weed, shews a humid climate. We were 
<lb/>going in the direction where a great deal of ivory is 
<lb/>drawn by people on the slave route and this induced 
<lb/>them to put hindrances in our way, refusing to 
<lb/>sell food, and misleading us &amp;c. <add place="inline" hand="#hand02">//</add> The time that could 
<lb/>be spent with safety had expired<add place="inline" hand="#hand02">,</add> our <unclear cert="low">aura</unclear> from food 
<lb/>was expended and <term type="disease">dysentry</term> fell upon us. I was 
<lb/>under explicit orders not to take any long journey 
<lb/>but have the <term type="boat">Pioneer</term> down to the sea by the Earliest 
<lb/>flood. I might have speculated on a late rise in that 
<lb/>river, but did not like the idea of failing in my 
<lb/>duty with the vessel, and gave up further progress. 
<lb/>The temptation to go on was <placeName>Lake Bemba</placeName><del type="strikethrough">was,</del> said 
<lb/>to be but ten days distant. Thence according to 
<lb/>native, and Arab report, issues the <placeName>River Loapula</placeName>
<lb/>or <placeName>Luapula</placeName> which flowing west ward forms the 
<lb/>Lakes <placeName>Mofu</placeName> or <placeName>Mofue</placeName> and <placeName>Moero</placeName>, then passing 
<lb/>the town of <placeName>Cazembe</placeName> it turns round to the North 
<lb/>and is lost in <placeName>Tanganyika.</placeName> Is there an outlet to 
<lb/><placeName>Tanganyika</placeName> on the west into the <placeName>R. Kasai</placeName> East of 
<lb/>where I formerly crossed that river? All agreed in 
<lb/>asserting that no river flowed Eastward into <placeName>L. 
<lb/>Nyassa</placeName>. Two small ones do. <choice><reg>B</reg><orig>b</orig></choice>ut at a distance 
<lb/>of say 80 or 90 miles from the Lake the watershed is to 
<lb/>the west. One should have no bias in investigating 
<lb/>these questions by the aid of travelled natives, but 
<lb/>I had a strong leaning to a flow from <placeName>Tanganyika</placeName>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_001969_0004"/><!--pb/@n='4'-->
<lb/>into <placeName>Nyassa.</placeName><del type="strikethrough" hand="#hand02">but</del> I wished I was <add place="above" hand="#hand02">however</add><unclear cert="low">shortly of one &amp;</unclear>
<lb/>by all. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>nd I had crossed so many running 
<lb/>streams, which from entering the Lake among <unclear cert="low">sheds</unclear>
<lb/>had not been observed from the boat in our first 
<lb/>visit, that before reaching <placeName>Kolakola,</placeName> I had come 
<lb/>to the conclusion that a large river was not needed 
<lb/>to account for the perennial flow of the <placeName>Shire.</placeName>
<lb/>I am sorry to give only native information instead 
<lb/>of observations by my own eyes; but having been 
<lb/>confined to work of much more importance 
<lb/>than exploration, the above was all I could do 
<lb/>when set free. The work on which I <add place="above" hand="#hand02">had</add> laboured 
<lb/>for years has all been spoiled by the Portugese <add place="inline" hand="#hand02">omit</add><!--this is an editorial "omit" for the word Portugese which has been ringed by hand02--> slave hunting, my only regret is ever having given 
<lb/>their nobles the smallest credence for a desire to civilize 
<lb/><placeName>Africa.</placeName></p>
<lb/><p>As we (the steward of the <term type="boat">Pioneer</term> and <del type="strikethrough" hand="#hand02">I</del><add place="above" hand="#hand02">myself</add>) were on 
<lb/>our metal not to overstep the limited time at our disposal 
<lb/>it may be worth mentioning, that we travelled 660 
<lb/>geographical miles in 55 travelling days - averaging 
<lb/>12 per day in straight lines. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he new leaves on 
<lb/>the trees of the plateau were coming out fresh &amp; 
<lb/>green there. <choice><reg>A</reg><orig>a</orig></choice>nd we reached this on the 31<hi rend="sup underline">st</hi> Oct<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi>
<lb/>to find all, except the evergreen ones by the streams 
<lb/>as bare of leaves as in  midwinter. </p>
<lb/><p>: <placeName>Shupunga</placeName> 10<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> Feb </p>
<lb/><p>P.S. <choice><reg>T</reg><orig>t</orig></choice>he river rose in tremendous force on 
<lb/>19<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> January. Much later than usual. It 
<lb/>extracted many a groan from me 
<lb/>for it was plain that I had plenty of time 
<lb/>to have examined <placeName>Bemba,</placeName> the beginning 
<lb/>I suppose of the drainage system which 
<lb/>finds an outlet by the <placeName>Congo.</placeName><persName>Mofu</persName> or 
<lb/><persName>Mofue</persName> was seen I believe by <persName>Monteiro</persName> in his 
<lb/>journey to <placeName>Cazembe.</placeName> We travelled part of 
<lb/>our way on the route from Quill<del type="strikethrough">wa</del>wa to 
<lb/>the same chief. I hope a report of my being 
<lb/>murdered has not reached my family 
<lb/>as they may believe it more the readily on 
<lb/>account of the loss already sustained. I have 
<lb/>never known any difficulty with an interior 
<lb/>tribe or any other not engaged in slaving<reg>.</reg>
<lb/>I am deeply grieved to hear of the death of our 
<lb/>good friend <persName>Admiral Washington.</persName>He did everything 
<lb/>in his power for us<reg>.</reg><persName> David Livingstone</persName></p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>