<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02--><!--TEI encoding revised and standardized by Adrian S. Wisnicki, 2015-2016-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_001873"><!-- LP106 -->
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Editor of the Medical Times and Gazette</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to Editor of the Medical Times and Gazette, 26, 27 January [1863]</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2006-10-09</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_001873</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="shelfmark">Private owner</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 1313.8</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient"><persName>Medical Times and Gazette, Editor of the</persName></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date from="1863-01-26" to="1863-01-27">26, 27 January [1863]</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">River Shire</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2004-11-16</date>
				<name xml:id="CO">Caroline Overy</name>Initial Transcription
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_001873_0001"/><!--pb/@n='127'-->
<lb/><cb xml:id="p127-colB" n="column b"/><space extent="2" unit="words"/><p rend="center">GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE.</p>
<lb/>
<lb/><p rend="center"><space extent="1" unit="words"/>ENGLISH LOSSES IN CENTRAL AFRICA.</p>
<lb/><p rend="center"><space extent="2" unit="words"/><hi rend="smallcaps">Letter from Dr. Livingstone</hi>. </p>
<lb/>
<lb/><p rend="center small">[To the Editor of the Medical Times and Gazette.] </p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent"><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi> - In a leading article in the <hi rend="italic">Medical Times and Gazette</hi>
<lb/>of July 5, 1862, headed "English Sacrifices in Central 
<lb/>Africa," after remarking on the general sickness that 
<w>pre-<lb break="no"/>vailed</w> at the mission station Magomero, you very naturally 
<lb/>ask "How, then, can we reconcile these sad facts with the 
<lb/>statement that 'the mission under the direction of Dr. 
<w>Living-<lb break="no"/>stone</w> settled down in an admirable station high up the river, 
<lb/>where the country is an elevated plateau, where the climate 
<lb/>is tolerably salubrious, and where a dense population is 
<lb/>immediately available for missionary work.'" The 
<w>quota-<lb break="no"/>tion</w> is from the Bishop, (a) and expresses the opinion which 
<lb/>I formed, and still hold, as to the general healthiness of the 
<lb/>plateau referred to. The spot, taken as a temporary residence 
<lb/>until extensive acquaintance with the whole region should 
<lb/>enable the head of the mission to select a suitable locality for 
<lb/>a permanent abode, was forty or fifty miles distant from the 
<lb/>"Elephant Marsh," and at an altitude of between 3000 and 
<lb/>4000 feet above it. We shall therefore try to think of the 
<lb/>marsh and mission station as distinct as Oxford and London. 
<lb/>The plateau is ten or twelve miles broad, and probably 100 
<lb/>in length. We happened to travel along it at the hottest 
<lb/>season of the year, and even then found the climate deliciously 
<lb/>cool. When previously in the Upper Shirè valley, at an 
<w>alti-<lb break="no"/>tude</w> of 1200 feet above the sea, we were drinking water at 84°, 
<lb/>and in one day mounting up to an altitude of between 3000 
<lb/>and 4000 feet, we had every few miles a gushing stream, with 
<lb/>the water at 65°. The air had that bracing effect which the 
<lb/>mountain breezes have at home, and we all struck by 
<lb/>observing far more very old people than we had seen anywhere 
<lb/>else. Our stay was too short for our own experience to be 
<lb/>worth anything; and the experience of the missionaries 
<lb/>amounts only to this, that without ordinary sanitary 
<w>pre-<lb break="no"/>cautions</w> the health is endangered here as it is everywhere else.</p>
<lb/><p>The missionaries were placed in very peculiar circumstances, 
<lb/>and such as probably they never anticipated. As we climbed 
<lb/>up the plateau together, and felt its refreshing breezes,we 
<lb/>met parties of Portuguese, with long lines of bound captives 
<lb/>in their possession. These were soon made free, and the 
<lb/>Bishop, trusting to the support of those who had sent him, 
<lb/>bravely took charge of them. These re-captives soon amounted 
<lb/>to 200; but in what follows I have only the testimony of the 
<lb/>missionaries themselves, for I then left, and pursued the 
<lb/>exploration of Lake Nyassa for some 225 miles. Magomero 
<lb/>was situated on the bend of a small river of exactly the same 
<lb/>shape as that into which General MacClellan, for "strategic 
<lb/>reasons," ran. It was shaded by lofty trees, which the poor 
<lb/>Bishop admired exceedingly, and resolved to preserve. The 
<lb/>efforts of the missionaries failed to prevent these 200 people from 
<lb/>depositing their droppings all over a space of less than 100 
<lb/>yards by 50, and it then was fitly described as a "pest hole." 
<lb/>For some months the people adjacent and around them brought 
<lb/>abundance of provisions for sale, and no one imagined that 
<lb/>these were all their surplus stores; but after the expenditure 
<lb/>of the surplus came famine. The missionaries nobly shared </p> 
<lb/><lb/><milestone unit="section" rend="line"/>
<lb/><space extent="3" unit="words"/><note n="a" anchored="true" rend="small center">The late Bishop Mackenzie.-<hi rend="smallcaps">Ed</hi></note>

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_001873_0002"/><!--pb/@n='128'-->
<cb xml:id="p128-colA" n="column a"/>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">their own provisions with the poor wretches whom they had 
<lb/>adopted, and were reduced to the same hard and scanty fare. 
<lb/>About fifty of the natives perished by ulcers and dysentery, 
<lb/>and to me the wonder is, not that in that foul den the whites 
<lb/>presented the sorry figure you have drawn, but that they were 
<lb/>not all cut off together. Now, don't blame them; they felt 
<lb/>the necessity of removing out of the pest hole, but the grass 
<lb/>had all been burned off, and new huts could not be built; 
<lb/>slave-hunting, at the instigation of the Portuguese of Tette, 
<lb/>was going on all around them; they were in new and untried 
<lb/>circumstances; had to retire to the lowlands; but still all 
<lb/>think that the plateau is the healthiest abode, and will return 
<lb/>as soon as possible.</p>
<lb/><p>The Bishop, whose untimely fate every one who knew him 
<lb/>must deeply deplore, never spared himself, and was foremost 
<lb/>in depriving himself of the comforts, which you rightly 
<lb/>conclude are indispensable to Europeans, in order to save his 
<lb/>orphan children. (b) He and Burrup were the strongest of the 
<lb/>party, and were proportionately disregardful of their health. 
<lb/>Exposed for more than a week previously to hard, fast 
<lb/>marches, worse fare, and drenching showers, he set out from 
<lb/>Magomero, ill with diarrhoea, on his last and fatal trip, and 
<lb/>began by walking through the stream, remarking that he 
<lb/>would soon be wet at any rate. After two days' walking in a 
<lb/>plight which you may imagine, he reached the Shirè, embarked 
<lb/>in a miserable small canoe, and after dropping down the stream 
<lb/>one day was upset, lost clothes and medicines, and went on, 
<lb/>of course, still wet - coffee, tea, and sugar all gone; it is 
<lb/>scarcely possible to conceive a more doleful plight: but let 
<lb/>any one go through the same amount of exposure in England, 
<lb/>and he will as certainly be cut off by consumption as the 
<lb/>Bishop and Mr. Burrup were by fever and dysentery. 
<lb/>When I began to travel I walked through streams, and braved 
<lb/>rains in the same way the Bishop did; but I found that I had 
<lb/>fever perpetually, and gave up the habit, though it was 
<lb/>really pleasant to have the extremeties cooled. You will 
<w>per-<lb break="no"/>form</w> a good service if you warn all Europeans going to the 
<lb/>tropics to take as good care of their health there as they do at 
<lb/>home. In addition to the loss of invaluable services, these 
<lb/>untimely deaths are a great misfortune to the cause of African 
<lb/>civilisation, because people immediately ascribe them to the 
<lb/>inevitable effects of the climate, and with it you say "it is of 
<lb/>no use to send missionaries where they cannot live." In our 
<lb/>expedition, though we have undergone exposure to which no 
<lb/>missionary need subject himself, we have had but two deaths 
<lb/>among a large number of Europeans in four years, and these 
<lb/>were caused by detention sorely against out will in most 
<lb/>unwholesome localities. </p>
<lb/><p>No great work can be accomplished without pain and 
<lb/>suffering, and even death. Those who, with you, "would 
<lb/>not say a word to damp the energy of missionaries and of 
<lb/>those that send them," must expect to hear cases like that of 
<lb/>the noble-minded Indian officer who lately fell a victim to 
<lb/>gigantic labours during the Indian famine, or that of Lord 
<lb/>Canning, and try to place a slight drag on the imagination. 
<lb/>Horror seems to lay hold on you at the bare mention of 
<lb/>"Elephant Swamp." I am actually to pass through it 
<lb/>to-morrow, and am only sorry that the enormous herds of 
<lb/>elephants - we have seen eight hundred in it at once - have 
<lb/>become so knowing we have no chance of getting a steak or 
<lb/>a foot. But see the effects of bad example: my imagination, 
<lb/>do as I will to prevent it, obstinately pictures you sitting on that 
<lb/>wilderness of eight hundred cesspools, which the 
<w>commis-<lb break="no"/>sioners</w> only the other day swept away, and drinking water 
<lb/>mixed, according to Dr. Acland, with all the abominations 
<lb/>and unutterable filthinesses which are poured out of Oxford, 
<lb/>Reading, etc., into your cup. Oh! you filter your water 
<lb/>through a few inches of sand, do you? I would not trust it 
<lb/>(unless I were in London) though filtered through the Great 
<lb/>Sahara. The delicious unconsciousness with which you 
<lb/>exclaim "Elephant Marsh; good heavens! what a vista of 
<lb/>deep swamp, rotting vegetation, flies, vermin, stinks, agues, 
<lb/>and dysentery do the words call up!" only excite a merry 
<lb/>laugh, which I beg you to believe has not one particle of 
<w>ill-<lb break="no"/>nature</w> in it, and the quotation, </p>
<lb/><p rend="center">"Oh, wad some power the giftie gie us, 
<lb/>To see oursels as others see us."</p>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">You have actually a larger area of cesspool and marsh around 
<lb/>and above London than exists in the Elephant Swamp, and to 
<lb/>the direful effects let typhus, typhoid, diphtheria, cholera, 
<lb/>consumption, scrofula, etc., testify. Here they are absolutely </p>
<lb/><lb/><milestone unit="section" rend="line"/>
<lb/><space extent="2" unit="words"/><note n="b" anchored="true" rend="small center">The orphans of the liberated slaves.-<hi rend="smallcaps">Ed</hi></note>
<lb/>
<lb/><cb xml:id="p128-colB" n="column b"/>
<lb/><p rend="no-indent">unknown. But our fever, if ill-treated, as by bleedings, or 
<lb/>not treated, as it was in the case of the missionaries at Lynyanti, 
<lb/>who took only a little Dover's powder, is as fatal as any two 
<lb/>in your catalogue. And while it would be "penny wise and 
<lb/>pound foolish" to make missionaries of inferior men, good men 
<lb/>ought invariably to be accompanied by a thoroughly educated 
<lb/>and well-paid Medical officer. <space dim="horizontal" extent="8" unit="chars"/> I am, &amp;c. </p>
<lb/><p>River Shirè, January 26. <space dim="horizontal" extent="8" unit="chars"/><hi rend="smallcaps">David Livingstone</hi>.</p>
<lb/><p>We have just heard the sad tidings that the Rev. H. C. 
<lb/>Scudamore has been cut off by fever about forty miles above 
<lb/>this, but not on the plateau. In this case there seems to 
<lb/>have been no undue exposure. He was skillfully treated by 
<lb/>Dr. Dickenson. I am bowed down in grief for our beloved 
<lb/>Scudamore. This case is different from those on which I 
<lb/>have remarked. - D. <choice><sic>S</sic><corr>L</corr></choice>. </p>
<lb/><p>Elephant Marsh, January 27.</p>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>