<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000538">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter to Robert N. Hayward, 17 July 1843</title><!-- Change -->
                <author>David Livingstone</author>
                <principal>Adrian S. Wisnicki</principal>
                <principal>Christopher Lawrence</principal>
                <respStmt xml:id="EM">
                    <name>E. Alexander Munson</name><!-- Change -->
                    <resp>Transcription</resp><!-- Change -->
                    <resp>Encoding</resp><!-- Change, remove, or add more <resp> as appropriate -->
                </respStmt>
				<respStmt xml:id="JM">
                    <name>Jared McDonald</name><!-- Change -->
                    <resp>Transcription</resp><!-- Change -->
                    <resp>Encoding</resp><!-- Change, remove, or add more <resp> as appropriate -->
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="AA">
                    <name>Angela Aliff</name>
                    <resp>Transcription</resp>
                    <resp>Encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="AW">
                    <name>Adrian S. Wisnicki</name>
                    <resp>Coding review</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>	
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
                <publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
                <pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2016</date><!-- Change if necessary -->
                <idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000538</idno><!-- Change as needed -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                         <country>South Africa</country><!-- Change as needed -->
                        <settlement>Johannesburg</settlement><!-- Change as needed -->
                        <repository>Brenthurst Library</repository><!-- Change as needed -->
                        <idno type="shelfmark">Book no. 5318, Acc. Reg. 4669</idno><!-- Change as needed -->
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno type="ccnumber">Letters, 0082</idno><!-- This the CC number; change, as appropriate -->
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote xml:id="U0"><label>Unknown Hand</label> This hand is unknown
                                but thought not David Livingstone's.</handNote>
                            <handNote xml:id="U1"><label>Unknown Hand</label> This hand is unknown
                                but thought not David Livingstone's.</handNote>
							<handNote xml:id="U2"><label>Unknown Hand</label> This hand is unknown
                                but thought not David Livingstone's.</handNote>
							<handNote xml:id="U3"><label>Unknown Hand</label> This hand is unknown
                                but thought not David Livingstone's.</handNote>
							<handNote xml:id="U4"><label>Unknown Hand</label> This hand is unknown
                                but thought not David Livingstone's.</handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
                <bibl type="sourceMetadata">
                    <title>Letter to Robert N. Hayward, 17 July 1843</title><!-- Change -->
                    <author xml:id="DL">David Livingstone</author>
                    <date type="composition" when="1856-04-04">17 July 1843</date><!-- Change -->
                    <placeName type="compositionPlace">Kuruman</placeName><!-- Change -->
                    <persName type="addressee">Robert N. Hayward</persName><!-- Change -->
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
				
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
			<change when="2015-12-17" who="#AW">Coding review</change>
            <change when="2015-12-17" who="#JM">Proofreading</change>
			<change when="2015-11-19" who="#AW">Initial coding review</change>
            <change when="2015-11-18" who="#EM">Initial transcription and XML encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
               
	<pb facs="liv_000538_0001" n="0001"/><!-- Change both @facs and @n -->
<lb/><dateline><placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> <date when="1843-07-17">17<hi rend="sup underline">th</hi> July 1843</date> <add place="above marginright" rend="gray" hand="#U0">MS 8/2</add></dateline>
<lb/>    
<lb/><salute>My Dear <persName>Hayward</persName></salute><!-- Change line info as appropriate -->
<lb/><p>Your kind and excellent <bibl>letter</bibl> afforded me quite a 
<lb/>treat and I feel it merited sincere thanks and a more prompt
<lb/>acknowledgement But having been during most of the time
<lb/>that has intervened far away from the region of postage
<lb/>I must be excused for what you may have considered a long
<lb/>delay. I hope you will not follow the example I have
<lb/>been compelled to give but write me again as soon as
<lb/>convenient. Everything from home is interesting so
<lb/>need not be at no loss as to the filling up of a <bibl>letter</bibl> much
<lb/>longer than the last</p>
<lb/><p>When I left <placeName><country>England</country></placeName> the <orgName>Directors</orgName> of our <orgName>Society</orgName> expected
<lb/>that <persName>Mr Moffat</persName> would soon follow &amp; by his knowledge of the
<lb/>people &amp; country assist us in choosing a locality for a new
<lb/><orgName>mission</orgName>, instructed me to remain at <placeName><settlement type="village">Kuruman</settlement></placeName> and endeavour
<lb/>to acquire as much of the language as possible before his arrival
<lb/>I did not however find it so difficult as they imagine it to be
<lb/>and finding too that <del type="strikethrough">frequent</del> in interrupted intercourse with the
<lb/><orgName>natives</orgName> was the best way of acquiring an almost unwritten
<lb/>language I very soon set off in order to obtain knowledge
<lb/>of the country &amp; people for myself. I have had three long
<lb/>journies into the interior, two of them occupied no less
<lb/>than 4 months each, yet I did not reach <placeName><settlement type="city"><choice><sic>Timbuctoo</sic><corr>Timbuktu</corr></choice></settlement></placeName> nor
<lb/>did I see anyone who had been much farther than myself
<lb/>A great fresh water lake lying a little beyond my farthest
<lb/>point north is the great barrier to penetrating far in that
<lb/>direction. It stretches from north <add place="above">East</add> <del type="strikethrough">West</del> to South West
<lb/>and should anyone take in a boat he might explore
<lb/>a great extent of country with very little trouble. The
<lb/><orgName>natives</orgName> have canoes upon it and it is called from them
<lb/>the <placeName><geogName type="lake">Lake of Mokhoro</geogName></placeName> (of the canoe) or according to the
<lb/>names of different nations living on its banks as of the <unclear cert="medium"><term type="tribe">Botleth</term></unclear> <add place="below">&amp;c</add>

	<pb facs="liv_000538_0002" n="0002"/>
<lb/><unclear cert="high">The</unclear> great drawback to travelling in the country is the slowness
<lb/>of our locomotives. The heavy lumbering <orgName>Dutch</orgName> waggon
<lb/><subst><del>a</del><add place="over-text">&amp;</add></subst> the riding ox are the only conveyances unless we choose
<lb/>to try our own lower extremities, I have been as far
<lb/>north as <measure><choice><abbr>Lat.</abbr><expan>Latitude</expan></choice> 22ยบ <choice><abbr>S.</abbr><expan>South</expan></choice></measure>
<lb/>and then is beyond every other <orgName>European</orgName>
<lb/>During my last journey I should probably have seen the lake
<lb/>had my people not been deterred from following me by
<lb/>a dread of <persName>Mosilikatze</persName>. I saw some women who had been
<lb/>taken captive by his men last. They escaped &amp; -
<lb/>reached the <placeName><region><term type="tribe">Bakwain</term></region></placeName> country (on the Tropic) during the time
<lb/>I was there. It had taken them nearly <measure>two months</measure> to reach
<lb/>it &amp; had subsisted by gathering the roots of the desert as <unclear cert="low">then</unclear>
<lb/>food by day &amp; climbing a high rock for protection by night
<lb/>The sight of these poor creatures was enough for my people
<lb/>near very weak hearts seemed to die within them, indeed they
<lb/>buried their noses in the sand as if the <unclear cert="medium"><region>Arabian</region></unclear> <seg type="weather">simoon</seg>
<lb/>had been passing &amp; declared it was madness to go a step
<lb/>near the tyrant. I was then obliged to leave them &amp;
<lb/>go forward on <term type="animal">ox</term> back with only the wild <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> as
<lb/>my guides, our diet consisted of all kinds of flesh that
<lb/>came within the range of any gun &amp; all sorts of roots
<lb/>when meat was awanting. Sometimes we had plenty &amp;
<lb/>at other times we feasted on what we saw in our
<lb/>dreams. I visited many new tribes &amp; was soundly treated
<lb/>by all. I had some intercourse with <term type="animal">lions</term> but thanks
<lb/>to kind Providence I did not recieve hurt from any
<lb/>The journey was more than <measure>two hundred miles</measure> beyond
<lb/>the place in which I left the wagoon yet the climate
<lb/>being fine I enjoyed the best of health although sleeping
<lb/>consistently on the bare ground. No consequence of
<lb/>the long intercourse with the <orgName>natives</orgName> which these journies

	<pb facs="liv_000538_0003" n="0003"/>
<lb/>afforded I soon acquired faculty in expressing myself in
<lb/>the language &amp; now it is nearly as natural to me as this English
<lb/>The knowledge of the country <del type="strikethrough">too</del> which I have acquired has
<lb/>been of service too for the <orgName>Directors</orgName> have instructed us
<lb/>to begin a new <orgName>mission</orgName> a spot chosen by me although 
<lb/><persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <choice><abbr>M</abbr><expan>M</expan></choice></persName><!-- Not sure who this is. AW --> has not yet arrived. It is very near to the
<lb/>place where <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Campbell</persName> in his progress of discovery
<lb/>thought proper to turn about &amp; go home. The iron works
<lb/>he heard of but was not permitted to see are situated
<lb/>there, the same reason which prevented him getting a sight
<lb/>of them prevails now &amp; it is a fear lest the iron should
<lb/>become bewitched by the presence of a stranger, they will not
<lb/>allow anyone who has had intercourse with the opposite sex
<lb/>since the commencement of the period in which they
<lb/>annually smelt the ore, To approach the furnaces. Iron
<lb/>bewitched you will say what is that. It is simply the effect
<lb/>of a too energetic working of the bellows and when they take
<lb/>out the iron burned to a cinder they exclaim behold the effects
<lb/>of witchcraft. <space extent="1" unit="chars"/>The evidence is so clear &amp; there before their
<lb/>eyes no one attempts to doubt it. <space extent="1" unit="chars"/>They then apply a larger
<lb/>portion of their prophylactics against witchcraft, put in
<lb/>fresh ore &amp; begin the process anew. All the people employed
<lb/>in these works sleep apart from their wives during the
<lb/>period of smelting. Their implements are most original
<lb/>The same I suppose as were invented by old <persName>Tubal Cain</persName>
<lb/>a piece of the bark of a tree folded on itself with tongs
<lb/>a stone is the forehammer and another the anvil of these
<lb/><orgName>antidiluvians</orgName>, yet they manage to make pretty neat
<lb/>work of it. The ore is found in great abundance &amp; nor
<lb/>covered by any soil which will be an advantage to our new
<lb rend="right"/>settlement</p>
	
	<pb facs="liv_000538_0004" n="0004"/>
<lb/><p>I may mention here that all the notions of these people concerning
<lb/>medicine are connected with the suggestion that witchcraft is
<lb/>extremely practiced <space extent="4" unit="chars"/>Indeed they seem to behave that no one
<lb/>would ever die unless he were bewitched, their <term type="occupation">doctors</term> suck
<lb/>out all manner of things from the <unclear><gap extent="4" unit="chars" agent="illegible"/>res</unclear> for their patients -
<lb/>these are exhibited &amp; I believed to have been put into the body
<lb/>by some witch, no good is done to a patient nor evil
<lb/>prevented except by their agency. Hence when I happen to cure
<lb/>an individual they immediately ascribe it to my powers as
<lb/>a <term type="occupation">wizard</term>. <space extent="1" unit="chars"/>They think too it is no matter how medicine is
<lb/>applied provided it is only near to the patient. If I give a
<lb/>child medicine &amp; <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> watch the mother will pour it on
<lb/>its head or drink it herself. Not matter how <w>na<add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">u</add>seous</w> the
<lb/>dose is if a patient expresses dislike to it some fellow
<lb/>standing by will gulp it down instantly. If a man is
<lb/>guilty of stealing from his relatives they give him an
<lb/>emetic in order to make him vomit his had propensity
<lb/>and the <term type="occupation">chief</term> of the <term type="tribe">Bakwains</term> <choice><orig>shewed</orig><reg>showed</reg></choice> me a root which he
<lb/>powdered &amp; sprinkled on his legs in order to cause
<lb/>him to run fast. <space extent="3" unit="chars"/>The friends of another <term type="occupation">chief</term> were very
<lb/>angry with me because having assisted him they asserted
<lb/>that instead of giving medicine to cure his disease I had
<lb/>given him some to change his heart. Some actually
<lb/>believed that I could raise the dead and perhaps it is owning to
<lb/>my supposed knowledge in the black art I have never
<lb/>yet had any thing stolen since I came to the <term type="tribe">Bechuana</term>
<lb/>country, you will perceive by these details that their notions
<lb/>of medicine are quite puerile, their knowledge on all
<lb/>other subjects is quite as much limited, a few fables contain
<lb/>all they have deserved from their ancestors and with respect
<lb/>to the future all to them is darkness</p>

	<pb facs="liv_000538_0005" n="0005"/>
<lb/><p>The impurities they practice I cannot mention, They follow out<add place="above marginright" rend="gray" hand="#U0">MS /8/2</add>
<lb/>the principles of <persName>Owen</persName> the socialist as far as they will go &amp;
<lb/>though each woman has her husband who fathers her
<lb/>children promiscuous intercourse is almost universal. Those
<lb/>gentlemen who admire the morality of the heathen would do
<lb/>well to examine before they sound its praises. The <term type="tribe"><w>Bechu<supplied>-</supplied>
<lb break="no"/>-anas</w></term> are great cowards yet if they can kill when there is
<lb/>little chance of being themselves killed they murder without
<lb/>compunction. <space extent="2" unit="chars"/>They make long incisions on their body
<lb/>the scars of which are their "scars of honour" the memorial
<lb/>of having murdered helpless women &amp; children, they are proud
<lb/>of these scars &amp; are not ashamed to point out those they
<lb/>have made in rememberance of having killed females
<lb/>A man is not ashamed either to say he cannot carry
<lb/>a small burden and he will go &amp; call his wife to do it
<lb/>These degraded beings we hope to raise to the level of
<lb/>humanity &amp; civilization. If it were to be done by our
<lb/>means I should despair but it is to be effected by the
<lb/>power of God and this causes me to hope. Much has
<lb/>already been done. There then is a church of about 300
<lb/>members. Many can read well &amp; generally they are clothed
<lb/>&amp; partially civilized. We hope the location to which I
<lb/>shall soon remove will be another centre of height &amp;
<lb/>civilization &amp; that good will ultimately be done to the
<lb/>distant interior. The people to whom we go are
<lb/>called the <term type="tribe">Bakhatla</term>. They live about <measure>20 miles</measure> beyond
<lb/>the spot where <persName>Mosilikatze</persName> was seen by <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName>
<lb/>I lately walked over what was once the site of his
<lb/>town &amp; where he suffered his last defeat by the <orgName>Boers</orgName>

	<pb facs="liv_000538_0006" n="0006"/>
<lb/>The grass had recently been burned off the country so I got a good
<lb/>view of the whole &amp; a few human bones were all I could discover
<lb/>of all that belonged to <persName>Mosilikatze</persName>, He is now situated about
<lb/><measure>350 miles</measure> North East of his former location, But still goes on
<lb/>in his murderous <choice><sic>carreer</sic><corr>career</corr></choice>, Last year he sent out a
<lb/>marauding party which scoured all over the Interior, and
<lb/>swept away all the <term type="animal">cattle</term> that came within their grasp. Many
<lb/>were killed &amp;the rest of the people are now living in
<lb/>holes in the rocks. This applies more especially to
<lb/>the <term type="tribe">Bamangwato</term>, <term type="tribe">Bakoa</term> &amp; <term type="tribe">Makalaka</term> all of whom I have
<lb/>visited. They live on the summit of a very high range
<lb/>of basaltic rocks. The same, I believe at no very
<lb/>distant date of active volcanic operations, there are many
<lb/>large cup shaped cavities in these rocks, with flat bottoms
<lb/>&amp; perpendicular sides destitute of vegetation, some of them
<lb/>as large as <placeName>Finsbury Square</placeName> &amp; more than <measure>300 feet</measure> deep
<lb/>they are rent &amp; riven in every direction, and in
<lb/>some parts covered with huge fragments which falling
<lb/>down &amp; <unclear cert="medium">infringing</unclear> on each other &amp; the rocks below
<lb/>form innumerable cavities into which these
<lb/><term type="animal">tubes</term> flee for shelter from their enemies. I entered one
<lb/>&amp; it was capable of containing a hundred individuals
<lb/>the entrance being so small a dozen men could stand
<lb/>&amp; defend it against the ingress of a single individual
<lb/>&amp; he crawling on all fours. <space extent="2" unit="chars"/>These holes as well as
<lb/>those in the <term type="tribe">Bakwain</term> country are covered with a totally
<lb/>different vegetation than that which exists on the plains
<lb/>on the latter it is principally of a thorny stunted
<lb/>character but as soon as you ascend the former
<lb/>thorns entirely dis<del type="strikethrough">s</del>appear. <term type="plant">Fig</term> trees abound &amp;

	<pb facs="liv_000538_0007" n="0007"/>
<lb/>The netile shoots up <term>tea tree</term> <measure>30 feet</measure> high &amp; more than <measure>two</measure>
<lb/>in diameter. <space extent="1" unit="chars"/>The tree which yields the <term type="tribe">Bushman</term> poison
<lb/>is also there very large. There it is a mere shrub.
<lb/>I hear it is stated at home that <persName>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moffat</persName> intends to go with
<lb/>the interior on a sort of exploring journey, I
<lb/>hope he may not fall a victim of the <unclear cert="high"><term type="ailment">fever</term></unclear> which
<lb/>then prevail. Near the <placeName><geogName type="lake">Lake Mokhoro</geogName></placeName> they are very
<lb/>fatal to the <orgName>natives</orgName>. Towards the East of our to be
<lb/>station they also prevail &amp; are very destructive to the
<lb/>inhabitants of <unclear><placeName>De Sagoa Bay</placeName></unclear>. Besides a <unclear cert="high">fly</unclear> exists 
<lb/>in that region or rather <choice><abbr>N.E.</abbr><expan>Northeast</expan></choice> of it which biting
<lb/>the <term type="animal">oxen</term> destroys them as soon as the first <unclear cert="low">one</unclear>
<lb/>falls.</p>
<lb/><p>The <orgName>Boers</orgName> from all I have seen of them, appear
<lb/>to deserve the character you bestow but you would not
<lb/>choose to mingle much with them. They are kind &amp;
<lb/>hospitable but very ignorant. Indeed the majority of
<lb/>them are destitute of that general information which
<lb/>makes company agreeable. <space extent="1" unit="chars"/>They have not the means of
<lb/>informing themselves &amp; have been the dupes of a set
<lb/>of unprincipled men in the <orgName>Colony</orgName>. I cannot go into
<lb/>the subject at <unclear cert="high"><w>pre<gap extent="1" unit="chars" agent="blot"/><supplied>s</supplied>ent</w></unclear> but I believe they are <unclear cert="medium"><gap extent="1" unit="chars" agent="blot"/><supplied>m</supplied>ore</unclear> to be
<lb/>pitied than blamed. The <orgName>Colonial government</orgName> has as large
<lb/>a share in their misdemeanour as any one else.
<lb/>They are generally such as respect religion But the frequent
<lb/>commission of the grossest immoralities by them makes
<lb/>me doubt whether they possess much more than they farm
<lb/>Their language is easy &amp; resembles the <term type="nationality">Scotch</term> but not
<lb/>having come much in contact with them I can only
<lb/>speak the <unclear>colloquaen</unclear> dialect, &amp; not very good at that.

	<pb facs="liv_000538_0008" n="0008"/>
<lb/>I need not give you any information respecting their recent
<lb/>rebellions <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="illegible"/> or of the imbecile dealings of the <orgName>Colonial
<lb/>government</orgName> as I am persuaded you will have heard of all by
<lb/>means of public papers</p>
<lb/><space extent="5" unit="lines" dim="vertical"/>

	<cb rend="vertical"/>
	<ab>
	<address>
<addrLine><del type="strikethrough">Care of <persName><choice><abbr>Rev<hi rend="sup underline">d</hi></abbr><expan>Reverend</expan></choice> D<hi rend="sup underline">r</hi> <gap extent="1" unit="chars" agent="hole"/><supplied>P</supplied>hillip</persName>, <placeName><geogName type="cape"><hi rend="underline">Cape <unclear cert="low">Tovon</unclear></hi></geogName></placeName></del></addrLine>
<addrLine><persName><choice><abbr>R.</abbr><expan>Robert</expan></choice> Hayward <add place="above" hand="#U2"><hi rend="large"><metamark/></hi></add> Esq<hi rend="sup underline">uire</hi></persName> <add place="above" rend="vertical large brown" hand="#U1"><del type="cancelled">Mr</del></add></addrLine>
<addrLine rend="right"><del type="cancelled"><placeName>Victoria Cresent</placeName></del></addrLine>
<addrLine rend="right"><del type="cancelled"><placeName>Ramsgate</placeName></del></addrLine>
<addrLine rend="right"><placeName><country><hi rend="underline">England</hi></country></placeName></addrLine>
	</address>
	</ab>

	<ab rend="upside-down">
	<addSpan spanTo="#add1" hand="#U3" rend="large"/><add place="over-text" rend="diagonal red" hand="#U4">6/1</add><address>
<addrLine><placeName>11 Church St</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName>Paddington Green</placeName></addrLine>
<addrLine><placeName><settlement type="town">London</settlement></placeName></addrLine>
	</address>
	<anchor xml:id="add1"/>
	</ab>

<!-- There are various postage stamps, and some red marks scattered through the page.-->

<lb/><p>I hope you will find time &amp; inclination to give me a long <bibl>letter</bibl>
<lb/>I should like to write <persName>Houlton</persName> but <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> know his address
<lb/>I am happy to hear that you have passed the college and
<lb/>beg leave to congratulate you on the event. But perhaps
<lb/>long ere this reaches you.  The pains &amp; fears of the examination
<lb/>will all be forgotten.</p> <closer> <salute>Believe me yours sincerely</salute> <signed><persName><choice><abbr>D.</abbr><expan>David Livingstone</expan></choice></persName></signed> 
</closer>


            </div>
        </body>
    </text>

</TEI>
